<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="5">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1845</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Notes on a Journey via Paris to London, Leeds, Low Moor, Sheffield, and Back in the Summer of 1845.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <lb/>
                <byline>By <docAuthor>Johann Conrad Fischer</docAuthor>,  Lieutenant Colonel of the Artillery.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Schaffhausen. Printed by J. J. Biegler’schen Buchdruckerei. <docDate>1846</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Titelseite</head>
                <p> <pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588384"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9848">[title page of the first edition]</term></p>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Preface</head>
                <p><pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588387"/> When I first visited <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> 52 years ago, and there, having found employ with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">mechanic</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493">Shoe Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet Street</placeName>, through which I had occasion to compare the extent to which this branch of industry had advanced and been perfected as opposed to that on the Continent, I must confess that my verdict was wholly in favour of England, and that scarcely any object of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> in this or that field need fear rivalry from abroad, a circumstance to which the early introduction of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent system</term> with its capacity to offer both inducements and protections might well have contributed, ensuring that the wares produced, almost without exception, combine a high degree of perfection with both solidity and utility.</p>        
                <p><pb n="IV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588388"/> Yet to the best of my knowledge, there was nothing especially new to be seen there – with the exception of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>, which on the Continent were all but unknown at the time – since the same things might be found elsewhere, only not as good.</p>
                <p>When, twenty years later, I visited this curious <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">island</placeName> again the moment the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">Continental Blockade</term> was lifted, I found great new phenomena in the aforementioned fields. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-1405">iron foundries</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9572">potteries</term>, among which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7567"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566">Wedgwood</orgName></persName></persName> seemed the primus inter pares or rather the princeps, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file factories</term>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plate</term>, the spun cotton and <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">mechanical looms</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">textile mills</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> had taken on a character of greatness and perfection of which, without seeing them for oneself, one can have no concept.</p>
                <p>Twelve or thirteen years later, when inclination and interest drove me to this country once again, the scale of everything, most notably the extent of London, had grown even more, so that a member of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">parliament</term>, when the matter was debated in September of that same year, had occasion <pb n="V" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588389"/> to say: “this year had seen the building of 26,000 new houses by the end of last week, though how many more will be finished by next Saturday I cannot say.”</p>
                <p>The already widespread deployment of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term>, the introduction of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lighting</term>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins’s</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8877">steam gun</term> and the construction of the gigantic <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888"><term ref="gfa-keywords-7622">tunnel</term></placeName> that seemed impossible but was made possible by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel</persName>, alongside all manner of other most interesting things, my brief notes on which are contained in the diaries<note>Gemeint sind die Tagebücher von <ref type="cross" target="../1825/1">1825</ref> und von <ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/1">1825–1827</ref>.</note> I kept of my travels in those years, imprinted themselves on my mind as a composition, which through vivid recollection of the same makes for a most alluring tableau. —As already mentioned, I committed my feeble and incomplete outlines of these things to my earlier diaries, the keeping of which, through long habituation, has become a compulsion, and which readers have received kindly and, disregarding their shortcomings, judged with circumspection, perhaps precisely because I did not presume to write deliberately for others. The few pages that follow, however, in which is contained the result of last year’s very brief journey, are too paltry in content for others to be alerted to the same. They shall not, therefore, <pb n="VI" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588390"/> be entrusted to the book trade, and are printed here, after the passage of almost a whole year, only because it did not seem worth my while to make them over to a publisher. It is for the sake of <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my family</persName> and friends, therefore, who wondered at my not having seen anything worthy of note or at my having deemed what I did see unworthy of mention, that this small volume takes its place alongside its predecessors. May they, or indeed anyone else who chances to lay hands on it, receive it as I wish, namely as a straightforward account, addressed to my own nearest and dearest, of a journey undertaken to foreign lands, and for me but one scene more in the aforementioned tableau.<lb/>
                    <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, the <date when="1846-06-21">21st June 1846</date>.<lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>, Lieutenant Colonel.<note>Das Tagebuch wurde 1846 bei der <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8309">J. J. Ziegler’schen Buchdruckerei</orgName> in Schaffhausen gedruckt.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588391"/>
        <body>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Schaffhausen–Basel, 14. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1845-07-14" n="1"><anchor/></placeName> On <date when="1845-07-14">14th July</date> I set off for <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> by express coach, and in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-718" when="1845-07-14" n="2">Jestetten</placeName> was joined by an <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> family, a gentleman, two ladies and a young boy, as travelling companions. They seemed pleased to have encountered one with whom they might converse in their native tongue, the occasion for which was Mr. Watson’s taking out an English map of <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe’s</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamship</term> routes. After we had talked about sundry related matters, his wife, remarking on the fact that I evidently understood English, presented me with a printed pamphlet and invited me to read the same. It was a fragment of a tract published by the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8252">Tract Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and contained two tales of conversion (the 867th and 868th, according to the tract), one of them entitled “The Railway Passenger” and the other the “Father’s Prayer”. Out of respect for her good intentions, and for the family as people who took such matters very seriously, it seemed to me, I read both tales in their entirety, despite finding them too bland and moralistic, all the more so since they bore the stamp of well-meaning fiction rather than that of true stories. After reading them, I made to return them <pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588392"/> but was obliged to keep them. The event reminded me of an earlier one, when one Madame <persName ref="gfa-actors-8253">Consentius</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2119">Königsberg</placeName>, a great admirer of [Barbara] <persName ref="gfa-actors-7877">von Krüdener</persName>, had visited me, and on taking her leave of me had given me two such tracts, which common folk in those days believed to possess a particular smell that if inhaled would make one an adherent of that then so famous lady. Soon afterwards, Mr. Watson slipped his <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver-bound</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">New Testament</term> out of its case and read aloud a chapter from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Saint John’s Gospel</term>, after which the conversation once again turned to more general matters.</p>
                <p>In <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1971" when="1845-07-14" n="3">Lauchringen</placeName> we were joined, much to my delight, by Pastor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7899">Merian</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2038">Oberhallau</placeName>, to whom, since I knew that he had likewise been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and understood English, I was able to give the aforementioned stories as reading material.</p>
                <p>At Berg near <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-991" when="1845-07-14" n="4">Lauffenburg</placeName> we were waylaid by a mendicant apprentice, who climbed in beside us, as did, soon afterwards, a farmer’s girl from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-132">Black Forest</placeName> wishing to avail herself of the baths in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2056">Säckingen</placeName>, who was likewise given such a tract. She held onto it for some time, albeit upside-down, and would have politely returned it had not the Englishwoman exhorted her: “Keep it, keep it!” which I then translated for her, telling her that she should keep it.</p>
                <p>Giving serious thought to what had just transpired, I wondered to myself, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588393"/> as I have done repeatedly ever since, whether such endeavours, as commendable and sincerely meant as they undoubtedly are, are not bound by any propriety of time, place and circumstance? But never once have I been able to answer that question and instead attach great value to the very profound message of the apostle: “But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut the door, pray to thy Father which is in secret.”<note>Matthäus 6,6.</note></p>
                <p>On arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-10" when="1845-07-14" n="5">Basel</placeName> that evening, my dear old friend <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">Wibert</persName> was already at the post office to welcome me and to accommodate me under his hospitable roof.</p>
                <p>How sorry I was that he could not be my travelling companion in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> as he had been fifty years ago!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Geschäftsgänge in Basel, 15. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>The greater part of the day was taken up with various visits and writing two letters home.</p>
                <p>I went first to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7969">Wölflin</persName>, who had recently returned from <placeName ref="gfa-places-205">Mexico</placeName> and was just then unpacking 5 cases of natural objects and artefacts from the land of the ancient Incas<note>Fischer verwechselt die Inkas mit den <placeName ref="gfa-places-205">Azteken</placeName>.</note>. I found them all fascinating, though most of all the <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName> objects that he had chanced to acquire, primarily a charming little pocket book, whose tortoiseshell binding was covered with characters arranged one below the other in columns, as is sometimes the case with <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egyptian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphs</term>. Its inside pages, twelve in number (they seem to have a dodecimal system, too), depicted the costumes and other attributes of the various classes of this curious people, <pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588394" break="no"/> the faces of the women being painted onto tiny, convex slivers of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9023">ivory</term> the size of a little fingernail, whereas the rest was all flat.</p>
                <p>Of the four large tableaux of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9641">sugar boiler</term> with its own ox <term ref="gfa-keywords-9324">gin</term> alongside it, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9161">stove-builder’s shop</term>, a landscape and a Chinese juggler with an entourage of monkeys and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9187">dogs</term>, it was the latter that interested me most, having never before seen anything like it in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. I once saw a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9685">comedy with dogs and monkeys</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-815">Salzburg</placeName> that certainly took things quite far, though for all that they were clad like the ladies and gentlemen that they supposedly represented, the faces peeping out from under the hats and bonnets were still those of dogs and monkeys. The Chinese, however, took the deception a stage further in that all had masks depending on the role they had to play, and as if that were not enough, there was a dog pulling a little cart bearing a basket full of masks, on which sat a monkey-coachman vigorously brandishing his whip.</p>
                <p>After a visit to my friend’s family, I had two meetings with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8254">E. P.</persName>, which for the most part had to do with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Schweizer-Eisenbahnen</term>, specifically <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">the line</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanz</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>. He raised what seemed to be some important objections to a very well written memorandum by a highly skilled and experienced member of our trade, <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588395"/> namely the want of passengers on the line via <placeName ref="gfa-places-2069">Ulm</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1329">Augsburg</placeName> and further east, which concern I felt bound to allay by noting that things would look very different once the line from Augsburg to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1988">Lindau</placeName> was finished. As to the money for the aforementioned line, he acknowledged that while he himself, like many other <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> establishments, had perhaps been able to provide an impetus, nothing positive had as yet been discussed, it having been observed that since <placeName ref="gfa-places-1899">Baden</placeName> did not wish to build the line itself, or so it had been heard, the necessary concessions on that side would first have to be secured, and that the very large sums required in such a case might well be raised in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>.</p>
                <p>There was just enough time for me to tell him of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">my invention</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term>, indeed the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">melting</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">casting</term> of all <term ref="gfa-keywords-9012">wrought iron</term> so as to retain its softness and malleability, and showed him some pieces that he took with him as specimens. Once he had seen these and tested them with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">file</term> and hammer, he cried out: “The <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> should have that!”, whereupon I remarked that I first wanted to hear what the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> had to say.</p>
                <p>Returning home past Basel’s many fine and sturdy public buildings and private homes, <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588396" break="no"/> all of them so clean and impeccably well kept both inside and out, I could not help but think that it was this same cleanliness, this same love of order – the daughters of quiet, steady industry that historically have long been at home in Basel – which in their wake have brought not some fly-by-night or will-o-the-wisp, but wealth built on solid ground and thriving as if of its own accord. A house in good order is one that is entered gladly. In this respect <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> appear in a much more favourable light than does <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">their neighbour</placeName>, which once believed itself to be the No. 1 of all the nations of this earth.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Basel–Paris, 16. bis 18. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">My friend</persName> accompanied me as far as the post office, where I departed at 7 o’clock in the morning on the post coach from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-10" when="1845-07-16T07:00:00" n="6">Basel</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, for an inside seat on which, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabriolet</term> being already occupied, I had to pay 56 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term>. The post coach belonging to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8255">Bureau des Diligences Royales</orgName> was much finer and better furnished than it used to be. — <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">Customs</term> in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2065" when="1845-07-16" n="7">St. Louis</placeName> were not very scrupulous, and since the product specimens that I declared of 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9858">kilogram</term> in weight are so valuable to me, I gladly paid the 1 franc and 46 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">centimes</term> levied.</p>
                <p>In <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1586" when="1845-07-16T12:00:00" n="8">Mulhouse</placeName> I chanced to have the pleasure of lunching with three esteemed young compatriots, whose industriousness and love of business in the one or the other métier might serve others as an example to follow, and conversed with them <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588397" break="no"/> on sundry matters relating to industrially made objects. To judge by past experience, however, I would henceforth have to abandon all hopes of pleasure. —And indeed, it was worse than I had anticipated; for quite apart from the fact that our company consisted of a German scholar who either slept or smoked, a young French army officer, and the wife of a factory worker from Mulhouse, who as a Parisienne had been bored to death there and had left her husband to return to what she considered to be heaven on earth, we never once stopped long enough to eat anything during the 23 hours to elapse between Mulhouse and Langres (which I had not expected given previous journeys). It being bourse day in Mulhouse, we had sat down to lunch at twelve o’clock sharp and set off again at 1, and by the time we sat down to breakfast in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1815" when="1845-07-17T11:00:00" n="9">Langres</placeName> it was already 11 o’clock the next morning, the <date when="1845-07-17">17th June</date><note>Gemeint ist der 17. Juli.</note>. I had no opportunity to make any important observations on that long stretch. Whereas the land was better <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">cultivated</term> than when I last journeyed through it in <ref type="cross" target="../1814/4">1814</ref>, when one saw only women at the plough, the coupes régulières undertaken by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon</persName> and his young cadre for the honour of the nation, or more likely his own glory, had in the meantime ceased. But the peasants’ dwellings in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1916">Champagne</placeName>, even as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1811" when="1845-07-18T00:00:00" n="10">Troyes</placeName>, where we arrived around midnight <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588398" break="no"/> and were able to drink a cup of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term>, were just as wretched as ever, especially when one compares their timbering, roofing, cramped conditions, workmanship, disposition and general filth to those of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> farmhouses.</p>
                <p>We breakfasted à la fourchette in a small town just beyond <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2016" when="1845-07-18" n="11">Nangis</placeName> and arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-118" when="1845-07-18T16:00:00" n="12">Paris</placeName> at 4 o’clock in the afternoon of the <date when="1845-07-18">18th</date>.</p>
                <p>Following one of the calling cards with which one is so generously regaled on alighting from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term>, I sought lodgings at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2230">Hôtel du Havre</placeName> on the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2120" when="1845-07-18" n="13">rue des vieux Augustins</placeName>. I cannot complain, since after my 50-hour journey and a light supper I was happy just to see a bed again, though I would not recommend this inn to anyone else.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Pariser Mode, Münzanstalt und Weiterreise, 19. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>On the journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1586">Mulhouse</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> (since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> returns that same day), I discovered above the filêts inside the carriage a printed pamphlet, which I leafed through out of sheer boredom. It was titled <term ref="gfa-keywords-9687">la Diligence</term> and seems to have been placed there deliberately, since it contained a whole host of advertisements for shops in Paris, contained within which were some blandly written stories, spiked with far-fetched words that do not belong to common parlance, which in spirit and style are very similar to those used in today’s fashion magazines. Among the advertisements was one which, to stand out from the others, had white letters on a black ground <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588399"/> and began with the rallying cry “Mort aux chapeaux de soie!” [Death to silk hats!], followed by a paean to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9688">castor hats</term> of the very best quality that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8256">Biget</persName> (to be found at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2122"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2123" when="1845-07-19" n="14">rue Rivoli no. 56</placeName></placeName>) was selling for 17 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> a piece. Needing such a hat, I set off thence and consequently had to walk all the way back to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1604" when="1845-07-19" n="15">prefecture</placeName>, before venturing even further afield to the banker Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2124" when="1845-07-19" n="16"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7811">Dassier</persName></placeName>, in whose counting house I met a young man from Schaffhausen (<persName ref="gfa-actors-8300">Rauschenbach</persName>), who deservedly enjoys great confidence there. After that it was off to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7509">Bréant's</persName> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1602" when="1845-07-19" n="17">mint</placeName>, which does such great work in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platinum</term>, and there, with Mr. Bréant himself guiding me through that labyrinthine building, to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7770">Barre</persName> to take provisional orders for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">steel for coin punches</term> of a quality that might rival that used for the excellent coins made by <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich’s</placeName> award-winning <placeName ref="gfa-places-2014">mint</placeName>. These two gentlemen viewed my specimens of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">cast soft bar iron</term></term> (the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9690">lockplate</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9691">cock</term> of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion flintlock</term>) with interest, and Mr. Bréant took the opportunity to tell me, much to my surprise, that they still had no really good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> and still preferred the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2042">Passau</placeName> model.</p>
                <p>After the mint, and shortly before departing on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName>, I had to return to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1604" when="1845-07-19" n="19">prefecture</placeName>, though only after calling at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2125" when="1845-07-19" n="18"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8301">Swiss delegation</persName></placeName>, where <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588400" break="no"/> a sum of 2 francs was demanded for the appendage of a stamp to my passport, presumably for the sake of the people of that nation, since not a single penny was asked of me anywhere else. Meanwhile, my errantry, as I can with some justification call it, afforded me something pleasant and unexpected in the form of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2126"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2004"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9693">obelisk of Luxor</term></placeName></placeName>, that fine monolith, a drawing of which I once possessed, albeit without knowing the interpretation of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphs</term> according to the key provided by <persName ref="gfa-actors-8257">Champollion</persName>.</p>
                <p>Three thoughts occurred to me on viewing this curious object: either <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName> in those days had had a large population of idlers that might be put to work on this seemingly futile undertaking, which given Egypt’s fertility and the small amount of effort required to <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">work the land</term> there is entirely plausible, or the ambitions of its rulers surpassed all moderation in the same proportion as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8770">pyramids</term> do ordinary buildings, to prove which one might cite <persName ref="gfa-actors-7856">Herodotus</persName>, or it had been agreed, which would be the most praiseworthy of these three theories, that there should be an enduring monument to the history, the laws and the mores of those times. —</p>
                <p>When <term ref="gfa-keywords-9693">this gift</term> of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7734">Ali Pascha</persName> to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8258">King of France</persName><note>Die Schenkung fällt in die Herrschaft von <persName ref="gfa-actors-8258">Karl X</persName>. Der Transport und das Aufstellen des Obelisken in Paris geschah unter <persName ref="gfa-actors-7478">Louis-Philippe I</persName>.</note>, which would be further embellished by its proximity to two extremely copious fountains (that the <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> have taste cannot be denied), <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588401"/> was first erected, the gazettes mocked the idea of mounting a pointed column on a pedestal. Quite apart from the fact that the newspapers are not the word of god, any impartial observer is bound to concede that the idea was in fact a good one. The throne of a king is likewise elevated above its surroundings, and this king, too, undoubtedly deserved a lofty position under all those stones.</p>
                <p>At half past two, feeling amply recompensed for all the hardships of the day by my reception at the mint, I paid 33 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> for a stage-coach to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName> and left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-118" when="1845-07-19T14:30:00" n="20">Paris</placeName>. As the capital’s new wall with its <placeName ref="gfa-places-2225">detached bastions</placeName> (which only future times may judge) receded into the distance, I was glad to be entering the pretty region of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2022">Normandy</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France’s</placeName> very own <placeName ref="gfa-places-78">Thurgau</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Shortly after midnight, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8738">right-hand</term> horse of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> stumbled and became so ensnared in its traces that we lost almost a whole hour, which in turn robbed us passengers of a whole day, since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne sur mer</placeName> and Calais depart at a fixed hour every day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Boulogne–Calais, 20. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1606" when="1845-07-20T10:00:00" n="21">Boulogne</placeName> at 10 o’clock in the morning. One travels so uncommonly fast compared to times past, and that despite all the passengers and goods. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> have learned this from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName>, <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588402"/> though they have yet to adopt their horses and fine, sturdy bridles. The 72-hour journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> is now accomplished in just 18 hours. The swindling that goes on at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inns</term> en route is extraordinary. No one takes anything without first asking what it costs, and the insistence of the persons employed to recommend lodgings in Boulogne is remarkable. —The harassment began 4 hours outside Boulogne at the foot of a steep hill where the horses had to slow down to a walking pace and some women were waiting to thrust their addresses into every passing coach; but just an hour nearer to Boulogne and we were again waylaid by three urchins on ponies, each of whom held a long hazel switch with calling cards clamped into its split end, so that by trotting briskly along beside the coach, they were able to poke these inside to us passengers. —The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> did not linger long in Boulogne and I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1607" when="1845-07-20T14:00:00" n="22">Calais</placeName> at 2 o’clock in the afternoon. The inn where I used to stay, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2127">Hotel de St. Louis</placeName>, had gone under; but I had a lucky star in the guise of an officer of the gendarmerie, who on my approaching him for directions guided me to an English establishment, (<placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2128" when="1845-07-20" n="23">Commercial Inn</placeName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8259">Warren</persName>), where I fancied myself already in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, the family having brought with them all the customs of their home country, characteristic among which was their practice of having one person in the dining room reverentially read aloud from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Bible</term> (it was a Sunday) while his neighbour <pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588403"/> downed copious amounts of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9697">rum</term>, albeit very quietly, as is also customary in England.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Querung des Ärmelkanals und Herr Hamers Reisetipps, 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>I slept for ten hours, which is surely pardonable in one who has been travelling for 8 days and who between <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1607" when="1845-07-21T10:00:00" n="24">Calais</placeName> only once saw a bed (in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, to be precise). Well might I afford myself that pleasure, for our Royal Mail <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Steamship</term>, having a draught of just 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, could not put to sea until high tide, which arrived late at around 10 o’clock in the morning. The company on the steamer, which despite its small size was furnished with a 65 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">engine</term> that in defiance of wind and waves drove the wheels at a rate of 29 revolutions per minute, was not very numerous, as almost all travellers who make the journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> take the route from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne sur mer</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1957">Folkstone</placeName>, a little port on the English coast, where they meet a branch line of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2186">Dover-London railway</placeName>. Calais, astonishingly, has suffered because of this, since anyone who wants to be at sea for just a few hours can now make the crossing via Boulogne and complete the passage in just 26¼ hours, whereas anyone who travels from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1926">Dieppe</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, a journey entailing 74 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> at sea, and from there continues by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to Paris will reach the same in the incredibly short time of just 16¼ hours, having covered 244 English miles altogether. The total costs of this journey over land and sea from Paris to London or vice <pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588404"/> versa, including all the railway and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> fares and lodgings – though not what is consumed en route, which of course one can limit as one wishes – are in the order of 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">fr.</term> or 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> at most, at least as long as one does not take a seat in the coupé of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> or in a first-class carriage on the railway but instead contents oneself with an inside seat and a second-class carriage. Here I am bound to make a remark that the parents of sons, who whether by inclination or for professional reasons or other circumstances venture forth into the world, would do well to take to heart, should they ever set eyes on it: Since the intercourse among nations has multiplied so greatly of late and been so greatly facilitated by the advent of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>, learning French and English in addition to one’s mother tongue (I am addressing German-speakers here), and prior to that some Latin, be it ever so little, since that language is the foundation and mother of the other two, as it were, has become a matter of the utmost urgency. Yet too many of us are loath to acknowledge this, or so it seems to me, and though the benefits to be derived from it need no further articulation here, I shall nevertheless provide a few examples of my own. There were, as I said, but a few passengers on the steamship, and all of them English. Although I conversed with most of those on board in turn, one of them in particular <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588405" break="no"/> took a special shine to me precisely because I spoke English so fluently, or so he told me, so that not only did he tell me everything that I might possibly want to know about what was to be done at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153">customs</placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2046">“Aliens Office”</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> and explain to me how to procure a seat on the train to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, an 88-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">mile</term> journey that can now be accomplished in 3 hours, but he also gave me a permit to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8455">Chinese Collection</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2129">Hyde-Park Corner</placeName>, which cannot be viewed for money, despite containing the finest and most intriguing artefacts from <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">that country</placeName>, that has now been returned to the world, as it were.<note>Wohl eine Anspielung auf das Ende des <term ref="gfa-keywords-9347">Ersten Opiumkriegs</term> und der daraus resultierenden Öffnung Chinas für den Welthandel.</note> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8260">Hamer</persName> (not Hammer, which is also a word in English) also told me that on arriving at the station in London, I should hand over my luggage to a porter and have him take it – a service for which I would not have to pay a penny – to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term>, which for just one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> would take me to whichever part of London I wished. —I pondered the word “cab” for some time, since I did not recall ever having heard it before; after asking for an explanation, however, it turned out that the English, being such assiduous time-keepers, have substituted this word for the word “cabriolet”, which after all is three syllables longer.</p>
                <p>My desire to become <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasick</term>, since I always feel better thereafter, <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588406"/> was not fulfilled, despite my having scooped up a cup of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">green seawater</placeName> and downed it all at once shortly after departing Calais, a method which has never before failed me. —When inspecting the inner fittings of the ship I came across an object, which on grounds of its simplicity and the effectiveness of its intended purpose, which was to bring diffuse light to the dark rooms below decks by means of just a small opening in the overhead, interested me greatly. Never before had I encountered an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9755">optical</term>, or rather <term ref="gfa-keywords-8633">dioptical</term>, tool being used in such a way. As the ship, owing to its low draught and to prevent seepage on a stormy sea, had very few high and low portholes (windows) mounted on its sides, each of the completely dark rooms below had a single glass prism inserted into a hole in the middle of the overhead, though always somewhat sunken into the deck so as to prevent it getting trodden on by the shoes of those pacing to and fro. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9699">This prism</term>, each triangular face of which was circa 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in length and 2 inches wide, was protected by a very thin and slender <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> frame or mount that was nailed onto the <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">wood</term>, and that despite having a squared surface area in a ratio of 12:2500 to the smallest room to be illuminated provided real daylight.</p>
                <p><pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588407"/> Might we all be as conscientious as they are in England about taking whatever is of practical benefit from a scientific discipline and actually putting it to use!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>«Sind Sie auch in England, Herr Obrist?», 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>We landed in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-07-21T13:00:00" n="25">Dover</placeName> in glorious weather at about 1 o’clock in the afternoon. Having previously been told what I had to do and where, I was astonished at the ease, the assurance and the calm with which our goods were transferred from the ship to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2153" when="1845-07-21" n="26">customs house</placeName> and from there to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>. Only the owner of the goods was admitted to the long table, of which the room contained several, on which all the cases, bags, chests etc. were laid out ready for inspection. Upon my declaration of those objects that I had in my case on which <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">duty</term> might be payable, I was politely told that it was not worth their while, which of course is wiser than wasting time filling 3 full sheets of paper with written descriptions all for the sake of a few <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreuzers</term>. Not even the paper in which the said items were wrapped was removed; instead they were merely lifted off the table. It was all over in less than 3 minutes, and for a fare of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">sixpence</term> (eighteen kreuzer) a customs house employee took my effects to the inn. I now had to report to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2046" when="1845-07-21" n="27">aliens office</placeName>; it cannot really be called a police station, as there were no people with frightful moustaches, grim faces and crooked <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipes</term> there. It rather consisted of just one uncommonly small room and in it a friendly gentleman <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588408"/> clad all in black, as are almost all people of quality in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. Here I had nothing to do other than to write my name on three printed certificates of arrival, one of which was handed over to me, while the other two he retained. It all took just two minutes. England, it seems, is not as afraid of foreigners as its neighbouring country. I can now stay as long as I wish, go wherever I wish, and, according to this certificate, am not subject to any conditions such as having to report to the officer in charge at the port of embarkation prior to my departure. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, by contrast, despite being in possession of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passport</term> issued by [the Swiss] authorities and signed by the French ambassador, I was unable to get out of the country without first having to run hither and thither, to endure all sorts of travails, and pay money for them to boot. Here, by contrast, entering and remaining in the country is facilitated in the extreme.</p>
                <p>The officer then asked me how things stood in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>? to which I replied that there was not much to boast about there. He responded to this merely by remarking that it seemed to him that through the <placeName ref="gfa-places-91"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9700">attack on Lucerne</term></placeName>, both sides<note>Gemeint sind wohl die Liberal-Radikalen und die Katholisch-Konservativen.</note> had now gone too far – which incidentally is a view that thousands upon thousands of us who have not been blinded by passion would subscribe to. While some, on reading this, would find my account of this day tedious, the reason I chose to record <pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588409"/>  it in such detail in my diary was to ensure that at least my nearest and dearest might form a vivid picture of how good it is to have some prior knowledge of the language of every country, and this one in particular. How many pleasures would I have missed, how many embarrassments would I have suffered, had I not known the whys and wherefores? —The French entertain this preconceived notion that one has to learn their language (la langue de l'Univers), yet do not thank one for it when one proves oneself capable of conversing with them in the same; the English, by contrast, while equally entitled to such grand claims, are more modest and show affection and respect for those who speak their mother-tongue, as I have experienced many times.</p>
                <p>When I was at dinner in Dover, I suddenly heard someone behind me ask: “So you, too, are in England, Mr. Obrist?” and on turning round saw that it was Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7948">Schönbein</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>. My delight on seeing him here, however, was greatly mitigated by our having but a few minutes in which to converse, I being on my way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and he to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, and by the news that my esteemed friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> was not at present in England. I bid him a good journey and said that should he choose to attend the forthcoming convention of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8103">Swiss Naturalists’ Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1196">Geneva</placeName>, <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588410"/> an event that I have always found stimulating and worthwhile but this year will not be able to attend, he should kindly extend my apologies to its president, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8261">de la Rive</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Von Dover nach London mit der Eisenbahn, 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> departed <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-07-21T15:00:00" n="28">Dover</placeName> at 3 o’clock. On the advice of my new friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8260">Hamer</persName>, who remained my travelling companion as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1957" when="1845-07-21" n="29">Folkstone</placeName>, I took a seat in the second class, for which the fare for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">88-mile</term> journey was 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> and 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, or 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term></p>
                <p>“I can already see that you care about our country and its people and ask all sorts of questions,” said he. “It is here in this class, where you will encounter a better sort of people, that you will obtain the most information, whereas I could not and would not recommend the third class, and as for the first class, not only is it populated mainly by fine ladies, but the prevailing tone there is very stiff and formal.” —Not far from Dover we came to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2187">that curious place</placeName> where, harnessing those elemental forces over which we now have dominion and that through science can make our servants, a whole mountain made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9199">limestone</term> was cast all at once into the depths of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">sea</placeName> solely to make room for the genius of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam trains</term>.<note>Fischer meint die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9806">Sprengung von Round Down Cliff</term> am <date when="1843-01-26">26. Januar 1843</date>.</note> Somewhat later we passed through several <placeName ref="gfa-places-2190">tunnels</placeName> of quite some length, our entrance into which was invariably advertised by a loud scream on the part of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">locomotive</term>. —The extreme darkness that reigns supreme in these passages makes one concur with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7947">Schiller</persName>:</p>
                <p><pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588411"/>“A dark and mysterious gate opens wide.<lb/> Beyond seem the shadow realms dreaded.<lb/> But sudden a region of bliss is descried.<lb/>Where autumn and spring-time are wedded”,<note>Zweite Strophe aus Friedrich Schillers Gedicht «Berglied», 1804. ((trans. Edgar Alfred Bowring, 1851))</note><lb/> – for the surrounding countryside is truly very fine and richly cultivated.</p>
                <p>At the speed at which one now travels – on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>, that is – everything flies by so fast that it is impossible to get a proper look at anything, still less to compose a description of it. Earlier times were better for that, as can be read in the thick volumes by <placeName ref="gfa-places-16"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7918"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9754">Nikolai in Berlin</term></persName></placeName>Nikolai [Gretsch] in Berlin and the account of <placeName ref="gfa-places-748"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9701">Sophie’s Journey from Memel to Saxony</term></placeName>. — Nonetheless, I took note of several objects that to me seemed not entirely trivial. First, there are the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hop gardens</term> that are so frequent here on <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England’s</placeName> southern and south-eastern flank. Had I not known that there are no <term ref="gfa-keywords-9620">vineyards</term> in England, I would have mistaken them for vines such as those that grow in our parts, for they use the same circa 6-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term>-long stakes, space them the same 33 to 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> apart, and treat the soil in much the same way too. How much <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">timber</term> must be saved compared to <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany’s</placeName> 20-foot-long hop poles? How much easier the procurement? And how many more plants can be grown on the same area? Being no <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agronomist</term>, I shall refrain from passing judgment, though I am bound to believe that the calmly analytical and mathematically minded Englishmen <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588412" break="no"/> must have found a significant advantage in this manner of hop-growing. Second, there is the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electro-galvanic</term><note>Korrekturanweisung aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588463">Erstdruck</ref>: «Correctur. Statt <term ref="gfa-keywords-9752">electrogalvanische</term>, lies: electromagnetische».</note> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term>, whose 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">copper wires</term></term> run alongside the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term> from one specially erected pole to the next, and whose speedy reports leave even the fastest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam train</term> far behind them like a lame horse; and third, there are the timber underlays for the iron rails, of which all those that I have seen in Germany and <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> were elongated <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">rectangles</term> or had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">rounded</term> underside, whereas those in England are equilateral <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">triangles</term>, which makes perfect sense to me; and not just because of the timber that is saved in this way, since they can be cut apart out of relatively thick planks, but also because on pondering the matter further, having at first glance not known what to make of them, I realised that as paradoxical as it seems, their resistance to the pressure from above, disregarding that from the sides, will be greater than that of the aforementioned shapes or cross-sections. At <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2130" when="1845-07-21" n="30">New Cross</placeName>, 10 miles from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, I at last came to that important <placeName ref="gfa-places-2198">place</placeName> where an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric line</term> is being laid parallel to the conventional one. This bold and audacious idea proves that no one in England is deterred by difficulties that do not carry within them <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588413" break="no"/> the impossibility of their removal. A large part of the tube, which depending on the needs of the moment is either open or sealed tight, has been laid (<placeName ref="gfa-places-1933">Dublin</placeName> has had such a line in operation for some time now), and on my pending return from the north of England I shall doubtless have occasion to make further remarks on this great innovation. Since it is still fiercely contested, if only on account of the many interests imperilled by it, I shall confine myself for now to observing that the rails are not only thinner than those of the ordinary railway alongside it, but also thinner than those that I saw in France and Germany – unless my eyes, in which I generally have great confidence, deceive me. How much difference in weight such a ⅓ reduction in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">thickness</term> and breadth actually brings per mile of line, assuming that third to be truly superfluous, I leave it to those to calculate who know, as does Nature herself, how to apply the lex parsimoniae without impairing solidity.</p>
                <p>At last I had the pleasure of arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1845-07-21T18:00:00" n="31">London</placeName> – healthy and happy, thank God – at 6 o’clock in the evening, and half an hour later was at my lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2131" when="1845-07-21T18:30:00" n="32">Bull &amp; Mouth Inn</placeName> located opposite the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2132">Post Office</placeName>. Thus a journey that had not been entirely free of travails, and with it today’s diary entry, ended with a letter <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>.</p>
        </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Alte und neue Bekanntschaften in London, 22. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>My most pressing appointment on the <date when="1845-07-22">22nd</date> was at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1845-07-22" n="33">mint</placeName>, where I was to meet Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, an outstanding <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588414" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8917">chemist</term>, who holds the important post of “Master of the Die Office”. On being told that he was in the country, I left him a copy of the letter, which I had previously translated into <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName>, that the assayer Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7848">Haindl</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName> had been so kind as to write to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7770">Barre</persName> at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1602">mint</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, extolling the quality of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">coin punch</term> with which I had supplied him, and left again with a promise to return the next day. —Then I went to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1845-07-22" n="34" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, a shareholder in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">large ironworks</term>, to whom my friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7525">E.</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Z.</placeName> had been so kind as to commend me, as also to several other most excellent iron and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel manufacturers</term> in the North of England. Mr. K. complained about the large number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term> that crack when <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">tempered</term>, and how even very dextrous workers have accidents with them. He then showed me one such punch, of a very low height, which in desperation they had sought to remedy by actually <term ref="gfa-keywords-194">welding</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> onto <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. This punch, of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter and octagonal in shape, presumably because round forging would have opened it up in the middle, had been kept low that it might remain whole on tempering, though its thinness also meant that it did not last long.</p>
                <p>I had a long conversation with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8263">K.’s son</persName> about the smelting of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and then again with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, for as I said, he is himself a shareholder in <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588415"/> a large ironworks as well as being a highly skilled smelter who has already won a prize for his work. —I left with an invitation to come again whenever I wished and the assurance that his father would be delighted to make my acquaintance and to commend me to a large ironworks in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2078">Yorkshire</placeName>, whose smelting with coke and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">cold blast</term> (as opposed to the hot blast used with anthracite) produces very good iron. Remarking on my ability to express myself adequately on the subjects in question, or so it seemed to him, he was confident that I would be well received there. After leaving him I proceeded to an esteemed compatriot of mine, Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-22" n="35"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Imthurn</persName></placeName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1646">Fenchurch Street</placeName>, and from there, on the off-chance that he might still be in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, went to call on my nephew Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">A. Winz</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">family</persName>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Imthurn and I talked for some time about the most pressing matter of the day in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, namely the means by which we might, with outside help, finance a <term ref="gfa-keywords-169"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">railway line</placeName></term> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> to Schaffhausen and from there to <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanz</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The letter from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7971">Zündel</persName> explaining in detail the obvious advantages of building a railway along the above route that I had delivered to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8254">P.</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, having first made a copy of the same, I now handed over to <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588416" break="no"/> Mr. Imthurn, along with still more details of the planned undertaking, that they might be of service to him here in promoting the formation of a company for this purpose in England.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer besucht das Patentamt, 23. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>After visiting Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-23" n="36"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Imthurn</persName></placeName> again, I returned to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1845-07-23" n="37"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582">mint</orgName></placeName>, where Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> welcomed me as an old friend. Since he had already examined the sample <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term> that I had left there the day before, he placed an order for the same in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">steel</term>, which he had hitherto procured from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman</persName>, he said, albeit with uneven results. I now showed him the components of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion lock</term> made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">cast bar iron</term>, which he found very interesting, and in answer to my question as to whether such a thing had ever been made in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> remarked that not only did he not know of a single instance of it but it had long been deemed all but impossible. Just as we were beginning to talk in greater depth about this object that seemed to matter so much to him, two gentlemen arrived wishing to speak to him forthwith, whereupon he asked me to visit him again on my return from the north of England, which I had told him was where I intended to go next after leaving him. Having been given an incorrect house number, my long walk from the mint to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-07-23" n="38"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">Winz</persName></placeName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-2135">Frederick Street</placeName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2112">Grays Inn Lane</placeName> was all for nothing, and I was glad to have time <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588417"/> to visit the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-23" n="39"><term ref="gfa-keywords-239">Register Office for Patent Applications</term></placeName><note>Möglicherweise besuchte Fischer Moses Poole in seinem privaten <placeName ref="gfa-places-2219">Patentbüro</placeName>.</note> and there acquaint the secretary, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName>, with my appendage of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708">caveats</term> to the priority of two of my inventions, the one of which now reads:<emph rend="italic">«for an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term>, proper to be mixed and fused with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">Pig-iron</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Steel</term> of every description, and also <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">Bar</term> or forged, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-2965">Scrape-iron</term>;»</emph> and the other: <emph rend="italic">«for a new way of making Horseshoes, and also Shoes for all other Kinds of Cattle»</emph>.</p>
                <p>He was very friendly, and as it seemed to him that I had not quite understood certain remarks of his, gave me a booklet about patent applications and how one must conduct oneself when making one, inviting me to come again the following day.</p>
                <p>At this juncture I cannot help but remark on what a difference I noticed between this – one might almost call it – amiability and the unpolished manners and moroseness of many an official in other countries.</p>
                <p>As it rained almost the whole day, and I had long errands to run, I took a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term>, which cost me 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">sh.</term> or 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> per hour. —That occasioned me sufficient opportunity to see the dangers and disadvantages of London’s much vaunted wooden paving, which it seems that even the circumspect and scrupulous English have all too hastily adopted, as many of the most frequented streets in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588418"/> are now paved in this way. Whenever it rains, the filth composed of dust, horse dung, abraded wood and detritus of all kinds becomes as slippery as black ice so that coachmen and carriers – whose horses, owing to the stone-paved streets in between, naturally do not wear <term ref="gfa-keywords-9709">sharpened shoes</term> for this purpose – are able to proceed only very slowly, yet still slide away and even fall from time to time. My coachman cursed the paving and said that in winter it was much worse.</p>
                <p>Having covered such distances, some of them by cab, some on foot, I concluded the day with letters to my <persName ref="gfa-actors-148"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">three sons</persName></persName></persName>, who are now established in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, telling them of my safe arrival in England and of the business affairs that occasioned the journey. I then had lunch, or rather supper, since it was after 7 o'clock by then, in a very genteel <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">coffeehouse</term> (the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2136" when="1845-07-23T19:00:00" n="41" cert="0">Post Office Coffeehouse</placeName>), where for exactly the same spread, a meal with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term> costs half what it does in the so-called hotels, where the luxuriousness of the interiors, as in the one in which I am currently residing, is excessive, but still has to be paid for by the guests.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Neveu Winz und hüttenmännisches Fachsimpeln mit Herrn K., 24. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>On the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1845-07-24">24th</date></placeName>, having obtained the correct address, I visited my nephew Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-07-24" n="42"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">Winz</persName></placeName> and his <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">family</persName>, but found him not at home, though I <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588419"/> was to meet him later at Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-24" n="43"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im-Thurn’s</persName></placeName>, who kindly accompanied me to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-24" n="44">Register Office</placeName>. There, for a registration fee of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds</term> and 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> (25 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>) Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName> entered my petition for two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708"><term ref="gfa-keywords-239">caveats</term></term> in the protocol just as I had previously written them up and presented to him. On the way back I again called on Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1845-07-24" n="45" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, to discuss with him some matters relating to the smelting of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and then again with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, and with hot or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">cold blast</term>. He told me that in general, smelting with anthracite is done with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9712">hot blast</term>, the air for which has to pass through a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9711">system of siphons</term> in which it is heated to a temperature at which <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> would melt, while the anthracite, having had to make the long journey through a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">furnace shaft</term> of 48 to 50 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in height, has already turned to coke by the time it enters the smelting chamber, whereas if coke is used directly cold blast is applied.</p>
                <p>He showed me a drawing of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1877"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2148">Alfredton</placeName></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1925">Derbyshire</placeName><note>Möglicherweise handelte es sich um <placeName ref="gfa-places-2215">Butterley Works</placeName>.</note>, which 40 years previously the proprietor <term ref="gfa-keywords-8491"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7601">Wilkinson</persName></term> had introduced at the Bradley <placeName ref="gfa-places-1752"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1756">Bradley ironworks</placeName></term></placeName>, but which since then had not received the attention, either in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> or on the Continent, that the nature of it deserved. I soon afterwards had an opportunity to persuade myself of its most salient advantage <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588420"/> in the operation of a small <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">cupola furnace</term> fired with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">charcoal</term>, which was blasted with air through not just one or two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9715">nozzles</term> on opposite sides of the furnace, as is done here and there, but three of nozzles spaced apart in an equilateral triangle.</p>
                <p>While in some places in England the stand for this is made of refractory <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">brick</term>, here the most excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-9714">sandstone</term> was used, as it was for the building itself. The iron obtained from smelting ore with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> was at any rate better, he said, though it was also dearer in most cases, since in his experience, 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term>, converted into coke, weighed only 3¾ cwt, and 2½ cwt of coke was necessary to extract 1 cwt of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9009">pig iron</term> from 35-per-cent ore. — My best source of information on this matter, he added, would be the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2137">Low Moor Ironworks</placeName>, where they smelted with cold blast and coke, to which I was to convey a letter of his. The works of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7794"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2215">Butlery Iron Company</placeName></orgName> in which he himself had a stake, meanwhile, used anthracite and hot blast. Exactly how low and narrow a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">coke-fired blast furnace</term> would have to be at its 3 principal diameters he could not say, though he was able to tell me where I might surely learn the same.</p>
                <p>After dinner, which was at 5 o’clock in the afternoon, <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588421"/> I went for a walk through <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1611" when="1845-07-24T17:00:00" n="46">Cheapside</placeName> and along <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1612" when="1845-07-24" n="47">Ludgate Hill</placeName> as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2026" when="1845-07-24" n="48">Fleet Street</placeName>, where whatever wares it may contain, one store after another seeks to outdo all the others in abundance, variety, elegance, and indeed luxury, and where, quite apart from whatever else is to be found stacked up in other English cities, and quite apart from the thousands of ships that come and go, one is soon persuaded that this country really is the world’s marketplace answering the world’s demand.</p>
                <p>As an example of this luxury, I shall mention a <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2139" when="1845-07-24" n="49">shop</placeName> I saw that sells shawls, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9452">silks</term> and such like fashion accessories. The said shop has ceilings twice the normal height, that is 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, and its entrance takes the shape of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9850">inward-pointing convex triangle</term>, whose severed apex is the doorway. The 4 points on each side are the 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term> columns, the spaces between which are filled by 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>, arranged to face each other so that what one actually sees are 8 panes of 18 feet in height and 3½ feet in width, behind which all the finest things are piled up in tiers. The inside walls, moreover, are likewise covered in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>, which at night, especially, when all the many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> are burning, makes for a most surprising sight on account of their being multiplied by all the many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>. This shop is located in the building called <placeName ref="gfa-places-2139">Gloucester House</placeName> <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588422"/> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612">Ludgate Hill</placeName>, which is owned by <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7852">Harvey &amp; Son</orgName>. —I lingered for a long time in front of this magazine in which all the most precious of the aforementioned articles were assembled and amassed, but still have no idea how this profligate display might retain its interest, given how much competition there is from others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer und Neveu Winz besuchen die Polytechnical Institution, 25. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1845-07-25">Today</date></placeName> my route more than once took me past the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2150" when="1845-07-25" n="50"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9718">statue</term></placeName> of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7756">Duke of Wellington</persName> erected two years ago, which shows him as a mounted general and whose oval plinth is inscribed solely with the name “Wellington”. Who modelled it and cast it I do not know<note>Der Künstler war <persName ref="gfa-actors-8264">Francis Leggatt Chantrey</persName>.</note>, but that the art of casting has brought forth a so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9719">patina</term> or Aerugo nobilis (which normally is at once a result and marker of great age), while the gentleman himself is still alive seems to me to be a breach of decorum. No such error was made on the outstanding casts to be seen in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName>, apart from there where it served to make them more readily apparent or promised to show the accomplishment of the artist to better advantage than would a wholly dark silhouette. Whether the horse is too large and too fat in relation to the figure of Wellington I dare not say, as nothing could be further from my mind than to pretend to be a judge of art.</p>
                <p>This morning, after a visit to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-25" n="51">Patent Office</placeName>, where I received the 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708">caveats</term> for my inventions from Mr. <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588423"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName>, I accompanied my nephew Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">A. Winz</persName> to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8341"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2140" when="1845-07-25" n="52">Polytechnical Institution</placeName></orgName> to see the curious objects that the arts and crafts of this country have lately brought forth, first and foremost among them the “working model” of the much talked-of, and, in respect of its practical utility, frequently and fiercely contested invention of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric railway</term> set up there by Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7944">Samuda</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7797">Clegg</persName>. The new objects, most of them from the field of engineering, were so extremely numerous that it would have taken days just to inspect them properly, nor does space permit even a superficial enumeration of the same; suffice it to say, therefore, that only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> can something at once so great and so instructive be accomplished, since only a <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">city</placeName> that will soon number 1½ million inhabitants can supply enough inquiring minds for the admission tickets needed to cover the costs of this undertaking. Here, therefore, I shall mention only the small, I believe 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> that had to run constantly in order to work the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term> needed keep the tube, which is circa 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term> long with an internal bore of about 5/4<term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term>, or so it seemed to me, sufficiently emptied of air to drive the 5 little wagons hooked one behind the other, each of which had a seat for one person. The front wagon, of course, <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588424"/> was attached to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> by means of a vertical rod. The rimmed tubes, moreover, each have a narrow opening or slit at the top that is opened only by the piston approaching from some distance away and then is closed again by special valves, thus ensuring that the said piston is always travelling through an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">airless</term> and air-tight tube. This extremely fast railway was mounted on a 3-foot-high gantry running alongside a basin filled with water 14 feet deep, on which a little <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> chugged around and a boy in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8858">diving bell</term> was dropped down to the bottom. —I must in all honesty confess that I arrived in England with quite a strong prejudice against atmospheric railways, doubting both their feasibility and what I imagined to be the manifold difficulties of maintaining a good, air-tight system capable of operating without interruption. Now that I have seen this model and the efficacy of the method – notwithstanding the small diameter of the tube – in action, however, and have learned that just such a railway, albeit not of any great length, has been running daily in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1933">Dublin</placeName> at greater speeds than a conventional <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> ever could and that the said railway is indeed used so that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">parliament</term>, responding to the extremely favourable expert report on it, <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588425"/> will not object to a concession being granted to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8269">company</orgName> now wishing to run such a railway from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1918">Croydon</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, a distance of 48 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, which owing to the advanced state of the preparations for the same will be able to go into service very soon and whose shareholders will doubtless have verified the feasibility of every aspect of the venture, I have now changed my mind and believe that atmospheric railways will supplant or modify conventional locomotive-driven railways if not wholly, then at least in part. As it is worth making the effort to know the factors that speak both for and against this new invention, and to do so before it becomes part of our lives so that when that happens, it will become apparent from its constant success or want of success which side was the most right, I would like to devote some space to the pros and cons of this most important matter such as I have been able to ascertain during my stay here in England.</p>
                <p>One principal objection that is made is that were there to be even the tiniest gap between the tubes and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term> being drawn along, as might happen very easily, the wagons would inevitably come to a standstill, as it would no longer be possible to create a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">vacuum</term>. <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588426"/> Responding to this certainly legitimate objection, Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7944">Samuda</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7797">Clegg</persName> claim that the air pump, which has a diameter of 57½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term>, is powerful enough to render the iron pipes airless over their entire length, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9176">pressure gauges</term> at either end at the same level, within just 5 to at most 6 minutes, so that even if air were to stream in through an imperceptible crack (a large one would be noticed immediately and could be refilled or another section of pipe inserted inside it so as not to occasion any great delay), the vacuum, though not complete, would still be sufficient to drive the piston, and with it the wagons, to the nearest station, which at worst would be ½ an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English mile</term> away (circa 5500 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>) – and at an acceptable speed, too, especially if, as could be easily enough accomplished, the number of piston strokes set in motion by the air pump were multiplied by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>. Having arrived at the station, a new system of pipes would commence, as it does in any case at one-mile intervals. —</p>
                <p>The second principal objection is the cost. This was likewise countered by the assertion, supported by a detailed calculation published in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9570">Times illustrated</term>, that the installation and operation of an atmospheric railway would cost less than ⅔ of what a railway run with conventional locomotives costs. To delve into the details <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588427" break="no"/> of this calculation would be going too far here, though it seems to me that this is a matter of great importance to railway entrepreneurs, since one cannot presume to present obviously incorrect information to a public such as that in England, where competent judges abound.</p>
                <p>The day’s business ended quite early with the purchase of various items and packing for tomorrow’s departure for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, 205 miles hence, the train for which leaves from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666">Euston Station</placeName>, which is itself some miles away from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2231">City of London</placeName>, where I am currently <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2131" when="1845-07-25" n="53">residing</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>London–Leeds, 26. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>For a fare of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> took me all the way to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1666" when="1845-07-26T11:00:00" n="54">Euston Station</placeName>, where for a seat in the second class to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> I had to pay 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pound</term> and 15 shillings or 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9722">Reichsgeld</term>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">train</term> departed at 11 o’clock in the morning. Notwithstanding the 20 stops and more en route with just enough time for people to get on and off, and that we were held up in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2074" when="1845-07-26" n="55">Weldon</placeName> for 5 and in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1257" n="56">Derby</placeName> for 25 minutes, so that we might eat some lunch, we still arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-26T18:30:00" n="59">Leeds</placeName> at half past 6 that evening, meaning that the astonishing distance of 205 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English</term> or 41 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term>, which translates into a rate of 12 miles per hour or twenty-four <term ref="gfa-keywords-9723">Wegstunden</term>, was overcome at a speed such as I have encountered nowhere else. It is all but impossible to observe anything at such a speed, though from time to time, there where the terrain by chance afforded an expansive view, <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588428"/> not far from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-30" when="1845-07-26" n="57">Coventry</placeName> where the hay was being brought in, I did have an opportunity to do so; it was a most <term ref="gfa-keywords-9724">instructive sight</term>, revealing how with just one horse and one man, mown grass might be swiftly and evenly distributed over a very large meadow that it might dry all the faster. —For the horse was hitched to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">hollow wooden cylinder</term> of some 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in length and 4 feet in diameter. This consisted of nothing but laths, which were spaced about 10 to 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> apart and nailed onto the two base plates or discs at either end. These in turn had an axle passing through them, attached to whose protruding <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">hubs</term>, as on a clover roller, were the two inward-pointing shafts that formed the traces for the horse. The cylinder was filled with mown hay through a hatch in the roller, like that on a cylindrical <term ref="gfa-keywords-9725">coffee roaster</term> only with slits. Once the hatch was closed, the man had the horse set off whereupon the cylinder rotated so that every time one of the openings was facing downwards some of the mown grass fell out of it, always across the full length of the slit and always at the same distance from the previous one, until finally the cylinder was empty and had to be refilled.</p>
                <p>The passenger carriages were fitted with something very sensible that I have so far seen nowhere else except in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>: namely three round apertures in the ceiling, which on the outside are shielded with a bell or cap made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">iron sheet</term>, <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588429"/> whose side walls in turn have around 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">slits</term> in them so as to promote the circulation of air without troubling the passengers, as when cold weather or rain or storms make it necessary to keep all the windows shut. At night, the middle of the three apertures is fitted with a lantern, since the trains in England run both day and night.</p>
                <p>The optical illusion of the crooked <placeName ref="gfa-places-2141">spire</placeName> of <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1917" when="1845-07-26" n="58">Chesterfield</placeName>, which I reported in my earlier diary, delighted me all over again, as did the farmers’ pretty little <term ref="gfa-keywords-9726">windmills</term>, which turn into the wind all by themselves, and each one of which supplies as much flour on average as any large household might need. Almost all the cuttings along the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to Leeds are through first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9727">marl</term> and then <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">limestone</term>, the strata and fissures of the more northerly areas bearing a certain resemblance to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2061">Swabian Alb</placeName>. Despite being tended with great care, the fruits of the field were far behind, and nowhere near as fine as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> or at <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">home</placeName>. Another peculiarity that warrants mention is that on <date when="1845-07-26">26th July</date>, all the women in the carriage were wearing fur collars around their necks and were wrapped in shawls.</p>
                <p>As I said, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> after 6 o’clock in the evening and took lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2142" when="1845-07-26" n="60">White Horse Hotel</placeName>. —In the dining room, a gentleman clad all in black had no sooner entered than he lay down, dirty boots and all, on the very fine canapé. <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588430"/> Yet no one said a word, not even when he had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipe</term> brought to him that he might smoke in that very same attitude, which was all that had hitherto been missing to demonstrate the kind of man he was. Eighteen years had passed since my last visit to England, and I had imagined that since so much else had changed in the way of transport and domestic interiors, then surely many of the customs and habits and the way people dressed would have changed, too, only this was not the case. Foreigners make little impression on these taciturn, obdurate islanders, and too few of them ever reach the interior in any case. And should those that do become too bumptious, as so many peddlers of wisdom are prone to do with us good-natured <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName>, here they are simply ridiculed, or, better still, treated with utter contempt. The Englishman knows very well what he wants and what he can and is proud and ambitious, though he does not advertise this, unlike certain other people who just love to adorn themselves in whatever scraps of glory they can scrape together.</p>
                <p>To return to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9072">tobacco-smoking</term>: I had imagined that since this nasty habit had made such alarming progress on the Continent these past few years, it could not be otherwise than that the English would likewise have found it impossible to resist; yet that was not the case at all. I believe I am not mistaken in this, <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588431"/> and gladly cite persons who have recently returned from England and report that among a thousand male persons of all classes one will find scarcely a single tobacco smoker.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Betrachtungen zum Verkehr in England, 27. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>—The whole <date when="1845-07-27">day</date> was taken up with writing and the evening with a walk, although it was very windy and cold, and with inquiries into <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">stage-coaches</term> that might be leaving for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1907">Bradford</placeName>, a small town 26 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, on the morrow, say, that being a Sunday, which in Leeds is observed even more sombrely than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, making it impossible to visit anyone. I was told that I might leave for Bradford on any one of the ten departures that day. This uncommonly frequent service to all sorts of places and with it the circulation of people, and hence of money, is a consequence of the extraordinary network of railways that has already spread out all over <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and of being able to travel from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666">Euston-Station</placeName> near London to the north of England within just 24 hours, there being 12 trains both day and night as well as 2 “extra trains”. Consequently, there have to be stage-coaches on hand to bring those arriving and departing from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">station</term> to their destinations, which may be 10 or even 20 miles hence. — To return to the Sabbath, I noticed that not until 7 o’clock in the evening did large numbers of people of every age and sex come out of the church, even as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9728">Methodist</term> preacher on the market square <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588432" break="no"/> was preaching most fervently down from his perch to the rapt crowd below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Low Moor Ironworks, 28. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Today, exactly 14 days after my departure from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>, I was to see a member of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8090">family</persName> again, and there, where <ref type="cross" target="../1814/27">30 years ago</ref>, at almost exactly the same time of year, I enjoyed such friendship as would be repeated, always with the same warmth, on all my later visits to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, as outlined in my diaries of those trips.</p>
                <p>I knew by then that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">old Mr. Gott</persName> had died some years previously, but was received in the customary manner by his son, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">John Gott</persName>, whom I met betimes in the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-28" n="61">counting house</placeName><note>Es ist unklar, ob Fischer die <persName ref="gfa-actors-8090">Familie Gott</persName> an ihrer Wohnaddresse in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2220">27 Guildford Street</placeName> oder einen ihrer beiden Fabriken <placeName ref="gfa-places-1788">Armley Mill</placeName> oder <placeName ref="gfa-places-1795">Park Mill</placeName> aufsuchte.</note>. He immediately invited me to dine with him at his spendid <placeName ref="gfa-places-1794">country seat</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1975">Kirkdale</placeName>, 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, which I politely declined on the grounds that I wished to visit the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2137">Low Moor</placeName>, which had been commended to me most warmly. —“Both are possible, my friend”, said he; “just come to me, and I shall appoint one of my clerks to drive you to the place [here he glanced at the clock], where in just a few minutes you will be met by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">Kutsche</term> that will take you to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1907">Bradford</placeName>. There, take a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9122">gig</term> to Low Moor, which is 3 miles hence, and be sure to have him wait ready to take you back to Bradford afterwards. You can then take the 4 o’clock coach back to Leeds, and since we dine at around 6 o’clock or later, you <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588433"/> will be back just in time to join us, my country seat being hard by Kirkdale, as you know.” I could not object to any of this, and as the old counting house clerk had already taken his hat down off its hook, I commended myself and left. “I was very glad to see you again”, said the clerk, once outside the door and on the street. “I recognized you right away, though 18 years have passed since you were last with us.” I, too, remembered him, and being told of the then still secret method of using a solution of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">caoutchouc</term> to render cloth water-proof.</p>
                <p>On arriving at the inn, I scarcely had time to go inside since the coach was just about to depart. —The road from Leeds to Bradford leads past <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1975" when="1845-07-28" n="62">Kirkdale</placeName> (an Old English or rather Anglo-Saxon word, Kirchthal in German), not far from which, situated in a park-like setting on a pretty little hill grown over with oaks and other deciduous trees, is Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott’s</persName> splendid <placeName ref="gfa-places-1794">country seat</placeName>. From there, one looks out onto the fine ruins, some of them with their forms intact and charmingly overgrown with ivy and other plants, of one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-6532"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9750">monasteries destroyed</term></term> under <persName ref="gfa-actors-7854">Henry VIII</persName> which gave this area its name, and which owing to its many factories, ironworks and <term ref="gfa-keywords-6116">coal mines</term> is now full of activity so that one passes by fields, <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588434"/> villages and individual houses of the most varied appearance.</p>
                <p>Not far outside Leeds, and then without interruption as far as Low Moor, I saw still more of the extraordinary industry of the English: for scattered along the edge of the country road were blocks that were somewhat prismatic in shape and that owing to their play of colours I would have taken for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">marble</term>, had they not been so lavishly glazed over. Later I saw some people working at these blocks, busily breaking them up for use as road-building material, whereupon I realised that this must be <term ref="gfa-keywords-336">slag</term> from a blast furnace at a nearby <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>, which to obtain a certain quantity of the same for processing, and to facilitate and expedite its loading and unloading, is evidently run off into iron crates. These are shaped as described above so that the 10-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>-heavy mass might fall out of them all the more easily and be ground up for use in lieu of gravel, which perhaps does not occur naturally in this region, making iron slag the best material that can be had for this purpose. Arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1907" when="1845-07-28T12:00:00" n="63">Bradford</placeName> at around 12 o’clock, I took a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9122">gig</term> (a two-wheeled chaise) at the Sun Inn staging post, and had him drive me to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2137" when="1845-07-28" n="64">Low Moor</placeName>, which to judge by the name I imagined to be on the valley floor, as indeed it was. —But the smoke from the 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnaces</term>, the long row of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9232">coking ovens</term>, <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588435"/> where small lumps of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> are passed through cylindrical sieves to separate them from the larger pieces and then <term ref="gfa-keywords-9732">coked</term> inside closed chambers stoked by women, and the long <term ref="gfa-keywords-9224">coking lines</term>, where the large but not necessarily excellent anthracite is coked in the customary way, as well as from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9400">refining</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">puddling</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8849">bloom furnaces</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9135">annealing furnaces</term> for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mills</term> made it impossible to take in the site of several <term ref="gfa-keywords-9730">acres</term> in size and criss-crossed all over with <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> bearing wagons solely for its own use in its entirety. On entering the same, or rather the “porter’s lodge”, my horse, at my request, was immediately unhitched and taken to a stable without my being pestered with probing questions as to who I was or where I had come from and what I wanted etc., as happens elsewhere. On the contrary, I was promptly assigned a young man who was to escort me to the owner of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7787">works</orgName>. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7812">Dawson</persName>, as the said gentleman was called, read the letter that I had handed to him and then, being somewhat unsteady on his feet, seized his hat and stick and took me on a 2-hour tour of the whole works, starting with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9231">charcoaling</term> and then proceeding to the blast furnaces and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term>, in which much to my astonishment they still had <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberating</term> furnaces, though they were used only for very particular purposes, he told me; presumably to cast <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">rollers</term>, which, <emph rend="italic">nota bene</emph>, they make themselves, <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588436"/> and for which they do not use a <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">cupola furnace</term>, since such a furnace would be unlikely to produce such very fine and very hard results. From there we went to the other aforementioned furnaces and to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9731">bellows</term> driven by two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> of 160 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> each. This supplies the cold <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">blast</term> used for all the furnaces here, since hot blast does not work for blast furnaces fired by coke, they tell me, though it does for those fired by anthracite. The blast pressure here is just 3½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> per [<term ref="gfa-keywords-9851"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">square foot</term></term>]<note>«Quadratfuss» im Erstdruck als Piktogramm dargestellt.</note>, which is saying a lot. — What interested me in particular about this works, and demonstrates how readily the English adopt whatever works in practice, was its use of a discovery made by that genius <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName>. — Perkins, of course, is an <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">American</placeName>, and as he himself told me 18 years ago, used to work as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9138"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8720">goldsmith</term></term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2073">Washington</placeName>. There he found that even the hardest English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">file</term> might be <term ref="gfa-keywords-8662">cut in twain</term> using no more than a very thin disc of soft <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">iron sheet</term>, as long as the said disc was clamped into a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9643">lathe</term> or something similar and rotated extremely fast. This method was being applied here on a large scale, where two such discs of circa 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in diameter and spaced far enough apart (I would guess about 10 feet) were attached to the same <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">drive shaft</term> and kept rigid and upright by <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588437"/> thick iron counterplates reaching up to 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> from the edge. These discs then rotate uncommonly fast. The finished rail rolls out of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term> and, if somewhat bent, is laid out on a long and completely flat iron plate to be hammered straight with a wooden mallet before being pushed against the spinning discs and so cut asunder by the same, as if it were mere <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">wood</term>. Underneath, the discs pass through a trough fed by a constant stream of cold water to keep them cool.</p>
                <p>The location is as favourable as it could possibly be for the operation of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>. It is close to major cities, most notably Leeds, and is surrounded by mineshafts from which not just <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">limestone</term>, but also <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> are extracted; and as the headgear for the mineshaft is at a higher elevation than the works, the railway wagons loaded with these materials can slowly roll down the incline towards it, the gradient being such that they move of their own accord without ever gaining too much speed, and so arrive at their destination, where they are unloaded ready to be pulled back up the hill by a horse on a different set of rails. Thanks to the coincidence of these circumstances, Mr. Dawson told me, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of anthracite, which is 112 English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> in weight, supplied to the charcoaling, or rather <term ref="gfa-keywords-9732">coking</term>, plant costs less than a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term>, or 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9722">Reichsvaluta</term>, to be more exact. The iron ores are poor, yielding only <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588438"/> 25 per cent iron, and have to be <term ref="gfa-keywords-8652">roasted</term> before they can be stoked into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term>. The limestone flux is added at a rate of 25 pounds per cwt extracted iron, meaning 6 pounds per cwt ore. As for coal, 3 cwt <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> is required per cwt of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">pig iron</term> to be run off, that is, 75 pounds per cwt of ore, which seems a lot to me. If the ratios of anthracite were reduced, one would need 120 pounds of anthracite per cwt, that is, circa 480 pounds for every cwt of smelted pig iron. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">pig iron</term> produced here is a fine grey colour, but not always of an even grain. Samples are therefore taken of every <term ref="gfa-keywords-3479">tapping</term>, and are duly numbered, as is the tapping itself, which forms a grate consisting entirely of small wedges like those used in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">cupola furnace</term>. The English are indeed much more conscientious about delivering iron of a consistently high quality to their consumers than are many iron masters on the Continent. But they also know from experience how much, in every respect, depends on the quality of the iron; and those who are familiar with how difficult it is to produce good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term> with coke or anthracite will not be surprised at the care taken with this, and indeed with the whole process as well, from the resmelting of the pig iron, to the fine iron, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8538">puddling</term> and the welding off, and still more treatment after that such as I never saw elsewhere, <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588439"/> the result of which is the most excellent iron made with coke that I have ever seen, even though it is sold dearer than all the others too. —It was time to return to Leeds, and I took my leave of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7812">Dawson</persName>, who had honoured the letter commending me to him by being most accommodating, providing me with not only the detailed explanations I desired but also samples of ore, limestone, coal, coke and iron at all stages of production, from pig iron to finished bar iron, for which I thanked him most heartily.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Abendgesellschaft in der Villa Gott, 28. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">post coach</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1960">Halifax</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-keywords-1760">Leeds</placeName> arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1907" when="1845-07-28T16:00:00" n="65">Bradford</placeName> at 4 o’clock and at 6 o’clock I was at Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott’s</persName> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1794" when="1845-07-28T18:00:00" n="66">country seat</placeName>.</p>
                <p>As he had not yet returned from town, a footman led me into a room where I might perform my toilet – which indeed was not unnecessary since I was returning from the bosom of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> where one is constantly enveloped in a cloud of smoke, coal dust and steam – and bade me await his master in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-1883">library</term>. With its exquisitely bound works both ancient and modern, its fine paintings and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">engravings</term>, its busts of Carrara <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">marble</term> standing on columns of coloured marble with white pedestals and furnishings of a piece, this room was a haven for the mind of anyone seeking respite from the travails of daily business.</p>
                <p><pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588440"/> The arrangement of three stuffed night owls standing sentinel in front of the great <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror</term> did not betray the purpose of their being there, and naturally I was loath to ask it of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-keywords-7843">Gott</persName> when he later came to fetch me and take me to the reception room, where 4 more gentlemen and 5 ladies were present. On entering the highly ornate dining room shortly after seven o’clock, we sat down, waited on by three footmen as well as the “butler”, to a most splendid dinner, which I, despite having gone for 12 hours with nothing but a little <term ref="gfa-keywords-9734">marshmallow tea</term> procured for me by an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9735">apothecary</term> in Bradford, could not enjoy. Being hoarse and unwell owing to a cold that I had caught while still in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, and with a medicine bottle in my pocket, I had to take care not to make matters worse and had to leave the many glasses of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wine</term> of all kinds served by the said butler untouched before me. After the ladies had withdrawn, as is customary here, the gentlemen remained seated for drinks and to discuss matters of interest to them, and it did not take long before the conversation turned to <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>. As Mr. Gott told me that he was very interested in this matter and would be accompanying an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9092">engineer</term> to the site of a new branch line the very next morning, I felt myself at liberty to raise the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">project</placeName> for a railway from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanz</placeName>, and to <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588441"/> urge upon him the importance of the favourable lay of the land, noting that to execute our plans we would nevertheless need outside capital since our own powers would not be sufficient to the task. —During dinner, it had seemed to me that I had seen the gentleman sitting opposite me somewhere before. With the ladies absent, we were now much closer to each other than hitherto, and when Mr. Gott suddenly cried out: “But let us hear what your compatriot has to say about this!” I immediately went over to him and discovered that it was Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7782">Bischof</persName> of Basel, with whom I had become acquainted some 18 or 20 years earlier, again as a friend of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName>. I was glad to be able to appeal to him in this or that matter, and he confirmed everything that I had hitherto asserted. —The footman then came to summon us into the tea room, leaving me with just enough time to ask Mr. Gott to ponder the matter and promising to write to him about it in due course. —As is well known, nowhere does one drink better <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, and with such circumstance, as one does in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. Though I had been foregoing this beverage for many years in the belief that it prevented me sleeping, here it proved a true elixir, since being unwell I had for several days been afflicted with the most terrible thirst. At the back of this tea room, which with its exquisite furnishings, wonderfully fragrant flowers and <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588442"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9580">hot-house plants</term>, its windows reaching almost down to the ground and glass doors giving onto the garden, might more properly be called a tea salon, was an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9736">organ</term> reaching almost to its very high ceiling. In the middle stood a large, round table of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8774">acajou</term> laid out with newspapers, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithographs</term> of the day and pamphlets illustrating the various phases in the marriage of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9862">Mr. Caudle &amp; his Wife</term>. Thanks to the typically English spirit of invention and improvement, the “changeable faces of <persName ref="gfa-actors-8273">Mistress Caudle</persName>” could be made to change by pulling a string attached to the back of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">engraving</term> that her physiognomy better fit the scene depicted. This is a device that the English clearly delight in, since one sees it displayed for sale in print shops everywhere at present.—Finally, to complete my description of this room, I have to note that on the day I was there, the <date when="1845-07-26">28th July</date>, there was a fire blazing in the hearth and that on leaving the house and stepping outside, one really did have the impression that the corn was becoming greener rather than yellower. —At around 10 o’clock I took my leave of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> and the assembled company, which at that moment was taking <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term>, and took the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> standing in front of the house to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-28T22:00:00" n="67">Leeds</placeName>, some 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> hence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer schreibt einen Brief an seine Enkelin, 29. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Almost the whole day was taken up with writing a long letter to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> and making a copy of the same, as well as <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588443" break="no"/> a letter to my granddaughter <persName ref="gfa-actors-7692">Mathilde</persName> so that my family back home will know where in the world I have got to, and concluded with my walking over to Mr. Gott's <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-29" n="68">counting house</placeName> and taking a stroll through that part of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">town</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The character of this city, which by the way is very large, is quite different from that of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. The general affluence and cleanliness of even the outlying streets, which is what we should apply as our measure, seems to me to be greater. Here, everyone who has hands works and earns a living by them. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">textile mills</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">flax spinning mills</term> are all flourishing, and the many <term ref="gfa-keywords-9341">obelisks</term> here, by which I mean the smoke stacks for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelters</term> that have multiplied so astonishingly and in some instances are 60 to 80 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> tall, are of greater benefit here than were their forebears in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName>, and when seen from a distance lend the city a very distinctive aspect. Except for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabs</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> to the station and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">post coaches</term> to the surrounding villages, there are not many people out riding or being driven, whereas the shops for the most part are attractive, and some of them well stocked.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Betrachtungen zum Eisenbahnwesen, 30. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Having spent almost the whole day writing, since the rainy weather that is more frequent in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> at this time of year did not permit us to go outside, I instead went through <term ref="gfa-keywords-9738">Bradshaw’s <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Railway</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Steam-Navigation</term>-Guide</term>, <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588444"/> which I had purchased while in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. I was astonished at how wide-ranging and detailed the information about <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> contained in this book actually is, and not just in relation to England but to other countries, too, those furthest afield from London being <placeName ref="gfa-places-1374">Alexandria</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-515">Constantinople</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-696">Petersburg</placeName>. And when one takes out the map of England and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019">Scotland</placeName> – all that is shown of <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Ireland</placeName> is the coastline and the distances of the various passages to England – and surveys the railways that have already been built, and even more so those that are in planning or for which concessions have been granted and in some cases are already being built, one no longer knows what to think or how one should imagine this song ending or where all the people who are to ride on these railways are to come from? —It is inevitable, I believe, that once the high-water mark has been reached, that is, once this railway-building has been taken to an extreme, a great crisis will ensue, after which only those railways (to say nothing of today’s <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, which given the current spirit of invention might easily be supplanted and rendered obsolete by some happily conceived and executed idea from one day to the next) will survive that run there where there is a natural need for them, namely those that operate from city to city, where there has been passenger and goods traffic for centuries and consequently <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588445"/> a demand. There will certainly have to be major reforms of how they operate if they are to pay off, for after comparing how they run here with those on the Continent, it seems to me that the number of personnel in relation to the number of journeys is very limited indeed (since to judge by the listings in Bradshaw, the trains run day and night with twenty departures every 24 hours). This explains why I have seen far fewer railwaymen’s cottages and fewer station-masters than elsewhere. Either the Englishmen are, or believe themselves to be, more sure of themselves, or, given the unusual speed with which one travels here, they would not be able to heed the warning signals early enough in any case; or perhaps the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term> lines running parallel to the railway might be used for signalling, though that seems improbable to me. One would expect these railways, through which people’s paths are crossing as never before, to make us more convivial; but of the eleven gentlemen in the dining room this evening, not one of them spoke a single word, unless it was with the attendant.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Reise nach Sheffield und Besuch eines alten Bekannten, 31. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>My business in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> concluded, I once again visited Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-31" n="69"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName></placeName> to discuss with him the probability, given how important connections by land and sea now are, of my finding in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> a company that might be inclined to join the shareholders from <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1899">Baden</placeName> that are investing in the – incidentally very short <pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588446"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185"><term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway line</term></placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Constanz</placeName>, and to remind him of the contents of the letter that I wrote him the day before yesterday, whereupon I received from him the assurance that he would write to me should such an occasion arise, and that if there were any other courtesy he might show me, he would do so most gladly. After receiving this renewed attestation of his friendship, I left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-31T13:00:00" n="70"> Leeds</placeName> at 1 o’clock on the branch line to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1845-07-31T15:00:00" n="71">Sheffield</placeName>, where I arrived at 3 o’clock. After first having lunch I set off to visit my old acquaintance Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1845-07-31" n="72"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName></placeName>. With 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908"> smelters</term> and 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9629">cementation furnaces</term> with which to convert <term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">Swedish iron</term> ore into <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> before smelting, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587">Sanderson &amp; Comp.</orgName> are the largest makers of cast steel in Sheffield.</p>
                <p>Just as I had imagined, I was greeted very amicably by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">old Mr. Sanderson</persName>, with whom I had made the journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1917">Chesterfield</placeName> to Sheffield <ref type="cross" target="../1825/57">20 years earlier</ref>, and was promptly taken on a tour of the whole works, which they certainly do not do with every guest.</p>
                <p>We went first to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9629">cementation furnaces</term>, one of which had only just recently been fired up, while the other was going at full tilt. Each of these furnaces had two chests filled with circa 160 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1779"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">Dannemora iron</term></placeName>, and three fires. This means that the flames <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588447"/> reverberate first in front of the chests, then in between them, and then up the rear wall, coming together again under the arch, where there are flues up into the chimney. Mr. Sanderson let me pull out a so-called eye, that is a plug of fireproof clay in the front wall of the furnace, that I might observe the play of the flames and the degree of heat inside the furnace, which it seemed to me had not yet reached its highest point, appearances being very deceptive whether the weather is fine or gloomy. From there we proceeded to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-121">steel foundry</term>, where nothing has changed these past twenty years – I might even say in the 50 years since <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName></persName> got his factory going. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">furnaces</term> are the same, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> are the same, and they are filled and loaded both cold and hot, the only difference being the funnel used in the latter case. —The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8634">pouring</term> was done with great care. Of the two first crucibles to be poured (each furnace has 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> containing circa 30 to 35 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>), one had a small hole and was more than half-emptied, whereupon the pourer quite sensibly poured off the remainder into the other crucible, since none of the crucibles, all of which have a flat and heavy lid, is truly full when it comes out of the furnace. The steel in this topped-up crucible was then carefully poured off in a thin and steady trickle into the middle of the <pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588448" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> sprue. The two crucibles inside the second furnace, which was opened immediately afterwards, were both good and were poured off in the same way. The pouring involves three men: the first lifts out the crucible and carries it to the sprues half-buried in a pit, the second holds it steady with his tongs, while the third uses a sharp <term ref="gfa-keywords-9740">crowbar</term> to prize off the lid and a small trowel to skim off the bits of <term ref="gfa-keywords-336">slag</term> floating on top. As there were several baskets of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> standing next to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelters</term>, I asked Mr. Sanderson how much coke he would need to smelt a Centner of steel, which he was able to tell me exactly. Believing that I had not understood him correctly, however, I repeated the question, to which he gave exactly the same answer as before. Now I was satisfied. When I told him the average consumption in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">my ironworks</placeName>, he cried out: <emph rend="italic">“You beat us! You beat us! You beat us!”</emph> One of the reasons, among many other, equally important ones, that I gave him as a possible cause of their high coke consumption he acknowledged as valid right away.</p>
                <p>Being still unwell, I did not pay any further visits today and concluded the day with the usual note-taking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Turton, Huntsman und chinesischer Tee, 1. August 1845</head>
                <p><date when="1845-08-01">August 1st.</date> —<placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> is a more attractive town than <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> and the surrounding countryside on one side of it is almost like <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>. It also seems more populous to me and to have even more <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588449"/> lavishly stocked shops with even more luxuries in their windows than in Leeds. But owing to the thousands of columns of black smoke that are constantly being replenished by the carts full of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> pulling up in front of them, anyone wanting to survey its incredible <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcan</persName> works from above would have to await a fine Sunday. Today, after paying my compliments to Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">T..... &amp; S..</orgName>, Manufacturers of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">Cast Steel</term></term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">Files</term></term>, I wanted to visit <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7540"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman’s hammer mill</persName></persName></placeName>, which is located next to a <placeName ref="gfa-places-2168">bridge</placeName> over the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">River Don</placeName>. 
                    TODO
                    <term ref="gfa-keywords-9337">Nähnadelfabrik</term> besuchen, und wegen einem Gedanken, der mir beigefallen, noch einmal mit Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName> sprechen.
                    
                    
                    I went first to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1845-08-01" n="74"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7543">T.....</persName></placeName>, where it seemed to me that my visit was embarrassing inasmuch as my name apparently meant nothing to them, as one of the gentlemen there told me. After exchanging a few compliments, therefore, I quickly took my leave. I was already at the gates through which the workshops and the counting house are reached (all the factories here are completely walled in and enclosed) when one of the gentlemen came after me and said that though I had surely seen similar factories, he would gladly show me his if I wished to see it. I accepted his offer out of politeness, but at the same time felt bound to show him, by the various remarks that I made both in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file smithy</term> and, even more so, in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">steel foundry</term>, where the smelting foreman visibly pricked up his ears, <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588450"/> that nothing of what they were showing me was either alien or new to me. —I was thereupon given some pieces of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> used to make them and the material they add to new crucibles to make them break like <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porcelain</term> and protect them against the corrosion of coke. I must say, incidentally, that I liked the way they did the actual smelting. Their ingots often had a depression on top, meaning that quite a lot had to be knocked off them at times; the coke consumption of an identically (and incorrectly) fitted furnace was somewhat lower than Mr. Sanderson’s, though the coke was dearer by 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">ton</term>, costing 15 instead of 14 shillings.</p>
                <p>That in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, where everything else is optimised, smelting should be lagging so far behind so that the maximum heat needed can be reached only when the ambient air is dry and cold is surprising; the most likely reason for this stability is on the one hand the cheapness of the fuel, and on the other the fact that the actual smelting is done by the smelters, whereas the gentlemen or factory owners attend only to the profits; and as their growing sales make these substantial indeed, they become so rich that they do not have to dream up new methods for that purpose, still less introduce them. <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588451"/> Their <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">steel smelters</term> as they are now can hardly be used to smelt pure <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term> without any carbon-containing additives or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platinum</term>, as I have done in mine, the proof of which, as mentioned earlier, I brought with me to England and just prior to the time of writing presented not only to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, but also to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></p>
                <p>Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7543">T.....</persName> was so kind as to give me directions to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9337">needle factory</term>, though what I had believed to be there, namely a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8973">wire-drawing works</term>, I did not find since that establishment is apparently located some miles outside <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>. The manufacture of such a small but important object was nevertheless interesting to see, even if one finds detailed descriptions of this same production process in various technological journals. Seeing the thousands of needles lying all at sixes and sevenses being shaken on an iron shovel to make them fall into line so that eventually they were all pointing in the same direction was a true pleasure. The beating and piercing of the eyes, the sharpening of the points, during which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9433">grinding stone</term>, which the “foreman” told me rotates at a rate of several hundred revolutions per minute, disappeared behind a dense shower of sparks, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">annealing</term> of the needles in oil and their fine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polishing</term> thereafter have, as I said, been adequately described elsewhere, though there was much to attract me in watching these various operations. <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588452"/> It is but a small part of human activity and endeavour, but how good it is that men, guided by what is practical and necessary, have applied themselves even to this business as one that is of real benefit to mankind, and how pathetic do those levellers of our times with their abysmal ideas look by comparison!</p>
                <p>Wishing to acquaint oneself with a city, and form a judgement of it in the space of just a few days, or even just a few hours, would be presumption bordering on the ridiculous; though to capture a few salient characteristics and summarise these can never be without interest.</p>
                <p>Here, therefore, I shall present only the one or other thing worthy of note that struck me on my morning and afternoon walks to all the many corners of this very industrious city, and leave it to others to comment as they see fit.</p>
                <p>Opposite the inn where I was residing <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1845-07-31" n="73">(Tontine house)</placeName> there was a certain Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8020">Schweppe</persName> (doubtless of German origin) who was selling a “Celestial Polishing Powder”. On entering his <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2183" when="1845-08-01" n="75">shop</placeName> I asked whether this powder might be applied to anything, and was told that yes, it might, though I forgot to inquire what kind of an effect it might have on certain people. —At the top of the same house were huge golden letters, almost two full stories high, with each word written below the other, as the <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName> are wont to do with their writing, <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588453"/> but saying nothing more than <placeName ref="gfa-places-2183">Old N. 12</placeName>, which presumably was the name of a once popular inn. There was also a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror-glass</term> panel, inscribed on which in gold lettering were all the many sorts of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beers</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wines</term> and liquor served there, including “funeral wines”. Whether the said “funeral wines”, like their ordinary equivalents, cheered the hearts of the bereaved doubtless depends on the circumstances under which they are actually consumed.</p>
                <p>The shops of the “ironmongers”, a trade somewhere between <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">ironware</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9102"><emph rend="italic">quincaillerie</emph></term>, are incredibly numerous and well-stocked, as only in Sheffield and <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> they would be. Among the many pieces they have on display are several of which I, at least, have neither a need, nor any notion or inkling of how they might be put to use. The English are such great speculators and so eager to save time for themselves and others that at a tanner’s shop I found foot measures, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9744">lasts</term> and all manner of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> tools such as are needed by shoemakers, so that such a one might procure everything needed to set up shop right here in this one place, without going a single step further. The tanner sold <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">wrought</term> and cast iron shoe tacks of all kinds, too, and as a curiosity to take home with me, I purchased <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588454" break="no"/> ¼ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> of the latter, 200 of them altogether, for which I paid 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term> or 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> in our money.</p>
                <p>This really is astonishing, though to defend the honour of <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austrian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term>, it must also be acknowledged that it has done something even more incredible, the town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-896">Steyer</placeName> being officially on record as having sold a dozen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razorblades</term>, which for religious reasons the <placeName ref="gfa-places-148">Turks</placeName> use only once even though each blade is furnished with its own case, as are all such razors, for just 22 kr. = 26 2/5 Rolta. —Indeed, products from all over the world are brought to market in England, and I am not even talking of how last week <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> was “flooded”, as it were, with glorious <term ref="gfa-keywords-8794">“pine-apples”</term>, a whole shipload of this one fruit having arrived there from <placeName ref="gfa-places-2017">New Providence</placeName>, but rather of the sale, also in London, of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829"><placeName ref="gfa-places-67">“Indian pale ale”</placeName></term>, which also enjoys the approbation of the local physicians.</p>
                <p>I lingered longest in front of the tea shops. Now that <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">this curious country</placeName> has been opened up to English trade, one sees all sorts of objects from there, but specifically <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea chests</term> of 1 to 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">cubic feet</term> in content and adorned all over with paintings. These would have required captions, of course, though much of what they show is understandable even without any. There were combat scenes, games, judicial proceedings, religious ceremonies, <term ref="gfa-keywords-3909">music</term> and performances on stringed instruments, <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588455"/> some of which resemble our own, though most are quite different, as well as scenes of domestic life. Especially disgraceful, however, are the feet, and of Chinese of both sexes, moreover, which are thicker at the bottom than at the top and not elongated by toes. Instead they are squeezed together to make them look rounded, like the feet of an elephant.</p>
                <p>The task that I had set myself for today was to visit the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1687" when="1845-08-01" n="76">hammer mill</placeName> of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman</persName></persName> steel foundry, which like every factory here is walled in, but is built in a manner that makes it quite unlike any other <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">hammer mill</term> in the world, being as similar to a medieval castle as one egg is to another.</p>
                <p>Although Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName> himself was not present, I was immediately let in, having not only told the foreman who I was, but having also asked him to thin out, for a fee, a piece of my own <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">steel</term> with my own name inscribed upon it, which I had brought with me from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> for this very purpose.</p>
                <p>All that I was wondering was whether Mr. Huntsman, with whom I had stood in this very same hammer mill <ref type="cross" target="../1825/1">20 years previously</ref>, had in the meantime made any changes to either the feed system or the style of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">heating furnace</term>, which turned out to be the case, in that he now had better control of the whole process and the furnace had been adapted to the use of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>. <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588456"/> The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">steam hammer</term> itself, however, is not exemplary, as the travel of the hammers is not proportionate, the larger ones being too slow and the smaller ones too fast. As their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9821">pathways</term>, moreover, are too wide and flat, each piece can be heated only briefly. This is no concern of theirs, however, since whatever does not become long or thin enough when heated is simply returned to the heating furnace, in which there are always plenty of pieces waiting to be <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">stretched</term>. While the English are masters of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">rolling</term>, I did not see a single good <term ref="gfa-keywords-9745">steam hammer</term> such as we have in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>.</p>
                <p>My day ended with my purchasing a few items, including a case bearing the Latin inscription Multum in parvo, and with packing, at least provisionally, for my departure on the morrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–London, 2. August 1845</head>
                <p><date when="1845-08-02">August 2nd</date>. — At Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson’s</persName> request, I returned to his <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1845-08-02T09:00:00" n="77">factory</placeName> at 9 o’clock in order to discuss with him an object to which he quite rightly attaches great importance. After taking my leave of him and, in my haste, enjoying a lunch of just a few cold cuts with bread and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term>, I left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1845-08-02T13:00:00" n="78">Sheffield</placeName> at 1 o’clock in the afternoon so as to reach <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, which is 165 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> away, by 7 o’clock that evening. —The journey as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1260" when="1845-08-02" n="79">Rugby</placeName> was extremely unpleasant because attached to the tail end of the long <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> was a so-called “propeller” (a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> that pushes while the front one pulls). This caused so much lurching <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588457"/> that one young lady became quite sick. This highly dangerous mode of locomotion will probably be abolished by an act of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">parliament</term>. One of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England’s</placeName> first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">mechanical engineers</term> expressed his own opinion of it by remarking that if one pushes against a rope that is lying completely straight, it will inevitably bend and veer off course no matter how thick it is, whereas if it is merely pulled from the front, it will always remain completely straight. Ordinarily there are just 2 stations over a distance of 200 English miles at which the train stops briefly and where there is a sign saying “Refreshments are to be had.” —Amazingly, one is then given what is not served anywhere else in England: soup, that is to say, a thick, meaty broth with some toasted bread that one has to crumble into it. A plate of such a soupy broth, however, costs 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr</term>.</p>
                <p>We arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1845-08-02T19:00:00" n="80">London</placeName> at 7 o’clock in the evening – safe and well, thank God, since it seems to me that not everything, be it the safety of the journeys or the provisioning of the passengers and other goods, is handled as carefully as it is in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavaria</placeName>, where such things are done much more conscientiously. With such a vast number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, “trains” and wagons loaded with goods, cattle and other objects, one can only marvel at it all, and can hardly conceive of the capital that has had to be invested in these gigantic undertakings, from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> all the way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1937">Edinburgh</placeName>. <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588458" break="no"/> Where it comes from or where it goes is impossible to say, for notwithstanding all of this, the rich are rich and the poor are poor, and the social conditions have not visibly changed, except that everything now seems more abundant and more splendid than it was before. On the other hand, one is bound to wonder, walking through the streets at night, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> are lit and the brightly illuminated shop fronts afford the eager eye an unbroken, mile-long row of treasures of all kinds, and where one sees people busy about their work and the thousands upon thousands of conveyances of all kinds, to say nothing of the boats covering the whole <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> – as I say, one is bound to wonder, seeing all this, how long we can continue to climb, and what may cause us to reach our culmination point, which, as with all earthly undertakings, is undoubtedly coming, be it in the near or distant future?</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> that took me from the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1666" when="1845-08-02" n="81">Euston</placeName> terminus, which is a long way from the centre of town, to the lodgings I took 20 years ago at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1845-08-02" n="82">St. Pauls Family Hotel</placeName>, cost me just 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Letzte Geschäfte in London, 3. August 1845</head>
                <p>This morning after church I had intended to visit my nephew Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-08-03" n="83">August Wintz</placeName></persName>, but from his landlord learned that he and his <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">family</persName> had already <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588459"/> departed for <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> the previous Thursday; may he arrive safely in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>!</p>
                <p>Although <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">Sundays</placeName> are no longer spent as quietly as they were in the past, which alone on account of the operation of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> now straddling the whole <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">kingdom</placeName> would no longer be possible in any case, given the astonishing amount of traffic they set in motion, the difference compared to <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> is nonetheless striking. When I travelled from <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName> fourteen days ago, we passed through villages in which there were builders laying bricks, carpenters sawing timber and farmers spreading manure on their fields; no one seemed to care that it was a Sunday. I also ran into people who may well have been to church that day, though one sees very few of them. Today at lunch I had the magnificent facade of <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2145" when="1845-08-03" n="84">St. Paul’s Church</placeName> before me, barely 100 paces hence, and studying that artistic feat of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4069">architecture</term> that vies with <placeName ref="gfa-places-2051">St. Peter’s</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-608">Rome</placeName>, I noticed what seemed to me to be such a violation of symmetry, which surely should be the Conditio sine qua non in such a building, that I cannot imagine how any discerning Englishman with an eye for trivia could have failed to notice it, since it stares one so in the face. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9057">frontispiece</term> supported by colonnades is flanked by two, not very high towers, high up on whose anterior facades are two round <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588460"/> oculi, of which the one on the tower on the right when facing the portal is filled with a clock dial, whereas the equivalent oculus on the left has been left open, serving only crows and bats as a convenient entrance and exit. Did wealthy London not have enough money for a second clock? Or could not the hole at least have been filled and adorned with something appropriate? —Spent the afternoon writing and procuring this and that ready for tomorrow’s departure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Besuch von Faraday und Reise nach Dover, 4. August 1845</head>
                <p><date when="1845-08-04">August 4th</date> — Today I went to take my leave of Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-08-04" n="85"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im-Thurn</persName></placeName> and thence to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7575"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1703" when="1845-08-04" n="86">Royal Institution</placeName></orgName>. I considered myself most fortunate to find him once again in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, he having returned there from a recreational visit to <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> just a few days previously. Our conversation turned primarily on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> and introduction of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electric</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term>, which one sees so frequently running parallel to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term>, and on the expansion of which this fine idea might yet be capable.</p>
                <p>He inspected the cast <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term> (horseshoes that had been worn for a while and then recast, and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9691">cock</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9690">lock plate</term> from a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion lock</term>) with both pleasure and interest, as also the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">3-ounce</term> piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platinum</term> melted down from offcuts and waste in one of my experimental <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term>. <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588461" break="no"/> I then presented him with a similar crucible, which I had brought with me to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> for him to use as he wished. —After taking my leave I had just enough time to pack and eat lunch before setting off for the distant <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2221" when="1845-08-04T19:00:00" n="87">station</placeName> from which the 7 o’clock <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-08-04T22:00:00" n="88">Dover</placeName> was to depart. The 88 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> were covered by 10 o’clock and after such an arduous day I was glad of the chance to rest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Dover–Gent, 5. August 1845</head>
                <p>The Royal Mail <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Steamship</term>, which owing to Queen <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Victoria’s</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9749">forthcoming visit</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2044">Rhine-Prussia</placeName> was crowded with passengers, departed from <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-08-05T10:00:00" n="89">Dover</placeName></placeName> at 10 o’clock in the morning and despite a fierce headwind arrived at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1625" when="1845-08-05T15:00:00" n="90">Ostend</placeName> at 3 o’clock.</p>
                <p>I had to wait for a long time to have my case and night bag examined at <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">customs</term>, but only to have them opened and then immediately closed again. Some of the womenfolk who had a whole arsenal of cosmetics and finery in their cases did not fare quite so well and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">douaniers</term> were not very gallant.</p>
                <p>After a brief lunch I went by <placeName ref="gfa-places-2189"><term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term></placeName> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1910" when="1845-08-05" n="91">Bruges</placeName> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1624" when="1845-08-05T22:00:00" n="92">Ghent</placeName>, where I arrived at about 10 o’clock, and owing to the many foreigners in town was able to find lodgings for the night only at the third inn at which I inquired.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Gent–Köln, 6. August 1845</head>
                <p><date when="1845-08-06">August 6th</date>. —The departure times of trains are not as exactly observed in <placeName ref="gfa-places-13">Belgium</placeName> as they are in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, where every minute counts. Instead, we passengers <pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588462" break="no"/> had to wait nearly an hour for the officials on duty and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> finally <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1624" when="1845-08-06T08:00:00" n="93">departed</placeName> at 8 o’clock instead of 7, taking us via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2007" when="1845-08-06" n="94">Malines</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2003" when="1845-08-06" n="95">Louvain</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1311" when="1845-08-06" n="96">Liege</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1" when="1845-08-06" n="97">Aachen</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1947" when="1845-08-06" n="98">Eschenyler</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1935" when="1845-08-06" n="99">Düren</placeName> and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1968" when="1845-08-06" n="100">Kerpen</placeName> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1845-08-06T22:00:00" n="101">Cologne</placeName><note>Die Strecke <placeName ref="gfa-places-2191">Köln–Aachen</placeName> wurde am  1. September 1841, die Verbindung <placeName ref="gfa-places-2192">Aachen–Liège</placeName> am 15. Oktober 1843 eröffnet. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2193">Gent und Liège</placeName> waren seit dem 1. Mai 1842 mit der Eisenbahn erschlossen.</note>, where we again arrived at 10 o’clock in the evening, and where I found very good lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2147" when="1845-08-06" n="102">Rheinischer Hof</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If there had been <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam engines</term> in use in <persName ref="gfa-actors-8265">Moses’</persName> day, doubtless he would not have sat <persName ref="gfa-actors-8266">Joshua</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-8267">Caleb</persName> in a <placeName ref="gfa-places-2044">Rhine-Prussian</placeName> one and charged them “to survey the land”, since it was impossible to see anything at all from our carriage. There, where there are normally windows, these trains had curtains that because of the rain were either drawn or lowered, and while they covered the opening just enough to prevent one seeing anything outside, where they should have closed properly around the edges they did not. The wind and rain thus had free rein, giving those sitting next to them a real dowsing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Köln–Schaffhausen, 7. bis 9. August 1845</head>
                <p>Arriving in Cologne on <date when="1845-08-07">August 7th</date>, I <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">boarded</placeName> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamer</term> that departed at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1845-08-07T05:00:00" n="103">5 o’clock</placeName> for <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1845-08-07T21:00:00" n="104">Mainz</placeName>, where I arrived at 9 o’clock in the evening, departing again at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1845-08-07T23:00:00" n="105">11 o’clock</placeName> and arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1098" when="1845-08-08T06:00:00" n="106">Mannheim</placeName> at 6 o’clock the next morning,</p> 
                <p><date when="1845-08-08">August 8th</date>. I then took the 7 o’clock <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1123" when="1845-08-08" n="108">Carlsruhe</placeName> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1122" when="1845-08-08T14:30:00" n="109">Freiburg im Breisgau</placeName>, where I arrived at half past two. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">post coach</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1845-08-09T05:30:00" n="111">Schaffhausen</placeName> departed at 3 o’clock.</p>
                <p><pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588463"/> I arrived back home on <date when="1845-08-09">August 9th</date>, at half past 5 in the morning, happy and healthy, thank God, and happy to be back among <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my dear ones</persName>.</p>
            </div>          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
