<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="5">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1845</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Notes on a Journey via Paris to London, Leeds, Low Moor, Sheffield, and Back in the Summer of 1845.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <lb/>
                <byline>By <docAuthor>Johann Conrad Fischer</docAuthor>,  Lieutenant Colonel of the Artillery.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Schaffhausen. Printed by J. J. Biegler’schen Buchdruckerei. <docDate>1846</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Titelseite</head>
                <p> <pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588384"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9848">[title page of the first edition]</term></p>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Preface</head>
                <p><pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588387"/> When I first visited <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> 52 years ago, and there, having found employ with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">mechanic</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493">Shoe Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet Street</placeName>, through which I had occasion to compare the extent to which this branch of industry had advanced and been perfected as opposed to that on the Continent, I must confess that my verdict was wholly in favour of England, and that scarcely any object of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> in this or that field need fear rivalry from abroad, a circumstance to which the early introduction of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent system</term> with its capacity to offer both inducements and protections might well have contributed, ensuring that the wares produced, almost without exception, combine a high degree of perfection with both solidity and utility.</p>        
                <p><pb n="IV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588388"/> Yet to the best of my knowledge, there was nothing especially new to be seen there – with the exception of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>, which on the Continent were all but unknown at the time – since the same things might be found elsewhere, only not as good.</p>
                <p>When, twenty years later, I visited this curious <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">island</placeName> again the moment the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">Continental Blockade</term> was lifted, I found great new phenomena in the aforementioned fields. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-1405">iron foundries</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9572">potteries</term>, among which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7567"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566">Wedgwood</orgName></persName></persName> seemed the primus inter pares or rather the princeps, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file factories</term>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plate</term>, the spun cotton and <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">mechanical looms</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">textile mills</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> had taken on a character of greatness and perfection of which, without seeing them for oneself, one can have no concept.</p>
                <p>Twelve or thirteen years later, when inclination and interest drove me to this country once again, the scale of everything, most notably the extent of London, had grown even more, so that a member of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">parliament</term>, when the matter was debated in September of that same year, had occasion <pb n="V" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588389"/> to say: “this year had seen the building of 26,000 new houses by the end of last week, though how many more will be finished by next Saturday I cannot say.”</p>
                <p>The already widespread deployment of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term>, the introduction of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lighting</term>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins’s</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8877">steam gun</term> and the construction of the gigantic <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888"><term ref="gfa-keywords-7622">tunnel</term></placeName> that seemed impossible but was made possible by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel</persName>, alongside all manner of other most interesting things, my brief notes on which are contained in the diaries<note>Gemeint sind die Tagebücher von <ref type="cross" target="../1825/1">1825</ref> und von <ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/1">1825–1827</ref>.</note> I kept of my travels in those years, imprinted themselves on my mind as a composition, which through vivid recollection of the same makes for a most alluring tableau. —As already mentioned, I committed my feeble and incomplete outlines of these things to my earlier diaries, the keeping of which, through long habituation, has become a compulsion, and which readers have received kindly and, disregarding their shortcomings, judged with circumspection, perhaps precisely because I did not presume to write deliberately for others. The few pages that follow, however, in which is contained the result of last year’s very brief journey, are too paltry in content for others to be alerted to the same. They shall not, therefore, <pb n="VI" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588390"/> be entrusted to the book trade, and are printed here, after the passage of almost a whole year, only because it did not seem worth my while to make them over to a publisher. It is for the sake of <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my family</persName> and friends, therefore, who wondered at my not having seen anything worthy of note or at my having deemed what I did see unworthy of mention, that this small volume takes its place alongside its predecessors. May they, or indeed anyone else who chances to lay hands on it, receive it as I wish, namely as a straightforward account, addressed to my own nearest and dearest, of a journey undertaken to foreign lands, and for me but one scene more in the aforementioned tableau.<lb/>
                    <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, the <date when="1846-06-21">21st June 1846</date>.<lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>, Lieutenant Colonel.<note>Das Tagebuch wurde 1846 bei der <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8309">J. J. Ziegler’schen Buchdruckerei</orgName> in Schaffhausen gedruckt.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588391"/>
        <body>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Schaffhausen–Basel, 14. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1845-07-14" n="1"><anchor/></placeName> On <date when="1845-07-14">14th July</date> I set off for <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> by express coach, and in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-718" when="1845-07-14" n="2">Jestetten</placeName> was joined by an <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> family, a gentleman, two ladies and a young boy, as travelling companions. They seemed pleased to have encountered one with whom they might converse in their native tongue, the occasion for which was Mr. Watson’s taking out an English map of <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe’s</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamship</term> routes. After we had talked about sundry related matters, his wife, remarking on the fact that I evidently understood English, presented me with a printed pamphlet and invited me to read the same. It was a fragment of a tract published by the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8252">Tract Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and contained two tales of conversion (the 867th and 868th, according to the tract), one of them entitled “The Railway Passenger” and the other the “Father’s Prayer”. Out of respect for her good intentions, and for the family as people who took such matters very seriously, it seemed to me, I read both tales in their entirety, despite finding them too bland and moralistic, all the more so since they bore the stamp of well-meaning fiction rather than that of true stories. After reading them, I made to return them <pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588392"/> but was obliged to keep them. The event reminded me of an earlier one, when one Madame <persName ref="gfa-actors-8253">Consentius</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2119">Königsberg</placeName>, a great admirer of [Barbara] <persName ref="gfa-actors-7877">von Krüdener</persName>, had visited me, and on taking her leave of me had given me two such tracts, which common folk in those days believed to possess a particular smell that if inhaled would make one an adherent of that then so famous lady. Soon afterwards, Mr. Watson slipped his <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver-bound</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">New Testament</term> out of its case and read aloud a chapter from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Saint John’s Gospel</term>, after which the conversation once again turned to more general matters.</p>
                <p>In <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1971" when="1845-07-14" n="3">Lauchringen</placeName> we were joined, much to my delight, by Pastor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7899">Merian</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2038">Oberhallau</placeName>, to whom, since I knew that he had likewise been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and understood English, I was able to give the aforementioned stories as reading material.</p>
                <p>At Berg near <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-991" when="1845-07-14" n="4">Lauffenburg</placeName> we were waylaid by a mendicant apprentice, who climbed in beside us, as did, soon afterwards, a farmer’s girl from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-132">Black Forest</placeName> wishing to avail herself of the baths in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2056">Säckingen</placeName>, who was likewise given such a tract. She held onto it for some time, albeit upside-down, and would have politely returned it had not the Englishwoman exhorted her: “Keep it, keep it!” which I then translated for her, telling her that she should keep it.</p>
                <p>Giving serious thought to what had just transpired, I wondered to myself, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588393"/> as I have done repeatedly ever since, whether such endeavours, as commendable and sincerely meant as they undoubtedly are, are not bound by any propriety of time, place and circumstance? But never once have I been able to answer that question and instead attach great value to the very profound message of the apostle: “But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut the door, pray to thy Father which is in secret.”<note>Matthäus 6,6.</note></p>
                <p>On arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-10" when="1845-07-14" n="5">Basel</placeName> that evening, my dear old friend <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">Wibert</persName> was already at the post office to welcome me and to accommodate me under his hospitable roof.</p>
                <p>How sorry I was that he could not be my travelling companion in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> as he had been fifty years ago!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Geschäftsgänge in Basel, 15. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>The greater part of the day was taken up with various visits and writing two letters home.</p>
                <p>I went first to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7969">Wölflin</persName>, who had recently returned from <placeName ref="gfa-places-205">Mexico</placeName> and was just then unpacking 5 cases of natural objects and artefacts from the land of the ancient Incas<note>Fischer verwechselt die Inkas mit den <placeName ref="gfa-places-205">Azteken</placeName>.</note>. I found them all fascinating, though most of all the <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName> objects that he had chanced to acquire, primarily a charming little pocket book, whose tortoiseshell binding was covered with characters arranged one below the other in columns, as is sometimes the case with <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egyptian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphs</term>. Its inside pages, twelve in number (they seem to have a dodecimal system, too), depicted the costumes and other attributes of the various classes of this curious people, <pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588394" break="no"/> the faces of the women being painted onto tiny, convex slivers of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9023">ivory</term> the size of a little fingernail, whereas the rest was all flat.</p>
                <p>Of the four large tableaux of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9641">sugar boiler</term> with its own ox <term ref="gfa-keywords-9324">gin</term> alongside it, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9161">stove-builder’s shop</term>, a landscape and a Chinese juggler with an entourage of monkeys and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9187">dogs</term>, it was the latter that interested me most, having never before seen anything like it in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. I once saw a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9685">comedy with dogs and monkeys</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-815">Salzburg</placeName> that certainly took things quite far, though for all that they were clad like the ladies and gentlemen that they supposedly represented, the faces peeping out from under the hats and bonnets were still those of dogs and monkeys. The Chinese, however, took the deception a stage further in that all had masks depending on the role they had to play, and as if that were not enough, there was a dog pulling a little cart bearing a basket full of masks, on which sat a monkey-coachman vigorously brandishing his whip.</p>
                <p>After a visit to my friend’s family, I had two meetings with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8254">E. P.</persName>, which for the most part had to do with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Schweizer-Eisenbahnen</term>, specifically <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">the line</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanz</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>. He raised what seemed to be some important objections to a very well written memorandum by a highly skilled and experienced member of our trade, <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588395"/> namely the want of passengers on the line via <placeName ref="gfa-places-2069">Ulm</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1329">Augsburg</placeName> and further east, which concern I felt bound to allay by noting that things would look very different once the line from Augsburg to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1988">Lindau</placeName> was finished. As to the money for the aforementioned line, he acknowledged that while he himself, like many other <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> establishments, had perhaps been able to provide an impetus, nothing positive had as yet been discussed, it having been observed that since <placeName ref="gfa-places-1899">Baden</placeName> did not wish to build the line itself, or so it had been heard, the necessary concessions on that side would first have to be secured, and that the very large sums required in such a case might well be raised in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>.</p>
                <p>There was just enough time for me to tell him of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">my invention</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term>, indeed the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">melting</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">casting</term> of all <term ref="gfa-keywords-9012">wrought iron</term> so as to retain its softness and malleability, and showed him some pieces that he took with him as specimens. Once he had seen these and tested them with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">file</term> and hammer, he cried out: “The <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> should have that!”, whereupon I remarked that I first wanted to hear what the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> had to say.</p>
                <p>Returning home past Basel’s many fine and sturdy public buildings and private homes, <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588396" break="no"/> all of them so clean and impeccably well kept both inside and out, I could not help but think that it was this same cleanliness, this same love of order – the daughters of quiet, steady industry that historically have long been at home in Basel – which in their wake have brought not some fly-by-night or will-o-the-wisp, but wealth built on solid ground and thriving as if of its own accord. A house in good order is one that is entered gladly. In this respect <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> appear in a much more favourable light than does <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">their neighbour</placeName>, which once believed itself to be the No. 1 of all the nations of this earth.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Basel–Paris, 16. bis 18. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">My friend</persName> accompanied me as far as the post office, where I departed at 7 o’clock in the morning on the post coach from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-10" when="1845-07-16T07:00:00" n="6">Basel</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, for an inside seat on which, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabriolet</term> being already occupied, I had to pay 56 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term>. The post coach belonging to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8255">Bureau des Diligences Royales</orgName> was much finer and better furnished than it used to be. — <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">Customs</term> in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2065" when="1845-07-16" n="7">St. Louis</placeName> were not very scrupulous, and since the product specimens that I declared of 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9858">kilogram</term> in weight are so valuable to me, I gladly paid the 1 franc and 46 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">centimes</term> levied.</p>
                <p>In <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1586" when="1845-07-16T12:00:00" n="8">Mulhouse</placeName> I chanced to have the pleasure of lunching with three esteemed young compatriots, whose industriousness and love of business in the one or the other métier might serve others as an example to follow, and conversed with them <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588397" break="no"/> on sundry matters relating to industrially made objects. To judge by past experience, however, I would henceforth have to abandon all hopes of pleasure. —And indeed, it was worse than I had anticipated; for quite apart from the fact that our company consisted of a German scholar who either slept or smoked, a young French army officer, and the wife of a factory worker from Mulhouse, who as a Parisienne had been bored to death there and had left her husband to return to what she considered to be heaven on earth, we never once stopped long enough to eat anything during the 23 hours to elapse between Mulhouse and Langres (which I had not expected given previous journeys). It being bourse day in Mulhouse, we had sat down to lunch at twelve o’clock sharp and set off again at 1, and by the time we sat down to breakfast in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1815" when="1845-07-17T11:00:00" n="9">Langres</placeName> it was already 11 o’clock the next morning, the <date when="1845-07-17">17th June</date><note>Gemeint ist der 17. Juli.</note>. I had no opportunity to make any important observations on that long stretch. Whereas the land was better <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">cultivated</term> than when I last journeyed through it in <ref type="cross" target="../1814/4">1814</ref>, when one saw only women at the plough, the coupes régulières undertaken by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon</persName> and his young cadre for the honour of the nation, or more likely his own glory, had in the meantime ceased. But the peasants’ dwellings in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1916">Champagne</placeName>, even as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1811" when="1845-07-18T00:00:00" n="10">Troyes</placeName>, where we arrived around midnight <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588398" break="no"/> and were able to drink a cup of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term>, were just as wretched as ever, especially when one compares their timbering, roofing, cramped conditions, workmanship, disposition and general filth to those of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> farmhouses.</p>
                <p>We breakfasted à la fourchette in a small town just beyond <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2016" when="1845-07-18" n="11">Nangis</placeName> and arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-118" when="1845-07-18T16:00:00" n="12">Paris</placeName> at 4 o’clock in the afternoon of the <date when="1845-07-18">18th</date>.</p>
                <p>Following one of the calling cards with which one is so generously regaled on alighting from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term>, I sought lodgings at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2230">Hôtel du Havre</placeName> on the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2120" when="1845-07-18" n="13">rue des vieux Augustins</placeName>. I cannot complain, since after my 50-hour journey and a light supper I was happy just to see a bed again, though I would not recommend this inn to anyone else.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Pariser Mode, Münzanstalt und Weiterreise, 19. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>On the journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1586">Mulhouse</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> (since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> returns that same day), I discovered above the filêts inside the carriage a printed pamphlet, which I leafed through out of sheer boredom. It was titled <term ref="gfa-keywords-9687">la Diligence</term> and seems to have been placed there deliberately, since it contained a whole host of advertisements for shops in Paris, contained within which were some blandly written stories, spiked with far-fetched words that do not belong to common parlance, which in spirit and style are very similar to those used in today’s fashion magazines. Among the advertisements was one which, to stand out from the others, had white letters on a black ground <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588399"/> and began with the rallying cry “Mort aux chapeaux de soie!” [Death to silk hats!], followed by a paean to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9688">castor hats</term> of the very best quality that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8256">Biget</persName> (to be found at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2122"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2123" when="1845-07-19" n="14">rue Rivoli no. 56</placeName></placeName>) was selling for 17 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> a piece. Needing such a hat, I set off thence and consequently had to walk all the way back to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1604" when="1845-07-19" n="15">prefecture</placeName>, before venturing even further afield to the banker Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2124" when="1845-07-19" n="16"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7811">Dassier</persName></placeName>, in whose counting house I met a young man from Schaffhausen (<persName ref="gfa-actors-8300">Rauschenbach</persName>), who deservedly enjoys great confidence there. After that it was off to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7509">Bréant's</persName> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1602" when="1845-07-19" n="17">mint</placeName>, which does such great work in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platinum</term>, and there, with Mr. Bréant himself guiding me through that labyrinthine building, to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7770">Barre</persName> to take provisional orders for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">steel for coin punches</term> of a quality that might rival that used for the excellent coins made by <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich’s</placeName> award-winning <placeName ref="gfa-places-2014">mint</placeName>. These two gentlemen viewed my specimens of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">cast soft bar iron</term></term> (the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9690">lockplate</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9691">cock</term> of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion flintlock</term>) with interest, and Mr. Bréant took the opportunity to tell me, much to my surprise, that they still had no really good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> and still preferred the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2042">Passau</placeName> model.</p>
                <p>After the mint, and shortly before departing on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName>, I had to return to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1604" when="1845-07-19" n="19">prefecture</placeName>, though only after calling at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2125" when="1845-07-19" n="18"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8301">Swiss delegation</persName></placeName>, where <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588400" break="no"/> a sum of 2 francs was demanded for the appendage of a stamp to my passport, presumably for the sake of the people of that nation, since not a single penny was asked of me anywhere else. Meanwhile, my errantry, as I can with some justification call it, afforded me something pleasant and unexpected in the form of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2126"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2004"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9693">obelisk of Luxor</term></placeName></placeName>, that fine monolith, a drawing of which I once possessed, albeit without knowing the interpretation of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphs</term> according to the key provided by <persName ref="gfa-actors-8257">Champollion</persName>.</p>
                <p>Three thoughts occurred to me on viewing this curious object: either <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName> in those days had had a large population of idlers that might be put to work on this seemingly futile undertaking, which given Egypt’s fertility and the small amount of effort required to <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">work the land</term> there is entirely plausible, or the ambitions of its rulers surpassed all moderation in the same proportion as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8770">pyramids</term> do ordinary buildings, to prove which one might cite <persName ref="gfa-actors-7856">Herodotus</persName>, or it had been agreed, which would be the most praiseworthy of these three theories, that there should be an enduring monument to the history, the laws and the mores of those times. —</p>
                <p>When <term ref="gfa-keywords-9693">this gift</term> of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7734">Ali Pascha</persName> to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8258">King of France</persName><note>Die Schenkung fällt in die Herrschaft von <persName ref="gfa-actors-8258">Karl X</persName>. Der Transport und das Aufstellen des Obelisken in Paris geschah unter <persName ref="gfa-actors-7478">Louis-Philippe I</persName>.</note>, which would be further embellished by its proximity to two extremely copious fountains (that the <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> have taste cannot be denied), <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588401"/> was first erected, the gazettes mocked the idea of mounting a pointed column on a pedestal. Quite apart from the fact that the newspapers are not the word of god, any impartial observer is bound to concede that the idea was in fact a good one. The throne of a king is likewise elevated above its surroundings, and this king, too, undoubtedly deserved a lofty position under all those stones.</p>
                <p>At half past two, feeling amply recompensed for all the hardships of the day by my reception at the mint, I paid 33 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> for a stage-coach to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName> and left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-118" when="1845-07-19T14:30:00" n="20">Paris</placeName>. As the capital’s new wall with its <placeName ref="gfa-places-2225">detached bastions</placeName> (which only future times may judge) receded into the distance, I was glad to be entering the pretty region of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2022">Normandy</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France’s</placeName> very own <placeName ref="gfa-places-78">Thurgau</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Shortly after midnight, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8738">right-hand</term> horse of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> stumbled and became so ensnared in its traces that we lost almost a whole hour, which in turn robbed us passengers of a whole day, since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne sur mer</placeName> and Calais depart at a fixed hour every day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Boulogne–Calais, 20. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1606" when="1845-07-20T10:00:00" n="21">Boulogne</placeName> at 10 o’clock in the morning. One travels so uncommonly fast compared to times past, and that despite all the passengers and goods. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> have learned this from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName>, <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588402"/> though they have yet to adopt their horses and fine, sturdy bridles. The 72-hour journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> is now accomplished in just 18 hours. The swindling that goes on at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inns</term> en route is extraordinary. No one takes anything without first asking what it costs, and the insistence of the persons employed to recommend lodgings in Boulogne is remarkable. —The harassment began 4 hours outside Boulogne at the foot of a steep hill where the horses had to slow down to a walking pace and some women were waiting to thrust their addresses into every passing coach; but just an hour nearer to Boulogne and we were again waylaid by three urchins on ponies, each of whom held a long hazel switch with calling cards clamped into its split end, so that by trotting briskly along beside the coach, they were able to poke these inside to us passengers. —The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> did not linger long in Boulogne and I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1607" when="1845-07-20T14:00:00" n="22">Calais</placeName> at 2 o’clock in the afternoon. The inn where I used to stay, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2127">Hotel de St. Louis</placeName>, had gone under; but I had a lucky star in the guise of an officer of the gendarmerie, who on my approaching him for directions guided me to an English establishment, (<placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2128" when="1845-07-20" n="23">Commercial Inn</placeName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8259">Warren</persName>), where I fancied myself already in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, the family having brought with them all the customs of their home country, characteristic among which was their practice of having one person in the dining room reverentially read aloud from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Bible</term> (it was a Sunday) while his neighbour <pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588403"/> downed copious amounts of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9697">rum</term>, albeit very quietly, as is also customary in England.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Querung des Ärmelkanals und Herr Hamers Reisetipps, 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>I slept for ten hours, which is surely pardonable in one who has been travelling for 8 days and who between <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1607" when="1845-07-21T10:00:00" n="24">Calais</placeName> only once saw a bed (in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, to be precise). Well might I afford myself that pleasure, for our Royal Mail <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Steamship</term>, having a draught of just 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, could not put to sea until high tide, which arrived late at around 10 o’clock in the morning. The company on the steamer, which despite its small size was furnished with a 65 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">engine</term> that in defiance of wind and waves drove the wheels at a rate of 29 revolutions per minute, was not very numerous, as almost all travellers who make the journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> take the route from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne sur mer</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1957">Folkstone</placeName>, a little port on the English coast, where they meet a branch line of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2186">Dover-London railway</placeName>. Calais, astonishingly, has suffered because of this, since anyone who wants to be at sea for just a few hours can now make the crossing via Boulogne and complete the passage in just 26¼ hours, whereas anyone who travels from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1926">Dieppe</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, a journey entailing 74 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> at sea, and from there continues by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to Paris will reach the same in the incredibly short time of just 16¼ hours, having covered 244 English miles altogether. The total costs of this journey over land and sea from Paris to London or vice <pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588404"/> versa, including all the railway and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> fares and lodgings – though not what is consumed en route, which of course one can limit as one wishes – are in the order of 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">fr.</term> or 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> at most, at least as long as one does not take a seat in the coupé of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> or in a first-class carriage on the railway but instead contents oneself with an inside seat and a second-class carriage. Here I am bound to make a remark that the parents of sons, who whether by inclination or for professional reasons or other circumstances venture forth into the world, would do well to take to heart, should they ever set eyes on it: Since the intercourse among nations has multiplied so greatly of late and been so greatly facilitated by the advent of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>, learning French and English in addition to one’s mother tongue (I am addressing German-speakers here), and prior to that some Latin, be it ever so little, since that language is the foundation and mother of the other two, as it were, has become a matter of the utmost urgency. Yet too many of us are loath to acknowledge this, or so it seems to me, and though the benefits to be derived from it need no further articulation here, I shall nevertheless provide a few examples of my own. There were, as I said, but a few passengers on the steamship, and all of them English. Although I conversed with most of those on board in turn, one of them in particular <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588405" break="no"/> took a special shine to me precisely because I spoke English so fluently, or so he told me, so that not only did he tell me everything that I might possibly want to know about what was to be done at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153">customs</placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2046">“Aliens Office”</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> and explain to me how to procure a seat on the train to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, an 88-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">mile</term> journey that can now be accomplished in 3 hours, but he also gave me a permit to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8455">Chinese Collection</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2129">Hyde-Park Corner</placeName>, which cannot be viewed for money, despite containing the finest and most intriguing artefacts from <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">that country</placeName>, that has now been returned to the world, as it were.<note>Wohl eine Anspielung auf das Ende des <term ref="gfa-keywords-9347">Ersten Opiumkriegs</term> und der daraus resultierenden Öffnung Chinas für den Welthandel.</note> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8260">Hamer</persName> (not Hammer, which is also a word in English) also told me that on arriving at the station in London, I should hand over my luggage to a porter and have him take it – a service for which I would not have to pay a penny – to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term>, which for just one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> would take me to whichever part of London I wished. —I pondered the word “cab” for some time, since I did not recall ever having heard it before; after asking for an explanation, however, it turned out that the English, being such assiduous time-keepers, have substituted this word for the word “cabriolet”, which after all is three syllables longer.</p>
                <p>My desire to become <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasick</term>, since I always feel better thereafter, <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588406"/> was not fulfilled, despite my having scooped up a cup of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">green seawater</placeName> and downed it all at once shortly after departing Calais, a method which has never before failed me. —When inspecting the inner fittings of the ship I came across an object, which on grounds of its simplicity and the effectiveness of its intended purpose, which was to bring diffuse light to the dark rooms below decks by means of just a small opening in the overhead, interested me greatly. Never before had I encountered an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9755">optical</term>, or rather <term ref="gfa-keywords-8633">dioptical</term>, tool being used in such a way. As the ship, owing to its low draught and to prevent seepage on a stormy sea, had very few high and low portholes (windows) mounted on its sides, each of the completely dark rooms below had a single glass prism inserted into a hole in the middle of the overhead, though always somewhat sunken into the deck so as to prevent it getting trodden on by the shoes of those pacing to and fro. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9699">This prism</term>, each triangular face of which was circa 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in length and 2 inches wide, was protected by a very thin and slender <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> frame or mount that was nailed onto the <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">wood</term>, and that despite having a squared surface area in a ratio of 12:2500 to the smallest room to be illuminated provided real daylight.</p>
                <p><pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588407"/> Might we all be as conscientious as they are in England about taking whatever is of practical benefit from a scientific discipline and actually putting it to use!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>«Sind Sie auch in England, Herr Obrist?», 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>We landed in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-07-21T13:00:00" n="25">Dover</placeName> in glorious weather at about 1 o’clock in the afternoon. Having previously been told what I had to do and where, I was astonished at the ease, the assurance and the calm with which our goods were transferred from the ship to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2153" when="1845-07-21" n="26">customs house</placeName> and from there to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>. Only the owner of the goods was admitted to the long table, of which the room contained several, on which all the cases, bags, chests etc. were laid out ready for inspection. Upon my declaration of those objects that I had in my case on which <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">duty</term> might be payable, I was politely told that it was not worth their while, which of course is wiser than wasting time filling 3 full sheets of paper with written descriptions all for the sake of a few <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreuzers</term>. Not even the paper in which the said items were wrapped was removed; instead they were merely lifted off the table. It was all over in less than 3 minutes, and for a fare of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">sixpence</term> (eighteen kreuzer) a customs house employee took my effects to the inn. I now had to report to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2046" when="1845-07-21" n="27">aliens office</placeName>; it cannot really be called a police station, as there were no people with frightful moustaches, grim faces and crooked <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipes</term> there. It rather consisted of just one uncommonly small room and in it a friendly gentleman <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588408"/> clad all in black, as are almost all people of quality in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. Here I had nothing to do other than to write my name on three printed certificates of arrival, one of which was handed over to me, while the other two he retained. It all took just two minutes. England, it seems, is not as afraid of foreigners as its neighbouring country. I can now stay as long as I wish, go wherever I wish, and, according to this certificate, am not subject to any conditions such as having to report to the officer in charge at the port of embarkation prior to my departure. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, by contrast, despite being in possession of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passport</term> issued by [the Swiss] authorities and signed by the French ambassador, I was unable to get out of the country without first having to run hither and thither, to endure all sorts of travails, and pay money for them to boot. Here, by contrast, entering and remaining in the country is facilitated in the extreme.</p>
                <p>The officer then asked me how things stood in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>? to which I replied that there was not much to boast about there. He responded to this merely by remarking that it seemed to him that through the <placeName ref="gfa-places-91"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9700">attack on Lucerne</term></placeName>, both sides<note>Gemeint sind wohl die Liberal-Radikalen und die Katholisch-Konservativen.</note> had now gone too far – which incidentally is a view that thousands upon thousands of us who have not been blinded by passion would subscribe to. While some, on reading this, would find my account of this day tedious, the reason I chose to record <pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588409"/>  it in such detail in my diary was to ensure that at least my nearest and dearest might form a vivid picture of how good it is to have some prior knowledge of the language of every country, and this one in particular. How many pleasures would I have missed, how many embarrassments would I have suffered, had I not known the whys and wherefores? —The French entertain this preconceived notion that one has to learn their language (la langue de l'Univers), yet do not thank one for it when one proves oneself capable of conversing with them in the same; the English, by contrast, while equally entitled to such grand claims, are more modest and show affection and respect for those who speak their mother-tongue, as I have experienced many times.</p>
                <p>When I was at dinner in Dover, I suddenly heard someone behind me ask: “So you, too, are in England, Mr. Obrist?” and on turning round saw that it was Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7948">Schönbein</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>. My delight on seeing him here, however, was greatly mitigated by our having but a few minutes in which to converse, I being on my way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and he to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, and by the news that my esteemed friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> was not at present in England. I bid him a good journey and said that should he choose to attend the forthcoming convention of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8103">Swiss Naturalists’ Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1196">Geneva</placeName>, <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588410"/> an event that I have always found stimulating and worthwhile but this year will not be able to attend, he should kindly extend my apologies to its president, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8261">de la Rive</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Von Dover nach London mit der Eisenbahn, 21. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> departed <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-07-21T15:00:00" n="28">Dover</placeName> at 3 o’clock. On the advice of my new friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8260">Hamer</persName>, who remained my travelling companion as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1957" when="1845-07-21" n="29">Folkstone</placeName>, I took a seat in the second class, for which the fare for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">88-mile</term> journey was 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> and 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, or 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term></p>
                <p>“I can already see that you care about our country and its people and ask all sorts of questions,” said he. “It is here in this class, where you will encounter a better sort of people, that you will obtain the most information, whereas I could not and would not recommend the third class, and as for the first class, not only is it populated mainly by fine ladies, but the prevailing tone there is very stiff and formal.” —Not far from Dover we came to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2187">that curious place</placeName> where, harnessing those elemental forces over which we now have dominion and that through science can make our servants, a whole mountain made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9199">limestone</term> was cast all at once into the depths of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">sea</placeName> solely to make room for the genius of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam trains</term>.<note>Fischer meint die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9806">Sprengung von Round Down Cliff</term> am <date when="1843-01-26">26. Januar 1843</date>.</note> Somewhat later we passed through several <placeName ref="gfa-places-2190">tunnels</placeName> of quite some length, our entrance into which was invariably advertised by a loud scream on the part of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">locomotive</term>. —The extreme darkness that reigns supreme in these passages makes one concur with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7947">Schiller</persName>:</p>
                <p><pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588411"/>“A dark and mysterious gate opens wide.<lb/> Beyond seem the shadow realms dreaded.<lb/> But sudden a region of bliss is descried.<lb/>Where autumn and spring-time are wedded”,<note>Zweite Strophe aus Friedrich Schillers Gedicht «Berglied», 1804. ((trans. Edgar Alfred Bowring, 1851))</note><lb/> – for the surrounding countryside is truly very fine and richly cultivated.</p>
                <p>At the speed at which one now travels – on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>, that is – everything flies by so fast that it is impossible to get a proper look at anything, still less to compose a description of it. Earlier times were better for that, as can be read in the thick volumes by <placeName ref="gfa-places-16"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7918"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9754">Nikolai in Berlin</term></persName></placeName>Nikolai [Gretsch] in Berlin and the account of <placeName ref="gfa-places-748"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9701">Sophie’s Journey from Memel to Saxony</term></placeName>. — Nonetheless, I took note of several objects that to me seemed not entirely trivial. First, there are the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hop gardens</term> that are so frequent here on <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England’s</placeName> southern and south-eastern flank. Had I not known that there are no <term ref="gfa-keywords-9620">vineyards</term> in England, I would have mistaken them for vines such as those that grow in our parts, for they use the same circa 6-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term>-long stakes, space them the same 33 to 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> apart, and treat the soil in much the same way too. How much <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">timber</term> must be saved compared to <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany’s</placeName> 20-foot-long hop poles? How much easier the procurement? And how many more plants can be grown on the same area? Being no <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agronomist</term>, I shall refrain from passing judgment, though I am bound to believe that the calmly analytical and mathematically minded Englishmen <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588412" break="no"/> must have found a significant advantage in this manner of hop-growing. Second, there is the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electro-galvanic</term><note>Korrekturanweisung aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588463">Erstdruck</ref>: «Correctur. Statt <term ref="gfa-keywords-9752">electrogalvanische</term>, lies: electromagnetische».</note> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term>, whose 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">copper wires</term></term> run alongside the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term> from one specially erected pole to the next, and whose speedy reports leave even the fastest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam train</term> far behind them like a lame horse; and third, there are the timber underlays for the iron rails, of which all those that I have seen in Germany and <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> were elongated <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">rectangles</term> or had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">rounded</term> underside, whereas those in England are equilateral <term ref="gfa-keywords-9849">triangles</term>, which makes perfect sense to me; and not just because of the timber that is saved in this way, since they can be cut apart out of relatively thick planks, but also because on pondering the matter further, having at first glance not known what to make of them, I realised that as paradoxical as it seems, their resistance to the pressure from above, disregarding that from the sides, will be greater than that of the aforementioned shapes or cross-sections. At <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2130" when="1845-07-21" n="30">New Cross</placeName>, 10 miles from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, I at last came to that important <placeName ref="gfa-places-2198">place</placeName> where an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric line</term> is being laid parallel to the conventional one. This bold and audacious idea proves that no one in England is deterred by difficulties that do not carry within them <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588413" break="no"/> the impossibility of their removal. A large part of the tube, which depending on the needs of the moment is either open or sealed tight, has been laid (<placeName ref="gfa-places-1933">Dublin</placeName> has had such a line in operation for some time now), and on my pending return from the north of England I shall doubtless have occasion to make further remarks on this great innovation. Since it is still fiercely contested, if only on account of the many interests imperilled by it, I shall confine myself for now to observing that the rails are not only thinner than those of the ordinary railway alongside it, but also thinner than those that I saw in France and Germany – unless my eyes, in which I generally have great confidence, deceive me. How much difference in weight such a ⅓ reduction in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">thickness</term> and breadth actually brings per mile of line, assuming that third to be truly superfluous, I leave it to those to calculate who know, as does Nature herself, how to apply the lex parsimoniae without impairing solidity.</p>
                <p>At last I had the pleasure of arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1845-07-21T18:00:00" n="31">London</placeName> – healthy and happy, thank God – at 6 o’clock in the evening, and half an hour later was at my lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2131" when="1845-07-21T18:30:00" n="32">Bull &amp; Mouth Inn</placeName> located opposite the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2132">Post Office</placeName>. Thus a journey that had not been entirely free of travails, and with it today’s diary entry, ended with a letter <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>.</p>
        </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Alte und neue Bekanntschaften in London, 22. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>My most pressing appointment on the <date when="1845-07-22">22nd</date> was at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1845-07-22" n="33">mint</placeName>, where I was to meet Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, an outstanding <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588414" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8917">chemist</term>, who holds the important post of “Master of the Die Office”. On being told that he was in the country, I left him a copy of the letter, which I had previously translated into <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName>, that the assayer Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7848">Haindl</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName> had been so kind as to write to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7770">Barre</persName> at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1602">mint</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, extolling the quality of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">coin punch</term> with which I had supplied him, and left again with a promise to return the next day. —Then I went to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1845-07-22" n="34" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, a shareholder in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">large ironworks</term>, to whom my friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7525">E.</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Z.</placeName> had been so kind as to commend me, as also to several other most excellent iron and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel manufacturers</term> in the North of England. Mr. K. complained about the large number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term> that crack when <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">tempered</term>, and how even very dextrous workers have accidents with them. He then showed me one such punch, of a very low height, which in desperation they had sought to remedy by actually <term ref="gfa-keywords-194">welding</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> onto <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. This punch, of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter and octagonal in shape, presumably because round forging would have opened it up in the middle, had been kept low that it might remain whole on tempering, though its thinness also meant that it did not last long.</p>
                <p>I had a long conversation with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8263">K.’s son</persName> about the smelting of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and then again with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, for as I said, he is himself a shareholder in <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588415"/> a large ironworks as well as being a highly skilled smelter who has already won a prize for his work. —I left with an invitation to come again whenever I wished and the assurance that his father would be delighted to make my acquaintance and to commend me to a large ironworks in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2078">Yorkshire</placeName>, whose smelting with coke and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">cold blast</term> (as opposed to the hot blast used with anthracite) produces very good iron. Remarking on my ability to express myself adequately on the subjects in question, or so it seemed to him, he was confident that I would be well received there. After leaving him I proceeded to an esteemed compatriot of mine, Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-22" n="35"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Imthurn</persName></placeName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1646">Fenchurch Street</placeName>, and from there, on the off-chance that he might still be in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, went to call on my nephew Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">A. Winz</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">family</persName>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Imthurn and I talked for some time about the most pressing matter of the day in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, namely the means by which we might, with outside help, finance a <term ref="gfa-keywords-169"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">railway line</placeName></term> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> to Schaffhausen and from there to <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanz</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The letter from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7971">Zündel</persName> explaining in detail the obvious advantages of building a railway along the above route that I had delivered to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8254">P.</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, having first made a copy of the same, I now handed over to <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588416" break="no"/> Mr. Imthurn, along with still more details of the planned undertaking, that they might be of service to him here in promoting the formation of a company for this purpose in England.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer besucht das Patentamt, 23. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>After visiting Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-23" n="36"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Imthurn</persName></placeName> again, I returned to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1845-07-23" n="37"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582">mint</orgName></placeName>, where Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> welcomed me as an old friend. Since he had already examined the sample <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term> that I had left there the day before, he placed an order for the same in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">steel</term>, which he had hitherto procured from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman</persName>, he said, albeit with uneven results. I now showed him the components of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion lock</term> made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">cast bar iron</term>, which he found very interesting, and in answer to my question as to whether such a thing had ever been made in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> remarked that not only did he not know of a single instance of it but it had long been deemed all but impossible. Just as we were beginning to talk in greater depth about this object that seemed to matter so much to him, two gentlemen arrived wishing to speak to him forthwith, whereupon he asked me to visit him again on my return from the north of England, which I had told him was where I intended to go next after leaving him. Having been given an incorrect house number, my long walk from the mint to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-07-23" n="38"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">Winz</persName></placeName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-2135">Frederick Street</placeName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2112">Grays Inn Lane</placeName> was all for nothing, and I was glad to have time <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588417"/> to visit the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-23" n="39"><term ref="gfa-keywords-239">Register Office for Patent Applications</term></placeName><note>Möglicherweise besuchte Fischer Moses Poole in seinem privaten <placeName ref="gfa-places-2219">Patentbüro</placeName>.</note> and there acquaint the secretary, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName>, with my appendage of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708">caveats</term> to the priority of two of my inventions, the one of which now reads:<emph rend="italic">«for an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term>, proper to be mixed and fused with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">Pig-iron</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Steel</term> of every description, and also <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">Bar</term> or forged, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-2965">Scrape-iron</term>;»</emph> and the other: <emph rend="italic">«for a new way of making Horseshoes, and also Shoes for all other Kinds of Cattle»</emph>.</p>
                <p>He was very friendly, and as it seemed to him that I had not quite understood certain remarks of his, gave me a booklet about patent applications and how one must conduct oneself when making one, inviting me to come again the following day.</p>
                <p>At this juncture I cannot help but remark on what a difference I noticed between this – one might almost call it – amiability and the unpolished manners and moroseness of many an official in other countries.</p>
                <p>As it rained almost the whole day, and I had long errands to run, I took a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term>, which cost me 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">sh.</term> or 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> per hour. —That occasioned me sufficient opportunity to see the dangers and disadvantages of London’s much vaunted wooden paving, which it seems that even the circumspect and scrupulous English have all too hastily adopted, as many of the most frequented streets in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588418"/> are now paved in this way. Whenever it rains, the filth composed of dust, horse dung, abraded wood and detritus of all kinds becomes as slippery as black ice so that coachmen and carriers – whose horses, owing to the stone-paved streets in between, naturally do not wear <term ref="gfa-keywords-9709">sharpened shoes</term> for this purpose – are able to proceed only very slowly, yet still slide away and even fall from time to time. My coachman cursed the paving and said that in winter it was much worse.</p>
                <p>Having covered such distances, some of them by cab, some on foot, I concluded the day with letters to my <persName ref="gfa-actors-148"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">three sons</persName></persName></persName>, who are now established in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, telling them of my safe arrival in England and of the business affairs that occasioned the journey. I then had lunch, or rather supper, since it was after 7 o'clock by then, in a very genteel <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">coffeehouse</term> (the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2136" when="1845-07-23T19:00:00" n="41" cert="0">Post Office Coffeehouse</placeName>), where for exactly the same spread, a meal with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term> costs half what it does in the so-called hotels, where the luxuriousness of the interiors, as in the one in which I am currently residing, is excessive, but still has to be paid for by the guests.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Neveu Winz und hüttenmännisches Fachsimpeln mit Herrn K., 24. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>On the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1845-07-24">24th</date></placeName>, having obtained the correct address, I visited my nephew Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-07-24" n="42"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">Winz</persName></placeName> and his <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">family</persName>, but found him not at home, though I <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588419"/> was to meet him later at Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-07-24" n="43"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im-Thurn’s</persName></placeName>, who kindly accompanied me to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-24" n="44">Register Office</placeName>. There, for a registration fee of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds</term> and 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> (25 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>) Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName> entered my petition for two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708"><term ref="gfa-keywords-239">caveats</term></term> in the protocol just as I had previously written them up and presented to him. On the way back I again called on Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1845-07-24" n="45" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, to discuss with him some matters relating to the smelting of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> and then again with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, and with hot or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">cold blast</term>. He told me that in general, smelting with anthracite is done with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9712">hot blast</term>, the air for which has to pass through a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9711">system of siphons</term> in which it is heated to a temperature at which <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> would melt, while the anthracite, having had to make the long journey through a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">furnace shaft</term> of 48 to 50 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in height, has already turned to coke by the time it enters the smelting chamber, whereas if coke is used directly cold blast is applied.</p>
                <p>He showed me a drawing of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1877"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2148">Alfredton</placeName></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1925">Derbyshire</placeName><note>Möglicherweise handelte es sich um <placeName ref="gfa-places-2215">Butterley Works</placeName>.</note>, which 40 years previously the proprietor <term ref="gfa-keywords-8491"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7601">Wilkinson</persName></term> had introduced at the Bradley <placeName ref="gfa-places-1752"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1756">Bradley ironworks</placeName></term></placeName>, but which since then had not received the attention, either in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> or on the Continent, that the nature of it deserved. I soon afterwards had an opportunity to persuade myself of its most salient advantage <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588420"/> in the operation of a small <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">cupola furnace</term> fired with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">charcoal</term>, which was blasted with air through not just one or two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9715">nozzles</term> on opposite sides of the furnace, as is done here and there, but three of nozzles spaced apart in an equilateral triangle.</p>
                <p>While in some places in England the stand for this is made of refractory <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">brick</term>, here the most excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-9714">sandstone</term> was used, as it was for the building itself. The iron obtained from smelting ore with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> was at any rate better, he said, though it was also dearer in most cases, since in his experience, 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term>, converted into coke, weighed only 3¾ cwt, and 2½ cwt of coke was necessary to extract 1 cwt of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9009">pig iron</term> from 35-per-cent ore. — My best source of information on this matter, he added, would be the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2137">Low Moor Ironworks</placeName>, where they smelted with cold blast and coke, to which I was to convey a letter of his. The works of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7794"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2215">Butlery Iron Company</placeName></orgName> in which he himself had a stake, meanwhile, used anthracite and hot blast. Exactly how low and narrow a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">coke-fired blast furnace</term> would have to be at its 3 principal diameters he could not say, though he was able to tell me where I might surely learn the same.</p>
                <p>After dinner, which was at 5 o’clock in the afternoon, <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588421"/> I went for a walk through <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1611" when="1845-07-24T17:00:00" n="46">Cheapside</placeName> and along <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1612" when="1845-07-24" n="47">Ludgate Hill</placeName> as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2026" when="1845-07-24" n="48">Fleet Street</placeName>, where whatever wares it may contain, one store after another seeks to outdo all the others in abundance, variety, elegance, and indeed luxury, and where, quite apart from whatever else is to be found stacked up in other English cities, and quite apart from the thousands of ships that come and go, one is soon persuaded that this country really is the world’s marketplace answering the world’s demand.</p>
                <p>As an example of this luxury, I shall mention a <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2139" when="1845-07-24" n="49">shop</placeName> I saw that sells shawls, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9452">silks</term> and such like fashion accessories. The said shop has ceilings twice the normal height, that is 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, and its entrance takes the shape of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9850">inward-pointing convex triangle</term>, whose severed apex is the doorway. The 4 points on each side are the 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term> columns, the spaces between which are filled by 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>, arranged to face each other so that what one actually sees are 8 panes of 18 feet in height and 3½ feet in width, behind which all the finest things are piled up in tiers. The inside walls, moreover, are likewise covered in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>, which at night, especially, when all the many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> are burning, makes for a most surprising sight on account of their being multiplied by all the many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirrors</term>. This shop is located in the building called <placeName ref="gfa-places-2139">Gloucester House</placeName> <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588422"/> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612">Ludgate Hill</placeName>, which is owned by <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7852">Harvey &amp; Son</orgName>. —I lingered for a long time in front of this magazine in which all the most precious of the aforementioned articles were assembled and amassed, but still have no idea how this profligate display might retain its interest, given how much competition there is from others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer und Neveu Winz besuchen die Polytechnical Institution, 25. Juli 1845</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1845-07-25">Today</date></placeName> my route more than once took me past the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2150" when="1845-07-25" n="50"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9718">statue</term></placeName> of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7756">Duke of Wellington</persName> erected two years ago, which shows him as a mounted general and whose oval plinth is inscribed solely with the name “Wellington”. Who modelled it and cast it I do not know<note>Der Künstler war <persName ref="gfa-actors-8264">Francis Leggatt Chantrey</persName>.</note>, but that the art of casting has brought forth a so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9719">patina</term> or Aerugo nobilis (which normally is at once a result and marker of great age), while the gentleman himself is still alive seems to me to be a breach of decorum. No such error was made on the outstanding casts to be seen in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName>, apart from there where it served to make them more readily apparent or promised to show the accomplishment of the artist to better advantage than would a wholly dark silhouette. Whether the horse is too large and too fat in relation to the figure of Wellington I dare not say, as nothing could be further from my mind than to pretend to be a judge of art.</p>
                <p>This morning, after a visit to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2002" when="1845-07-25" n="51">Patent Office</placeName>, where I received the 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9708">caveats</term> for my inventions from Mr. <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588423"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName>, I accompanied my nephew Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">A. Winz</persName> to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8341"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2140" when="1845-07-25" n="52">Polytechnical Institution</placeName></orgName> to see the curious objects that the arts and crafts of this country have lately brought forth, first and foremost among them the “working model” of the much talked-of, and, in respect of its practical utility, frequently and fiercely contested invention of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric railway</term> set up there by Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7944">Samuda</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7797">Clegg</persName>. The new objects, most of them from the field of engineering, were so extremely numerous that it would have taken days just to inspect them properly, nor does space permit even a superficial enumeration of the same; suffice it to say, therefore, that only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> can something at once so great and so instructive be accomplished, since only a <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">city</placeName> that will soon number 1½ million inhabitants can supply enough inquiring minds for the admission tickets needed to cover the costs of this undertaking. Here, therefore, I shall mention only the small, I believe 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> that had to run constantly in order to work the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term> needed keep the tube, which is circa 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term> long with an internal bore of about 5/4<term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term>, or so it seemed to me, sufficiently emptied of air to drive the 5 little wagons hooked one behind the other, each of which had a seat for one person. The front wagon, of course, <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588424"/> was attached to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> by means of a vertical rod. The rimmed tubes, moreover, each have a narrow opening or slit at the top that is opened only by the piston approaching from some distance away and then is closed again by special valves, thus ensuring that the said piston is always travelling through an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">airless</term> and air-tight tube. This extremely fast railway was mounted on a 3-foot-high gantry running alongside a basin filled with water 14 feet deep, on which a little <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> chugged around and a boy in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8858">diving bell</term> was dropped down to the bottom. —I must in all honesty confess that I arrived in England with quite a strong prejudice against atmospheric railways, doubting both their feasibility and what I imagined to be the manifold difficulties of maintaining a good, air-tight system capable of operating without interruption. Now that I have seen this model and the efficacy of the method – notwithstanding the small diameter of the tube – in action, however, and have learned that just such a railway, albeit not of any great length, has been running daily in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1933">Dublin</placeName> at greater speeds than a conventional <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> ever could and that the said railway is indeed used so that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">parliament</term>, responding to the extremely favourable expert report on it, <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588425"/> will not object to a concession being granted to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8269">company</orgName> now wishing to run such a railway from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1918">Croydon</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, a distance of 48 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, which owing to the advanced state of the preparations for the same will be able to go into service very soon and whose shareholders will doubtless have verified the feasibility of every aspect of the venture, I have now changed my mind and believe that atmospheric railways will supplant or modify conventional locomotive-driven railways if not wholly, then at least in part. As it is worth making the effort to know the factors that speak both for and against this new invention, and to do so before it becomes part of our lives so that when that happens, it will become apparent from its constant success or want of success which side was the most right, I would like to devote some space to the pros and cons of this most important matter such as I have been able to ascertain during my stay here in England.</p>
                <p>One principal objection that is made is that were there to be even the tiniest gap between the tubes and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term> being drawn along, as might happen very easily, the wagons would inevitably come to a standstill, as it would no longer be possible to create a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">vacuum</term>. <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588426"/> Responding to this certainly legitimate objection, Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7944">Samuda</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7797">Clegg</persName> claim that the air pump, which has a diameter of 57½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term>, is powerful enough to render the iron pipes airless over their entire length, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9176">pressure gauges</term> at either end at the same level, within just 5 to at most 6 minutes, so that even if air were to stream in through an imperceptible crack (a large one would be noticed immediately and could be refilled or another section of pipe inserted inside it so as not to occasion any great delay), the vacuum, though not complete, would still be sufficient to drive the piston, and with it the wagons, to the nearest station, which at worst would be ½ an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English mile</term> away (circa 5500 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>) – and at an acceptable speed, too, especially if, as could be easily enough accomplished, the number of piston strokes set in motion by the air pump were multiplied by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>. Having arrived at the station, a new system of pipes would commence, as it does in any case at one-mile intervals. —</p>
                <p>The second principal objection is the cost. This was likewise countered by the assertion, supported by a detailed calculation published in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9570">Times illustrated</term>, that the installation and operation of an atmospheric railway would cost less than ⅔ of what a railway run with conventional locomotives costs. To delve into the details <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588427" break="no"/> of this calculation would be going too far here, though it seems to me that this is a matter of great importance to railway entrepreneurs, since one cannot presume to present obviously incorrect information to a public such as that in England, where competent judges abound.</p>
                <p>The day’s business ended quite early with the purchase of various items and packing for tomorrow’s departure for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, 205 miles hence, the train for which leaves from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666">Euston Station</placeName>, which is itself some miles away from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2231">City of London</placeName>, where I am currently <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2131" when="1845-07-25" n="53">residing</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>London–Leeds, 26. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>For a fare of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> took me all the way to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1666" when="1845-07-26T11:00:00" n="54">Euston Station</placeName>, where for a seat in the second class to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> I had to pay 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pound</term> and 15 shillings or 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9722">Reichsgeld</term>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">train</term> departed at 11 o’clock in the morning. Notwithstanding the 20 stops and more en route with just enough time for people to get on and off, and that we were held up in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2074" when="1845-07-26" n="55">Weldon</placeName> for 5 and in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1257" n="56">Derby</placeName> for 25 minutes, so that we might eat some lunch, we still arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-26T18:30:00" n="59">Leeds</placeName> at half past 6 that evening, meaning that the astonishing distance of 205 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English</term> or 41 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term>, which translates into a rate of 12 miles per hour or twenty-four <term ref="gfa-keywords-9723">Wegstunden</term>, was overcome at a speed such as I have encountered nowhere else. It is all but impossible to observe anything at such a speed, though from time to time, there where the terrain by chance afforded an expansive view, <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588428"/> not far from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-30" when="1845-07-26" n="57">Coventry</placeName> where the hay was being brought in, I did have an opportunity to do so; it was a most <term ref="gfa-keywords-9724">instructive sight</term>, revealing how with just one horse and one man, mown grass might be swiftly and evenly distributed over a very large meadow that it might dry all the faster. —For the horse was hitched to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">hollow wooden cylinder</term> of some 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in length and 4 feet in diameter. This consisted of nothing but laths, which were spaced about 10 to 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> apart and nailed onto the two base plates or discs at either end. These in turn had an axle passing through them, attached to whose protruding <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">hubs</term>, as on a clover roller, were the two inward-pointing shafts that formed the traces for the horse. The cylinder was filled with mown hay through a hatch in the roller, like that on a cylindrical <term ref="gfa-keywords-9725">coffee roaster</term> only with slits. Once the hatch was closed, the man had the horse set off whereupon the cylinder rotated so that every time one of the openings was facing downwards some of the mown grass fell out of it, always across the full length of the slit and always at the same distance from the previous one, until finally the cylinder was empty and had to be refilled.</p>
                <p>The passenger carriages were fitted with something very sensible that I have so far seen nowhere else except in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>: namely three round apertures in the ceiling, which on the outside are shielded with a bell or cap made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">iron sheet</term>, <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588429"/> whose side walls in turn have around 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">slits</term> in them so as to promote the circulation of air without troubling the passengers, as when cold weather or rain or storms make it necessary to keep all the windows shut. At night, the middle of the three apertures is fitted with a lantern, since the trains in England run both day and night.</p>
                <p>The optical illusion of the crooked <placeName ref="gfa-places-2141">spire</placeName> of <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1917" when="1845-07-26" n="58">Chesterfield</placeName>, which I reported in my earlier diary, delighted me all over again, as did the farmers’ pretty little <term ref="gfa-keywords-9726">windmills</term>, which turn into the wind all by themselves, and each one of which supplies as much flour on average as any large household might need. Almost all the cuttings along the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to Leeds are through first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9727">marl</term> and then <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">limestone</term>, the strata and fissures of the more northerly areas bearing a certain resemblance to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2061">Swabian Alb</placeName>. Despite being tended with great care, the fruits of the field were far behind, and nowhere near as fine as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> or at <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">home</placeName>. Another peculiarity that warrants mention is that on <date when="1845-07-26">26th July</date>, all the women in the carriage were wearing fur collars around their necks and were wrapped in shawls.</p>
                <p>As I said, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> after 6 o’clock in the evening and took lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2142" when="1845-07-26" n="60">White Horse Hotel</placeName>. —In the dining room, a gentleman clad all in black had no sooner entered than he lay down, dirty boots and all, on the very fine canapé. <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588430"/> Yet no one said a word, not even when he had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipe</term> brought to him that he might smoke in that very same attitude, which was all that had hitherto been missing to demonstrate the kind of man he was. Eighteen years had passed since my last visit to England, and I had imagined that since so much else had changed in the way of transport and domestic interiors, then surely many of the customs and habits and the way people dressed would have changed, too, only this was not the case. Foreigners make little impression on these taciturn, obdurate islanders, and too few of them ever reach the interior in any case. And should those that do become too bumptious, as so many peddlers of wisdom are prone to do with us good-natured <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName>, here they are simply ridiculed, or, better still, treated with utter contempt. The Englishman knows very well what he wants and what he can and is proud and ambitious, though he does not advertise this, unlike certain other people who just love to adorn themselves in whatever scraps of glory they can scrape together.</p>
                <p>To return to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9072">tobacco-smoking</term>: I had imagined that since this nasty habit had made such alarming progress on the Continent these past few years, it could not be otherwise than that the English would likewise have found it impossible to resist; yet that was not the case at all. I believe I am not mistaken in this, <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588431"/> and gladly cite persons who have recently returned from England and report that among a thousand male persons of all classes one will find scarcely a single tobacco smoker.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Betrachtungen zum Verkehr in England, 27. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>—The whole <date when="1845-07-27">day</date> was taken up with writing and the evening with a walk, although it was very windy and cold, and with inquiries into <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">stage-coaches</term> that might be leaving for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1907">Bradford</placeName>, a small town 26 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, on the morrow, say, that being a Sunday, which in Leeds is observed even more sombrely than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, making it impossible to visit anyone. I was told that I might leave for Bradford on any one of the ten departures that day. This uncommonly frequent service to all sorts of places and with it the circulation of people, and hence of money, is a consequence of the extraordinary network of railways that has already spread out all over <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and of being able to travel from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666">Euston-Station</placeName> near London to the north of England within just 24 hours, there being 12 trains both day and night as well as 2 “extra trains”. Consequently, there have to be stage-coaches on hand to bring those arriving and departing from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">station</term> to their destinations, which may be 10 or even 20 miles hence. — To return to the Sabbath, I noticed that not until 7 o’clock in the evening did large numbers of people of every age and sex come out of the church, even as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9728">Methodist</term> preacher on the market square <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588432" break="no"/> was preaching most fervently down from his perch to the rapt crowd below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Low Moor Ironworks, 28. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Today, exactly 14 days after my departure from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>, I was to see a member of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8090">family</persName> again, and there, where <ref type="cross" target="../1814/27">30 years ago</ref>, at almost exactly the same time of year, I enjoyed such friendship as would be repeated, always with the same warmth, on all my later visits to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, as outlined in my diaries of those trips.</p>
                <p>I knew by then that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">old Mr. Gott</persName> had died some years previously, but was received in the customary manner by his son, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">John Gott</persName>, whom I met betimes in the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-28" n="61">counting house</placeName><note>Es ist unklar, ob Fischer die <persName ref="gfa-actors-8090">Familie Gott</persName> an ihrer Wohnaddresse in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2220">27 Guildford Street</placeName> oder einen ihrer beiden Fabriken <placeName ref="gfa-places-1788">Armley Mill</placeName> oder <placeName ref="gfa-places-1795">Park Mill</placeName> aufsuchte.</note>. He immediately invited me to dine with him at his spendid <placeName ref="gfa-places-1794">country seat</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1975">Kirkdale</placeName>, 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, which I politely declined on the grounds that I wished to visit the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2137">Low Moor</placeName>, which had been commended to me most warmly. —“Both are possible, my friend”, said he; “just come to me, and I shall appoint one of my clerks to drive you to the place [here he glanced at the clock], where in just a few minutes you will be met by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">Kutsche</term> that will take you to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1907">Bradford</placeName>. There, take a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9122">gig</term> to Low Moor, which is 3 miles hence, and be sure to have him wait ready to take you back to Bradford afterwards. You can then take the 4 o’clock coach back to Leeds, and since we dine at around 6 o’clock or later, you <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588433"/> will be back just in time to join us, my country seat being hard by Kirkdale, as you know.” I could not object to any of this, and as the old counting house clerk had already taken his hat down off its hook, I commended myself and left. “I was very glad to see you again”, said the clerk, once outside the door and on the street. “I recognized you right away, though 18 years have passed since you were last with us.” I, too, remembered him, and being told of the then still secret method of using a solution of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">caoutchouc</term> to render cloth water-proof.</p>
                <p>On arriving at the inn, I scarcely had time to go inside since the coach was just about to depart. —The road from Leeds to Bradford leads past <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1975" when="1845-07-28" n="62">Kirkdale</placeName> (an Old English or rather Anglo-Saxon word, Kirchthal in German), not far from which, situated in a park-like setting on a pretty little hill grown over with oaks and other deciduous trees, is Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott’s</persName> splendid <placeName ref="gfa-places-1794">country seat</placeName>. From there, one looks out onto the fine ruins, some of them with their forms intact and charmingly overgrown with ivy and other plants, of one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-6532"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9750">monasteries destroyed</term></term> under <persName ref="gfa-actors-7854">Henry VIII</persName> which gave this area its name, and which owing to its many factories, ironworks and <term ref="gfa-keywords-6116">coal mines</term> is now full of activity so that one passes by fields, <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588434"/> villages and individual houses of the most varied appearance.</p>
                
                
                
                
                <p>Unweit von Leeds schon, und dann ununterbrochen bis nach Low Moor sah ich wieder eine eigenthümliche Industrie der Engländer. Ich gewahrte nämlich an dem Rand der Landstrasse von Distanz zu Distanz Blöcke von etwas prismatischer Form hingelegt, die ich wegen ihrem Farbenspiel, wenn sie nicht auswendig eine Glasur gehabt hätten, für <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">Marmor</term> würde angesehen haben. Später traf ich Leute bei diesen Blöcken an, die sie zerschlugen und Strassenmaterial daraus machten, und da erkannte ich, dass es <term ref="gfa-keywords-336">Hohenofenschlacke</term> von einem benachbarten <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Eisenwerk</term> seyn müsse, die man wegen einem bestimmten Quantum im Mass für deren Verarbeitung, und wegen leichterem und geschwinderem Auf- und Abladen, in eiserne Kasten laufen lasse, die, um ein leichteres Herausfallen dieser wenigstens 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> schweren Massen zu bewirken, oberwähnte Form erhalten, und die man, wenn hinreichend verkleinert, statt Kieselsteinen verwende, von denen vielleicht ohnediess keine in der Nähe Vorkommen, da bekanntlich Eisenschlacke das Beste ist, was man in dieser Beziehung haben kann. In <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1907" when="1845-07-28T12:00:00" n="63">Bradford</placeName> um 12 Uhr angelangt, nahm ich bei dortigem Sonnenwirth, der zugleich Posthalter ist, ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-9122">Gig</term> (zweirädrige Chaise), und fuhr nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2137" when="1845-07-28" n="64">Low Moor</placeName>, welches ich mir seinem Namen nach schon, ziemlich tief im Grunde denken konnte. Es war auch wirklich so. — Der Rauch aber aus den 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">Hochöfen</term>, der langen Reihe von <term ref="gfa-keywords-9232">Coksöfen</term>, <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588435"/> wo die kleinen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> durch cylindrische Siebe von den grossen geschieden und in geschlossenen Räumen durch Weibsbilder <term ref="gfa-keywords-9732">verkokt</term> werden, dann von den langen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9224">Kohlenmeilen</term>, wo die grossen, aber nicht ganz vorzüglich guten Steinkohlen in gewohnter Weise verkohlt werden, dann von den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9400">Refining</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">Puddling</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8849">Bloomfurnaces</term>, sowie von den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9135">Glühöfen</term> für die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">Hammer-</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">Walzwerke</term> verhinderte, das ganze, viele <term ref="gfa-keywords-9730">Morgen</term> Landes bedeckende, und für eigenen Gebrauch überall mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Schienenwegen</term> durchkreuzte Werk auf einmal ganz zu übersehen. Bei dem Eingang in dasselbige, oder des Porters-Lodge, wurde mein Pferd, als ich einem der Herren nachfrug, sogleich ausgespannt und in Stall geführt, ohne dass man mich, wie es etwa anderswo geschieht, mit naseweisen Fragen: wer ich seye, woher ich komme und was ich wolle etc.? belästigte, sondern es wurde mir gleich ein junger Mensch mitgegeben, der mich zu einem der Eigenthümer des <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7787">Werks</orgName> führte. Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7812">Dawson</persName>, so hiess er, nachdem er den Brief, den ich ihm übergeben, gelesen, nahm sogleich Hut und Stock, er war etwas übel zu Fuss, und führte mich volle 2 Stunden überall herum, wo er bei der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9231">Köhlerei</term> den Anfang machte, mich dann zu den Hochöfen und in die <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">Giesserei</term> führte, in welcher sie zu meiner Verwunderung auch noch <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">Reverberiröfen</term> hatten, aber, wie er mir sagte, sie nur für gewisse Zwecke gebrauchen. Ich vermuthe für die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">Walzen</term> zu giessen, die sie, <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588436"/> was wichtig ist, selbst machen, und die wirklich vorzüglich schön und bedeutend hart waren, und die man in den <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">Cupoloöfen</term> fast nie in der Weise und mit Sicherheit erlangen kann. Von dort gingen wir zu den andern bereits erwähnten Oefen und zu dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9731">Gebläse</term>, welches durch zwei <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">Dampfmaschinen</term>, jede von 160 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">Pferdekraft</term> betrieben wird, um für alle Feuer den erforderlichen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">Wind</term> zu geben, den sie aber überall nur kalt gebrauchen, weil der warme Wind, wie er mir sagte, für Hochöfen mit Cokebetrieb nicht, wohl aber mit Steinkohlenbetrieb dienen könne. Die Spannung des Windes hier ist für die Hochöfen 3 ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pfund</term> per [<term ref="gfa-keywords-9851"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Quadratfuss</term></term>]<note>«Quadratfuss» im Erstdruck als Piktogramm dargestellt.</note>. was schon viel sagen will. — Was mich in diesem Werk noch sehr interessirte, und beweisst, wie die Engländer alles, was praktisch gut ist, sogleich annehmen, ist die Anwendung einer Entdeckung, die der geniale <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName> machte. — Wohlgemerkt, Perkins ist ein <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">Amerikaner</placeName>, und betrieb früher, wie er mir vor 18 Jahren sagte, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2073">Washington</placeName> die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9138"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8720">Goldschmiedprofession</term></term>. Er fand nämlich, dass es möglich seye, mit einer ganz dünnen Scheibe von weichem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">Eisenblech</term> die härteste englische <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">Feile</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8662">entzweizuschneiden</term>, wenn man dieser Scheibe auf dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9643">Drehstuhl</term> oder sonstwo eine äusserst schnelle Rotation gebe. Dieses wird nun hier im Grossen angewendet. Zwei solcher Scheiben von circa 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fuss</term> Durchmesser, die in gehöriger Entfernung (meiner ungefähren Schätzung nach mochte sie 10 Fuss betragen), auf ein und demselben <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">Wendelbaum</term> befestiget, und durch bis <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588437"/> auf 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term> gegen den Rand hinausgehende, dicke, eiserne Gegenplatten gerade und steif gehalten werden, laufen mit einer ungemeinen Schnelligkeit herum. Die von dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">Walzwerk</term> aus fertige, und wenn etwa verkrümmt, mit einem hölzernen Schlegel auf einer ganz ebenen, langen, eisernen Platte gerade gerichteten Schiene, wird an diese Scheiben angedrückt, und von denselben, als wenn es <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">Holz</term> wäre, durchschnitten. Unten laufen die Scheiben in einem Trog mit beständig zufliessendem kalten Wasser, dass sie kalt bleiben.</p>
                <p>Hinsichtlich des Betriebs von diesem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Eisenwerk</term> ist die Lage dafür so günstig als nur möglich. In der Nähe bedeutende Städte und namentlich Leeds; umgeben von Schachten, wo aus ein und demselbigen, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">Kalk</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">Eisenerz</term> herausgefördert wird, und wo die damit beladenen Wagen auf ihrem Schienenweg, der gegen das Werk hinunter, da der Haspel des Förderschachtes höher liegt, ein Planum inclinatum von nur so viel Gefäll bildet, dass dieselben ganz von selbst, aber ohne in schnellen Lauf zu kommen, an dem Ort ihrer Bestimmung anlangen, dort entladen, und auf einem andern Schienenweg durch ein Pferd wieder hinaufgeschafft werden. Durch das Zusammenwirken dieser Umstände kommt, wie mir Herr Dawson sagte, der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> Steinkohlen, zu 112 englischen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pfunden</term> gerechnet, zum Verkohlungs- oder eigentlich <term ref="gfa-keywords-9732">Vercokungsplatz</term> geliefert, nicht vollkommen auf 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Penny</term>, oder scharf gerechnet auf 2 ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9722">Reichsvaluta</term>. Die Eisenerze sind arm und geben nur <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588438"/> 25 Procent Eisen, und müssen aber, ehe man sie in den <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">Hochofen</term> aufgeben kann, zuerst noch <term ref="gfa-keywords-8652">geröstet</term> werden. Der Zuschlag vom Kalk ist 25 Pfd. zum Ctr. Eisen, den die Erze geben, und hiemit auf den Ctr. Erz circa 6 Pfd. Der Kohlensatz ist 3 Ctr. <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term> per den Ctr. des zu erhaltenden <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">Roheisens</term>, oder 75 Pfd. per 1 Ctr. Erz, was mir ziemlich viel scheint. Würde man die Verhältnisse auf Steinkohlen reduciren, so brauchte man für jeden Ctr. circa 120 Pfd. Steinkohlen, oder für jeden Ctr. des zu erschmelzenden Roheisens circa 480 Pfd. Das hier erzeugte <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">Roheisen</term> ist schön grau, doch nicht immer gleich im Korn. Es werden desnahen von jedem <term ref="gfa-keywords-3479">Abstich</term> Muster genommen, und wie der Abstich, der einen Rost bildet und aus lauter kleinen Gänsen besteht, wie man sie in die <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">Cupolo-Oefen</term> gebraucht, nummerirt. ln dieser Beziehung Eisen von bestimmter und verlangter Qualität an den Consumenten zu liefern, sind die Engländer viel gewissenhafter, als manche Hüttenherren des festen Landes. Sie wissen aber auch wohl aus eigener Erfahrung, wie viel in jeder Beziehung von der Güte des Eisens abhängt, und wem bekannt, wie schwierig die Darstellung von gutem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">Stabeisen</term> mit Coke oder Steinkohlen erzeugt, ist, der wird sich über ihre Sorgfalt nicht wundern, welche auch hier auf diesem Werk bei der ganzen Prozedur, nämlich dem Umschmelzen des Roheisens, fine Eisen, dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8538">Puddeln</term>, Abschweissen und dann noch einer sonstigen Behandlung, die ich anderwärts nie gesehen, beobachtet wird, <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588439"/> und das Ergebniss hat, dass dieses Eisen als das vorzüglichste mit Coke bereitet, gilt, aber auch theurer als alles andere verkauft wird. — Es war Zeit, wieder nach Leeds zurückzukehren, und ich beurlaubte mich bei Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7812">Dawson</persName>, der dem Empfehlungsbrief durch möglichste Zuvorkommenheit, die sich nebst jeder gewünschten Erläuterung noch auf die gefällige eigenhändige Zustellung von Erz-, Kalk-, Steinkohlen-, Coks- und Eisenmustern durch alle Stadien hindurch, vom Roheisen bis zum fertigen Stabeisen erstreckte, die grösste Ehre machte, mit bestem Dank.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Abendgesellschaft in der Villa Gott, 28. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Um 4 Uhr Abends kam die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">Postkutsche</term> von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1960">Halifax</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-keywords-1760">Leeds</placeName> gehend durch <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1907" when="1845-07-28T16:00:00" n="65">Bradford</placeName>, und um 6 Uhr war ich auf dem <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1794" when="1845-07-28T18:00:00" n="66">Landsitz</placeName> von Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName>.</p>
                <p>Er war noch nicht aus der Stadt zurück, und nachdem mich der Bediente vorher in ein Zimmer geführt, um meine Toilette machen zu können, was in der That, aus dem Schooss eines <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Eisenwerks</term> zurückgekehrt, wo man ununterbrochen in Wolken von Rauch, Kohlenstaub und Dampf eingehüllt ist, nicht unnöthig war, ersuchte er mich dann, in die <term ref="gfa-keywords-1883">Bibliothek</term> einzutreten. Mit kostbaren Werken älterer und neuerer Zeit, und kostbar eingebunden, mit kostbaren Gemälden und <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">Kupferstichen</term>, mit Büsten von cararischem, auf Säulen von buntem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">Marmor</term> mit weissen Postamenten stehend, und mit entsprechendem Ammeublement war dieses Asyl für den Geist, der von dem täglichen Geschäftsleben Erholung sucht, ausgeschmückt.</p>
                <p><pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588440"/> Von der Aufstellung von drei ausgestopften Nachteulen, die wie Wächter vor dem grossen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">Spiegel</term> standen, konnte ich den Grund ihres Hierseyns nicht errathen, mochte aber natürlicher Weise nicht darnach fragen, als mich später Herr <persName ref="gfa-keywords-7843">Gott</persName> abholte, um mich in das Besuchzimmer zu führen, wo noch 4 Herren und 5 Damen anwesend waren. Nach sieben Uhr in den reich geschmückten Speisesaal eintretend, setzten wir uns zu einem sehr splendiden Mittagessen nieder, bei welchem drei Bediente nebst dem Kellermeister (Butler) aufwarteten, an dem ich mich übrigens, obschon ich seit 12 Stunden, mit Ausnahme von etwas <term ref="gfa-keywords-9734">Eibischwurzthee</term> in Bradford, das mir der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9735">Apotheker</term> verschafft hatte, nicht erlaben konnte. Heiser und unwohl, in Folge einer Erkältung, die ich mir schon in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> zugezogen hatte, und einer Arzneiflasche in der Tasche, musste ich mich schonen, um aus Uebel nicht ärger zu machen, und die viererlei Gläser zu viererlei <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">Weinen</term> standen unbenützt vor mir. Nachdem die Frauenzimmer, wie gewohnt, sich von der Tafel zurückgezogen, wo dann die Herren noch zum Trinken und Besprechen sie interessirender Gegenstände sitzen blieben, kamen sogleich die <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term> auf das Tapet, und da mir Herr Gott sagte, er gehe morgen mit einem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9092">Ingenieur</term>, da er viel Interesse an diesem Gegenstand nehme, für Anlegung einer Zweigbahn wohin, so fand ich es angemessen, das <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">Projekt</placeName> von der <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhauser</placeName>-<placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Konstanzer</placeName> Eisenbahn, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> her sich ziehend, zur Sprache zu bringen, und ihm die <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588441"/> Wichtigkeit sowie die günstige Beschaffenheit des Terrains auseinanderzusetzen und dabei zu bemerken, dass wir aber noch fremder Kapitalien für Ausführung dieses Plans bedürfen, da eigene Kräfte nicht ausreichen. — Schon am Mittagessen glaubte ich einen mir gerade gegenüber sitzenden Herrn irgendwo gesehen zu haben; wir waren nun wegen Abwesenheit der Frauenzimmer näher zusammengerückt, und da rief Herr Gott auf einmal aus: wir wollen hören, was Ihr Landsmann dazu sagt? — ich gieng gleich zu ihm hinüber, und da ergab es sich, dass es Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7782">Bischof</persName> von Basel war, den ich vor 18 oder 20 Jahren auch bei Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName> als Freund von Hause kennen gelernt hatte. Ich war nun froh, mich auf ihn wegen Manchem beziehen zu können, und er bestätigte Alles, was ich vorgebracht hatte. — Der Bediente kam, um uns in das Theezimmer zu rufen, und ich sagte dem Herrn Gott nur noch kurz, er solle die Sache in Betrachtung nehmen, ich wolle ihm aber noch schreiben. — Bekanntlich trinkt man den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">Thee</term> nirgends besser und noch mit so viel Nebenumständen begleitet, als wie in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. Ich hatte zwar diesem Getränk, von dem ich glauben musste, es verursache mir Schlaflosigkeit, schon seit einigen Jahren entsagt, aber hier wurde er mir zur wahren Lebensquelle, da ich schon einige Tage von heftigem Durst wegen meinem Unwohlseyn geplagt war. In diesem Theezimmer, oder vielmehr Theesaal, mit den kostbarsten Meubeln nebst herrlich duftenden Blumen und <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588442"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9580">Treibhauspflanzen</term> ausgeschmückt, war im Hintergrund, die vordern fast zur Erde reichenden Fenster nebst der Glasthüre gingen gegen den Garten hinaus, eine bis an die Decke der sehr hohen Zimmer reichende <term ref="gfa-keywords-9736">Orgel</term> aufgestellt, und dann in der Mitte stund ein grosser, runder Tisch von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8774">Acajou</term>, mit Zeitungen, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">Lithographien</term> des Tages, und den Heften der Zerrbilder überlegt, die die verschiedenen Phasen des ehelichen Lebens von <term ref="gfa-keywords-9862">Mr. Caudle &amp; his Wife</term> (Herrn Caudle und seiner Frau) vorstellend, welchen der englische Erfindungs- und Verbesserungsgeist nun noch veränderliche Gesichter von <persName ref="gfa-actors-8273">Frau Caudle</persName> (changeable faces of mistress Caudle), die durch Schnürchen hinter dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">Kupferstich</term>, an denen man zieht, an ihren Platz gebracht werden, damit die Physiognomie zur dargestellten Scene auch recht passe, woran sich, wie es scheint, die Engländer sehr ergötzen, denn man sieht sie gegenwärtig in allen Kupferstichläden zur Schau und zum Verkauf ausgestellt.— Zum Schluss der Schilderung dieses Zimmers bemerke ich noch, dass heute, am <date when="1845-07-26">28. Heumonat</date>, im Kamin ein lustiges Feuer brannte, und in der That, wenn man in das Freie hinauskommt, bedünkt Einen, das Korn werde immer grüner, statt gelber. — Um 10 Uhr beurlaubte ich mich bei Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> und der Gesellschaft, welcher noch <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">Kaffee</term> herumgeboten wurde, und ein vor der Thüre stehendes <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">Cab</term> brachte mich in das 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> entfernte <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-28T22:00:00" n="67">Leeds</placeName> zurück.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer schreibt einen Brief an seine Enkelin, 29. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Mit dem Schreiben eines grossen Briefes an Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> und der Copianahme da<pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588443" break="no"/>von, sowie eines Briefes an meine Enkelin <persName ref="gfa-actors-7692">Mathilde</persName>, damit meine Familie zu Hause auch wisse, wo ich in der Welt seye, ging beinahe der ganze Tag hin, den ich noch mit einem Gang auf das <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-29" n="68">Comptoir</placeName> von Herrn Gott und einem Spaziergang durch einen Theil der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Stadt</placeName> beschloss.</p>
                <p>Der Charakter dieser, übrigens sehr grossen, Stadt, ist von dem von <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> ganz verschieden. Der allgemeine Wohlstand und die Reinlichkeit selbst in den entlegenen Strassen, denn dort muss man den Massstab anschlagen, scheint mir grösser zu seyn. Alles, was eben nur Hände hat, arbeitet hier, und verdient hiemit. Die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">Tuchmanufacturen</term> und die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">Flachsspinnereien</term> sind sehr im Flor, und wie sich die Menge der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9341">Obelisken</term>, die mehr Nutzen bringen, als ihre Brüder in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypten</placeName>, ich meine die zuweilen 60 bis 80 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fuss</term> und noch darüber sich erhebenden Kamine der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">Dampfmaschinen</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">Schmelzöfen</term> etc. vermehrt hat, ist erstaunend, und gibt der Stadt von Weitem ein ganz eigenthümliches Ansehen. Reiten und Fahren, mit Ausnahme der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">Cabs</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">Omnibus</term> zum Bahnhof und der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">Diligencen</term> nach den Seitenörtern, sieht man hier gar nicht viel; die Läden hingegen sind im Allgemeinen schön, und manche sogar reich ausstaffirt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Betrachtungen zum Eisenbahnwesen, 30. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Beinahe den ganzen Tag mit Schreiben zubringend, da das in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> in dieser Jahreszeit häufigere Regenwetter als bei uns das Ausgehen nicht erlaubte, durchging ich noch <term ref="gfa-keywords-9738">Brad-Shaws, Railway und Steam-Navigation-Guide</term> (Bradshaws Anleitung für Benützung der <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588444"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term> und der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Dampfschiffe</term>). Es ist erstaunend, wie vielerlei und wie genaue Angaben nicht nur blos in Beziehung auf England, sondern auch noch auf andere Länder (wovon die drei von <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> entferntesten Punkte, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1374">Alexandria</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-515">Constantinopel</placeName> und <placeName ref="gfa-places-696">Petersburg</placeName> sind), dieses Buch, das ich schon in London kaufte, hinsichtlich der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term> und der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Dampfschifffahrt</term> enthält, und wenn man die dem Buch beigefügte Karte von England und <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019">Schottland</placeName>, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Irland</placeName> sind nur die Küsten und Ueberfahrtsdistanzen nach England angezeichnet, zur Hand nimmt, und die schon ausgeführten, noch mehr aber die projektirten, concessionirten, und zum Theil schon in Angriff genommenen Eisenbahnen überschaut, so weiss man gar nicht mehr, was man denken und welche Vorstellung man sich von dem Ende des Liedes machen soll, und wo die Menschen herkommen sollen, diese Bahnen alle zu befahren? — Es wird und muss, wenn die Sache einmal auf das Höchste gestiegen, das heisst, übertrieben ist, eine, und zwar wie ich glaube, dann eine sehr grosse Krisis eintreten, und nur die Bahnen werden sich halten können (von den <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">Locomotiven</term>, wie sie jetzt sind, rede ich gar nicht, denn bei dem Erfindungsgeist unserer Tage können sie von heute auf morgen durch eine glücklich gedachte und ausgeführte Idee beseitiget und unnütz gemacht werden), wo das natürliche Bedürfniss, nämlich von Städten zu Städten, wo schon seit Jahrhunderten Verkehr und Waarenzug im Gange war, die Beibehaltung gebieterisch <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588445"/> fordert. Jedenfalls werden noch bedeutende Reformationen im Betrieb eintreten müssen, wenn sie sich gut rentiren sollen, und bei angestellter Vergleichung, wie es hier, und dann wieder auf dem festen Land ist, scheint mir das Dienstpersonale im Verhältniss der Zahl der Fahrten (denn laut der in Händen habenden Liste gehen, weil Tag und Nacht gefahren wird, in je 24 Stunden zwanzig Mal die Trains ab) wirklich sehr beschränkt zu seyn; namentlich gewahrte ich weit weniger Bahnwärterhäuschen, und hiemit also auch weniger Bahnwärter, als anderwärts. Entweder sind die Engländer, oder glauben sich wenigstens so, ihrer Sache sicherer, oder wegen der ungemeinen Schnelligkeit, womit man fährt, könnten ihre Warnungszeichen kaum früh genug bemerkt werden, oder vielleicht, was mir nicht wahrscheinlich vorkommt, könnte der neben den Schienenwegen hinlaufende <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">Telegraph</term> für Signale benutzt werden. Man sollte glauben, dieses Eisenbahnwesen würde die Leute, da sie nun einander so in die Kreuz und Quere begegnen, mehr zu gesellschaftlicher Unterhaltung veranlassen, aber von eilf Herren, die diesen Abend im Speisesaal waren, redete keiner kein Wort, als etwa mit dem Aufwärter.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Reise nach Sheffield und Besuch eines alten Bekannten, 31. Juli 1845</head>
                <p>Meine Geschäfte in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> beendigt, nachdem ich Herrn <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2220" when="1845-07-31" n="69"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName></placeName> noch einmal besucht und wegen der Wahrscheinlichkeit mich mit ihm besprochen, ob etwa eine Gesellschaft in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> durch die Wichtigkeit der Verbindungen der Länder und Meere, die die übrigens auf einer <pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588446"/> so kurzen Strecke von <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> über <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270">Waldshut</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> u. <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Constanz</placeName> herzustellende <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185"><term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term></placeName> sich mit <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">schweizerischen</placeName> und <placeName ref="gfa-places-1899">badischen</placeName> Actionairs zu vereinigen geneigt finden würde, und ihn noch einmal auf den Inhalt meines vorgestern an ihn geschriebenen Briefes aufmerksam gemacht, und dann von ihm die Versicherung erhalten, dass, wenn irgend ein Anlass von der Art sich zeigen sollte, er mir schreiben werde, und in seiner Bemerkung, wenn irgend er mir etwas Angenehmes erweisen könne, er es mit Vergnügen thun werde, einen neuen Beweis seiner Freundschaft erhielt, verreiste ich um 1 Uhr Nachmittags von <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1760" when="1845-07-31T13:00:00" n="70"> Leeds</placeName> nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1845-07-31T15:00:00" n="71">Sheffield</placeName>, wo ich, die Seiteneisenbahn benutzend, um 3 Uhr anlangte, und nach dem Mittagessen noch zu meinem alten Bekannten, Herrn <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1845-07-31" n="72"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName></placeName>, hingieng. Herr <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587">Sanderson &amp; Comp.</orgName> sind die grössten Gussstahlfabrikanten in Sheffield, denn sie haben 36<term ref="gfa-keywords-2908"> Schmelz</term>- und 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9629">Cementiröfen</term>, um das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">schwedische Eisen</term>, ehe sie es einschmelzen, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahl</term> zu verwandeln.</p>
                <p>lch wurde, was ich auch vermuthen konnte, von dem <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">alten Herrn Sanderson</persName>, mit dem ich <ref type="cross" target="../1825/57">vor 20 Jahren</ref> einmal von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1917">Chesterfield</placeName> nach Sheffield reiste, sehr freundschaftlich empfangen, und, was nicht für Jedermann der Fall ist, in der ganzen Fabrike herumgeführt.</p>
                <p>Wir giengen zuerst zu den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9629">Cementiröfen</term>, wovon einer kürzlich angezündet und der andere in vollem Gange war. Jeder dieser Oefen hat zwei Kisten, mit circa 160 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1779"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">Dannemora-Eisen</term></placeName> gefüllt, und drei Feuer. Das heisst, die Flamme <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588447"/> reverberirt vorn an der Kiste, dann mitten zwischen beiden, und dann an der hintern Wand hinauf, und spielt wieder gemeinschaftlich an dem Gewölbe durch die Zuglöcher hinaus in das Kamin. Herr Sanderson liess mir zu Gefallen ein sogenanntes Auge öffnen, das heisst einen Zapfen von feuerfestem Thon an der Vorderwand des Ofens herausziehen, dass ich das Spiel der Flamme und den Grad der Hitze im Ofen beobachten könne, die, wie es mir schien, noch nicht den höchsten Punkt erreicht hatte, wo übrigens der Schein bei hellem oder bei dunkelm Wetter sehr trüglich ist. Von dort giengen wir in die <term ref="gfa-keywords-121">Stahlgiesserei</term>. Seit zwanzig Jahren, ja ich möchte sagen seit 50 Jahren, wo <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName></persName> seine Fabrikation hauptsächlich in Schwung brachte, ist durchaus nichts geändert. Es sind die gleichen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">Oefen</term>, es sind die gleichen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">Tiegel</term>, und sie werden kalt wie warm, nur mit dem Unterschied, dass Letzteres durch Trichter geschieht, gefüllt und beschickt. — Das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8634">Giessen</term> geschah sehr vorsichtig. Von den zwei ersten Tiegeln, die gegossen wurden, (jeder Ofen hat 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">Tiegel</term>, circa 30 bis 35 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pfund</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahl</term> haltend,) hatte der eine ein kleines Loch und war mehr als zur Hälfte ausgelaufen; der Giesser goss dann den Rückstand, der noch im Tiegel blieb, was sehr verständig war, in den andern, da kein Tiegel voll ist, wenn er aus dem Ofen herauskommt, weil sie ganz flache dicke Deckel haben; und dann den nun ganz angefüllten in einem zarten Strom, und sehr sorgfältig die Mitte des <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">eisernen</term> Eingusses einhaltend, in den<pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588448" break="no"/>selben. Von dem zweiten Ofen, der unmittelbar darauf geöffnet wurde, waren beide Tiegel gut, und wurden in gleicher Weise gegossen. Zum Giessen sind drei Mann: der erste hebt die Tiegel heraus und tragt sie zu den Eingüssen hin, die in einer Grube zu ihrer halben Höhe in der Erde stehen, der zweite fasst ihn mit seiner Zange, während der dritte den Deckel mit einem scharfen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9740">Hebeisen</term> wegdrückt, und mit einer kleinen Kelle die wenige obenaufschwimmende <term ref="gfa-keywords-336">Schlacke</term> wegzieht. Da mehrere Körbe mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term> neben den <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">Schmelzöfen</term> standen, so frug ich Herrn Sanderson, wie viel Coke er brauche, um einen Centner Stahl zu schmelzen, was er mir dann genau angab. Ich glaubte dennoch, ihn nicht recht verstanden zu haben, und wiederholte die Frage, die er aber ganz wie das erste Mal beantwortete. Nun war ich vergnügt. Ich sagte ihm nun, was ich bei <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">meinen Einrichtungen</placeName> im mittlern Durchschnitt brauche, da rief er drei Mal aus: <emph rend="italic">You beat us! You beat us! You beat us!</emph> (Sie thun uns hinunter!) Einen Grund, nebst mehrern andern eben so wichtigen, führte ich ihm sogleich als Ursache ihres grossen Verbrauchs an, dessen Gültigkeit er sogleich einsah.</p>
                <p>Immer noch unwohl, machte ich heute keine weitern Besuche und beschloss nur den Tag noch mit den gewöhnlichen Anzeichnungen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Turton, Huntsman und chinesischer Tee, 1. August 1845</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-01">1. August</date>. — <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> ist ein schönerer Ort als <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>, namentlich ist auch die Umgebung von der einen Seite fast <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">schweizerisch</placeName>. Die Volksmenge scheint mir auch grösser und noch mehr <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588449"/> reich ausgestattete Läden und noch grössern Luxus an den Fenstern derselben, als in Leeds; aber es muss Sonntag und sonst helles Wetter seyn, wenn man diese ungeheure Werkstätte des <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcans</persName> ganz übersehen will, weil immer tausende von schwarzen Rauchsäulen aufsteigen, die durch die beständig anfahrenden Karren, mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term> gefüllt, immer neue Nahrung erhalten. Heute wollte ich nach abzugebender Empfehlung an die Herren <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">T..... &amp; S..</orgName>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">Gussstahl-</term></term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">Feilenfabrikanten</term></term>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsmans</persName></persName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687">Hammerschmiede</placeName>, die an dem <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">Donfluss</placeName> nächst der <placeName ref="gfa-places-2168">Brücke</placeName> liegt, und dann eine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9337">Nähnadelfabrik</term> besuchen, und wegen einem Gedanken, der mir beigefallen, noch einmal mit Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName> sprechen. Ich gieng zuerst zu Herrn <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1845-08-01" n="74"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7543">T.....</persName> </placeName>. Es kam mir vor, als genire sie mein Besuch ein wenig, da sie, wie mir einer der Herren sagte, mich dem Namen nach gar wohl kannten, und darum empfahl ich mich nach wenigen gewechselten Complimenten sogleich wieder. Als ich schon an der Hofthüre war, durch die man zu den Werkstätten und dem Comptoir gelangt, (denn alle Fabriken sind ummauert und eingefangen) so kam einer der Herren nach und sagte, ich werde zwar auch schon ähnliche Fabriken gesehen haben, allein, wenn ich es wünsche, wolle er mir doch auch die seinige zeigen. Aus Höflichkeit nahm ich das Anerbieten an, glaubte aber nun auch, durch allerhand Bemerkungen, die ich in der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">Feilenhauerei</term> und dann besonders in der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">Gussstahlfabrike</term> machte, wo der Melter oder Schmelzmeister sehr die Ohren spitzte, zeigen zu müssen, <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588450"/> dass mir eigentlich von allem, was sie mir zeigten, nichts fremdartig oder neu erscheine. — Ich wurde auf dieses mit ihren <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">Tiegelstücken</term>, mit ihrem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">Thon</term> dazu, und dem Material, welches sie den neuen Tiegeln zusetzen, um selbige im Bruch <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porzellanartig</term> und gegen das Anfressen von dem Coke schützend, beschenkt. Uebrigens muss ich sagen, dass mir die Führung der Schmelzungen wohl gefiel. Ihre Lingots waren öfter oben tief eingesenkt, so dass zuweilen viel davon musste obenher abgeschlagen werden; auch war der Cokeverbrauch bei übrigens gleicher (fehlerhafter) Einrichtung der Oefen, nach ihrer Angabe etwas geringer, als bei Herrn Sanderson, die Coke hingegen etwas, nämlich 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">Tonne</term>, theurer, da sie 15 Shilling kosteten, statt 14.</p>
                <p>Man wird sich wundern, dass in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, wo Alles so vervollkommnet wird, die Schmelzeinrichtung noch so zurück seyn soll, und zwar so, dass sie nur den höchsten Grad von Hitze, den sie bedürfen, dann erzwingen können, den eine ganz günstige, das heisst trocken und kalte Temperatur der Luft gewährt; allein die Wohlfeilheit des Brennmaterials einerseits, und anderseits dass die Praxis nur in den Händen der Arbeiter (Schmelzer) zu liegen scheint, und die Herren oder Fabrikeigenthümer hingegen sich mit der Rendita, die namentlich durch den grossen Absatz zu vorzüglicher Bedeutung wird, und sie wirklich reich macht, begnügen, ohne für diesen Zweck neue Verfahrungsarten auszudenken und sie einführen zu müssen, mag wohl der wahrscheinlichste <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588451"/> Grund der Stabilität seyn. In ihren <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">Stahlschmelzöfen</term>, sowie sie jetzt sind, werden sie wohl schwerlich reines <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">Stabeisen</term> ohne kohlenstoffhaltige Zusäze, oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">Platina</term>, schmelzen, wie ich es in den meinigen gethan habe, und wovon ich unmittelbar vor der Zeit, wo ich dieses schreibe, die Beweise, wie früher erwähnt, mit nach England gebracht, und sie nebst dem Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> noch Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7843">Gott</persName> und Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName> vorgelegt habe.</p>
                <p>Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7543">T.....</persName> hatte die Güte, mich noch in eine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9337">Nadelfabrik</term> zu führen; ich traf aber das, was ich dort vorhanden glaubte, nicht an, nämlich die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8973">Drahtzieherei</term>, die von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> einige Meilen entfernt liegt. Die Heranbildung eines so kleinen und doch so wichtigen Gegenstandes war mir dennoch interessant zu sehen, obschon man in verschiedenen technologischen Schriften ziemlich ausführliche Beschreibung dieser Fabrikation antrifft. Mit Vergnügen sah ich, wie die in tausendfältiger Verwirrung durcheinander liegenden Nadeln durch ein künstliches Schütteln auf einer eisernen Schaufel sich zuletzt ganz in Ordnung und ein und derselben Richtung aneinander legten. Das Schlagen und Lochen der Oehre, das Zuspitzen, wo ein ununterbrochener dichter Feuerstrom den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9433">Schleifstein</term>, der, wie mir ein Werkführer (Foreman) sagte, mehrere hundert Umläufe in der Minute macht, bedeckt, das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">Härten</term> der Nadeln in Oel, und das sinnreiche <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">Poliren</term> derselben ist wie gesagt schon genugsam beschrieben und bekannt, aber das Anschauen dieser so verschiedenen Operationen hatte doch für mich viel Anziehendes. <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588452"/> Es ist dieses nur ein kleiner Theil menschlichen Thun und Treibens, aber wie gut ist es, dass auch diesem Geschäft, sich der der Menschheit wirklich nützende, das heisst an das Practische und Nothwendige sich haltende Geist, demselbem zugewendet hat, und wie erbärmlich stehen die Gleich- und Ebenmacher unserer Tage mit ihren bodenlosen Ideen, im Vergleich dagegen, nicht da!</p>
                <p>Eine Stadt in wenigen Tagen, oder gar noch in wenigen Stunden kennen lernen zu wollen und zu beurtheilen, wäre eine Anmassung, die in das Lächerliche fällt; allein gewisse Züge aufzufassen und diese zusammenzustellen, sind nie ohne Interesse.</p>
                <p>Eint und Anderes fiel mir in dieser Beziehung in dieser so gewerbthätigen Stadt, die ich heute Vor- und Nachmittags in sehr zerschiedenen Richtungen durchstrich, als bemerkenswerth auf, und führe es desswegen an, den Commentar dazu Andern überlassend.</p>
                <p>Gerade dem Wirthshaus über, wo ich wohnte <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1845-07-31" n="73">(Tontine house)</placeName>, verkauft ein gewisser <persName ref="gfa-actors-8020">Schweppe</persName> (wahrscheinlich deutschen Ursprungs) Celestial polishing powder (himmlisches Polirpulver!). Ich trat in den <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2183" when="1845-08-01" n="75">Laden</placeName> ein und frug, ob es auf Alles anwendbar sey? man sagte mir ja; aber ich vergass, mich zu erkundigen, was es etwa bei manchen Leuten für eine Wirkung haben möchte? — Gleich oben an dem Haus war mit so grossen vergoldeten Buchstaben, dass sie die Länge von beinahe zwei Stockwerken einnahmen, und jedes Wort, wie die <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinesen</placeName> es zu thun pflegen, unter das <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588453"/> andere gesetzt, gar nichts angeschrieben als <placeName ref="gfa-places-2183">Old N. 12</placeName> (alt Nummer 12), vermuthlich die Bezeichnung einer ehemals sehr gangbaren Pintenschenke, und dann auf einer grossen Tafel von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">Spiegelglas</term> mit goldenen Buchstaben ein Verzeichniss von einer Menge <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">Bier-</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">Wein-</term> und Liqueursorten, unter welchen auch der Artikel Leichenweine (Funeral Wines) sich befand; ob dergleichen Trauerweine, gleich ihren ordinairen Brüdern, das Herz der Menschen erfreuen, mag wohl von den jedesmaligen Umständen abhangen.</p>
                <p>Ungemein reich ausstaffirt und in grosser Zahl, was aber auch nur in Sheffield und <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> so der Fall seyn kann, sind die Magazine oder Läden der Ironmonger (ein Gewerb, das zwischen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672"></term>Eisen- und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9102">Quincailleriehändlern</term> inne steht,) ausstaffirt, und es sind in der That viele Stücke da zu sehen, wovon wenigstens ich, weder das Bedürfniss, noch die Anwendung davon kannte, oder errathen konnte. Bei einem Gerberladen, so speculativ sind die Engländer und für Zeitersparniss für sich und Andere bedacht, fand ich alle Werkzeuge von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">Eisen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahl</term>, nebst Fussmass, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9744">Leisten</term> etc., was immer ein Schuhmacher bedarf, zum Verkauf ausgestellt, so dass er an einem und demselben Ort Alles, was er nöthig hat, um sich, wenn es seyn muss, ohne auch nur einen Schritt weiter zu gehen, sogleich, um auf der Stelle etablirt zu seyn, haben kann. Auch Schuhnägel waren da von allen Arten, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">geschmiedete</term> und gegossene. Als eine Art von Merkwürdigkeit, sie mit nach Hause zu nehmen, kaufte ich von letzt<pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588454" break="no"/>genannten ¼ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pfund</term>, 200 Stück enthaltend, wofür ich 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Penny</term> oder 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> unsers Geldes bezahlte.</p>
                <p>Dieses ist wirklich erstaunend, aber, zur Ehre der <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">österreichischen</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">Industrie</term> sey es gesagt, dass sie das noch Unglaublichere zu Wege bringt, indem, was amtlich zu erweisen ist, in Stadt <placeName ref="gfa-places-896">Steyer</placeName> das Dutzend <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">Rasiermesser</term>, die zu religiösem Gebrauch für die <placeName ref="gfa-places-148">Türken</placeName> nur einmal dienen dürfen, aber die Klinge übrigens wie ein anderes Rasiermesser mit seiner Schaale versehen ist, um 22 kr. Münz = 26 2/5 Rolta verkauft wird. — Ueberhaupt werden in England die Erzeugnisse der ganzen Welt zu Markte gebracht. Ich will nicht von dem reden, dass in voriger Woche <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> gewissermassen mit den herrlichen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8794">Ananas</term> (Pine-apples) überschwemmt wurde, indem eine ganze Schiffsladung, einzig aus dieser Frucht bestehend, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-2017">New-Providence</placeName> anlangte, sondern, sowie in London, so wird auch hier <placeName ref="gfa-places-67">indisches</placeName> weisses Bier (<term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">indian pale Ale</term>), welches sich überdies der Anrühmung der Aerzte erfreut, verkauft.</p>
                <p>Am längsten hielt ich mich vor den Theeläden auf. Seit <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">dieses merkwürdige Land</placeName> nun dem englischen Handel weit mehr zugänglich und geöffnet ist, als früher, sieht man eine Menge Gegenstände, namentlich aber <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">Theekisten</term> von 1 bis 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Cubicfuss</term> Inhalt, mit Malereien nach ihrer Art verziert. Dieselben brauchten freilich einen Commentar, aber doch vieles ist auch verständlich ohne einen solchen. Sie stellen Gefechte, Spiele, gerichtliche Verhandlungen, religiöse Ceremonien, <term ref="gfa-keywords-3909">Musik-</term> und Saitenspiel-Unterhaltungen, wovon <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588455"/> theils Instrumente den unsrigen ähnlich, meistens aber auch ganz, fremdartig sind, vor, sowie Szenen aus dem häuslichen Leben. Schändlich aber sind bei allen Chinesen beiderlei Geschlechts die Füsse vorgestellt. Unten dicker wie oben, keine durch Zehen verlängerte Fussform. Sie sind zusammengepresst und sehen, weil sie dadurch rundlicht werden, wie Elephantenfüsse aus.</p>
                <p>Noch hatte ich mir zur Aufgabe des Tages gemacht, in des Gussstahlfabrikanten <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7729"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1687" when="1845-08-01" n="76">Huntsmans Hammerschmiede</placeName></persName></persName> zu gehen, die, wie alle Fabriken, auch geschlossen, übrigens aber von einer Bauart ist, wie keine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">Hammerschmiede</term> in der ganzen Welt, denn sie sieht einem Kastell aus dem Mittelalter so ähnlich, wie ein Ei dem andern.</p>
                <p>Obschon Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName> nicht anwesend war, erhielt ich, da ich sogleich dem Werkführer nicht nur sagte, wer ich wäre, sondern ihn noch ersuchte, mir um die Gebühr ein Stück von meinem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">Stahl</term> und mit meinem Namen bezeichnet, welches ich zu diesem Behufe mit von <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> genommen hatte, dünner auszustrecken, ohne weiters Zutritt.</p>
                <p>Es wunderte mich nur, ob Herr Huntsman, mit dem ich <ref type="cross" target="../1825/1">vor 20 Jahren</ref> selbst in der Hammerschmiede war, einige Veränderungen in der Zustellung, oder in der Art des <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">Wärmfeuers</term> vorgenommen habe, was nun wirklich der Fall war, indem man noch besser Alles in seiner Gewalt hat, und die Einrichtung eine für Verwendung von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term> sehr verständige ist; die <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588456"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">Hammerschmiede</term> aber ist kein Muster, denn der Gang der Hämmer ist nicht proportionirt, die grossen gehen zu langsam, die kleinen zu geschwind, und die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9821">Bahnen</term> aller sind zu breit und flach, was nur kurze Hitzen vorzunehmen erlaubt; sie bekümmern sich aber nicht gross darum, was in einer Hitze nicht lang oder dünn genug wird, kommt wieder ins Warmfeuer, in welchem immer Stücke genug zum <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">Verstrecken</term> vorräthig liegen. Im <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">Walzen</term> sind die Engländer Meister, aber nicht einen guten <term ref="gfa-keywords-9745">Hammergang</term> habe ich gesehen, wie wir in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Deutschland</placeName> und der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName> besitzen.</p>
                <p>Mit dem Einkauf einiger Gegenstände, worunter auch ein Etui mit der lateinischen Aufschrift: Multum in parvo, und dem vorläufigen Einpacken für die Abreise auf den morgenden, beschloss ich den heutigen Tag.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–London, 2. August 1845</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-02">2. August</date>. — Vormittag um 9 Uhr ging ich auf Ansuchen von Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName> noch ein Mal in seine <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1845-08-02T09:00:00" n="77">Fabrik</placeName>, um mich mit ihm über einen Gegenstand, auf den er, und mit Recht, einen grossen Werth legte, zu besprechen. Nachdem ich mich bei ihm beurlaubt und in der Eile noch als Mittagessen etwas kaltes Fleisch, nebst <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">Bier</term> und Brod genossen, verliess ich <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1845-08-02T13:00:00" n="78">Sheffield</placeName> um 1 Uhr Nachmittags, um noch bis Abends 7 Uhr nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> zu gelangen, welches 165 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> davon entfernt ist. — Bis nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1260" when="1845-08-02" n="79">Rugby</placeName> war die Fahrt äusserst unangenehm, weil an dem langen <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Train</term> hinten ein sogenannter Propeller (ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">Locomotiv</term>, das schaltet, während das vordere zieht,) angebracht war, und ein so starkes Schwanken <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588457"/> verursachte, dass einem jungen Frauenzimmer ganz übel wurde. Wahrscheinlich wird durch eine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9351">Parlamentsacte</term> diese höchstgefährliche Beförderungsweise abgeschafft werden. Einer der ersten <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">Mechaniker</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">Englands</placeName> hat seine Meinung darüber schon in der Art abgegeben, dass wenn man an einem gerade liegenden langen Seil stosse, so werde es sich, wenn auch noch so dick, krümmen und aus der Richtung gehen, hingegen wenn man nur vornen daran ziehe, so bleibe es immer in ganz gerader Linie. Es sind gewöhnlich nur 2 Stationen, wo auf die Distanz von 200 englischen Meilen etwelche, aber nur kurze Zeit angehalten wird, und steht dann angeschrieben: Refreshments are to be had. — Wunderlicher Weise gibt man einem, was man sonst in England nirgends bekommt, Suppe; nämlich dicke Fleischbrühe und etwas geröstetes Brod, das man dann selbst einbrocken muss. Ein Teller aber mit solcher Suppenbrühe kostet 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term></p>
                <p>Abends um 7 Uhr kamen wir Gottlob wohlbehalten in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1845-08-02T19:00:00" n="80">London</placeName> an, denn in der That scheint mir nicht Alles so vorgekehrt zu sein, sowohl für die Sicherheit der Fahrten, als der Besorgung der Passagiere und anderm Gut, als wie solches in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Oesterreich</placeName> und <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Baiern</placeName> mit viel grösserer Gewissenhaftigkeit geschieht. Uebrigens muss es einem bei der Unzahl von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">Locomotiven</term>, von Trains und Transportwägen, von Gütern, Vieh und andern Gegenständen nur noch wundern, dass es so geht, und was für ein Capital in diese so riesenhafte Unternehmung, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> bis <placeName ref="gfa-places-1937">Edin<pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588458" break="no"/>burgh</placeName>, gesteckt ist, kann man sich gar keinen Begriff machen; man weiss nicht, wo es herkommt und wo es hingeht, denn diesem Allem ungeachtet sind die Reichen reich und die Armen arm, und die gesellschaftlichen Verhältnisse haben sich nicht sichtbar verändert, nur scheint alles in grösserer Menge oder grösserer Pracht vorhanden zu sein gegen früher, obschon man sich anderseits fragen muss, wenn man Abends durch die Strassen geht, wo die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">Gaslichter</term> schon in denselben und den Läden ihr Glanzfeuer verbreiten, und dem schaulustigen Auge so mancherlei Schätze in ununterbrochener meilenlanger Reihe sich darbieten, und man dann noch das Treiben der Menschen und die tausend und tausend Fuhrwerke aller Art, der Schiffe, welche die <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Themse</placeName> bedecken zu geschweigen, ich sage, man muss fragen, wenn man alles dieses betrachtet, wie lange wird es auch noch im Steigen begriffen sein, und welche Ursachen werden den Culminationspunkt, wie bei allem Irdischen, herbeiführen, und wann, etwa in naher oder ferner Zukunft?</p>
                <p>Ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">Cab</term> brachte mich von dem Terminus zu <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1666" when="1845-08-02" n="81">Euston</placeName>, der sehr weit von der Mitte der Stadt entlegen ist, gegen die sehr billige Taxe von 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term>, nach meinem vor 20 Jahren gehabten Logis in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1845-08-02" n="82">St. Pauls Family Hotel</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Letzte Geschäfte in London, 3. August 1845</head>
                <p>Vormittag nach der Kirche wollte ich meinen Neveu, Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7968"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2218" when="1845-08-03" n="83">August Wintz</placeName></persName>, besuchen, vernahm aber von dessen gewesenem Hauspatron, dass er schon am Donnerstag mit <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588459"/> seiner <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306">Familie</persName> nach der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName> abgereist seie; möge er wohl in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> anlangen!</p>
                <p>Obschon der Sonntag <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">hier</placeName> nicht mehr so still zugebracht wird, wie früher, was schon wegen dem Betrieb der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term> nach allen Richtungen im <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">Königreich</placeName> nicht mehr möglich ist, weil es erstaunend vieles Fuhrwerk in Bewegung setzt, so sieht man denn doch gegen dem gegenüberliegenden <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">Frankreich</placeName> einen grossen Unterschied. Als ich vor vierzehn Tagen von <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName> reiste, so mauerten in einigen Ortschaften, wo wir durchkamen, die Maurer, es arbeiteten die Zimmerleute, man führte Dünger auf die Felder, und es genirte sich wegen dem Sonntag Niemand, obschon es mir schien, auch Leute angetroffen zu haben, die in einer Kirche gewesen sein mochten, deren man übrigens wenige sieht. Heute an dem Mittagessen hatte ich auf die Entfernung von kaum 100 Schritten die prächtige Façade der <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2145" when="1845-08-03" n="84">St. Pauls-Kirche</placeName> vor mir, und als ich dieses Kunstwerk der <term ref="gfa-keywords-4069">Architektur</term>, welche mit der <placeName ref="gfa-places-2051">St. Peters-Kirche</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-608">Rom</placeName> wetteifern soll, recht betrachtete, bemerkte ich, wie es mir wenigstens vorkam, einen solchen Verstoss gegen die Symmetrie, die bei einem solchen Gebäude eine Conditio sine qua non sein sollte, dass ich nicht begreifen kann, wie solches den scharfsichtigen und auch Unwichtiges genau musternden Engländern hat entgehen können, da es doch vor der Nase liegt. Das <term ref="gfa-keywords-9057">Frontispice</term> nämlich, von Colonaden getragen, ist durch zwei nicht sehr hohe Thürme begränzt, an deren Vordermauer in gehöriger Höhe zwei runde <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588460"/> Oeffnungen angebracht sind, wovon die des Thurmes zur rechten Hand, wenn man vor dem Portal steht, mit einer Uhrtafel ausgefüllt, während die entsprechende Oeffnung am andern Thurm offen gelassen ist, und den Krähen und Fledermäusen zu einem bequemen Ein- und Ausgang dient. Hat man nicht Geld genug in diesem reichen London zu einer zweiten Uhr, oder könnte nicht wenigstens das Loch ausgefüllt und mit etwas Schicklichem verziert werden?— Mit Schreiben brachte ich den Nachmittag zu und zur morgenden Abreise noch eint und anders vorläufig besorgend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Besuch von Faraday und Reise nach Dover, 4. August 1845</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-04">4. August</date> gieng ich für Abschiedsnahme zu Herrn <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1845-08-04" n="85"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im-Thurn</persName></placeName>, und dann noch zu Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> in der <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7575"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1703" when="1845-08-04" n="86">Royal-Institution</placeName></orgName>. Ich schätzte mich sehr glücklich, ihn wieder in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> anzutreffen, wohin er erst Tags vorher von einer Erholungsreise nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">Frankreich</placeName> zurückgekehrt war. Unsere Unterredung drehte sich vorzüglich um die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">Erfindung</term> und Einführung des <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electrischen</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">Telegraphen</term>, den man schon so häufig mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term> parallel laufend erblickt, und der Ausdehnung, die diese schöne Idee noch zu erhalten fähig seyn möchte.</p>
                <p>Mit Vergnügen und Interesse betrachtete er die gegossenen Stücke von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">Stabeisen</term> (Hufeisen schon eine Zeitlang von den Pferden getragen, und dann frisch gegossene, und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9691">Hahn</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9690">Schlossblech</term> von einem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">Percussionsschloss</term>) dann ein Stück <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">Platina</term> von 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">Unzen</term> aus Abschnitten und Abfall in einem meiner <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">Experimentir-Tiegel</term> zusammengeschmol<pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588461" break="no"/>zen, einen ähnlichen Tiegel, den ich mit nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> gebracht hatte, stellte ich ihm zu seinem beliebigen Gebrauch zu. — Nach genommenem Abschied hatte ich gerade noch Zeit, gar einzupacken und zu Mittag zu speisen, um mit dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Train</term>, der Abends um 7 Uhr aus dem weitentlegenen <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2221" when="1845-08-04T19:00:00" n="87">Bahnhof</placeName> abgieng, nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-08-04T22:00:00" n="88">Dover</placeName> zu verreisen. Um 10 Uhr hatten wir die 88 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> zurück gelegt und war froh, nach einem mühevollen Tag nun ausruhen zu können.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Dover–Gent, 5. August 1845</head>
                <p>Um 10 Uhr Morgens fuhr das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Postdampfschiff</term>, das wegen dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9749">bevorstehenden Besuch</term> der Königin <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Victoria</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2044">Rheinpreussen</placeName> mit Reisenden überfüllt war, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1845-08-05T10:00:00" n="89">Dover</placeName></placeName> ab, und lief um 3 Uhr Nachmittags, des widrigen Windes ungeachtet, in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1625" when="1845-08-05T15:00:00" n="90">Ostende</placeName> ein.</p>
                <p>Ich musste auf dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">Zollhause</term> lange warten, bis die Reihe zum Untersuchen an meinen Koffer und Nachtsack kam, die dann aber auch nur geöffnet und wieder geschlossen wurden. Manchen Frauenzimmern, die ein ganzes Zeughaus von Putz- und Modesachen in ihren Reisekisten hatten, ergieng es nicht so gut, und die <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">Douaniers</term> waren nicht sehr galant.</p>
                <p>Nach einem kurzen Mittagessen gieng ich noch auf der <placeName ref="gfa-places-2189"><term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term></placeName> über <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1910" when="1845-08-05" n="91">Brügge</placeName> nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1624" when="1845-08-05T22:00:00" n="92">Gent</placeName> ab, wo ich gegen 10 Uhr anlangte und wegen den vielen Fremden erst im dritten Wirthshause ein Nachtquartier bekommen konnte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Gent–Köln, 6. August 1845</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-06">6. August</date>. — In <placeName ref="gfa-places-13">Belgien</placeName> wird die Zeit mit Abgang der Trains nicht so eingehalten wie in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, wo die Minute zählt, und die Passa<pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588462" break="no"/>giere hatten fast eine Stunde auf die Bureau-Beamteten zu warten. Um 8 Uhr gieng, statt um 7 Uhr, der Train <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1624" when="1845-08-06T08:00:00" n="93">ab</placeName>, und die <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term> führte uns über <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2007" when="1845-08-06" n="94">Malines</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2003" when="1845-08-06" n="95">Louvain</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1311" when="1845-08-06" n="96">Liege</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1" when="1845-08-06" n="97">Aachen</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1947" when="1845-08-06" n="98">Eschenwyler</placeName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1935" when="1845-08-06" n="99">Düren</placeName> und <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1968" when="1845-08-06" n="100">Kerpen</placeName> nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1845-08-06T22:00:00" n="101">Köln</placeName><note>Die Strecke <placeName ref="gfa-places-2191">Köln–Aachen</placeName> wurde am  1. September 1841, die Verbindung <placeName ref="gfa-places-2192">Aachen–Liège</placeName> am 15. Oktober 1843 eröffnet. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2193">Gent und Liège</placeName> waren seit dem 1. Mai 1842 mit der Eisenbahn erschlossen.</note>, wo wir auch wieder Abends um 10 Uhr anlangten, und ich im <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2147" when="1845-08-06" n="102">Rheinischen Hof</placeName> ein sehr gutes Quartier fand.</p>
                <p>Wenn schon zu <persName ref="gfa-actors-8265">Moses</persName> Zeiten die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">Dampfwagen</term> wären im Gebrauch gewesen, so würde er wahrscheinlich den <persName ref="gfa-actors-8266">Josua</persName> und <persName ref="gfa-actors-8267">Caleb</persName> nicht in einen <placeName ref="gfa-places-2044">rheinpreussischen</placeName> gesetzt haben, «das Land zu erkundigen», denn von diesem konnte man nichts sehen, weil rings herum die Vorhänge, statt wie anderwärts Fenster sind, um des Regens willen gezogen oder heruntergelassen waren. Sie bedeckten von der Oeffnung gerade so viel, dass man nichts sehen konnte, hingegen hatten dann Wind und Regen an dem Rand herum, wo sie hätten schliessen sollen, aber nicht schlossen, freies Spiel, und die zunächst sassen bekamen eine ordentliche Bescheerung davon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Köln–Schaffhausen, 7. bis 9. August 1845</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-07">7. August</date> <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">schiffte</placeName> ich mich <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1845-08-07T05:00:00" n="103">Morgens um 5 Uhr</placeName> auf dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Dampfboot</term>, das nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1845-08-07T21:00:00" n="104">Mainz</placeName> abfuhr, ein, wo ich um 9 Uhr Abends anlangte, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1845-08-07T23:00:00" n="105">um 11 Uhr</placeName> wieder abging, und Morgens früh um 6 Uhr,</p>
                <p>Den <date when="1845-08-08">8. August</date>, in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1098" when="1845-08-08T06:00:00" n="106">Mannheim</placeName> ausstieg, um 7 Uhr> auf der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1123" when="1845-08-08" n="108">Carlsruhe</placeName> vorbei, nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1122" when="1845-08-08T14:30:00" n="109">Freiburg im Breisgau</placeName> abreiste, und um halb 3 Uhr dort ankam. Um 3 Uhr ging der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">Postwagen</term> nach <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1845-08-09T05:30:00" n="111">Schaffhausen</placeName> ab, der mich</p>
                <p><pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16588463"/> Den <date when="1845-08-09">9. August</date>, Morgens um halb 6 Uhr, Gottlob glücklich und wohl wieder zu den <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">Meinigen</persName> brachte.</p>
            </div>          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
