<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Traveljournal 1794</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage><figure xml:id="fig0">
            <graphic url="images/JCF1794-Titelblatt.jpg"/></figure>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main"><pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618097"/> Diary of a Journey from Coppenhagen to Stokholm in the Spring of 1794.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
               <lb/>
            <byline>By <docAuthor>Johann Conrad Fischer</docAuthor>, Journeyman Coppersmith of Schaffhausen in Switzerland.</byline>
               <lb/>
            <docImprint>Schaffhausen <docDate>1845</docDate>. Printed by Franz Hurter at Jordan House.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
         <div type="content">
            <head>Title Page</head>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>Dedication, 26 November 1844</head>
            <p><pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618099"/> To my esteemed friend Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">J. J. Wibert</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>.</p>
            <p><pb n="V" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618101"/> Dearest Friend!<lb/>More than half a century has passed since we made the journey together, whose description, written almost wholly in your presence, is contained in the following pages. — You, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9451">silk dyer</term>, and I, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9261">journeyman coppersmith</term>, were by no means suited to the task of observing properly all the interesting things we encountered in that country, at least in those days still seldom visited by foreigners, and describing them in a manner that did them justice. — Through improved schools and much greater knowledge imparted today in the many kinds of educational institutions to much younger people than we were then, who had already reached our nineteenth and twentieth year, 
               <pb n="VI" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618102"/> 
               it would be easy for them to treat a similar subject with a much more learned air. — </p>
            <p>For this reason, I never considered publishing this fragment from my diary, which, as you know, I kept regularly while in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>, though I regret the loss of those pages containing the notes on our return journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-142" type="itinerar" n="88">Stokholm</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-32">Denmark</placeName>: Losing our way one night in the snow-covered forest of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1477" type="itinerar" n="89">Ostgothland</placeName>, and the rebuke of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8629">potash burners</term>, whose fire served us as a guiding star; the approach to the deep mine shafts in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1478" type="itinerar" n="90">Adelfors</placeName>; the visit to the Swedish <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">hammer mills</term> and the adventure in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1479" type="itinerar" n="91">Malmöe</placeName> with the local <term ref="gfa-keywords-8414">constable</term>, to whom we were denounced as <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> spies for once haven spoken French to each other at a campsite along the way; <pb n="VII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618103"/>  and the daring crossing in a small open boat from that city, which had become so uncanny to us, to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-427" n="92">Coppenhagen</placeName>. —</p> 
            <p>But just as the invalid still relishes talk of the battles fought in days of old, the merchant of prosperous speculations during great world transformations; the artist of praise bestowed on him; in general, every man of that which made an impression on his mind in the past, especially when it showed him in a pleasant light, so, my dear friend! will I never forget the years we spent together, admittedly only in the modest character of fledgling craftsmen, roaming the lands and seas, seeking and taking on work, where we believed it conducive to the mastery of our chosen professions, and then, after returning to <pb n="VIII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618104"/> our dear <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">homeland</placeName>, practising them for many years, and thank God! not without success.</p>
            <p>For you, too, this time in our youth remains unforgettable, as your steadfast friendship has shown me, and these experiences, rare even in so long a series of years, have led me to dedicate these pages to you as a testament to our enduring friendship before we, in the none too distant future, are called upon by HIM, who so graciously protected us in all manner of danger, to embark on a far more significant journey than any before. Vale!</p>
            <salute>Your most devoted friend <lb/>
               <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>, Cantonal Councilor and Lieutenant Colonel of Artillery.
               <lb/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, <date when="1844-11-26">26. Nov. 1844</date>.<note>The Journal was printed by <persName ref="gfa-actors-1128">Franz Hurter</persName> in Schaffhausen in 1845.</note></salute>
         </div>
               <div type="day" subtype="preface">
                  <head>Youth and education</head>
                  <p>Foreword.</p>
                  <p><pb n="IX" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618105"/> Although this small manuscript has been given to the printer, it is not, being of interest to only a few, intended for the public at large, and therefore not for the book trade, but rather only for particular persons who are closer to me. — As it is possible, however, that the one or other, who do not know me personally or have not known me in the past, might get hold of it and, on reading, raise the question of how it could be that in those dark times (as some think), a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9261">journeyman coppersmith</term> could also have been a writer? I think it fair to offer them some information about myself and how, in my youth, instruction was given here to 
                     <pb n="X" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618106"/> the sons of all burghers who found themselves inclined to receive it in the so-called <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7375">Latin school</orgName>. —</p>
                  <p>There was taught, namely, those subjects which in institutes of that kind were seen as necessary at that time, including Greek, which was added, however, in the higher classes. In addition to textbooks as instructional aids, there was also the rod, which the one or other gentlemen, both spiritual and temporal, knew to employ with great skill, and no little effect. — Having reaped some dose of the rewards from all the above-mentioned instructional aids, I left school <date from="1787-09-14" to="1788-09-13">in my fourteenth year</date> to learn the coppersmith trade from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7376">my father</persName>. — He was a strict, well-travelled, and highly skilled man with experience of the world; in nine years he had travelled through <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-149">Hungary</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-119">Poland</placeName>, <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-1566">Prussia</placeName>, <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-32">Denmark</placeName>, and <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, where he worked for five years in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1889">Woolwich</placeName> in the <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-1567"><term ref="gfa-keywords-55">Royal Foundry</term></placeName> for its then director <persName ref="gfa-actors-7373">Schalch</persName> of Schaffhausen, in part as a chaser, in part as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9117">foundryman</term>. He returned to <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> via <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName> and <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> and, in addition to practising his profession, continued to make <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire-fighting pumps</term> to good effect into a ripe old age. During my apprenticeship, Schaffhausen was home to, among many astute scholars and statesmen, two excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematicians</term>. The first was Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7372">Jezler</persName>, a furrier <pb n="XI" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618107" break="no"/> by trade, friend and kindred spirit of the great <persName ref="gfa-actors-5432">Leonhard Euler</persName>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9132">globes</term>, exhibited in the <placeName type="place" ref="gfa-places-1568">city library</placeName> and made with his own hands, and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9463">Sphaera armillaris</term>, with, insofar as they have been completed, drawings of almost inimitable precision, as well as his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8429">Elementa Matheseos</term><note>The author of Elementa Matheseos was <persName ref="gfa-actors-7378">Christian Wolff</persName> and not Christoph Jetzler.</note>, are a testament to his profound knowledge and superb workmanship.</p>
                  <p>In his way of thinking and living, a modern-day <persName ref="gfa-actors-7396">Cato</persName>, he was misunderstood and therefore hated by many, as happens more readily in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9761">republics</term> than elsewhere, until his death. — The second of these two noble citizens was Captain of Artillery Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7377">Hurter</persName>, a genuine example of a thoroughly honest and patriotic man. Both gave free lessons (not just to young, but even to married men) in arithmetic and geometry, as well as, to a few who showed interest, in trigonometry, the doctrine of conic sections, and algebra. — I was fortunate enough to find myself among the latter, which has had a decisive influence on the course of my life thus far, in that I was not only introduced to a new province of the mind, and to a most fundamental science, but was also <pb n="XII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618108"/> thereby early acquainted with the value of time, and as a consequence of this was prompted to write an account book on it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="day" subtype="preface">
                  <head>Frankfurt–Chemnitz, spring 1792 to spring 1793</head>
                  <p>During my apprenticeship, I read <persName ref="gfa-actors-7378">Wolf's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8423">mathematical essentials</term>, as far as I was able to grasp them, from one end to the other; then some writings on the physical sciences and, on the advice of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7376">my father</persName>, who wanted to educate me for the world I was about to enter, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8421">Jesus Sirach</term> very diligently, along with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7380">Jablonsky's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8424">Conversations Lexicon</term> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-5432">Euler's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8422">Introduction to Algebra</term>, which I chose as a companion, and, on my departure from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="1">Schaffhausen</placeName>, carefully packed it into my harness, which my father made an indispensable condition for me to take on my back when he sent me abroad with three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8411">Louisd’or</term> and a reversible great coat as a suit for Sundays. — He wanted to observe, as I later surmised, how I well I managed my money. Satisfied, it would seem, that I asked of him not a single <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreutzer</term> for a year and a half (fortunately there were no cigars at the time, which now play so large a part in the purses and imaginations of young people from the working and serving classes), he did not hesitate to immediately put 70 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term> at my disposal, when later, having worked in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, I wanted to buy books, clothes and tools on my departure. —</p>
                  <p><pb n="XIII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618109"/> What a pleasant and valuable acquaintance I made during my travels on account of the above-mentioned book, I convey here in this episode. — </p>
                  <p>After working at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9261">coppersmith</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7382">Sandmann</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-47" type="itinerar" notAfter="1792-07-04" n="2">Frankfurt am Mayn</placeName> for some 6 months in <date when="1792">1793</date>, namely during the <date when="1792-07-14"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7381"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8386">coronation of the last German emperor</term></persName></date><note>The Emperor's coronation took place in July 1792 and not in 1793.</note>, the prince who had proven himself noble and excellent in the face of so many misfortunes, I continued my journey, almost always in bad weather and often completely drenched, through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1480" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="3">Hesse</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1481" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="4">Thuringia</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-748">Saxony</placeName>, in hopes of obtaining a place in a <date from="1792-12" to="1793-03">winter workshop</date> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-87" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="6">Leipzig</placeName>, which, however, did not come to pass. Making my way from there via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1482" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="7">Penig</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-514">Dresden</placeName>, I was given a place in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1106" type="itinerar" when="1792" n="9">Chemniz</placeName>, hoping against hope, by the aldermann there, Mr ♀smith<note>Alchemistic symbol for copper.</note> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7383">Müller</persName>, as he used to sign his name, since he had no journeyman but only one apprentice. — He was a forthright, adept and wealthy man, entirely of the old sort, and as a true Saxon patriot he despised the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1566">Preussen</placeName> most sincerely and from the bottom of his heart for the many terrible things they had done to his fatherland during the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9762">Seven Years' War</term>; and whenever he felt the need to vent his bile, he came to speak on this subject. — Because, in keeping with the honourable custom of the time, we were to be in the workshop by five o'clock <pb n="XIV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618110"/> even in the winter, we ate dinner at seven o'clock in the evening, and, so, I usually read <term ref="gfa-keywords-8422">Euler's Algebra</term> after dinner, leaving the book on the windowsill of the living room when I went to bed. Now it so happened that the children of my master, from his second marriage, got the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9763">smallpox</term>, and the doctor was summoned. — When he came to write his prescriptions, he happened to see the book I had left behind and opened it. — He then asked my master who was reading the book, and he told him the journeyman. — After which the doctor asked him if the journeyman understood what he was reading, to which my master replied that he did not know. —</p>
                  <p>Now, so it was that I was working on the street then on a so-called wash copper of the kind used by bleachers and dyers, which due to its size could not be made in the workshop. — Around this time, Doctor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7385">Tenner</persName>, as was his name, was writing <term ref="gfa-keywords-8846"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8412"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8425">a book on rapid bleaching</term></term></term> by means of (as he then called it) <term ref="gfa-keywords-8405"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8495">dephlogisticated muriatic acid</term></term> and wanted to include with it the necessary drawings of boilers, etc. He then asked Mr. Müller how many cubic feet of water the boiler being made on the street would hold, to which he replied that he could not say, <pb n="XV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618111"/> except that it would hold approximately so and so many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8712">«Dresden buckets»</term> full. — To this the doctor replied, if your journeyman understands the book, he too can answer my question, and will you be so kind as to tell him to bring me the calculation on Sunday afternoon; and, he added, pulling out his watch, calculate, too, if the hour hand is on the number 7, and the minute hand on 12, on how many minutes or seconds of the dial the minute hand will catch up with the hour hand and cover it? — At dinner, the master conveyed to me everything the doctor had said, adding: «Listen, my son (as he had grown accustomed to calling me when in good spirits), do everything properly, so as to earn the doctor’s respect.» — That same evening, I solved the two, in fact, not all too difficult problems, wrote them down the following evening, and on Sunday delivered them to the doctor, to whom I had been directed in his study, where, along with a not insignificant library, various mathematical and physical instruments were located. — After he had looked over the calculations, giving his praise, and after we had discussed his instruments, he invited me to join him for the evening and led me through another room into a hall where the gentlemen and ladies <pb n="XVI" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618112" break="no"/> of the most distinguished families in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1106">city</placeName> were gathered. — He introduced me and, it would seem, in so pleasing a way for me that I received a general invitation for all Sundays for as long as I intended to stay in Chemniz, an invitation which I used with modesty. —</p>
                  </div>
               <div type="day" subtype="preface">
                  <head>Saxony, Brandenburg and Hamburg, spring to October 1793</head>
                  <p><date when="1793-03">The following spring</date>, I went to <persName ref="gfa-actors-7383">my master's</persName> brother in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1108">Freyberg</placeName> in the Ore Mountains, stayed with him for some time, looked at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9189">metalworks</term> there, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelting furnaces</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9581">cuppelation furnaces</term>, the specialist workshops, and the small <term ref="gfa-keywords-8790">amalgamation work</term>, the large one had burnt down, and copied excerpts from manuscripts of the mining operations there, as opportunity would allow. — I could not find work in <placeName ref="gfa-places-514" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="11">Dresden</placeName>, but, at the request of a dear friend and schoolmate, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7386">Conrad Vogler</persName> – a journeyman carpenter, who was extremely skilful at his profession, later became a teacher of writing and drawing at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7375">local Gymnasium</orgName>, and then architect of the state – I remained several weeks to see the curiosities of this residence and to visit the neighboring city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1483" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="12">Königstein</placeName>, from whence I made my way via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1484" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="13">Grossenhayn</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1485" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="14">Treuenbrizen</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-664">Potsdam</placeName>. — Between <placeName ref="gfa-places-1486" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="15">Beliz</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1485">Treuenbrizen</placeName>, while sitting on a spruce trunk at the edge of a thicket eating my lunch, I read on a pole the inscription: «Royal Sow Garden», which, as a stranger to hunting <pb n="XVII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618113" break="no"/> terminology, puzzled me greatly, at first. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-16" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="16">Potsdam</placeName>, I found work with Master <persName ref="gfa-actors-7436">Sasse</persName>. I would very much have liked to find a place with the coppersmith <persName ref="gfa-actors-7387">Jury</persName>, where <date when="1793">just then</date> work had commenced on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8413">the four famous horses of driven copper</term>, which later travelled from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2149">Brandenburg Gate</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, and returned from there to their rightful home as just retribution for the victor’s pride. Nevertheless, as I knew the journeymen well, I went there almost every day after work to learn the techniques necessary to build such colossal works. — </p>
                  <p>The workshops of <placeName ref="gfa-places-16" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="17">Berlin</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-497" type="itinerar" when="1793" n="18">Hamburg</placeName> in which I worked offered nothing of significance, so <date when="1793-10">in October of the same year</date> I boarded a ship in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1487" type="itinerar" when="1793-10" n="19">Travemünde</placeName> for the journey to <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>.</p>
                  </div>
               <div type="day" subtype="preface">
                  <head>Copenhagen, October 1793 to April 1794</head>
                  <p>The journey was without incident save dropping anchor before the chalk mountains of the island of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1488" type="itinerar" when="1793-10" n="20">Möen</placeName> on account of fog. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-427" type="itinerar" when="1793-10" n="21"> this royal city Königsstadt</placeName>, together with my dear traveling companion <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">Wibert</persName>, from whom I was never to part again after <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName>, I came to live with my great uncle, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7388">Laurenz Spengler</persName>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8976">wood turner</term> of the court and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8415">custodian of the art chamber</term> (as he was called at that time). As a common, and one might well <pb n="XVIII" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618114"/> add, impoverished journeyman wood turner whose father worked as a bricklayer here for day wages, he left Schaffhausen to perfect himself to such an extent under the tutelage of then, in Europe, renowned artistic turner <persName ref="gfa-actors-7390">Täuber</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1136">Regensburg</placeName> and, later, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-6">Amsterdam</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, that when he came back to Coppenhagen, the then King <persName ref="gfa-actors-7391">Frederick V</persName> appointed him court turner<note>Lorenz Spengler was appointed Turner to the Royal Court in 1745, while <persName ref="gfa-actors-8270">Christian VI</persName> was still on the throne.</note>, gave him an apartment in the castle, and later, on account of his broad education, appointed him librarian to the queen, and after that, custodian of the art chamber. Introduced to completely different circles of society than I had previously been afforded by my status, from which I had neither suffered, nor ever been ashamed, though I would later be called to higher things by all manner of life events, I took as great advantage of my stay with him as was possible. I studied Danish and English, learned the art of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8976">wood turning</term> – all of this together with my friend Wibert –, attended by special privilege the private lectures on <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term>, which the then chamberlain, later court marshal <persName ref="gfa-actors-7392">von Hauch</persName> delivered to an audience of gentlemen and ladies of the court, supported by a selected collection of instruments of all kinds, and frequently spent time with my great uncle in his precious <term ref="gfa-keywords-9065"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8924"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8416">collection of conchylia, minerals and paintings</term></term></term>, the value of which was estimated at 12,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8417">ducats</term>. —</p>
                  <p><pb n="XIX" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618115"/> From a poor journeyman wood turner, as I already mentioned, he gradually, through his great talent and tireless diligence, became a member of numerous learned societies in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName> and was notably recognized as one of the greatest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8924">conchyliologists</term> of his time. He enjoyed the favour of all the kings under whom he lived, and, though preferred and honoured by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7393">Struensee</persName>, and, because at court and in the confidence of the most excellent men, intimately acquainted with all the threads of intrigue against this favourite of fortune and the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7398">queen</persName>, he was one of the few on whom the consequences of this bloody drama had no effect, and he retained all his posts, as well as the respect and goodwill of those high and low, until his <date when="1807-12-20">death</date> at the age of 87. — A ripe age! yet still not long enough to experience the joy of seeing his worthy son <persName ref="gfa-actors-7394">Conrad Spengler</persName>, who succeeded him in his post as director of the Royal Museum, <date when="1829">raised</date> to the rank of Knight of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8404">Order of Dannebrog</term> as a special distinction. —</p>
                  </div>
               <div type="day" subtype="preface">
                  <head>Sweden and London, April and May 1794</head>
                  <p>Already during my stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>, I made a brief excursion to <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>; the second journey, however, which inspired these pages, I took immediately before <date notBefore="1794-05-19" notAfter="1794-06-01">my sea voyage</date><note>Owing to the mention of the sea battle on 13 Prairial and an entry in Fischer's friendship album, we can deduce that Fischer must have made this sea voyage between 19 and 23 May 1794.</note> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1264" type="itinerar" n="93">Helsingör</placeName> across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1489" type="itinerar" n="94">Kattegat</placeName> and the dangerous <placeName ref="gfa-places-1490" type="itinerar" n="96">Tschager-Rak</placeName>, past the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1769">Kullen Lighthouse</placeName><note>Fischer may here have confused Kullens Fyr with <placeName ref="gfa-places-2162" type="itinerar" n="95">Skagen Fyr</placeName>, which lies between Kattegat and Skagerrak.</note>, up to <pb n="XX" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618116" xml:id="TB1_p_XX"/> the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2161" n="97">jagged rocky coasts</placeName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-109">Norway</placeName>, then southwest across <placeName ref="gfa-places-1491" type="itinerar" n="98">Dogger Bank</placeName> – where only a few weeks later on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8406"><date when="1794-06-01">1 June</date></term> the English Admiral <persName ref="gfa-actors-7864">Howe</persName> not only beat, one can say, but almost entirely destroyed the French fleet, which had ventured into the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2021">North Sea</placeName><note>The battle took place off the French coast in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2156">Atlantic</placeName> and not in the North Sea, as Fischer writes.</note> – and on to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, landing in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1492" type="itinerar" n="99">Deal</placeName> before reaching <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" n="100">London</placeName> to work for the master mechanic <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493" type="itinerar" n="101">Shoe Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet Street</placeName>, until <persName ref="gfa-actors-7376">my father</persName>, already <date notBefore="1795-05-04" notAfter="1796-05-03">74 years old</date>, summoned me <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7389"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1795" n="102">home</placeName></persName></persName>.</p>
                  <p>One may rightly take offence at the style and manner in which this fragment of my diary is written, however, it did not flow from the pen of a scholar but that of a young craftsman, which is why I left everything as I wrote it down at that time, in order to show the many deficiencies of youth; with me the deficiency remains, which, although at an advanced age, I feel nevertheless — the longer, the more acutely. — </p>
               </div>
       <div type="day">
          <head>Kopenhagen–Helsingör, 7 April 1794</head>
          <p><pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618117"/> On <date when="1794-04-07" type="travelday">7 April 1794</date>, I departed from <placeName ref="gfa-places-427" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="23">Coppenhagen</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1496" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="24">Hirschholm</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1264" type="itinerar" when="1794-04" n="25">Helsingör</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1497" type="itinerar" when="1794-04" n="26">Helsingburg</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1502" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-08" n="27">Landskrona</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-519" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-11" n="28">Jonköping</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1512" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="33">Lynköping</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1513" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="34">Norrköping</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1515" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="35">Nyköping</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1569" type="itinerar" when="1794-04" n="37">Fitya</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1570" type="itinerar" when="1794-04" n="36">Södertelja</placeName><note>Travelling from Nyköping to Stockholm, one first goes through Södertälje and afterwards Fittja.</note> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-142" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="40">Stokholm</placeName> with my friend <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">Wibert</persName> and Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7397">Boysen</persName>, who was sent by the house of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7834">Fröhlich und Comp.</orgName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1494">Christianshafen</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1495">Svinesund</placeName>, in order to purchase a ship there for the same.</p>
          <p>The so-called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1499">King's Way</placeName> leads from <placeName ref="gfa-places-427" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="23">Coppenhagen</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1496" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="24">Hirschholm</placeName>, as to all the pleasure palaces on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1498">Seeland</placeName>, and the excellent quality of the road gives it exclusive right to this name, though all country roads on this island are rather close to perfection. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1496" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="24">Hirschholm</placeName> is a royal pleasure palace, about halfway between Coppenhagen and Helsingör, which has not been inhabited since the time of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7391">Frederick V</persName> and has thus fallen here and there into disrepair for lack of reparation. It is quite large; the design is very pleasing and according to the newer taste, but the location is not at all well chosen, as it is very low, without prospect, and in a swampy and marshy area. The palace itself is also surrounded by water <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618118"/> in the form of a moat, so that communication with the banks on this side can be cut off completely by lifting the drawbridges. </p>
          <p>The palace garden is the most charming feature of the whole area, and the avenues adorned with the most beautiful trees provide the most pleasant coolness and shade for visitors in the summer; what is more, the song of birds, so particularly fond of this area, make this place quite charming.</p>
          <p>The road from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1496">Hirschholm</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1264">Helsingör</placeName> is equally as good as the one from <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName> to Hirschholm, and one gladly pays the toll demanded for every mile travelled, rather than ruin wagons and horses on unkept roads.</p>
       </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Helsingör and Öresund</head>
            <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-1264" type="itinerar" when="1794-04" n="25">Helsingör</placeName> is situated on the northeastern tip of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1498">Seeland</placeName> and, there, lies the smallest distance of any in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1573">Sound</placeName> between this island and the coast of <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>. This city, whose inhabitants number around 5,000 , is very small but quite nicely constructed and most fortuitously situated. If you stand on the so-called bridge (paa Broen), the place where the small ships and boats dock and goods are loaded and unloaded, you have a view with, perhaps, few equals in the world, surpassed only by that of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1501">Marienlyst</placeName> and the old tower <placeName ref="gfa-places-1504">Gernä</placeName> in Sweden, about which I will write more below.</p>
            <p><pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618119"/> A large number of ships of all kinds and from all seafaring nations can be seen waiting in this strait, as they are forced to anchor until they have been cleared and paid the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9764">Sound Tolls</term> to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7399">King of Denmark</persName>. Their quantity is often so great that the Sound appears to be covered with a forest of mast trees. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7437">Houden</persName>, a merchant who clears the English ships sailing to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2040">Baltic Sea</placeName>, assured me that once during the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9765">American war</term> more than 600 ships came to Helsingör in a single day. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">dues</term> on all ships passing through amount to 3½ million Danish <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">thalers</term> annually, which the King alone receives. On the outermost tip of Helsingör lies the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1500">castle and stronghold Cronburg</placeName>. The castle itself is constructed in a very beautiful Gothic style, and its 4 towers, as well as the main structure, are made of hewn stones. It is now inhabited by no one save the steward; though it once was suited for the stately residence of kings. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7398">Queen Mathilde</persName>, mother of the present <persName ref="gfa-actors-8296">Crown Prince</persName> and wife of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7399">Christian VII.</persName>, was taken into custody here after her arrest by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7393">Struensee</persName> until after the end of the trial, when an English ship brought her back to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">her fatherland</placeName>. This castle is surrounded, especially on the seaward side, by strong fortifications, all of them spiked with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannons</term>, <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618120" break="no"/> which serve both to defend it and, if necessary, to block passage through the Sound, stopping ships to ensure they pay dues. Outside the walls of Helsingör is a beautiful newly built pleasure palace called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1501">Marienlyst</placeName>. It is situated on the slope of a hill, so that from the rear one can enter on the second floor via a small bridge. Below is a very beautiful garden, adorned with tree-lined avenues, flowerbeds and nicely crafted figures of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9714">sandstone</term>. To the right is a small section reserved for non-native trees and plants, as well as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9580">greenhouse</term>. On the left, once beyond the garden gate, a snaking path leads to the top of a hill from which one has the most beautiful prospect.</p>
            <p>Continuing along this small ridge, one arrives at a somewhat elevated plateau, on which stands a round tower, on the western side of which is attached a thinner but equally high one, through which a staircase ascends. The tower has no roof, but a battlement of the old sort, with merlons and crenels on all sides. This tower is still quite new and would be quite splendid were it half again as high. It is there partly to lend the plateau a romantic appearance and partly to enjoy an even wider prospect from its pinnacle.</p>
            <p><pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618121"/> Nearby, on the side of a hill and covered in tree bark, is a little hermit's cabin, next to which a small stream falls in its sloping bed, forming delightful cascades over the cliffs in its path. This spot is called the hermitage, a quite fitting name, especially once the surrounding bush of firs and spruces has grown to a better size. The whole area, epitomized by the tower and the small footpaths winding around the hills covered with fir trees and bushes, is referred to as an English garden. </p>
            <p>About the building of Marienlyst it should be added that it is constructed in the antique style and has a flat roof covered in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, surrounded by a railing. At the top of the hill, where this building stands, is a pavilion with a resting bench, and this is, in fact, the real place from which to enjoy the most beautiful and widest prospect. Below, one sees <placeName ref="gfa-places-1264">Helsingör</placeName> and, just above, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1497">Helsingburg</placeName> with its old tower. Between these two cities, one can observe the many ships arriving, departing and anchoring. To the left, one can see far into the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1489">Cattegat</placeName>, whose waves meet the horizon, and to the right, one can see the shores of Seeland, adorned with villages and country houses <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618122"/> until just below <placeName ref="gfa-places-1571">Sophienberg castle</placeName>, and just above it, the Swedish town and former fortress of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1502">Landskrona</placeName>. Between these two places lies the small but very charming island of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1503">Hveen</placeName>, which has become quite famous for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9342"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1572">observatory</placeName></term> built on it by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7400">Tycho Brahe</persName>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9409">ruins</term> of which are still visible. There are no villages on the island, but three noble manors (Herren Gaards), and the island is under Swedish jurisdiction. </p>      
            <p>I do not know the exact width of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1573">Sound</placeName> between Helsingör and Helsingburg, but it can be safely assumed to be 15,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8408">geometric paces</term>. I calculated this width in the following manner: When we left land, I noted the time exactly, and also took note of how many strokes of the oar the boatmen made in each minute and how far the ship travelled with each pull; I found that one could assume 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> for each stroke of the oar, and thus, because 30 pulls were made per minute, the ship covered a distance of 300 feet every minute; now, we were underway for exactly 50 minutes, so if time is multiplied by speed, or 50 by 300, we get the size of the space or 30,000 feet, which is 6000 feet more than half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German mile</term>. 
            </p>  
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Helsingborg and the Swedish national character</head>
            <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-1497" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-07" n="26">Helsingburg</placeName> is a small town, which does not even deserve to be called a city, having neither gates nor walls; the construction of the houses is very mediocre, <pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618123"/> even poor for most. I first noticed here a practice that prevails throughout <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>, but of which nothing is known either in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-32">Denmark</placeName>, namely to sprinkle the hallway and the floors of the rooms with the most delicate shoots of fir branches (awns), which give off a very pleasant fragrance and prevent soiling by the shoes.</p>
            <p>It is rightly said that rivers and seas are the true borders between nations.</p>
            <p>Though separated by only a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1573">narrow strait</placeName>, the difference between the <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Swedes</placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-32">Danes</placeName> is astonishingly striking.</p>
            <p>I am too little acquainted with the national character and the physical and moral conditions of these two peoples to be able to detail the differences in manners, habits and ways of thinking; what I note here is merely that which is so striking that it is difficult for it to escape one's notice, unless one travels through a country with his eyes closed.</p>
            <p>The first thing one notices is the excellent education, character and stature one encounters without exception, so that it appears to be a hereditary trait of the Swedish nation. To that one must add the pleasantness in exchange and the politeness and friendliness in behaviour towards foreigners. This is true not only of the gentry but of the whole nation, <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618124"/> neither on the street nor in the villages will one pass natives to this country without them taking off their hats and greeting the stranger. They are also so free and unselfconscious in all their doings, yet with such decency, that they not only surpass the Danes by far, but might serve as a model for the Germans as well. As for the food and drink, they are quite good and, but for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wine</term>, consists largely of local products. Their <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term> is excellent and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8860">brandy</term> strong. The latter beverage, which is never consumed in warmer countries, at least by the more distinguished, is here the favourite of the nation, and even in the most proper society, a glass of brandy is drunk first, before sitting down to eat. There are three main sorts of bread — <emph rend="italic">swart Bró</emph>, <emph rend="italic">kaka Bró</emph>, and <emph rend="italic">sód</emph> or <emph rend="italic">Vek Bró</emph>. The first is found only in the countryside and is exceptionally dark and coarse, being barely an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> thick and round, the size of a plate. In the middle there is a hole through which to put a rod, which, when full, is then hung in the parlour. It is as hard as zwiebak and is usually broken into pieces with a hammer before being eaten. The second is found only in cities and, perhaps, at an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term> (<emph rend="italic">Gästgifwargaard</emph>) in the provinces. It is very white, round and not a quarter inch thick. It is usually eaten <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618125" break="no"/> with butter spread on it and it is as hard as stone and only because of its thinness it is easy to crunch. The third sort has the shape of a common loaf of 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> and is yellow on the inside. It is only available in cities and is always eaten fresh. It is mixed with anise and fennel, giving it a not unpleasant sweetish taste, from which it gets the name Süssbrod.</p>
            <p>They say the Swedes are dishonest: I have had too little contact with them to be able to judge or speak from experience. It is true that in Sweden there are permanent factions and, therefore, discord within the nation, out of which arises distrust, and this, once present, is a source from which all the passions spring that divide people and poison forthrightness.</p>
            <p>Just as their manner is pleasant, so too is their language. It is quite melodious, the words are well articulated, and one does not hear as much rasping as in Denmark. Foreigners who have already acquired some knowledge of the language before they travel the country, or who at least speak Danish, are highly regarded by them.</p> 
              <p>Many Swedes, at court and on the seacoast, speak English and French, but less so German, which they pronounce almost as poorly as the French.</p>
            <p>Returning to the subject of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1497">Helsingburg</placeName>, there is little more that can attract attention <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618126"/>than the tower standing on the mountain above the city that they call <placeName ref="gfa-places-1504">Gernä</placeName> in Swedish. This tower is very old and once served as a fortress. It is square and on one side there is an octagonal tower of the same height, but much thinner, in which there is a stone staircase. It is 40 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term><note>The tower is actually 35 metres or 115 feet high. Either Fischer overestimated the height or this is a printing error, which would explain the word "only".</note> wide, but only about 250 feet high. The view from there is even more extensive than that from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1501">Marienlyst</placeName>, and one can see <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>, which is 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term> away, with the naked eye. Around this tower was once a town, also called Helsingburg, but nothing is left of it now, save some ditches and the ruins of walls.</p>
       </div>
        <div type="day">
           <head>Helsingborg–Landskrona, 8 April 1794</head>
           <p>On <date when="1794-04-08" type="travelday">8 April</date>, we travelled from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1497">Helsingburg</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1502" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-08" n="27">Landskrona</placeName>, which is only two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">miles</term> away. This city, too, lies close to the sea and was once fortified, though now it has all deteriorated. The nearby <placeName ref="gfa-places-1574">citadel</placeName> that protects and commands the city appears to be in somewhat better condition. Although this city, like Helsingburg, is located in one of the most fertile provinces of Sweden, namely in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1505">Skåne</placeName>, and enjoys the most excellent conditions for trade, it very ill reputed and does not well reflect the country’s prosperity.</p> 
        </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>Landskrona–Jönköping, 9–11 April 1794</head>
                  <p>On <date when="1794-04-09T04:00:00+02:00" type="travelday">9 April</date>, we left <placeName ref="gfa-places-1502">this place</placeName> again early in the morning at 4 o'clock <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618127" break="no"/> to continue our journey to <placeName ref="gfa-places-519" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-11" n="28">Jonköping</placeName>. This city is located 39 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term> from Landskrona, in the province of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1506">Smaaland</placeName>. Along the entire distance between these two places one encounters not a single spot of civilization, to say nothing of a city. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9377">post stations</term> (<emph rend="italic">Skiutsplasserne</emph>) are usually located at farms or a small grouping of wooden huts that hardly deserve to be called villages. It is astonishing how little the land is cultivated, how large stretches of the most beautiful land lies barren. Forests cover most of the country, and we travelled for a day and a night in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1505">Skåne</placeName> and Smaaland without once really being out in the open. Farmers plant no more than they require for their livelihoods, and this inactivity can have various causes. For example: The great distance from the cities, lack of money and little need. Another great impediment to the cultivation of the land is that most of farmers belong to so-called Herren Gaards, which oblige them to labor almost constantly for their landlords in what they call <emph rend="italic">Hofferi</emph>, so that they have very little time left to cultivate their own fields. One does not see fruit trees anywhere, although I do not believe the country’s location in the north would prevent the fruit from ripening. Out in Skåne, <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618128"/> the houses are built mostly of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9406">timber frame</term> and earthen plaster walls; however, further into the country, all the houses, barns, stables, etc. are made of layered beams, with moss in the spaces between them. The roofs, too, are made of wood and covered with earth. The fireplaces are built of field stones held together by mortar. They also serve as the cooking stove, and when, in the evening, the fire, which has been kept burning all day in the winter, goes out, the opening of the smoke chamber is closed with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9778">wooden flap</term> (whose design very much resembles the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9766">wooden well sweeps</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>), in order to block out the cold that would otherwise force its way in. Windows in their houses are very rare and they have only two or at most three in the entire structure, usually on the southern and western sides. It is astonishing how many <term ref="gfa-keywords-3456">looms</term> are to be found everywhere; indeed, I do not recall having encountered a house in the country without this very useful piece of equipment, and it is a credit to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> of the nation that every family provides itself with most of the means of satisfying its most urgent needs.</p>
               </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Jönköping and surroundings, 11–12 April 1794</head>
            <p>On the <date when="1794-04-11" type="travelday">11th</date> we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-519" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-11" n="28">Jonköping</placeName> and stayed there for the night until the <date when="1794-04-12" type="travelday">following morning</date>. It is a very small town, made entirely <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618129"/> of wooden houses, but inhabited by professionals and merchants; there are no gates or walls at all, and the barriers along the road alone make it possible to call it a town. It is located at the southern end of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1507">Wettern Lake</placeName>, in the province of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1506">Smaaland</placeName>, in a very scenic area. About three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">miles</term> above Jonköping, on a high cliff, are the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9409">ruins</term> of a once beautiful castle, called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1508">Brahus</placeName>, which, when a fire broke out in the nearby village, also caught fire by way of airborne sparks, and all that was combustible fell victim to the flames.</p>
            <p>Just across from the castle in the middle of the lake lies an extremely charming island called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1509">Wisingsiö</placeName>, on which there are several villages and noble manors. The surrounding area is quite charming and must be a paradise for a lover of solitude in summer. I say for a lover of solitude, for there are probably few more deserted areas of this kind in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>, and blessed by nature with such qualities.</p>
            <p>I have very nearly forgot to mention that between Jonköping and Brahus one passes a small town, which is so insignificant that one can write nothing more about it than its name, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1510" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-12" n="29">Gränna</placeName>. From <placeName ref="gfa-places-1508" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-12" n="30">Brahus</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1512" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="33">Lynköping</placeName>, a path leads along the lake for a while, <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618130"/> before veering off to the right. Something struck me in particular: On the entire journey from Jonköping to Lynköping, on the great Wettern Lake, whose length is over 15 and greatest width over 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term>, I did not see a single ship or boat, neither on the shore nor on the lake; clear evidence of <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden’s</placeName> low population in proportion to the size of the country.</p>
            </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Jönköping–Linköping, 12–13 April 1794</head>
            <p>Between <placeName ref="gfa-places-519">Jonköping</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1512">Lynköping</placeName> are some rather nice looking villages, thanks to the many noble manors in the vicinity. The most distinguished among them are <placeName ref="gfa-places-1753" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-12" n="31" cert="0">Osta</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1733" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-12" n="32">Raby</placeName>, and are located in the province of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1477">Ostgothland</placeName>. The land in this province is extremely stony and rocky, yet better cultivated than the fertile soil in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1505">Skåne</placeName>. Here they have a peculiar habit of maintaining fertilized soil, but only in the densely wooded areas of Sweden and other northern countries where the abundance of wood is too great. They cut from a stretch of forest those trees that are useful for building ships and houses, and the thinner ones, together with the trunks of the thicker ones and the underbrush, are set on fire and burned to ashes. A man-made dam of earth creates a barrier for the fire to keep it from spreading too far. Once everything has turned to ashes, the soil is broken up with a special plow without wheels, which is common in all rocky <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618131"/> and mountainous areas of the north, and thus sown into the ash. As the ashes are very good fertilizer, and the whole field is mixed with it, they yield very good and considerable harvests on these places several years in a row.</p>
            <p>Coming from Ostgothland to the province of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1511">Südermanland</placeName>, one often encounters beautiful and picturesque areas. High mountains, rocks and wide valleys, through which meander lakes, small rivers, and streams, soon made me believe I had been transported to <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, had not the penetrating cold of the northeast wind reminded me that I was in a somewhat more northerly region, and so blown away all the images conjured in my mind as quickly as they arose. We arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1512" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13T02:00:00+02:00" n="33">Lynköping</placeName> in the night, or rather at <date when="1794-04-13T02:00:00+02:00">2 o'clock in the morning</date>. This little town is not big, though quite well constructed, at least insofar as could be seen by the bright moonlight, which in the northern countries makes the nights almost equal to the day. It has as few gates and walls as other Swedish cities, and only barriers, which, however, one never passes without first being asked by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9301">toll collectors</term>about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8926">contraband</term> and being visited, if need be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>Linköping–Stockholm, 13–14 April 1794</head>
               <p>From <placeName ref="gfa-places-1512">this place</placeName>, it is still 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1513" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="34">Norrköping</placeName>, a city of rather large circumference. The reason for this is the trade that goes on here. There is a stream <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618132"/> with a rather strong current by the name of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1514">Mottala</placeName> flowing through the city, which originates from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1507">Wettern Lake</placeName> and flows into the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2040">Baltic Sea</placeName>; it is also deep enough that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9747">ships of three masts</term> can sail all the way into town. All Swedish products that are exported, though chiefly <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, are brought here from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1506">Smaaland</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1477">Ostgothland</placeName> and other neighboring provinces, and then shipped to other countries. Likewise, these provinces are, in turn, supplied from this city with such articles as are brought there by ships and are not native to <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>. The houses are quite handsome, but almost all of them are made of layered beams; most of the buildings are painted red or yellow, whereas it is very rare to see one whose walls are covered with mortar and whitened.</p>
               <p>From Norrköping to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1515" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-13" n="35">Nyköping</placeName> is also but 9 more <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">miles</term>, which is quite far in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, but rather near in Sweden. One can tell by the greater number of houses and villages in the landscape that one is approaching a capital city. Another reason for the larger population of this province may be its proximity to the sea, where it is easier for the inhabitants to sell the products of the country to foreigners. The town of Nyköping is not large but quite pretty, and the town hall, which is also the inn, would be a point of pride <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618133"/> for even the largest city. Whether much trade or commerce goes on in this place I cannot say, for it was <date when="1794-04-13">Sunday</date> and the stores were closed. However, I suspect so based on the prosperity that seems to prevail here, which is always proof of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term>. There is also a considerable river flowing by this town, whose waters soon after pour into the wide bosom of the Baltic Sea.</p>
               <p>About an hour away from <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1518">Catharine Church</placeName> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1516">Süder-Malm</placeName> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9342"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1519">observatory</placeName></term> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1517">Norder-Malm</placeName> are visible, as these structures are very high; the rest of the city remains hidden behind the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term> mountains.</p>
               <p>
                  Stokholm has neither proper gates nor walls nor any other traditional fortifications. Before reaching the barriers, one passes a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1577" type="itinerar_Stockholm" when="1794-04-14" n="38">bridge</placeName> that traverses a part of Lake <placeName ref="gfa-places-1520">Mäler</placeName> and is supported by the water, so that it, too, rises and falls with the latter. The first street one enters when approaching from this side is called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1578" type="itinerar_Stockholm" when="1794-04-14" n="39">Hornkrok</placeName>. It is very long and quite steep. It does not give one a good idea of the beauty of Stokholm, as there are such miserable huts in it as I have hardly seen anywhere in the country; when one comes to the end of the street, however, which is also its most inspiring segment, the impression is immediately changed. Thereupon one sees the whole of Stokholm and <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618134"/> the beautiful buildings and churches within it, along with the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1521">Royal Palace</placeName>, which, like its inhabitant, clearly distinguishes itself from the other houses for its magnificence and size.</p>
         </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>First impressions of Stockholm, 14 April 1794</head>
               <p>It was the <date when="1794-04-14" type="travelday">14th of April</date> when we arrived in this <placeName ref="gfa-places-142" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="40">royal city in the north</placeName>, and as the weather was most pleasant, we seized the opportunity that very afternoon to look around a bit. The first thing we noticed were the columns that bear the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9057">frontispiece</term> of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1524" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="41">Royal Mint</placeName>, and are of the same order that has been found only recently in the newly discovered city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1522">Pestum</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>.<note n="*" type="original" place="bottom"><ref type="cross" target="fig2">Drawing on the last page</ref>.</note> They have no pedestal, the base rests directly on the earth and their capitals most closely approximate those of the Tuscan order. Crossing the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1734">bridge</placeName> where the mint stands, one sees, on the left hand side in the middle of the stream atop a rock jutting out of the water, a small pavillion, which is a very pretty sight and is called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1523">Strömborg</placeName>. There was no direct passage otherwise from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1521" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="43">palace</placeName> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1517">Norder-Malm</placeName>, rather, bridges went on both sides of the palace in non-parallel directions across the river. Now, however, from the central portico of the palace a magnificent <placeName ref="gfa-places-1525">stone bridge</placeName> leads to the opposite <placeName ref="gfa-places-1579" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="45">Norges Torg</placeName>, at the end of which, on a pedestal of cut and polished <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8402">statue of Gustav I.</term><note>The statue is not of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7406">Gustav I</persName>, but of <persName ref="gfa-actors-8271">Gustav II Adolph</persName>.</note> on horseback stands in double life size. <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618135"/> The statue is cast and in place, however, it has been encased in a housing, which will remain in place until the bridge is finished. For the payment of a few <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term>, one can view the statue, which is one of the most beautiful and largest in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. The model for it was made in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2177">workshop</placeName> of Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7401">Sergel</persName>, the royal sculptor, and cast by a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7403">Frenchman</persName>, whose name is unknown to me. The location of this statue is, however, well chosen, for firstly, it is at the end of a beautiful bridge, just opposite the palace, and secondly, it is in a large square, which is beautifully adorned by two residences built after the same model, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1527" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="47">one of which</placeName> is home to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7438">Princess</persName>, sister of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7404">recently deceased King</persName>, and the other to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1526" type="itinerar" when="1794-04-14" n="48">Opera House</placeName>. There are four columns of Swedish <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term> in the Princess' residence, which are particularly curious for their thickness and height. The diameter of each is 2½ and their height 16 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> and made of a single stone. So excellent is their polish that one can see oneself reflected in it. The railing on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1580">Ritterholm Bridge</placeName> is of the same type of stone, and equally beautifully polished.</p>
            </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>Gamla Stan</head>
                  <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName> is divided into five parts, some of which are islands, others are semi-islands, and are known by the following names: <placeName ref="gfa-places-1529">Stokholm</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1528">Königsholm</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1516">Südermalm</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1517">Nordermalm</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1530">Lagersland</placeName>. <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618136" break="no"/> On Stokholm itself, which is an island, there is the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1521">Royal Palace</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1531">house of nobility</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1532">town hall</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1524">mit</placeName> and that place or street, which is called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1534">Schiffbrüke</placeName>. The palace is situated very high up and can be seen from everywhere. It has many similarities with the recently burnt down <placeName ref="gfa-places-1533">Christiansburg</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>, except that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-4069">architecture</term> is simpler and more noble, which makes it more impressive. Since everything about it is so beautiful, it is striking that the windows should look so awful and much more miserable than those in most homes of ordinary citizens. On the eastern side of the palace is the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1534" type="itinerar" n="49">Schiffbrüke</placeName>, a square or street where all the ships coming from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2040">Baltic</placeName> dock. This area is extremely pleasant and the houses around it are inhabited by the first and richest tradesmen. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1535" type="itinerar" n="50">customs house</placeName> is very beautiful and massive and was built under <persName ref="gfa-actors-7404">Gustav III</persName>. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1536" type="itinerar" n="51">bank</placeName>, too, is by no means a coarse building and is also located on this square. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1537" type="itinerar" n="52">stock exchange</placeName> is located a little higher up in the city and was also built by the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7404">recently deceased king</persName>. It is very magnificent both inside and out, and if not one of the largest, certainly one of the most beautiful in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. From the outside it is decorated by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9057">frontispiece</term> with colonades and from the inside by marble busts of distinguished merchants and other great men. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1532" type="itinerar" n="54">town hall</placeName> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1735" type="itinerar" n="53">Riddarhustorget</placeName> is also quite beautiful, but it is lost in comparison to the adjacent <placeName ref="gfa-places-1531" type="itinerar" n="55">House of Nobility</placeName>. <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618137"/> This is a very large, as well as magnificent building, and the meetings of the knights and imperial estates are usually held there. Below in front of this building stands the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8401">statue</term> of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7406">Gustav Wasa</persName>, a little larger than life-size, cast in metal, dressed in ancient Roman attire, with a laurel wreath on his head and a scepter in his right hand. Every day from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., a crowd of citizens from all walks of life gather at the Riddarhustorget to hear something new, to do business, and converse with one another. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1538" type="itinerar" n="58">Ritterholm</placeName> is connected to the Riddarhustorget by a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1580" type="itinerar" n="57">stone bridge</placeName>. On it is the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1539" type="itinerar" n="59">Ritterholm Church</placeName>, where the royal funerals are held, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8414">Reichsdrost's</term> house<note>Since no official residence is recorded, Fischer must have been referring to the private palace of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7405">Carl Axel Wachtmeister</persName>, who held the office of Reichsdrost at the time.</note> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8400">model chamber</term>. The Reichsdrost is first after the King and the head of the knighthood. He has his own guard and soldiers and used to be held in high esteem, although the King assumed sovereignty. The model chamber is in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1540" type="itinerar" n="60">old royal house</placeName> (Gamla Kongshuset) and the current director of it is a skilled mechanic by the name of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7407">Norberg</persName>. It is wonderful to have galleries, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9767">art and nature cabinets</term> in big cities and residences, but such a model chamber is still preferable for the practical benefits it brings.</p>
               </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Royal Model Chamber</head>
            <p>There is no discipline of handicraft or science in which applied mechanics <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618138"/> is found that does not have models of the machines commonly employed in it, and what is most excellent is that only the newest and best are selected for the chamber. The models are divided into six classes. The first contains those that belong to the rural homestead, such as sowing machines, threshing machines, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9779">sifting machines</term> and all kinds of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9324">mills</term>.</p>
            <p>The second contains models of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9780">baking ovens</term>, brewing stills, kilns and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9781">parlor stoves</term>, and <term ref="gfa-keywords-90">the like</term>, and is aimed primarily at the art of economical heating and cooking.</p>
            <p>The third contains <term ref="gfa-keywords-9782">equipment</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9143">mining structures</term> and works driven by water, among which a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> for pumping out the water is of particular note. Made in the English manner by Asessor Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7408">von Engström</persName>.</p>
            <p>The fourth contains machines for factories and craftsmen, such as <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">spinning machines</term>, twisting machines and belt machines, special <term ref="gfa-keywords-3456">hoisery looms</term>, ventilators, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9789">copper engraving presses</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8628">file cutting machines</term>.</p>
            <p>The fifth contains models of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9783">locks</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9784">bridges</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9785">dams</term> and other water structures, including <term ref="gfa-keywords-2607"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9788">pumping stations</term></term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9786">dredging machines</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9787">trestle hoists for removing bollards</term>.</p>
            <p>The sixth contains equipment of various buildings and related amenities, as well as models of joints of the beams of various church towers, and constructions <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618139" break="no"/> of reflection mirrors with clockworks on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9271">lighthouses</term>. There were also experimental machines, to show the force of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9478">water wheels</term> in proportion to the different types of fall.</p>
            <p>To see the speed of the fall of bodies, in proportion to their unequal gravity in a vacuum. To illustrate the parabolic line of the spheres in a curved trajectory.</p>
            <p>In addition to this quantity of models of all kinds, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1538"><placeName ref="gfa-places-142">there</placeName></placeName> is also a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8399">mechanical alphabet</term> compiled by the Privy Councilor of Commerce <persName ref="gfa-actors-7409">Polhem</persName>, which illustrates the full range of simple movements, 80 pieces in all.</p>
            <p>In order to make this <term ref="gfa-keywords-8400">collection</term> quite useful, the director<note>The editor of the 1779 catalogue was Jonas Norberg (1711–1783), the former director and the father of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7407">Jonas Adolf Norberg</persName>.</note> published a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8428">catalog</term> of all the pieces there, together with a short review of each and whether it had already been accomplished or was feasible on a large scale. Since this catalog is very inexpensive, it can be purchased by poor and rich alike. If someone asks for a description, drawing or model, he will receive it, of whatever kind it may be, for a reasonable fee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>The other areas of Stockholm</head>
            <p>The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1541" type="itinerar" n="63" cert="0">glassworks</placeName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7410">Appelquist</persName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2179">factory</placeName> are located on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1528" type="itinerar" n="62">Königsholm</placeName>. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1581" type="itinerar" n="61">bridge</placeName> leading to it is rather unsafe due to its length and difficult passage in the evening. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1516" type="itinerar" n="64">Süder-Malm</placeName> is extensive and is dominated by the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1518" type="itinerar" n="65">Catharina church</placeName>, both because of its elevated position and its beautiful construction.<note>In the printed version, this section was not indented.</note></p>
            <p>Süder-Malm, like the whole area <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618140"/> around <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName>, consists of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term> cliffs, and there are certainly few towns whose buildings have such good foundations as those of the Swedish residence.</p>
            <p>The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1517" type="itinerar" n="67">Norder-Malm</placeName> is of the same nature as the rest of the city, and also very beautifully built, whereby the two palaces on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1579" type="itinerar" n="68">Norges-Torg</placeName> (Norder market) are especially noteworthy. Not far from there stands the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1542" type="itinerar" n="69">theater</placeName>, a gothic structure with four towers on each of the four corners, which was formerly a royal residence. In the summertime, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1544" type="itinerar" n="70">public garden</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1543" type="itinerar" n="71">St. Jacob's Church</placeName> offers many pleasures to visitors, both because of its proximity and its beautiful grounds. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1545" type="itinerar" n="72">Drottningen Gatan</placeName> (Queen Street), which is the longest and straightest street in all of Stokholm, also has very beautiful private buildings. It is also on Norder-Malm and at its higher end on a hill is the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9342"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1519" type="itinerar" n="73">observatory</placeName></term>. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1546" type="itinerar" n="74">Schiffsholm</placeName> is a small island on which there are only buildings for storing ship materials; there are also <term ref="gfa-keywords-9059">galleys</term> constructed expressly for this purpose belonging to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8278">Archipelago Fleet</orgName>. It is a pleasant walk on the pier, and at the very end a bridge leads to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1547" type="itinerar" n="75">castle</placeName>. On <placeName ref="gfa-places-1530" type="itinerar" n="76">Laagersland</placeName> I saw no large public buildings, and the houses that are on it are very average.</p>
         </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>Travelling with Plagemann: the German School and the cannon foundry</head>
                  <p>Through the friendship of Doctor <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618141"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7411">Lüdeke</persName>, to whom I was formally introduced, I became acquainted with a man whose society I found as useful as I did amusing during my stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName>. It was Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7412">Plageman</persName>, Rector at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7446">German school</orgName>, who acquainted me with the most excellent sights <placeName ref="gfa-places-2155" type="itinerar" n="77" cert="0">there</placeName>. I first admired his beautiful collection of microscopic objects, of which he owns over 300 pieces. The most remarkable among them were from the plant kingdoms: skeletons of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8865">boxwood</term> and other leaves, distinctive very thin pieces of wood and marrow, cut lengthwise as well as crosswise. From the animal kingdom: the insect ephemeridae along with the shell. The pearly cornea of different insect eyes. Wings of an American bosphori. A St. John's worm. The scale of a tench fish, as well as other scales, and infusorians in a drop of water. From the mineral kingdom: Crystals of different salts: kitchen salt, saltpeter, salarmoniac, cypric vitriol and verdigris. He also showed me a vertical and horizontal <term ref="gfa-keywords-9827">sundial</term> he had made, on which one can immediately find the noon line of the location one is in. Also, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9132">globe</term> of the earth, equipped with a sundial on the frame. If one sets the axis of this globe parallel to the world axis, and the pointer on the disk to that hour which the shadow on the sundial indicates, <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618142"/> one can immediately see in which place of the world it is noon or midnight or any other hour of the day. There are also other kinds of problems that can be solved with this sort of globe, the inventor of which is Mr. Plageman himself. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7413">His son</persName> showed me a nice collection of Swedish cut stones, like <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">marble</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term>, a kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8753">porphyry</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9392">quartz</term> and spath, and an ancient rune stick with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9411">runic writing</term>. Afterwards we went to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8647"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1548" type="itinerar" n="78">cannon foundry</placeName></term>, where we inspected both the foundry and the place where they are <term ref="gfa-keywords-8398">turned and drilled</term>. The entire apparatus is quite simple. A large cog wheel, driven by horses, sets a horizontal gear in motion, to which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon's</term> cascable is attached, so that it rotates along with it. In the front, the cannon also has a support so that it cannot move out of position, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8663">drill</term>, which consists of a square iron rod with a drill head shaped like this <figure xml:id="fig1"><graphic url="images/JCF1794_1_Bohrkopf.jpg"/></figure>, lies in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8963">groove</term> of a beam and is continually pressed against the cannon by a screw attached behind it, so that it penetrates deeper and deeper until the borehole has reached its determined length. Parallel to the axis of the cannon are support beams made of thick iron rods, on which the turning tools rest, whereby it is then <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618143"/> turned to the desired width on the outside at the same time as the drilling of the inside of the cannon.</p>
               </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Travelling with Plagemann: visiting Sergel, Helvius and Appelqvist</head>
            <p>From the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1548">foundry</placeName> we proceeded to Professor <placeName ref="gfa-places-2177" type="itinerar" n="79" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7401">Sergel</persName></placeName> to see the figures of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9123">gypsum</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">marble</term>, etc. made under his direction. There were a number of statues, busts, bas-reliefs and studies there. What merits the most attention is <term ref="gfa-keywords-8395">the piece depicting Cupid and Psyche</term>, where the former attempts to leave, but the latter, awakened by the oil falling on her from the lamp, tries to hold him back. Aficionados confirm that it is a piece with few equals, and the beauty of nature is so perfectly imitated that one contemplates it with indescribable pleasure. Cupid's wings are so thin as to appear perfectly transparent, and his head, or rather the expression on his face, makes speech redundant; the same is true, if possible, to an even higher degree for Psyche. The piece is life-size and of cararic marble. There is also <term ref="gfa-keywords-8420">a figure of the recently deceased King Gustav III in gypsum</term>. It is to be <term ref="gfa-keywords-8396">cast in metal</term> and placed on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1534">Skeppsbron</placeName>. He is dressed in traditional Swedish costume, has the tiller of <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName> in his left hand and the olive branch in his right. From there we visited the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2178" type="itinerar" n="80" cert="0">steel factory</placeName></term> of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7415">Helvius</persName>, who was the first to found such a factory here. For <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">sanding</term> they use <term ref="gfa-keywords-9769">emery</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9768">tree oil</term> and for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polishing</term> <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618144"/> the finest emery and wooden discs. Embossed buttons are punched by means of a kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9328">coin press</term>, and flat buttons whose edges are not round are shaped on a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8820">basset lathe</term></term>. From Mr. Helvius we continued on to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2179" type="itinerar" n="81" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7410">Appelquist</persName></placeName>, who holds the title of Capitain Mechanicus. What is small at Helvius, is large here, and [Applequist] does not limit himself only to small steel pieces, but manufactures all the tools of professionals, whole iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887">lathes</term>, large winches and presses, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire pumps</term>, and in short, whatever is required. Downstairs are <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">smithies</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> and casting facilities, and upstairs are lathe operators, carpenters, blacksmiths and other workers. Among all manner of special machines there is also a <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">loom that weaves by itself</term> when a crank attached to it is turned. Moreover, there is a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8543">copying machine</term>, which consists of two metal <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">rollers</term> of very diligent workmanship. If one wants to copy a letter, one takes a damp sheet of paper and places the letter on top of it and then draws it between the rollers, whereby everything is printed clearly, albeit in reverse on the white sheet. It should be noted, however, that the letter must be written with a special sort of ink. If one is not accustomed to reading backwards, one need only use a common mirror, so that the letters appear in their correct order.          
            </p>
            </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Travelling with Plagemann: glass works, cartographer Akerman and engraver Martin</head>
            <p><pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618145"/>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9124"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1541">glassworks</placeName></term>, which is located on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1528">Königsholm</placeName>, is also worth visiting. Not only drinking glasses, bottles, beakers, flasks and retorts are made there, but also instruments for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9061">production of gases</term> and other instruments useful in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term>. An iron tube 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">fuss</term> long and ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> thick, a similar rod, a kind of farrier's knife and a proper pair of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8661">scissors</term>, along with a wooden chair are all the equipment they have. When they want to blow something, they take out approximately as much molten glass on the iron tube as required. The equal pressure of the air gives it a round shape during the blowing, and anything that is to have a flat bottom is given one by pressing it onto an iron plate. If the vessel cannot be finished in the first step, it is put back into the furnace and softened, and this process is repeated until the vessel is ready for use. From the glassworks we went to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2175" type="itinerar" n="83" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7416">Ackermann</persName></placeName>. He is occupied primarily with the production of land and sea <term ref="gfa-keywords-3527">maps</term>, as well as <term ref="gfa-keywords-9132">globes</term> of both kinds. His work is very well known and also very well executed. He was working just then on four globes of two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in diameter, which were destined for <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">Coppenhagen</placeName>. One pair for the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8296">Crown Prince</persName> and the other pair for a private gentleman. The price of each pair is 50 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">Thaler</term>. <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618146"/> A pair of globes of 10 inches in diameter costs 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">Reichsthaler</term>. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-2180" type="itinerar" n="84" cert="0">collection</placeName> of Stokholm and other Swedish prospects by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8837">copper plate engraver</term> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7417">Martin</persName> is very beautiful, as is the manner in which they are made. The outline is <term ref="gfa-keywords-9770">etched</term> and then colored with watercolors along with shadows and light, so that it looks as if the whole thing were painted by hand. He also has a collection of portraits of famous men, as well as other <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">engravings</term> he has made, which confer on him a more than mediocre rank in the art of engraving. Among his prospects is one that deserves special attention for its great scope and the quantity of objects presented to the eye. It is a view from the garden on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1549" type="itinerar" n="66">Moses Bake</placeName> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1516">Südermalm</placeName>. We went there ourselves the following day and were rewarded for the small effort of climbing the mountain by the beautiful panorama. From here, one can see the entire island, on which <placeName ref="gfa-places-1529">Stokholm proper</placeName> lies with the palace and the other beautiful buildings; also, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1528">Königsholm</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1517">Norder-Malm</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1530">Lagersland</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1546">Schiffsholm</placeName> and, situated atop a granite rock, its <placeName ref="gfa-places-1547">castle</placeName>, whose 16 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8718">twelve-pounders</term> do not offer the most edifying view for the townspeople, as they all direct their sights towards the city. Not far from there, the so-called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1562">Thiergarten</placeName> forms the horizon, and its trees <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618147"/> are reflected in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1551">Salt-Siö</placeName>, between which and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1520">Mäler-Siö</placeName> one sees the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1550">Strömmen</placeName> flowing through the <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">city</placeName>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9342"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1519">observatory</placeName></term> opposite Moses Bake is quite excellent, both in terms of its location and equipment, and is furnished with precious instruments. The roof of the tower, which stands on the gallery, can be lifted off, and a deep cellar is dug into the ground below, so that one can see the stars even during the day. But these devices, they say, are not necessary for the current <term ref="gfa-keywords-8812">astronomer</term>, who prefers to go to concerts or elsewhere rather than to observe the movements of Jupiter's satellites, or to seek out the orbits of distant Uranus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Travelling with Plagemann: circumnavigator Sparrman</head>
            <p>At Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2155" type="itinerar" n="77" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7412">Plageman's</persName></placeName> I also had the opportunity to observe through a 1½ foot <term ref="gfa-keywords-7442"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8387"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7418">Cuff telescope</persName></term></term> the solar spots, of which we could count five and clearly distinguish them. Afterwards we visited Professor <placeName ref="gfa-places-2176" type="itinerar" n="85" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7423">Sparman</persName></placeName>, who had circumnavigated the world and was kind enough to show us all the remarkable items in his impressive <term ref="gfa-keywords-8394">collection</term>, which not only contains a large quantity of products from the three natural kingdoms, which he has collected on his travels in all four parts of the world and often at the risk of his life; but he also possesses a fair number of weapons, musical and economic instruments from the inhabitants of the islands in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1996">Pacific</placeName>, as well as from <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">China</placeName> <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618148"/> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1964">Cape of Good Hope</placeName>.The portraits of all the savages, whose islands he visited, lend even greater value to his collection. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8751">cannibals</term>, or man-eaters, are particularly notable for their heinous appearance. They cut all kinds of shapes into their faces, which they then rub with powder of a certain herb, so that the scar remains permanent, and believe thereby to acquire a quite fearsome appearance, to terrify their enemies. At Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2181" type="itinerar" n="86" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7424">Modeer's</persName></placeName>, Secretary of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7435">Patriotic Society</orgName>, we examined the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8393">models</term> belonging to this organization. They are almost all related to the field of <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agriculture</term>, with the exception of one model for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8398">canon drilling</term> and another for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror grinding</term>.</p>
            </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Drottningholm</head>
            <p>Before leaving <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName>, I visited <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1563" n="87">Drottningholm</placeName> Castle, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">mile</term> away. It is located on the shore of a small lake, over which a floating bridge crosses, in a very charming valley. Its main building is not large, but very tasteful; the steward lives in one of the side wings and will guide anyone who asks around the castle for a small fee. The first rooms contain nothing remarkable except the paintings with which they are decorated. Most of them are by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7425">Ehrenström</persName>, a Swedish artist who lived at the end of the last century. The most distinguished other pieces are two cascades by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7426">Lauterburg</persName>, along with two seascapes. <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618149" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8391">Psyche and Cupid</term>Psyche and Cupid by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7427">la Grainé</persName> and an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8392">Endimion</term> by the same. Venus on a chariot drawn by doves by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7428">Laschevec</persName>. A penitent Magdalena by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7429">Werdmüller</persName>, and portraits by Helderström<note>The person referred to is <persName ref="gfa-actors-7858">Pehr Hilleström</persName>.</note> and other Swedish painters.</p>
            <p>Next comes the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8389">collection of naturalia</term>, which is very precious and excellently arranged. Among the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8924">conchylia</term> there is one with a 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> long «spiral staircase», which is said to have cost 2000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">Thaler</term>, a large penna marinae and beautiful echinites as principal pieces. A torpedo and a very large lamprey adorn the quantity of specimens belonging to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9190">ichthyological</term> collection. Among the birds they have, in addition to many northern species, very well preserved colibris and birds of paradise, a penguin and many other rare birds from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1996">South Seas</placeName>. The American opossum and the armadillo I observed with particular pleasure, seeing them here for the first time. As for the snakes preserved in spiritus vini and also dried, none of them is exquisitely rare or could not be found in other European repositories. Among the minerals there are not only the rarest pieces from the Swedish <term ref="gfa-keywords-6116">mines</term>, but also from other places. In general, enough is said about the value of this collection, if one adds that the great <persName ref="gfa-actors-7432">Linnaeus</persName> created and arranged it for the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7404">recently deceased king</persName>.</p>
            <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8799">antiques</term>, which are in the adjoining <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618150"/> rooms, were purchased primarily by the king during his stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>. They are <placeName ref="gfa-places-608">Roman</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-821">Greek</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egyptian</placeName>, but nothing more can be said of them than that they are antiques.</p>
            <p>The cork model of a temple in the newly discovered city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1522">Pestum</placeName> and some beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9729">marble</term> vases are probably the best of all the <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italian</placeName> stuff. In the last room is the reference library of the King, it is not overly abundant, but well-chosen. It struck me to see the portrait of his former favourite <persName ref="gfa-actors-7431">Armfeldt</persName> there, at a time when the conspiracy against the Ducal Regent had already been discovered.</p>
            <p>The garden behind the palace is quite extensive and beautiful enough for such a northern region. There are <term ref="gfa-keywords-8388">many figures in it of lead</term><note>Fischer describes only the bronze sculptures of de Vries. There is no information about lead sculptures.</note>, but they are poorly made and most of them are damaged. Not far from the entrance, one immediately encounters the famous <term ref="gfa-keywords-8390">group of Laocoön</term>, and then <term ref="gfa-keywords-8419">the dying sons and daughters of Niobe</term>. In general, Roman mythology is quite abundant, but <term ref="gfa-keywords-8418">the figures of Vertumnus and Pomona</term> at the entrances of the garden could be omitted here with good reason, as their bounty does not extend below sixty degrees north latitude anyway.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Stockholm–Copenhagen, April 1794</head>
            <p>That <date when="1794-04" type="travelday">same evening</date>, when I <placeName ref="gfa-places-142" type="itinerar" n="88">returned</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1563">Drottningholm</placeName>, I set out with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">Wibert</persName> <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618151"/> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-427">return journey</placeName>. Although it was April and 8 o'clock in the evening, it was still quite bright. In June, one can read and write in Stokholm the whole night through without having to use a light in the least, and better up in <placeName ref="gfa-places-44">Finland</placeName>, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1564">Tornea</placeName>, at the same time of year the sun does not set for almost the whole month, as it then, when it is almost 23 degrees above the equator, shines away over the North Pole.</p>
            </div>
         <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618152"/>
               <div type="annex">
                  <head>Appendix: Drawing of the columns in the Royal Mint in Stockholm</head>
                  <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618153"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <graphic url="JCF1794_2_Saeule.jpg/images"/>
                        <figDesc>Column under the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9057">frontispiece</term> of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1524">mint</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-142">Stokholm</placeName>, in the style of those found at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1522">Pestum</placeName>.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
         <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618153"/>
         <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618154"/>
         <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618155"/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>