<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="7">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1851</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="jcf">
                    Handschriftliche Widmung durch <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>
                </handNote>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Journal of a trip to the Exhibition in London and to some industrial cities in England in the summer of 1851.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <lb/>
                <byline>By J. C. Fischer, Lieutenant Colonel. With appended lithographic illustration.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Schaffhausen. Printed by Murbach &amp; Gelzer. <docDate>1853</docDate>.</docImprint><note>The following dedication is found in Fischer's handwriting in the copy of the Journal which was used as the basis for this edition: "For Kantonsrath Amman of Ermatingen, his esteemed travel companion to the industrial exhibition in London, and as a memento. The Author."</note>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Title page</head>
                <p><pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618482"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9847">[title page of the first edition]</term></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Thoughts about the Great Exhibition in London 1851</head>            
                <p>Foreword.</p>
                <p><pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618484"/> Anyone who, for 60 years, through more or less active involvement in the technical field, combined with observation of what has newly emerged in the areas of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term>, finds himself in the position of being able to make a comparison between what existed in <date to="1791-12-31" from="1791-01-01">1791</date> and what presently exists in <date to="1851-12-31" from="1851-01-01">1851</date>, he must, in observing the progress made in this period relative to what happened in earlier periods of the same duration, be astonished, one might say dumbfounded, by what the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">world's fair in London</term></placeName> presents to us this year; and one is compelled almost involuntarily to exclaim "Enough, now; stop at once, human spirit, to work as you do; repose, and savour, as well, the fruits of your so manifold endeavours, for everything is transitory, after all!" — But that <pb n="IV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618485"/> is the nature and the prerogative of the eternally prevailing human spirit, emanating from the Creator and moving through both passing and future generations, to produce again and again in greater perfection, or in some alternative way, what the ravages of time devour from the earthly. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">glass palace</placeName>, with its thousand glories, will disappear again from the Earth, leaving no trace of its existence, yet only to make way, once again, for something new. These simultaneously exhilarating and disheartening reflections by no means exclude the homage that must be paid to the present with its achievements and to this world exhibition, in particular; and I, whose record of it is contained in these pages (kept, admittedly, for frequent lack of time, sometimes only sparsely), do not regret this trip in the slightest; no one, however, should expect to find here an index or catalogue or, much less, a systematic description of even a fraction of the exhibits; this is simply my diary, the account I give to myself of how I spent my time. Illustrated and non-illustrated papers will provide enough coverage of the exhibition, without exhausting it, while my final verdict, after having observed <pb n="V" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618486" break="no"/> and repeatedly observed, is that one can describe, another can listen to or read the description, but will, insofar as I infer from my own experience, never have or be able to obtain a genuine impression of this extraordinary event, if he has not seen it for himself. — As satisfied as I am with the outcome of what I had hoped to see and saw, limited as it was to just a few things, and also with the verdict I reached on the small and inconspicuous things I sent to the exhibition, which I perhaps owe only to the circumstance that they were objects of a peculiar kind, I was even more satisfied with the results of my stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, as well as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, and some pages of my diary filled up in an interesting way that quite deeply imprinted in my memory for recollection, and I close the same with thanks to the Highest that only a few weeks before my <date when="1852-09-14">seventy-ninth birthday</date>, in full strength, I was able to undertake the journey to this <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">remarkable island</placeName> and to add these notes about it to those from earlier times.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, <date when="1852-07-21">21 July 1852</date>.<note>The Journal was printed by <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7553">Murbach &amp; Gelzer</orgName> in Schaffhausen in 1853.</note>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">I. C. Fischer</persName>.
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Schaffhausen–Freiburg, 12 June 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="1" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618488"/> On <date when="1851-06-12" type="travelday">June 12th</date>, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="1">Schaffhausen</placeName> at 1 o'clock in the afternoon, via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1618" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="2">Stühlingen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1619" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="3">Lenzkirch</placeName>, for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="5">Freiburg</placeName>. Regardless of the weather conditions, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1620" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="4">Höllenthal</placeName> always remains a most fascinating natural phenomenon. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9069">geognosist</term> must ask himself what tremendous forces created this deep and vertical cleft to form the bed of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1621">Treisam</placeName>? — The most striking scenes are visible only on a moonlit night, as was the case today. How must it have been for the solitary wanderer in earlier times, as he left this yet uninhabited realm of shadows and entered, full of awe, the lowlands of paradise? — This, as did a little later the so daringly constructed and artificially perforated <placeName ref="gfa-places-1622">tower</placeName> of the minster in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122">Freiburg</placeName>, which stood out just as peculiarly, and has defied the force of the elements in unshakeable solidity for almost a millennium, made an immense impression on me. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1848"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8770">pyramids</term></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName> do not withstand comparison, neither in craftsmanship nor in beauty, with this magnificent structure, which was born of the old German spirit. — These were my thoughts, more or less, <pb n="2" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618489"/> and with far fewer resources than we have at our disposal today, this miracle could be accomplished, as we stopped in front of the post office in Freiburg around 11 o'clock and took up our quarters for the night at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1713" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="6">Engel</placeName>, amazed to find no strangers there at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Freiburg–Mannheim, 13 June 1851</head>
                <p>I say we, for I had as traveling companions two other <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName>, a worthy compatriot, Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName>, and Cantonal Councillor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">Ammann</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-984">Ermatingen</placeName>, on whom the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7451">current President of France</persName> often called when he was still living in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1165">Gottlieben</placeName>. On the <date when="1851-06-13" type="travelday">13th</date>, they accompanied me on the rather monotonous journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="7">Freiburg</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1123" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="8">Carlsruhe</placeName>, where we parted ways, as they also undertook an excursion to <placeName ref="gfa-places-47">Frankfurt</placeName>.</p>
                <p>	I had enough time in the afternoon to visit Director <persName ref="gfa-actors-7452" type="met">Ziegler</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7453" type="met">Kachel</persName> Currency Councillor. From the former, I learned of important developments that were to compel the member states of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8307">German Custom's Union</orgName> to raise <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">tariffs</term> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, which, however, as clear as the reasons for this appear to be, are not being duly observed in <placeName ref="gfa-places-17">Bern</placeName> for reasons that cannot be discussed here. From the latter, I learned that the renowned <persName ref="gfa-actors-7960"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8437">Uhlhorn press</term></persName> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9063">minting currency</term> (which I had already seen in operation in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName>) was victorious at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">London exhibition</term> for its efficiency over the one displayed there by the excellent mechanic Maudsley<note><persName ref="gfa-actors-7454">Henry Maudslay (1771–1831)</persName> was an outstanding mechanic and is considered the father of the machine tool industry in England. Fischer is here very probably referring to Maudslay's sons, who continued the family enterprise after their father's death. It is not clear which of the two sons – whether <persName ref="gfa-actors-7896">Thomas Henry Maudslay (1792–1864)</persName> or <persName ref="gfa-actors-7897">Joseph Maudslay (1801–1861)</persName> – Fischer means here.</note> that operated by a different system. <pb n="3" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618490" break="no"/> It was even viewed with pleasure by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen Victoria</persName> and the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7456">Duchess of Nemours</persName>. At 4 o'clock, I left again by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="11">Mannheim</placeName>, visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7457" type="met">Eisenhardt</persName> there, and after dinner at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1712" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="13">Teutscher Hof</placeName>, wrote these lines.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Mannheim–Cologne, 14 June 1851</head>
                <p>	The <date when="1851-06-14" type="travelday">14th</date>. Although there is much to enjoy about a journey on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName> by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="14">Mannheim</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-82" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="15">Cologne</placeName>, owing to the ever-changing and remarkable view of the shoreline in fine weather, which not only permits a stay on the deck but even invites one to do so, it becomes rather tedious when one is confined to the cabin or the so-called salon by cold, storm or rain, as was the case today in contrast to yesterday's beautiful, warm, though somewhat windy day. Also, for me at least, there was no one to engage in instructive or interesting conversation among the few educated passengers, so I was able to recover some sleep, which I had lost the two previous days by going to bed late and getting up very early; <persName ref="gfa-actors-35"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">we</persName></persName></persName> arrived in<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> Cologne at 7 o'clock in the evening, where I took up my quarters at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1711" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="17">Kölnischer Hof</placeName>.</p>  
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Cologne–Ostend, 15 June 1851</head>
                <p>The <date when="1851-06-15" type="travelday">15th</date>. Today was far more interesting to me, with respect to various observations, than was yesterday, though the speed of the journey by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rail</term> hardly allows for the observation of any objects <pb n="4" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618491"/> outside it. — I was attracted, first, by the generally so very sectioned terrain, and then by the excellent cultivation of the soil, the further along one progresses, until finally entering <placeName ref="gfa-places-1623" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-15" n="18">Flanders</placeName>. The horticultural crops, particularly the vegetables, seem to be far more advanced than our own, but even more interesting to me was the number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">factories</term> of all kinds, whose existence, as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, is indicated by the high chimney stacks, and also by the numerous shipments of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> parts, as well as by the quantity of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> ores and the pure zinc derived from them.</p>
                <p>There may come a time when the discovery will be made why <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> has not become wholly <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, or iron, in a given case, has not become either <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> or zinc, since I have much reason to believe that the primary matter of these three <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term> is one and the same — A hypothesis about this, if it were in itself as simple as nature in its workings, could perhaps make one ridiculous, and yet I want to cite a case that would seem to give some support to my conjecture. As is well known, iron and copper, especially when they are melted together in fairly equal quantities, do not combine even in the highest flux, but instead, regardless of whether the mixture is poured into moulds or allowed to cool in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>, <pb n="5" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618492"/> separate distinctly from one another like oil and water, and only a small percentage, due to <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">stoichiometric</term> relationships, is absorbed by one from the other, yet the essential character of both metals remains. However, I had already accomplished this bond in various ratios in <date from="1814-01-01" to="1814-12-31">1814</date>, and I made it known under the name "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8522">yellow steel</term>" in the diary of my trip to England in 1814, published in <date from="1816-01-01" to="1816-12-31">1816</date> by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7458">H. Remigius Sauerländer</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2">Aarau</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If one did not know that this was a metal compound, or so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term>, one might say: it is not <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, because it has a yellow colour and a different <term ref="gfa-keywords-9116">specific weight</term>, while another might say: but it is also not <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, because it is yellow and is drawn by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">magnet</term> like iron, and it is also not <term ref="gfa-keywords-3405">gun metal</term>, and not <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term>, because, when thrown red-hot into water, it becomes hard, almost like <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>. However, the art to the formation of this metal, which I will call <emph rend="italic">a</emph>, is to add something that is lacking in each of the two individual substances; if that something, or these new basic elements, were not added, ♀ + ♂ would not = <emph rend="italic">a</emph>, and so iron will neither become copper nor zinc, nor will zinc become iron, if these essential additives, which enable their transformation, are missing. As I should have noted at the outset, my better understanding<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> in the meantime <pb n="6" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618493"/> has led me to believe, in contradiction with general opinion, that these metals are not simple bodies, though I readily admit that my above hypothesis concerning the existence of multiple basic elements of these metals does, indeed, have its weaknesses. However, the fact itself, of transference from one matter into another, still remains, and as long as we do not know the manner of formation of the metals, the bonding agent of their various atoms and the stoichiometric relationships necessary for this purpose, the dispute as to whether they are simple or compound will remain unresolved.</p>
                <p>With these thoughts, not knowing how better to occupy my time on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term>, I arrived at the station in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1624" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-15" n="19">Ghent</placeName>, where the immensely light, yet solid construction of the two buildings whose columns of great height and width are made entirely of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and whose roofs are composed only at the bottom of a single band of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> and, then, up to the top, entirely of glass, captivated my full attention, so that I also invited <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">my two traveling companions</persName></persName>, who arrived with me in <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cologne</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-47">Frankfurt</placeName>, to view this graceful and peculiar building. — I wondered, is it the case, here, that the architect of this station in Ghent<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note>, earlier, and <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7459">Paxton</persName>, who built the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Glass Palace</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, later, had similar ideas without knowing of one another; as <persName ref="gfa-actors-3060">Newton</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7460">Leibniz</persName>, where, <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618494"/> while the former invented his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8439">fluxions</term>, the latter founded the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8440">doctrine of calculus infinitorum</term>?</p>
                <p>	I had continued to hope that it would still be as before that a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> would leave <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-15" n="20">Ostend</placeName>, where we arrived in the evening after 7 o'clock, for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> the following morning, so that I could get a full night’s rest instead of the few hours I had slept the previous three nights, especially as I was, in fact, still a kind of convalescent, and my doctor had, perhaps only semi-voluntarily, released me from his care to make this strenuous journey. Alas, it was to be a true night of suffering, such as I had never experienced on my frequent sea voyages. It had been windy all day, but towards evening it became much stronger and mixed with rain. After a short dinner in Ostend, my two travel companions and I boarded the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8441">Royal Mail Steamship</term>, which, according to a new schedule, sets sail every evening at 10 o'clock. We had taken our places on the first available seat or in the salon, and as long as the ship was still in the harbour, the passengers passed to and fro, there might have been 20 to 24 of them, and all were in good spirits. In the meantime, I delighted in the small round windows, of which there were only five on either side along the entire length of the salon and which resemble those on our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8946">Schaffhausen steamship</term> to a hair's breadth, spreading in the daytime <pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618495" break="no"/> just the same pleasant darkness so beloved by the English in their meditations and which might well inspire us to meditate too: yet, alas, it was to be otherwise. No sooner were we at sea than the violent swaying of the ship and the jolts made it clear that it was quite unsafe out there, and those with more sensitive natures soon began to suffer from <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasickness</term> in its full, ravaging form. My fairly good constitution withstood it for a long time, however, with the swaying of the ship, which became more violent from hour to hour, combined with repulsion at the effects of this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">disease</term>, which is similar to cholera for its rapid spread among the passengers lying about in every direction, and their groaning and moaning, I could no longer endure it, and I do not recall ever having suffered so much during the at least four-hour duration of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Arrival in Dover, 16 June 1851<note>In the original print, this section and the preceding one were conjoined.</note></head>
                <p>On <date when="1851-06-16" type="travelday">June 16th</date>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName>, who could no longer bear to remain in the salon, which looked more like a death chamber, remained on deck from 3 o'clock in the morning on, despite the storm and rain, and today he reported to me, as we recounted our tales of woe, which even afterwards imposed on us a strict diet, that in that same hour the waves had become so high that they sometimes reached the helmsman at his post, who then quite phlegmatically shook the water off his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">India rubber</term> coat. After 9 o'clock in the morning (the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8441">steamboat</term> was unable to land at low tide, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618496" break="no"/> so remained on the high seas), we were picked up by smaller boats, and soon after were able to have our belongings, of which the night bags were not inspected at all, and the suitcases only superficially, taken to the inn. As a comment on the fact that nothing, not even misfortune, can be had cheaply in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, I will add that the waiter on the steamboat, who had the courtesy to provide the victims of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">disease</term> with the necessary basins, of which there was at most one, for every two persons, was paid 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> or 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr</term>. of our money per person; then it cost another 36 kr. per person to get from the steamboat, which should have but failed to taken us, to shore on the other boat, and finally I had to pay 36 kr. to the porter, who carried my suitcase and the night bag to the inn, which was only the third house from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153">customs office</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If, by chance, anyone should be bored by this tale of woe, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">my two aforementioned traveling companions</persName></persName> will confirm word for word, then rightfully so, for so too am I. Only once was I compelled to laugh in the midst of all the misery, when the thought occurred to me, if only a skilled caricaturist were at hand to depict all the postures<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> and expressions of this heap of suffering humanity with the brush of a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7461">Hogarth</persName>. —</p>
                <p><pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618497"/> Of the ladies on board there is nothing to be said. The door to their salon remained closed, as is only proper; certainly, however, there will have been no lack of genuine sentimentality among them. Somewhat restored at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1715" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-16" n="21">inn</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7462">Hippgrave</persName>, after having written a letter <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">home</persName> and inviting them to join me, I walked around the town with my two traveling companions to see if they were satisfied by the first impression this, one might say in some respects, wonderland had made on them.</p>
                <p>	Aside from the picturesque setting of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, we admired the lavishly decorated<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> stores and the generally accomplished works displayed therein, and lastly, the inviting <term ref="gfa-keywords-9449">seaside resorts</term>, so appropriately designed. Weary from the previous night's events, and weary from writing, I will retire for the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Dover–London, 17 June 1851</head>
                <p>	<date when="1851-06-17" type="travelday">June 17th</date>. After a delightful night's sleep, and some notes taken after breakfast, I left for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="23">London</placeName> by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rail</term> at a quarter past 9 o'clock.</p>
                <p>	Inside the barbarous wooden boxes of the second-class carriages, which reveal this island's ferociously speculative spirit, we were joined by two Englishmen and the daughter of one of them, a young woman of about 14 years of age. Her father told me that she had already been with <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618498"/> relatives in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> for 6 years and spoke German, which was, indeed, the case and superbly so. I have often remarked that children learn foreign languages much quicker than adults do, though the mental powers of the latter are more developed. Whoever wants to teach his children the knowledge and practice of other living languages at an early age should rather employ child caretakers and maids (the so-called governesses are usually too precise and, at least in their imagination, too learned) as teachers of those foreign languages than a professor with his<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> syntax and grammar, who has perhaps been torturing students with it for thirty years, and yet cannot himself speak any of the languages he teaches.</p>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">My two traveling companions</persName></persName> were pleased to be able to converse with her, and through her with her father, who, as he informed me, was a landowner in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1627">York</placeName> but lived in London. He was a highly educated and well-travelled man, spoke French and German<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> in addition to his mother tongue, and perhaps it is due to the fact that I conversed with him in all three languages, in turn, that when I took leave of him at the train station in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, he pulled out his wallet and presented me with his visiting card, which read, "Mr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7463">Minet</persName>, 19, Old Quebeckstreet, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1717">Oxfordstreet</placeName>, near the marble arch," <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618499" break="no"/> together with an invitation to certainly pay him a visit. While the invitation from an Englishman who hardly knew me was extraordinary to me, I will accept it.</p>
                <p>	In the hustle and bustle of collecting<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> our baggage, which is not assigned numbers as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, and for which, even if heavy and numerous, one never pays anything, I lost my two traveling companions, who, by the way, had to take a completely different route to their lodging than I did to mine.</p>
                <p>	Upon arriving at the same, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="24">St. Paul's Family Hotel</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1700">St. Paul's Churchyard</placeName>, I certainly would not have been given a room, since there has been another owner there for 4 years now, if the head waiter had not fortuitously recognised me straight away and promised to find me a room in the house, or elsewhere if no one left, by evening. Since it was barely 1 o'clock, and dinner is not until after 4 o'clock, I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1615" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="25">Newgate Street</placeName> to visit the ironmonger Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2201"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</orgName></placeName><note>Both brothers, Samuel and Daniel Fenn, had their business in Newgate Street. It is not clear which Mr. Fenn Fischer visited.</note>, with whom I had already become acquainted in <date when="1794">1794</date>, when I was then working for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName>, a mechanic in London, but did not find him at the shop, and bought various things for my wardrobe, which I had not wished to carry with me from home.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="day">
                    <head>The exhibition site: first impressions, 17 June 1851</head>
                    <p>After dinner I immediately boarded an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> to be taken for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term> (this is the fare from the area where I am staying) <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618500" break="no"/> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition building</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="26">Hyde park</placeName>, a little over 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> away: — not to go inside, but only to get a first impression of its position, circumference, style and execution, so that it would be independent of the interior, as the soul of the entirety. I was convinced that this impression must be different from the one conveyed by drawings, since the latter encompass neither foreground nor background, just as little as the side walls, of any importance to convey the proper scale of the whole, which even a linear scale, incidentally, would not provide. I have just had an idea, and <ref type="cross" target="../1851/36">at the end of this volume</ref>, I will attempt to establish a scale, at least for the citizens of my beloved <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">hometown</placeName>, that will produce a fairly accurate estimate of the extent of this building, and that will make the numbers comprehensible.</p>
                    <p>	The building is positioned rather low on the landscape, very close to the bank of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1628">Serpentine River</placeName>, and the main façade is often obscured by oak trees, some of which stand very close to it, which greatly diminishes the impression that this palace, if free of this environment and standing on some elevation, would otherwise make. The choice of this building site was, however, an unavoidable necessity that cannot be faulted; however, one is mistaken to imagine this glass palace as transparent, like a lantern. Of the high, narrow window frames formed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast-iron</term> columns, 24 are filled with an uninterrupted series of planed wooden boards, painted light brown, to the left and right of which 4 such frames are filled with glass. The <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618501" break="no"/> description I provide here applies only to the ground floor; I can say nothing about the superstructure, which, along with the roof, is completely covered with glass. I walked around the entire building, which is surrounded, as it seems to me, too closely and at an oppressive distance, by a heavy iron fence, which forms between the two only a narrow alley that is filled with all manner of woodwork and broken boxes, among which, in turn, individually submitted objects of lesser importance, which were not brought into the building, because they could not be disassembled, such as, for example, on the northern side a large stone crucifix from <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>. An exception to the above is the southern wall or the short side of the building, from which the aforementioned iron fence stands at a greater distance, forming a beautiful space or courtyard, on which can be found <term ref="gfa-keywords-9575">earthenware</term> in dimensions likely never before produced, for use as vessels for chemicals, as well as other receptacles; crooked and straight pipes of stoneware for conducting water and other liquids, and thus coated neither inside nor out with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9129">glaze</term>, but glazed, like a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8446">Selters mineral water jug</term>, by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9218">salt vapours</term> produced in the kiln; immensely heavy <term ref="gfa-keywords-8796">anchors</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9285">ships</term> and equally immense blocks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coal</term>; <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618502" break="no"/> then a column made from a single piece of cut and polished <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term>, 20 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high and without a capital; large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9426">slate</term> slabs; a wall of hollow bricks, of which I had already conceived and for whose production I had received an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8447">imperial license</term> in <date when="1826">1826</date> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>; beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8830">sculptural</term> objects, along with several other striking sculptural and architectural ornamentations; as well as interesting lifeboats, etc., about all of which the catalogues report far better than is possible for me to do in so brief an overview.</p>
                    <p>	It was interesting to see the crowd walking to and fro, since it was already about 7 o'clock in the evening. Riding, it would seem, is fashionable again among the women; I observed several, each accompanied by her cavalier, riding up and down the avenue along the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1629">New river</placeName> side; they wore dark blue long riding dresses, and, as if by agreement, small round felt hats, like the so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8448">Hecker hat</term>", though I believe, as daughters of Eve, their thoughts under these hats are less revolutionary than lustful. The calmness and decency among this crowd was remarkable, and it did not seem to me at all that I had seen any arrested expressions as those that appear in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> on the eve of a revolution, or after it has already broken out. <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618503" break="no"/> The police are not at all bothersome; one is pleased to see them, as they are not mouchards<note>French slang for "spy".</note>, but rather polite and eager to serve. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> were already beginning to burn in the stores, which prompted me to return to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="26.1">my lodging</placeName> to write the foregoing and retire for the day at 11 o'clock in the evening.</p>    
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's first visit, 18 June 1851</head>
                <p>	The <date when="1851-06-18" type="travelday">18th</date>. At the usual time in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, namely after 10 o'clock in the morning, I commenced my daily business, visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7863" type="met">Howard</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7468" type="met"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2134" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="28">Im Thurn</placeName></persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469" type="met"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1703" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="29">Faraday</placeName></persName>, for whom, since he had gone out, I left my card, and then went from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="30"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, where I stayed until 6 o'clock in the evening.</p>
                <p>	From the outside, as I already thought to myself yesterday, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">building</placeName> did not make the extraordinary impression on me that I had expected, and the reasons for this are as follows: first, for its immense length, it has no corresponding height, though the transept from the ground to the highest point of the semicircular vault measures 108 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">English feet</term>. In this case, however, it was wise to concentrate on the special requirements of the situation, rather than follow standard protocol. Secondly, due to its proximity to the trees and its somewhat low position, the building cannot be viewed as a whole. Yet, upon entering, one has no choice but to be astonished by the very idea of it. How so many nations of the world, and in such different ways, have paid homage to it, and how these various displays, <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618504" break="no"/> despite their variety of material and form, have been so judiciously united into a whole — and to think that all this, including the colossal structure itself, was erected in such an incredibly short and strictly defined period. It would be a conceited, one might say quite ridiculous, undertaking to describe even a few of these multitudinous objects in any detail. The catalogues, public newspapers, and men of letters who have already written about this subject, or who will write about it in the future, say enough on this subject. However, one item particularly attracted my attention today, whose beauty must certainly be admired by all, and whose absolute uniqueness — namely the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8450">fountain</term>, which, by my estimation, has a height of 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, all parts of which are made of the most beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9105">crystal glass</term>, weighing almost 90 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>, and over whose uppermost bowl or basin the water falls, first, as a large veil and then, further down, in beautiful cascades, which, in the absence of flowing water, can be immediately transformed into the most dazzling and largest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">candelabra</term> in the world. There are several other fountains of various kinds in the building, including one whose stone basin measures 36 feet in diameter, yet in these immense spaces is neither disruptive or conspicuous.</p>
                <p>The second thing that captured my attention for some time <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618505"/> were the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8502">wax figures</term>, life-size and adorned with their ornaments, of an Indian and his wife from the primeval forests of <placeName ref="gfa-places-250">Amerika</placeName>, the redskins, as they are called. Such a race of humans still exists, in contrast to those of the most advanced culture. One recognises at first sight that they are quite faithful reproductions, and without being a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7882">Lavater</persName>, one sees in the exceedingly pronounced features, hardened by toil, exertion, and even the highest indifferentism, a coarseness, cruelty, and then again languor, and yet they too are human beings!</p>
                <p>	I note only in passing that in no country in the world would it have been possible to compile such a collection of the most remarkable things that the savage, semi-savage and highly civilised peoples have produced in art and craftsmanship, as is the case here. — Anyone who has seen this exhibition will carry the impression of it with him for the rest of his life, yet one must never expect anything but a fragmentary account of it.</p>
                <p>	Around 7 o'clock in the evening, I went to supper in a neighbouring, very nice <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">dining establishment</term>, where many of the gentlemen and ladies who had also come from the exhibition were present in several rooms, and lived, while enjoying everything in equal quality, 50 percent cheaper than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my hotel</placeName>, which is located in the city, where everything is much more expensive.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's second visit, 19 June 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618506"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-19">June 19th</date></placeName>. After having gone early in hopes of visiting Dr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7470" type="met">Bolley</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471" type="met">Colladon</persName>, our two <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioners at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> (both staying in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="31">Finsbury Square</placeName>, a place, in fact, for its great distance from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition hall</placeName> not at all convenient for the duties of their office) and encountering neither, I was given a warm and cordial reception by England's first chemist, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName>, at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7575"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1703">Royal Institution</placeName></orgName>, and I was amply compensated for the long journey from Finsbury Square, where the above-mentioned compatriots are staying, to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1696" type="itinerar_London1851" when="1851-06-19" n="33">Albemarle Street</placeName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="34">Picadilly</placeName> by the most fascinating conversation I had with him.</p>
                <p>After almost an hour of discussion concerning primarily <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">pyrotechnical</term> objects, as well as the articles I had sent to the exhibition in response to a request I had received <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">at home</placeName>, I returned to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="35">exhibition</placeName>, which was not very far away (about half an hour). The thousands of echoes from the newspapers of all civilised countries will, without ever being able to exhaust the subject itself, describe it. I have already said how ludicrous it would be for a single individual to attempt anything remotely of the sort, and so I shall not, however many times I should go there, comment at all at length on what I have seen and admired.</p>
                <p><pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618507"/> <date when="1851-06-19">Today</date> I devoted myself first and foremost (it is forgivable for a father) to the search in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austrian</placeName> department for the submissions made by two of my sons who are established in that beautiful country, so richly endowed with natural treasures of all kinds.</p>
                <p>	Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8272"><persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName></orgName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName> delivered six tableaux of the most diverse assortment of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> and a seventh of samples of cast steel rods, the quality of whose shape, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">cut</term> and grade is to be judged by the jury at a later point in time, and Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-6330"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold Fischer</persName></orgName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-158">Traisen</placeName>, an exceptional collection of articles from the field of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-56">malleable Castiron</term>," which, though manufactured in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> earlier, albeit under a veil of secrecy, I also invented, and for which I was once awarded exclusive <term ref="gfa-keywords-8447">privilege</term> in <date when="1829">1829</date> by His Majesty the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7381">Emperor Francis</persName>. These articles of malleable cast iron were complemented by a number of beautifully crafted <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindles</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term> from his factory. On my remark to one of the custodians, who are distributed throughout the building in small offices, that the labels ("tikets"), that is, the small plates bearing the name of the exhibitor and the number assigned to his products in the catalogue, were missing, I was given permission with the greatest generosity to add anything I should think appropriate in this regard myself. However, since these articles <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618508"/>  had been placed under Austrian protection, I thought it appropriate not to preempt but to inform the I &amp; R Commissioner, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472">v. Buschek</persName>, of the matter by letter.</p>
                <p>	Altogether, one notices a great obligingness towards all strangers everywhere, and especially among the police, as well, and how so much attention is paid to everything without one being aware of it. The following may serve as evidence. Among the articles in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9828">my shipment</term> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, of which I had an illustration made <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">at home</placeName> by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-404">Beck</persName>, the drawing teacher, an engraving of which I commissioned in <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, there were also two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8971">daggers</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteoric steel</term> of very beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damask</term>. Upon looking after my things at the exhibition, these daggers, which had been placed in a rather exposed location, had gone missing.</p>
                <p>	I was nearly convinced that they had vanished, and so I inquired with an official. The latter immediately sent a policeman to another official, who, as would be the case, had been entrusted with the supervision of the articles of the Swiss department. He arrived forthwith and retrieved them from behind a large piece of meteoric steel, where they had been placed for greater security. They were then given a more suitable place for viewing.</p>
                <p>	Thousands and thousands of objects, each of them peculiar in its own way, remain unobserved, depending on the character of the observer, <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618509" break="no"/> yet, for one thing the industrious and ingenious country of England has compelled the attention of every visitor, and this is that in which it also claims highest rank in the world, namely, the quantity of its curious machines; they produce all manner of things before the spectator's very eyes. Here, they artfully <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">weave</term> beautiful and complex designs. There, they print; there, they <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">spin</term>; there, hundreds of the most sensible machines and tools are displayed, all designed to save time and serve perfectly the needs of life, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agriculture</term>, luxury and the arts, and in the very midst of these various machines, at the side of a fountain, of which there are many in the building, in general, providing ample water for cooling and drinking, a millstream rushes in perpetual flow from the opening of an upright parallelepiped (tall narrow box), as if from a monstrous gullet, 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high, and in a width of approximately 6 feet, into a relatively large basin. One cannot see where the water comes from, one cannot see where it goes, like the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8454">Danaids' barrel</term>, the basin never fills.  I wondered why, so as to make the whole thing still more imposing, they had not enclosed this surprisingly prosaic box with planks of imitation rock? In <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">Frankreich</placeName>, where they well-versed in the wrapping of everything in a pleasing manner, they would certainly <pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618510"/> have done something of the sort, and in <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>, where they still delight in miracles, they would perhaps even have added a <persName ref="gfa-actors-8265">Moses</persName> with a staff. The English have not yet reached the zenith of figurative poetry. According to my calculation, I had covered eleven <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> on foot between 9 o'clock in the morning and after 5 o'clock in the evening on my long walks, and now faced the bleak prospect of making yet another considerable journey to the city, as all the carriages from the exhibition building were occupied. At the far end of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="36">Picadilly</placeName>, I was fortunate enough to be able to occupy a seat vacated by another passenger on an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term>, and to have my highly afflicted body brought to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="37">my lodging</placeName>, to finally have supper at about 7 o'clock, and to write down the foregoing ruminations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>On life in London, 20 June 1851</head>
                <p>	<placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-20">June 20th</date></placeName>. The big cities are, with few exceptions, unpleasant and ruinous for those condemned to spend their entire lives there; they are veritable dungeons! Happy is he who is permitted to pass his days in honourable employment in our beautiful <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">fatherland</placeName>! — Londoners are never, or only very rarely, smiled upon by a sky as clear as our own, or rather, nearly the whole year through, they see nothing but the pall of smoke and dust spread so abundantly and vaporously over the metropolis. They do not behold the beautiful meadows, the running brooks, the green <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618511"/> forests, much less the silver crown of our <placeName ref="gfa-places-5">Alps</placeName>! — Grey and black-brown rows of houses without end, the ceaseless sound and noise of innumerable carts, laconic conversation or complete silence in the dining rooms of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inns</term> and even common taverns, where each of the arrivals first looks around in search of an unoccupied table, and as quickly as possible barricades himself behind an excessively large newspaper. This is but a brief, and certainly unexaggerated, sketch of London life, on the whole. — The bright side of all this, however, is that they are far more for domestic life than their neighbours across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">channel</placeName>, and that their quietude, and the spirit of study and advancement thus cultivated, applied even to the most inconspicuous of things, renders them capable of the astonishingly great things which they have already accomplished, and continue to accomplish. To these thoughts and comparisons, I was prompted by the various activities of the day, which I began and ended with difficulty, though it became interesting enough to me through an encounter with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9502">steel manufacturer</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1631">Newcastle upon Tyne</placeName>. I could not go to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, nor to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8455">Chinese collection</term>, which is not far from it, and made no other acquaintance than that of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-20" n="38">the banker where I withdraw the money</placeName> I need, and much is needed, indeed. It is good to have earned it in advance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>The "five shilling evening", 21 June 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618512"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-21">June 21st</date></placeName>. After a few outings very early in the morning, that is, in these late summer days at half past 7 o'clock, when most shops are still closed and there are not very many people or carriages on the street, I went to the counting house of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-21" n="39">bank Paynes &amp; Smith</placeName>, for which I had received a cheque (payment order) of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L.</term> 30 yesterday, so that if someone else should present it for payment, I would not be obliged to honour it. However, only a few subordinates were there, who undertook to carry out my request, but told me that I would have to come back at 9 o'clock, as payments would not be issued until such time. The situation was as follows: The night before, while I was away, my tailor came to collect my coat for altering, however, in that very coat was my purse containing the cheque. I did not return home that evening until after 9 o'clock, by which time there was nothing I could do. <date when="1851-06-21" type="travelday">This morning</date>, after leaving the bank, I went directly to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1736" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="40">fabric shop</placeName> where I knew the tailor was working. — If, said the owner, the purse was in your coat, you will certainly get it back and whatever may be in it, upon which he went immediately to the tailor himself and brought back the purse and its contents in no time at all. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, there is much deceit, but also much honesty, I believe more of the latter than of the former. In this city, the drink in particular makes <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618513"/> people poor and unhappy. The latter among all classes.</p>
                <p>	Regarding punctuality in all those businesses where, to a certain extent, mathematical precision prevails, which certainly has its advantages, I would like to add that when I returned to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7583"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-21" n="41">bank</placeName></orgName> a little before 9 o'clock, I was asked to take a seat on a <term ref="gfa-keywords-4350">bench</term> opposite the table at which the five cashiers conduct their business. About five minutes before 9 o'clock, the official to whom I was to present the payment order arrived. I held it in my hand and showed it to him, but he said not a word. Instead, he emptied several sacks of gold into a drawer together with the familiar shovel used to scoop it out again, and did nothing more.</p>
                <p>	At the stroke of 9 o'clock, however, he asked me only, Do you prefer <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9826">banknotes</term>? I replied gold. Without even counting (there were whole and half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8456">sovereigns</term>), he poured the gold into the pan and out of it onto the table without taking any further notice of me. I counted it anyway, and it was quite correct. — In order to know where Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7473">Wilson's</persName> office in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="42">glass palace</placeName> (one could not have chosen a better name) might be, I asked a "policeman" when I arrived there where I might find it, and he pointed me to a completely different, very distant side of the building. I found it <pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618514"/> all right, but did not encounter the man himself. About half an hour had passed since I decided to go home, when a police officer approached me quite some distance away from the spot. I thought to myself, What does he want? You have not done anything unlawful, after all. Then he stopped me and asked politely if I had found the office, to which I replied that I had, but this was proof to me of how carefully they observe people, for I was dressed in English style, that is to say in black. From him I first learned that the exhibition would remain open until the <date to="1851-10-31" from="1851-10-15">end of October</date>, which I was glad to hear, since <persName ref="gfa-actors-148"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">two of my sons</persName></persName>, who are established in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, were also planning to visit <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> later. I have already said how humble and polite these "policemen" are. They are all handsome, well-chosen people with dark blue tail coats, on the collar of which is embroidered the number under which the officer is registered, dark blue pantaloons, fine round hats, white gloves and, under their arm, a rolled-up overcoat of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">Indiarubber</term> (caoutschouc)" for dubious weather, but neither <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipe</term> nor <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre</term>, nor moustache. Well acquainted with the great city, or at least with the district assigned to them, anyone unsure of his bearings can obtain better information from no one, which they willingly give, even accompanying you for a distance, provided <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618515"/> that you speak English. — Today, being Saturday, the entrance fee, instead of 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term>, was now 5 shillings, like all Fridays and Saturdays. The rooms, however, were quite empty and, as I noted earlier, realised that, just as those less fortunate, richer people can grow equally accustomed to paying only a shilling for the same thing rather than five.</p>
                <p>	I remarked something else on this five-shilling evening, which was attended almost exclusively by people in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">equipages</term>, in proof of the great backward stride of the English in complying with the spirited catechism of the radicals. They still remain devoted to the so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8458">Zopfthum</term>" (whether this scurrilous term is of German or Swiss origin I do not know) among the general public in their country, by holding on to the good things from earlier times that have been recognised by experience, without making their eradication a popular idea to the general population, which then has the good fortune to be declared emancipated for the moment, in the form of brass music and chorale singing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A fulfilling Sunday spent writing, 22 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-22">June 22nd</date></placeName> Today, being Sunday, I began writing early, having stopped yesterday owing to genuine fatigue. Later I walked through the beautiful, rather extensive, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-22" n="45">Cheapside</placeName>, and would have liked to go into a "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Coffeeroom</term>" for a glass of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale</term> or claret, but apart from the fact that all the stores were hermetically sealed, so too were the doors. Even at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my inn</placeName>, the exterior door <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618516"/> was closed, and only those who knew the secret could open it by turning the knob, otherwise one had to ring the bell. Returning to the inn, I asked the innkeeper, since I was in the habit of paying by the day, to bring me the bill, but he politely asked me to wait until morning. Whether this is the case at all inns, or whether he is some kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9456">sectarian</term>, I do not know, but I do know that on the mainland they are more willing to take whatever money falls into their hands, they are not so particular about it, so as not to deter visitors. However little the Sabbath observance is to be despised, but rather to be honoured in the highest degree, if it comes from a sincerely thankful heart, where then every day becomes a Sabbath day, Christ Himself taught us the best lesson about it, when the Pharisees, whom those of our days resemble to a hair's breadth, asked Him for His opinion on it. An English woman spoke very earnestly to me about the fact that Parliament allows <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabs</term> ("cabriolets") to drive around town on Sunday and that <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroads</term> are allowed to operate, citing the God-fearing principles that have been practiced in her family, in that, when her dear father died and the funeral took place on a Sunday, the body (one does not carry it in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, one drives it to the churchyard) was not conveyed by her own horses, but by <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618517" break="no"/> hired ones. — I thought to myself, so it is they who are compelled to commit the sin of desecrating the Sabbath to spare her own from punishment. — In a province neighbouring the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">canton of Schaffhausen</placeName>, one often sees painted on the farmhouses a burning house, and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7474">St. Florian</persName> in immense proportions beside it with a bucket of water, which he pours over the flames. Beneath one such painting, a jester wrote, "O great, holy Florian, save my house, set others on fire." — Is that not a fitting passage for this story?</p>
                <p>	I spent the rest of the day writing to my youngest son <persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold</persName>, who, like his two older brothers<note>The persons referred to are <persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">Wilhelm Fischer (1803–1882)</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer (1804–1888)</persName>.</note>, has also earned his living and reputation in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> through diligence and skill. For all three of them, the Horatian saying "Ubi bene, ubi patria"<note>The correct phrase is "Ubi bene, ibi patria" (Where it is well with me, there is my country). The saying was coined by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7576">Cicero </persName>and not Horace.</note> remains true to this day, even though the true <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> man, in almost all cases, is drawn back to his birthplace in later years. Among other things, I told him in my letter: "Yesterday I visited my old inn, where I used to live, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1695" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="43">Cross Keys</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1726">Wood Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheap Side</placeName>, and the alley, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="44">Shoe lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet Street</placeName>, where I worked for the mechanic <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName> <ref type="cross" target="../1794"><date when="1794">57 years ago</date></ref>." — London does not change the way other cities do, it merely grows larger. Its brick houses always remain black, sad and monotonous; — Everything in the <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618518"/> world has two sides! England has its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition of industrial diligence</term>, which is temporary, and we have that, which nature in so manifold a way and in ever-renewing beauty, spreads out before us in all the glory of its creative power.</p>   
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's fourth visit, 23 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-23">June 23rd</date></placeName>. This morning, in the interest of my son, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName>, I wrote a letter to the Austrian commissioner in question, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472">v. Buschek</persName>, to acquaint him with the matter and to ask for redress, as a truly significant error had taken place regarding <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8272">his submission</orgName> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, both with regard to the omission of the display in the official catalog and in the name of the exhibitor on the objects themselves. Afterwards, I visited Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2134" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="46"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468" type="met">Im Thurn</persName></placeName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName> on private business. In the course of our conversation, we came to speak of a Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7475">Spencer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1631">Newcastle upon Tyne</placeName>, with whose <persName ref="gfa-actors-7476">son</persName> I had become acquainted a few days ago, and he told me that he had recently won his case for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9469">spiral springs</term> vs. <term ref="gfa-keywords-8932">cylinder springs</term>, for the so-called buffets on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, which, following the sale of his patent right to five other persons, secured him an annual income of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L. St.</term> 1900, or about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 23,000 of our money. Only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are inventions, the offspring of observation, <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618519"/> contemplation, and experiment to attain certainty, so highly valued in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term>. It is a pity that this mistaken country values only the practical and useful, while the doctrine of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9157">fundamental rights</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, of the learned professors and attorneys (who, for the sake of science, did not allow even a speaker, let alone a writer, the slightest grammatical mistake or, anything in their view, a formal error) has once again so quickly foundered. My transport from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-22" n="48"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, it almost bordered on a miracle, did not last more than two minutes for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> This time the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> drove on the opposite side of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1628">Serpentine River</placeName>, which is really only a rather large pond, like one of the smallest Swiss lakes, but which looks very impressive on the beautiful grounds of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698">Hyde park</placeName>, and pleasure boats with sails and "rigging" of not insignificant size sail around on it. After I had delivered a supplementary manuscript to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7473"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="49">office of Professor Wilson</placeName></persName>, providing details concerning my submission to the exhibition, I re-entered the building. The more one becomes acquainted with it, the more, I would say, one's senses dull to all that one sees and the less one desires to say anything about it, given the absolute impossibility <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618520"/> of any coherent description. Today I had a special purpose. In the entire catalogue, I found only one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre</term> listed among the items from <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName>; and in my shipment, there were articles of true Damascus, or as I call it, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteor steel</term>. Unfortunately, my wish to compare the Damascus was not fulfilled, for the sabre was hung too high and, moreover, was still in its sheath. I did see the three Egyptian commissioners, however. Two of them had the mixed features of the Negro and the Caucasian races, both in colour and in the restless, not very congenial gaze. The third, probably an Egyptian <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">German</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName>, stood out among them, like the modern, silver <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">candelabras</term> among the other, equally precious, genuine Egyptian products in their display. — One of the real Egyptians, (all three of them wore European attire, with the exception of their red hats with black tassels) had a five-pointed golden star on a golden chain, and below it the <placeName ref="gfa-places-148">Turkish</placeName> crescent, a curious emblem, to which our European diplomats might justifiably take exception. I stayed in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition building</placeName> until half past six in the evening, without having enjoyed a single thing that morning, but before leaving I viewed quite attentively the celebrated diamond <term ref="gfa-keywords-8459">Kooh-i-Noor</term>, or Mountain of Light, which is the property of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indian</placeName> prince <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618521" break="no"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7477">Runject Singh</persName>, and whose (presumed) value, judging by the calculation and estimation hitherto used for smaller diamonds, amounts to 2,000,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L. Sterling</term>, for it would be a shame not to have seen this magnificent jewel the size of Earth, to which, if I were hungry, I would have preferred half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> of bread. Going by general opinion, everyone is disappointed by this piece, and I would not give a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreuzer</term> to see it again. Even the women, who are otherwise not impervious to diamonds, walk away unmoved. A large rectangular railing encloses a similar pedestal. Inside this railing, which is equipped with a door, there are always two police officers. On the pedestal lies a blue-velvet cushion covered by a large dome-like cage of round, gilded iron bars. On two minuscule columns, equally gilded and barely 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> high, in a casing lying across it, rests now this wonder of the world, to which neither the foggy atmosphere of London, nor the genius of the English — who otherwise know how to effect many things —  by covering it with boards and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas light</term>, could give the brilliance that this white piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9227">carbon</term> (according to the explanation of our <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemists</term>) should have. As I said, it was already half past six o'clock. The people employed <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618522"/> in the building for this purpose covered the objects displayed on the stands with cotton cloths, and visitors walked quietly and without crowding towards the doors. Fortunately, among the many thousands hurrying home, I found a spot in an omnibus that took me all the way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="50">Cheapside</placeName> to an excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">tavern</term>, where I was able to eat enough to make up for my forgotten lunch.</p>
 </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's highlights of the Exhibition, 24 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-24">June 24th</date></placeName>. As an addendum to <date when="1851-06-23">yesterday’s</date> thoughts on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, there remains for me, as certainly for many thousands and thousands of visitors, aside from those things of general interest, namely the idea of this undertaking and its splendid execution, only a relatively very small part, for the sake of which I can be pleased to have witnessed this spectacle, for that is what I would like to call it, as regards both objects and people. Four main things, however, will remain in my memory as products of artistic creation. Namely, the portrait of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">queen</persName> on a life-size <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porcelain tablet</term>, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7478">Louis Philippe</persName> commissioned at the time of the<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8461">Entente cordiale</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1635">Sevres</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>; then, the large, absolutely flawless <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror made from a single cast</term>, 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high and 10 feet wide; furthermore, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8450">crystal fountain</term> of which I have already made mention. All three of these objects are the greatest triumph of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8462">halurgy</term>, to which, to a degree, the porcelain<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> must also be counted, and then, fourthly, the triumph of the <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618523"/> spirit, which controls the elements and natural forces according to its will and shows itself in all its power in the totality of the present machines and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, which even have <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rails</term> beneath them on which to run and for whose operation only a slight movement of the finger is required to transform its latent energy in the blink of an eye into powerful propulsion. These are the general impressions that can never be gained in such a way anywhere else. Of a thousand and one other things piled up here, the shop floors in great cities, especially in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> itself, offer a daily exhibition. One can say that the entire magazines of luxury articles and precious fabrics are veritable shops at the exhibition, namely glass cases, far larger than those of many stores in reality, where the objects contained therein can be viewed, but not touched. Nothing comes into being in the world at once in all its potency, yet it is astonishing how quickly in the course of time the current needs of society in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are provided for, from which the Englishman, and he is quite right, for this is the only true means of prolonging life, reckons chiefly the profit of time.</p>
                <p><date when="1851-06-24">Today</date>, because I now had at my disposal every means of transportation required <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618524"/> to do a great deal in less time, I travelled and did business from 10 o'clock in the morning until 4 o'clock in the evening, which astonished even me. — A <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> that I hired by the hour, for which I had to pay 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> each, took me first from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1700" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="51">St. Paul's Church</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="52">Finsbury Square</placeName> to the two <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioners, from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="53">Mint</placeName> by the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1727">Tower</placeName>, and then to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="54">Billeter Square</placeName>, and yet, after a rather long conversation with him, I was at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="55">London Bridge</placeName> by 2 o'clock. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9829">Since yesterday evening at 3 o'clock</term>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-1221">fire</term> had been raging on the opposite bank, which had broken out in a paper factory and enveloped several <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hop</term> warehouses. In today's newspapers, the damage to the various <term ref="gfa-keywords-237">insurance companies</term> was already estimated at 200,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L. Sterling</term> or 240,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term>. Aside from the firemen and the police, no one was bothered about this fire, except to linger a little out of curiosity. It was strange that when the first and second warehouses were burning with a vehemence that made it almost impossible to approach them, and the third warehouse had been saved from the fire completely, that it suddenly broke out in the fourth. The English expression for it was, "It was the fiend who did it," which suggests arson. Fiend is synonymous with Satan. On the banks of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, I purchased a ticket for one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboats</term> leaving every quarter of an hour from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639">Greenwich</placeName> and <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618525" break="no"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1640">Gravesand</placeName>, which for the 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="56">Greenwich</placeName> cost 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term>, or 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> and in half an hour I was there, and a willing Englishman immediately called a carriage driver, who after collecting the tax of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term> (3 kr.), guided me across the very wide Thames, where I arrived in a very short time at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8969"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7479"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7480"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7569"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1702" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="57">steamship factory of Misters Robinson &amp; Rüssel</placeName></orgName></persName></persName></term>. At the desk, I asked for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544">Baird</persName>, who, according to his earlier calculations, should have been back in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> long ago from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, where he had assembled the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8946">steamboat</term>, but this was not the case, as I was able to infer from a letter I received <date when="1851-06-23">yesterday</date> suggesting that not everything was in order there yet. I found it conspicuous that one of the gentlemen immediately asked me if I was a partner, to which I replied no, I was co-owner of another steamship. After some conversation, which seemed a bit suspicious to me and which did not quite correspond with the remark Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544">Baird</persName> once made to me in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, "You are my only friend", I was soon on my way. Again, a boat picked me up at the shore, and in the middle of the ever-turbid Thames, delivered me to the fast steamer Najade for the return trip, whereas the Sybille<note>The steamships Najade and Sybille mentioned by Fischer are not listed in Lloyd's "Register of British and Foreign Shipping 1850 &amp; 1851". This suggests that they were Thames ferry steamers, small ships weighing less than 100 gross tonnes.</note> had brought me. Every quarter of an hour, one is sure to encounter a steamboat going down to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1640">Gravesand</placeName>, <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618526"/> which is 22 miles from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName>, or up to London.</p>
                <p>	In the evening by 4 o’clock, I was back in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="58">my quarters</placeName>my quarters. This is the great savings in time I spoke of earlier. Later, I went to a nearby dining establishment, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1709" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="59">Metropolitan Tavern</placeName>. In elegance of tableware, it surpassed those at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my hotel</placeName>, and the price of everything, and equally good, was ¼ less than at my lodging, though it only went by the name of tavern, and not hotel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer and his exhibits, 25 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-25">June 25th</date></placeName>. This morning I went for the third time to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-25" n="60">Finsbury Square</placeName> to our <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioner Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471" type="met">Colladon</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1196">Geneva</placeName> and found him at home. From him I learned that Prof. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7470">Bolley</persName>, his colleague, had gone home and was unlikely to return. It also seems to me that one commissioner is sufficient, since everything is so well organised, and there is a clerk <persName ref="gfa-actors-7481">Steiger</persName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">glass palace</placeName> every day, who speaks all three languages, German, English and French, has been living in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> for 16 years and can<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> provide any necessary information. A good deal of money could have been spared in Switzerland, but this has probably happened to other governments as well; expenditures in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are not to be taken lightly, and the most regrettable thing is that they will hardly benefit those <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618527"/> who made them, neither the governments nor the individuals. Nevertheless, I would have had no occasion for this visit had I not already made the acquaintance of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471">Colladon</persName> <date when="1825">26 years ago</date> at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8103">Swiss Natural Historical Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1271">Solothurn</placeName>; incidentally, this is the place to say it, as a Swiss it was also agreeable to him that the little that I contributed to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> was there only by itself. Namely, my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus meteor steel</term></term> and objects made from it, as well as the samples of the alloy of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> in various proportions that I invented, which was previously considered impossible. Be the verdict of the jury of its day what it may, I can testify that I was initially reluctant to send anything to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, as I considered my achievements in this case too insignificant for a jury that was meant to judge, so to speak, the industry of all four regions of the world, and that I only did so after our first magistrates at the time requested that I do so. They wished to see something to represent the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">canton</placeName> and trusted that I would be willing to do so, though I had no hope of success.</p>
                <p>	From Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471">Colladon</persName> I proceeded to my old and highly esteemed friend, Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483" type="met">Brande</persName>, Director of the Stamp Office at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1636" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-25" n="61">Mint</placeName></orgName>. — The English have a good memory for friendship, this I have <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618528"/> still found to be true. In our conversation about the nature of metals, we both remained static at the boundary that it had so far implacably set for our research. I reiterated my old idea that water in some form or another acts as a bonding agent for metal atoms. I said that I had told him the same thing <date when="1826">25 years ago</date><note>Compare journal 1825—1827 p. 32 and journal 1846 p. 28.</note> and that he had corrected me when I used the expression water and had noted that it was not water but <term ref="gfa-keywords-8741">hydrogen</term>. I now have reason to believe, however, based on my observations that at least another third form than water, which is a compound, and hydrogen, which, on the other hand, is believed to be a simple body, must exist. He neither contradicted nor confirmed, the way the English do, who prefer to be rather too silent than to talk too much, which is the most sensible thing even in politics, where, on the other hand, our beloved youth (jeunesse), who endeavour to improve the world, speak out in volumes, but who, once dependent on the crutch and the armchair, will likely change their tune.</p>
                <p>	If only I could tap the sources of knowledge that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, and <persName ref="gfa-actors-5424">Liebig</persName> have given us! — The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> invented by me, of which I have already spoken above, and the samples of which I presented to him consisted of 8 parts old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and 3 parts <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, interested him very much as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8917">chemist</term>, <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618529" break="no"/> and it seemed to me that it almost made him disbelieve certain theories contained in the books, since here we have an indisputable fact. He took me into the mint, where he showed me an almost unbelievable break in a press frame of immense thickness and quite sound casting, and then into the water tower, which contains, at a height of 70 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in an iron basin of 50,000 cubic feet, the best drinking water, drawn from a tapped spring by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>, serving equally well for consumption and to extinguish fires. We also visited the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term>. It is almost unbelievable what long sheets of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> lie about waiting to be processed there, or perhaps only understandable, since this little <placeName ref="gfa-places-402">Albion</placeName> dominates the world far more than <persName ref="gfa-actors-7451">Napoleon</persName> or his predecessors ever did through conquest.</p>
                <p>	When I consider, as I write this, that it is only the twelfth day since I left home, that I have travelled through so many countries, have had such a stormy sea voyage, and have already seen so many astonishing things, and think back to the times of my first journey on foot to <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, in <date when="1787">1787</date>, and how everything was then, bad and narrow roads, only footbridges instead of bridges over the two, often so torrential, forest waters of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1642">Wutach</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1643">Steinach</placeName>, I can hardly recognise myself in the drive that has been given to the human spirit since then: will it continue like this, <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618530"/> where will we end up!? And who will guarantee that the idea does not arise, if the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8464">aether</term> be suitable for respiration, or if a surrogate is found, <term ref="gfa-keywords-6029">to establish contact with other worlds</term>, which, I might add, the Creator makes quite easy for us through something that is generally avoided like a bitter medicine, namely, through the simple medium of death, "where (as <persName ref="gfa-actors-7947">Schiller</persName> so beautifully expresses it) the spirit is stripped of the earthly, separates itself in flames from its shell, and drinks the pure air of the aether!"<note>Fischer is quoting, in slightly modified form, from Friedrich Schiller's poem Life and the Ideal.</note></p>
                <p>	One would have enough to write about in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> if limited to only the new things that happen every day, yet they accumulate so quickly as to become immediately obsolete and easily forgotten. Who would not have stopped to watch a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9829">burning fire</term> that had already been raging for two days, which, as already mentioned, I myself witnessed yesterday on my way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> to embark for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639">Greenwich</placeName>, or rather who would not have watched it for a long time? Yet, as I said, this was not the case. People were going back and forth across <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> with their usual alacrity, and I, too, spoke to my fellow passenger on the steamboat about it only as long as we were in its vicinity.</p>
            </div>   
                <div type="day">
                    <head>Fischer's walks through London, 26 June 1851</head>
                    <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-26">June 26th</date></placeName>. Devoting myself quite early to some business, before intending to go to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="66"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, as the former might lead to some interesting remarks <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618531"/> in the future and confirm that the straightest and clearest path in business always leads most surely to the goal. — If I were a writer of novels, instead of giving an account to myself of the time I have spent, and if I had the talent for it, I could write a rather thick book with truths from my experiences, which would look quite like a novel. So much for all that. Before I went to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, I was curious to know, since my way led me through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1644" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="63">Lombard Street</placeName>, coming from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="62">Billeter Square</placeName>, what had become of my two traveling companions, Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName> and Cantonal Councillor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">Ammann</persName>, whom I had only met once by chance in the Crystal Palace, but although they were staying in this street, I could not find the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1708">City Hotel</placeName>. An old woman instructed me to go to St. George’s Court<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note>, and there, in the rearmost part of it, was their lodging, called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1689" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="64">St. George and Vulture</placeName>, but they had already departed. The building is not so terrible and seems to be frequented mostly by Germans, among whom are probably a number of refugees. In London, however, they do not make their fortune with their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9830">beards</term>, just as little as with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9635">cigars</term>, and I appeal to all those who have been in London to say whether they have ever encountered a single person out of a thousand people in the street <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618532"/> with a cigar or a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">pipe</term> in his mouth. Time has too great a value in England for this pastime.</p>
                    <p>	The English commoners have not yet entirely abandoned their intolerance of foreign manners, dress and coiffure. When I worked in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> fifty-seven years ago, anyone with foreign attire very soon had what they call "a mob at ones heels", and the honorific name they attached to such an individual was generally "french Dog", insofar as in the great generality the geographical knowledge of this mob extended only to French, and Dutch, inhabitants of <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName>; but on this day, <date when="1851-06-26">June 26th 1851</date>, I read in the morning in the eminent newspaper <term ref="gfa-keywords-8465">Morning Chronicle</term>, a very general article about the reactionary policy of <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, in which the large number of troops, which this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9093">monarchy</term> still has standing on its feet in the face of gloomy financial conditions, is criticised, but is partly excused by the political behaviour of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1566">Preussen</placeName>, which is not called by any nice name, and adds that the same (i.e., number of troops) is necessary owing to the garrisons that <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> must keep in its large cities, such as <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-251">Prague</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1909">Brixen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1965">Hohenlinden</placeName> (I read the words for the third time). Incidentally, it is known, insofar as it was published in the newspaper, that, when the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1728">Scheldt</placeName> was opened under his <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618533"/> administration, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7503">the great Pitt</persName><note>In all likelihood <persName ref="gfa-actors-7503">William Pitt the Elder</persName>. The Scheldt question and access to the river mouth for trade was a political issue of international importance. Access to the river had already led to a brief conflict in 1784 and shortly thereafter once more during the French Revolution. The river was opened again in 1792. It cannot be ruled out, however, that Fischer was referring to the son, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7931">Pitt the Younger</persName>, since the Scheldt question was still relevant during his term of office.</note> asked, "where is that d. Escaut?" — Where is that damned Scheldt? Just as in <date when="1814">1814</date>, when I came to England, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9301">customs officer</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, to whom I said that I was from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> in Switzerland, asked me in all seriousness whether missionaries also visited us. In the diary of my travels at that time, I immediately recorded this question and my answer to it, which can still be found in print. The English hunger for newspapers must be fed every day, and, for the same price, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7504">John Bull</persName> is fed just as great a variety of stories as a stranger who ventures haphazardly into this or that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">eating-house</term> in London. To come back to the subject of all manner of foreigners' beards and how repugnant they are, as it seems, to the English commoners, I read <date when="1851-06-26">on the same day</date> in the newspaper <term ref="gfa-keywords-8466">Punch</term>, which otherwise treats no one with mercy, a complaint about the English commoners and their ragamuffins, of whom, by the way, one sees less than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, that they have carried their insolence against Germans with beards so far as to run after them in the vicinity of the exhibition building and to present them with old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> in mockery.</p>
                    <p>	This tendency to imitate the custom of times long past in beards and frumpy old German attire, which good taste rejects, will hardly last long, however.</p>
                    <p><pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618534"/> Many times, as I walked down <placeName ref="gfa-places-1644">Lombard Street</placeName>, a narrow and not very long street, where several bankers and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9064">money changers</term> reside, I have stopped in front of the currency exchange house <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7581"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1704" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="65">Spielman &amp; Comp.</placeName></orgName>, as almost everyone does who has not yet discovered the displays in its windows of large pans, filled mostly with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> and then covered with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9091">banknotes</term> and other paper money, and, in addition to these riches, layers of gold bars weighing 4-6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> and more. Today, however, I was particularly attracted by a pan of <placeName ref="gfa-places-629">Californian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">wash gold</term>, and I am certainly not exaggerating when I estimate the weight of gold contained in this pan to be about 40 pounds, and thus worth at least 30,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term>. As gold it is of no interest to me, but immensely so for its form. The general character is as follows: flat, mostly elongated round leaves, approximately as thick as a playing card and even thicker, up to the size of a fingernail. This, however, is not the marvellous thing, but rather the conglomeration, the fusion of these leaflets without any apparent gangue ("Lode"). They can be best compared to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> flakes that are formed when (in our country at least) young women (sometimes also unmarried older ones) observing the usual traditions, pour liquefied lead into water on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9746">St. Andrew's Eve</term>, in order to discern from its shape <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618535" break="no"/> whether they will soon find a husband.</p>
                    <p>	I have devoted so much time to studying <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term> in regard to their formation and destruction, I deliberately use these unscholarly expressions, that I was quite disturbed by the sight of these peculiar formations today. Something else struck me about this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term>, namely its reddish, somewhat dingy colour, in contrast to the otherwise solid gold that has accumulated into its natural state, of which I own a beautiful specimen from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1645">Calandaberg</placeName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-57">Grisons</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>	Following the advice of the synopsis enclosed with the catalogue, I devoted my attention today more to the individual objects of particular interest to me than to wandering around in the extensive halls, looking at everything and seeing nothing, and recorded what I thought worthy of later recollection. In the end, I recorded a far larger inventory than I had assumed and will probably write several pages at another time than at this late hour (half past midnight) about the observations I made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>On the English export market, 27 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-27">June 27th</date></placeName>. Today, a full day of business, was a very tiring one for me, although important in its consequences, insofar as I will have to stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> probably longer than I had intended. <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618536"/> I went first to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="67"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7505" type="met">Cammell</persName></placeName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, the largest steel manufacturer in England, whom I had met before, and who, in his conversation with me, declared that his business had expanded to the extent that he was now making 50 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term> a week of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">casting</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467">spring steel</term>, that is, over 1000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>. Then I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="68">Billeter Square</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1646">Fenchurch Street</placeName> and from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1647" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="69">Phoenix Foundry</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1648">Southwark</placeName>, far across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, where I watched the casting of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8468">bearings</term> (a kind of bushing for the axles of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>), consisting of a patented white and soft material, which I know, and discovered some ingenious devices for it. About the properties of these bearings, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7506">Dewrance</persName>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9026">inventor</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> owner, told me that they perform quite well over not too great distances, but turn into a kind of "Decomposition" of black sludge when the friction is sustained for too long a period over great distances, such as from London to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1937">Edinburgh</placeName>.</p>
                <p>	My business was concluded in a further conversation with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505" type="met">Cammell</persName> at his office in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="70">Barge Yard</placeName>, near the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1650">Mansion House</placeName>, whereby I merely remark that only as the English have the whole world as a market for their manufactured goods, their immense turnover makes it possible for them to offer everything so cheaply and, thereby, to crush other <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618537" break="no"/> manufacturers, where they are not subjected to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9444">tariffs</term> in other countries. For one must know that, for example, in the case of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9502">steel production</term>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName> sells his rolled spring steel for 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term> or 7½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. If we assume that he has only half a Kreuzer of pure profit on each <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> after deducting all expenses (<date when="1826">25 years ago</date> the steel manufacturers in England still calculated a profit on 3 Kreuzer per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>, as Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7507">Tailor</persName>, then director of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7508">iron and steel works "at the seven Oaks,"</orgName></term></term> informed me), then there still remains a net profit of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 833 per week, or 40,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term> for the whole year, for large-scale production. Manufacturers on the mainland cannot emulate this, as under no circumstances (I am referring to the production of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> here) is it possible to make a profit that even approaches a fiftieth of a percent. Incidentally, what we have just said can be applied to almost all types of products. So much for today. Later, perhaps only after my return, I will come back to this subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A bathing expedition, 28 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-28" type="travelday">June 28th</date></placeName>. One often plans to do something in the morning, and by evening, nothing has come of it. Since in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> on Saturday afternoon and on Sunday one is to a certain extent quite left to oneself, the freedom to think only of oneself is considerable, and I therefore had in mind for these two days and Monday to head for <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618538"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, or at least for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, whose <placeName ref="gfa-places-2029"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9449">seaside resorts</term></placeName> are inviting enough in the current heat. However, my business in the morning and writing a letter <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">home</persName> in the afternoon delayed my departure in order to reach either of these places in time, so I decided to go to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1652" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-28" n="71">Leicester Square</placeName>, where I was told there was a bathhouse. From the outside it looks quite respectable, and there are four doors, the first and second for ladies of the first and second classes. A similar partition was provided for the gentlemen. I went to the first class bureau and was given two towels and a coin, marked first class, but I immediately lost all desire to enter when asked to pay no more than six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> (18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term>). I was then directed to a narrow gallery, which had equally narrow baths and where about 30 people sat in a queue on benches against the wall, who in the order in which they arrived were directed to a bath as soon as one was vacant. By my calculation, I would have had to wait another 1½ hours, and so I returned my coin and towels, and received, contrary to expectation, my money back. Too overheated from all the walking, I entered a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8920">chemist's</term> to drink a jug of natural <term ref="gfa-keywords-8446">seltzer water</term>, which, since he told me about it, I followed up with a portion of an artificial one, <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618539" break="no"/> which I thoroughly enjoyed for its plentiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9226">carbonation</term>. Regarding it as unhealthy, the "Chemist" was reluctant to give much approval to so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9194">Gingerbeer</term>," of which I had already partaken in the morning, as it has an extremely pleasant taste, and which is frequently consumed in summer.</p>
                <p>	On my way home, I encountered two street sweepers in operation, each of which was drawn by a horse. In these devices, too, which do the work of 20 maids, we see the spirit of the English. On a two-wheeled cart is an oblong wooden box open at the top, at the rear of which, at a suitable distance, an iron axle passes through a cylindrical brush of about 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in length and 2½ to 3 feet in diameter. It has two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur gears</term> that interlock with the spur gears of the same size attached to the inner of the two hubs, so that when the horse advances, the broom, which has just enough slack as to always rest on the street, also rotates from back to front, sweeping the street and pushing the collected matter in front of it. When a quantity of refuse has been collected, the driver stops, scoops it into the box and continues his journey.</p>
                <p>As an addendum to my remarks, referring mainly to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> objects <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618540"/> mentioned at the end of my notes from <date when="1851-06-26">June 26th</date>, which I was prevented from writing by fatigue and the late hour I would have had to devote to them, I mention, first of all, a collection of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, known as "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8469">Wootz</term>," from <placeName ref="gfa-places-397">Bombay</placeName>, and then the unshaped <term ref="gfa-keywords-9497">steel blooms</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1729">Golconda</placeName>, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7609">Tavernier</persName> mentions in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8470">records of his travels</term>. This wootz consists of small lumps or "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9249">Reguli</term>," almost always of the same weight, which were cooled in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>. I still possess a fourth of such a lump, which was given to me by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7509">Bréant</persName>, Inspecteur des <placeName ref="gfa-places-1934">Essais</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, in <date when="1826">1826</date>. A whole lump of this kind commonly weighs ⅞ of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>. This steel is hard, very difficult to <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">forge</term>, it damascenes, yet, at least in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europa</placeName>, does not produce long-lasting cutting instruments. The latest opinion about this steel, albeit erroneous, is that it consists of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">magnetic iron</term>". More accurately, one might say it is made of magnetic ironstone. The Golconda lumps are thin and wide, often very porous, and such a lump, which is usually broken into four parts, yields four beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">damask</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre blades</term>, however, often with what the English refer to as "Flaws." I would also mention that this steel is very durable and of excellent quality. Among the stone-cutting tools, I saw a useful device for the hammers, which we call two-pronged hammers, namely steel spikes, which are pointed at the top and bottom and serve two <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618541" break="no"/> purposes; they are simply inserted into the iron hammer, which has a rectangular conical hole. If a man has a dozen such spikes, he can work for days without having to run to the blacksmith again, and that is enough for today.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Further highlights of the Exhibition, 29 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-29">Sunday, June 29th</date></placeName>. In my daily entries, for which I often, even in the height of summer, had to spend hours of the night, I touched on some things only briefly, or not at all, in the hope of mentioning them at a more convenient time. For these things, Sundays in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are quite suitable if one does not travel and, therefore, the following addendum.</p>
                <p>I have already remarked in my earlier notes that nothing would be easier than to report something new, or never before seen, every day. Yet, how the various forms of charlatanism, which at bottom is so contrary to the serious and scrutinizing character of the English, though it does not seem to fail in its intended effect and can flourish alongside the genuinely new, good and interesting, is almost incomprehensible and must surely derive from the surprisingly one-sided education of the people. Every day, on my way to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, in the high streets of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, but especially in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Piccadilly</placeName>, one of the broadest and most beautiful streets of London that leads to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698">Hydepark</placeName>, I saw six shabby fellows on the sidewalk ("Flags") walking back and forth in procession, one behind the other, all day long. <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618542"/> Each of them carried a large wooden frame attached to a flat pole on the paper cover of which was advertised in large red letters, where one might see a view of the "Holy land" and acquire a faithful image of the city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1768">Jerusalem</placeName> at the time of our Saviour for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> (six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>). Anyone who knows the history of the terrible destruction of that city 70 years after Christ (fulfilling the prophecy), as it was handed down to us by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7510">Flavius Josephus</persName>, would be astonished at such deception of the public. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1653"><placeName ref="gfa-places-491">Rheinau Monastery</placeName></placeName> also boasts such an ancient <term ref="gfa-keywords-9776">illustration</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1768">Jerusalem</placeName>, that is, unless it has been stolen from it, like another precious picture book depicting the traditional dress (if I am not mistaken) of the 13th and 14th centuries, at a time when its true owners had no control over their library. However, that illustration is rather more a city plan bearing its location from later times than an illustration like the one above and, in any case, does not bear this presumptuous inscription.</p>
                <p>	When circa 2000 years ago the famous <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematician</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7511">Archimedes</persName> (whose tomb in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1730">Syracuse</placeName>, already overgrown with weeds, was renovated and restored by the equally famous <persName ref="gfa-actors-7576">Cicero</persName>, during his time as proconsul in <placeName ref="gfa-places-434">Sicily</placeName>), after having made the great discovery of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9116">specific gravity</term> of bodies in the bath and, thereby, exposing the fraud of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8720">goldsmith</term>, who substituted alloyed <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618543"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> for the pure gold that the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8276">king</persName> had given him to make the royal crown, repeated his joyful <emph rend="italic">ἑvϱεκα!</emph> <note>Correct spelling: ηὕρηκα.</note>( I have found it!), he could hardly have imagined that some two thousand years later, in the far north, in the vicinity of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1706">Thule</placeName>, in the "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tinlands</term>" (what is today England) a tailor would adopt his exclamation regarding the men's dress shirts he manufactures, in order, by means of this enigmatic word, to demonstrate to the gullible London public, who are, in fact, not very well versed in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-821">Greek</placeName> language, that he alone had discovered the one true cut for men's dress shirts.  — And, yet it is so — and in several of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">coaches</term>, which travel daily to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, one finds this Greek tailor's pronouncement on a large advertising leaflet. I have already said it repeatedly, and I will say it again, the charlatanry in England is beyond belief, and it seems that they love it for it appears in such great variety.</p>
                <p>	Indeed, it is astonishing how people in this cosmopolitan city resort to the most incredible things to earn money or to acquire things, and yet the people of the lower classes, despite all manner of industriousness, are not one whit better off than they are in our own country, or rather, not even as well off as those in our own. They have nothing to cultivate. Forests, fields and pastures, not to speak of vineyards, <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618544"/> remain unknown to many, who, it is said, never get out of London their whole lives. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName>, who has offices here, as well as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-497">Hamburg</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-389">New York</placeName>, proclaimed with great chagrin upon seeing a coloured illustration of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967"><placeName ref="gfa-places-97">my steelworks in the Mühlenthal</placeName></placeName>: "This is where I want to live! I'll not stay in London! — The bustle is too great, and nothing but wear and tear." Last week's newspaper reported 870 deaths, and this week's just 100 more, namely 970.</p>
                <p>	Again, in one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> that travel daily to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, there was a rather large coloured <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithograph</term> print at the front, inside, depicting a beautiful young woman and an elder gentleman. Half of the young woman’s hair was in its natural colour, namely an garrish red, while the other half was a glossy raven black, and the gentleman, half of whose hair and Van Dyke beard, was more white than grey, with the other half transformed into a beautiful nut-brown, what the English call "auburn", by virtue of the artistry of the hair dresser, whose address in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Picadilly</placeName>, where he lives, was appended to the lithograph.</p>
                <p>My visits to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> on several days <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618545"/> only taught me that, if visiting it is to be of use to anyone with a specific purpose in mind, one must, apart from the most prominent and generally admired objects, turn away completely from the superfluity of what is there and limit oneself only to what can serve this purpose to the greatest extent possible, and that is why I only note, in these leisure hours and later, those things that particularly interested me, as I write first and foremost only for myself, knowing that <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my family</persName> and few friends will gladly make do with what is sufficient for myself. These pages are, as usual, only an account I give myself for the purpose of recollection.</p>
                <p>	In view of my limited leisure time, I devoted my attention almost exclusively to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-289">mineral</term>, and, in conjunction with these, <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> objects and their processing, as well as the machines and tools available for this purpose. As a result, the notes I took there and then, which constitute the synopsis in hand, were unfortunately almost too brief and catalogue-like to be instructive or engaging for anyone but myself by way of recollection.</p>
                <p>Specimens<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8471">plumbago</term> from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1654">Borrowdale pit</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1655">Cumberland</placeName>, this curious mineral, which in the great heat of our <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618546" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelting furnaces</term>, when pulverised, does not even agglutinate, are the richest in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9227">carbon</term>, the analysis yielding 90 parts in 100, and only the 10 remaining parts consist of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9212">silicon</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8654">iron oxide</term>, interested me as <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> material, as well as various specimens of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8472">hydraulic lime</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8473"><placeName ref="gfa-places-608">Roman cement</placeName></term>, of which the basic constituents are as a rule always <term ref="gfa-keywords-9212">silicon</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8785">alum</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">lime</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8832">magnesia</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9002">siderite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9460">soda</term>. I passed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coal</term> samples of all kinds and sizes only with regret, as the various and weak veins in <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">our canto</placeName>n (we cannot even apply the term "coal field") only seem to tantalise, and even to date in the whole of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, which seems to be situated at too high an altitude for a coal field, though they also occur in England not far from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1656">Ashford</placeName> in a tunnel 300 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> above the sea. Cut into standard sized pieces, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1657">Stavely</placeName> coals are said to be twice as useful both as fuel and as ship's ballast, since they leave no empty spaces between them when loaded.</p>
                <p>	Samples of artificial fuel, meaning solid lumps produced by strong pressure and mixed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9561">tar</term> from coal residue and the like, can be put on a par with so-called <placeName ref="gfa-places-127">Russian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8475">carboline</term>, and under certain circumstances can be regarded as a worthwhile product. Whether or not <term ref="gfa-keywords-2570">coals</term> prepared from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8476">tanbark bricks</term> are worthy of interest can only be determined by use and <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618547" break="no"/> comparison of their effect with other fuel, just as little can be said about the various types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ores</term>, the majority of which belong to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8653">clay ironstones</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8654">hematites</term>, the latter of which are added to the former, as they are poorer in content, to improve yield. <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Steel</term> samples from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1658">Ulverstone</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Ironworks</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlery</term> made from this steel, made by direct <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> (red bloodstone, which is very fine in the quarry, something not entirely desirable), interested me very greatly. Finely ground samples of this ore, with which they <term ref="gfa-keywords-8757">carburise</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> in England, are also on display here. This is nothing new, however; to date, the product has always been unreliable when produced in an open fire of any kind. To be done successfully, the only reliable method for this procedure is in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>; however, only very rich iron ores, yielding 60 to 70 pCt.<note>Abbreviation for percent (%).</note>, are suitable for this. We have such ores in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1659">Bella Luna</placeName>, but, to my knowledge, they do not occur in England. The model of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">throat</term> of which is closed after each charge with a valve-like lid, and the flame emitted through a side furnace to be used for special purposes, was also not without interest to me. However, I was not able <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618548" break="no"/> to learn anything of the results obtained with it.</p>
                <p>	The large <term ref="gfa-keywords-8479">silver</term> cake, weighing just over 7½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> and worth <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 40,000, obtained using <persName ref="gfa-actors-7577"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8478">Mr. Pattinson's process</term></persName>, is remarkable for its size and the manner in which it was displayed. By means of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8477">segregation process</term>, or rather skimming off the still liquid <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> with a perforated shovel from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> that has already solidified in the melting pot, it is melted again in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberatory furnace</term>, and the residual lead is oxidised (a kind of abrasion process), leaving silver of great purity.</p>
                <p>	I spent some time examining the various <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> samples by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7512">Stirling and Morris</persName>. I first need to know more about their success in application before I will comment on their merits or shortcomings.</p>
                <p>	Their patented so-called “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8481">Patenttoughened</term>" iron<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> consists of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8508">puddled iron</term> into which, while still liquid in the furnace, chunks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9012">wrought iron</term> are thrown in – a product, which owing to the insufficient fusion, as the latter chunks do not turn into liquid, could only be extolled as excellent by a patent-addicted Englishman.</p>
                <p>	Malleable bell metal is ludicrous. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9133">Bells</term> are cast, not forged. It is well known that the hardest bell metal <pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618549" break="no"/> always produces the most beautiful tone. Their union metal appears to be a mixture of six parts <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> and one part <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term>, which, if not invented by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7513">Rinnmann</persName>, was first described by him in his history of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. In the samples of copper-iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">compound</term> there is evidence of free iron that has separated from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, which happens very easily if the proper techniques are not carefully practiced.</p> 
                <p>After lunch on this leisurely Sunday, I walked from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-29" n="73">my lodging</placeName>, not always in the mood to write, from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612" type="itinerar_London1851" when="1851-06-29" n="74">Ludgate Hill</placeName>, partly as a shortcut, but primarily out of curiosity, through the narrow, crooked side streets to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-29" n="75">Blackfriars Bridge</placeName> to observe life and the hustle and bustle on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>. Good God, I thought, whoever is condemned to spend his life in these dingy black buildings in the middle of the city, as it were, with their sparse, dusty windows and dark, cheerless rooms, must have grown accustomed to them from his youth. Only the conveniences to be found within the least of them offer some little compensation. Bread, meat, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term>, milk and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> are brought into the house. Water is in the kitchen and light in the room, for, to produce light, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas flows out of the pipe</term> as soon as a valve is turned and ignites with a small bang when a burning piece of paper is held up to it. <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618550"/> One needs neither <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">lamp</term> nor <term ref="gfa-keywords-8593">wick trimmer</term>, though the gas flame does blacken, and everything in these dwellings is so dark and gloomy that one is glad only to see the open sky again and be out in the fresh air again.</p>
                <p>	Having arrived on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661">Blackfriars Bridge</placeName>, I could not without repeated astonishment, though I had seen it before but not to such a degree, contemplate the number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">passenger steamers</term> moving up and down every second of the day, as they are the real <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> on water. At one moment I counted 12 moving between <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661">Blackfriars</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> alone and, on the whole, some 30 going up and down within a little less than an hour. What struck me, and it is likely the latest design, were the low and narrow smoke-free funnels on a few of them, while others were still emitting thick black clouds of it. These new boats were also not exceptionally long, but narrow, and cut across the bow and built with a very tight curvature. The speed of the wheels, and thus of the ship, was quite fast, which is easier to achieve with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high-pressure steam engines</term> than with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8955">atmospheric</term><note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> ones. It is quite mind-boggling to think how the immense capital for everything one sees could have been raised.</p>
                <p><pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618551"/>Yet, it is more the circulation than the amount of money that is visible here. Each new generation inherits from the preceding one its debts and its money, then, generally speaking, continues its activity for 30 years before stepping down again from the stage to make room for a new one.</p>
                <p>	Anyone who has seen the cottages of the inhabitants of our northernmost regions can imagine at best, albeit without certainty, how it might have looked here nearly 2000 years ago, when <persName ref="gfa-actors-7514">Julius Caesar</persName> undertook his march to Britain, and not far from this place cut his pile bridge across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> (some of these piles were excavated about 50 years ago and preserved in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1662">Leverian Museum</placeName>, where I saw them. They are made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8983">oak</term>, but black through and through like <term ref="gfa-keywords-8981">ebony</term>, and just as hard).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer on the visit by the British seamen, 30 June 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-30">Monday, June 30th</date></placeName>. Last week, at her expense, the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen</persName> had her own <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7578">sailors</orgName>, namely those who are exclusively on duty on the two royal yachts, brought to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName> on a special train on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroad</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1663">Spithead</placeName>, where, if I am not mistaken, these ships are docked. They all appeared in their blue jackets, white "Trousers" and simple oilcloth hats with wide brims, very handsome, indeed. Many still adorned with cords for good behaviour. This seems to me an excellent idea to encourage emulation. <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618552" break="no"/> Corporals, sergeants and sergeant majors must be in every company, even if there is not an excellent man among them, and they have their badges of distinction, as is quite respectable. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">Medals</term> are also awarded, especially in wartime, for special service, though it is not always wartime, in which case they seem to be appropriate for good conduct in peacetime, as well. The <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen's</persName> idea of making the exhibition accessible to her <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7578">sailors</orgName> has since been extended to other persons unable to visit the exhibition for reasons of duty, of their distance from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, or want of funds. Orphans and boys from seminaries have also been admitted, and today, while I was sitting at breakfast, there passed by my windows five wagons decorated with tree branches and flags, some of which were designed only for people to stand in so-called "Vans" and others for people to sit in, and each <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">wagon</term> drawn by four horses, all five of which could together hold well over 300 people. They were the workers from two factories. This example will now, for better or worse, have to be imitated by many others, which will significantly increase revenues for the exhibition. In the end, <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> always finds the greatest part of its resources in itself, for when one considers the costs of this undertaking, which have already been incurred <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618553"/> and are yet to be incurred, then what the foreigner contributes is, in fact, virtually nothing, for he can have his fill of the exhibition four days a week from 10 o'clock in the morning until 7 o'clock in the evening for 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shillings</term> or 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term></p>
                <p>	Before leaving for the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="78">exhibition</placeName> on this foggy, mid-summer morning, I paid a visit to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7463" type="met">Mind</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1717" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="76">Oxford Street</placeName>, who received me hospitably, and also introduced me to his wife and elder daughter, as his and his younger daughter's traveling companion from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> to London. After that I headed to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472" type="met">v. Buschek</persName>, Imperial <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austrian</placeName> Commissioner, at his office, 43 <placeName ref="gfa-places-1731" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="77">Clarges Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Picadilly</placeName>, in order to discuss important matters regarding the oversight in the catalogue concerning the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-6330">exhibits of my son</orgName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName>.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head> Fischer's seventh visit, 1 July 1851</head>
                <p><date when="1851-07-01" type="travelday">July 1st</date>. In anticipation of soon leaving <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, so that I might travel to the north of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> before my journey <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>, I spent the whole day in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-01" n="79">exhibition halls</placeName>, where one can refresh oneself as necessary, without having to leave the building.</p>
                <p>For myself, as well as for those who may get hold of this little manuscript some day, I will include the things that were most interesting to me today in pencil, comparing them with the suggestions in the synopsis, and then I will stop; after all, one can never really be finished.</p>
                <p><term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">Files</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9458">sickles</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9457">scythes</term> with mostly <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618554"/> riveted<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> handles are available from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> in great quantity, as well as steel samples of all kinds, of which, however, I noticed a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9510">cast bar</term> ("Ingot"), of which, as usual, the upper part was cold formed, but which also contained the bubbles (holes inside from gas that is not expelled or absorbed by means of additives), which they call "Piping", so common in English castings.</p>
                <p>	Also on display are <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">stamps</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">medals</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8756">engraved</term> in the usual way, but whose lower half contains either welded <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, or the whole cylinder or truncated <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">cone</term> in a ring of welded <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term>, proving how the English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, as a result of its lower resistance to contraction during extinguishing and cooling in water, in comparison with several types of cast steel from the continent, tends to crack during <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term>, as sadly demonstrated by the precious <term ref="gfa-keywords-8342">master stamp</term>, made in English steel, of our <term ref="gfa-keywords-9773">Swiss V-franc coins</term>, which had been so excellent in its intended conception and design.</p>
                <p>	The beauty of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-16"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8498">Berlin cast-iron wares</term></placeName>, which in my opinion are produced most exquisitely in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>, also evoked much enthusiasm here. This was magnified by the completed masterpiece of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8499"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavarian lion</placeName></term> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8642">bronze</term>, which enabled those who had not enjoyed the great pleasure of seeing the colossal <term ref="gfa-keywords-8500">statue of the Bavaria</term> <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618555"/> for themselves in the beauty of its form and the art of its casting, to imagine what a magnificent monument of taste and art <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7515">King Ludwig</persName> must have erected during his reign.</p>
                <p>	Returning to the subject of iron casting in <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName>, I note from my own experience that a small addition of English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term> to the cast iron gives it a similar disposition to take on the finest contours of the mould when cast, as does the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> from phosphoric <term ref="gfa-keywords-8483">marsh ore</term>, which, it is believed, is the preferred casting material in Berlin.</p>
                <p>	Because it is, to an extent, related to <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgy</term>, and inasmuch as these natural substances are used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-18">photography</term>, I mention a new improvement that has come about in that field, namely that the so-called negative paper (the paper which receives the first or reverse impression of the chemical light rays in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8913">camera</term> [the English never say camera obscura]) is now substituted by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">mat-ground</term> glass plates, which, as is never mentioned, however, must, of course, be covered with a similar coating that is receptive or sensitive to light rays, as the so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9348">energiatype</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9808">photographic paper</term>.</p>
                <p>	Also very interesting is a true <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver plating</term> of glass, instead of coating it with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8781">mercury</term> and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin foil</term>.</p>
                <p><pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618556"/>Between the narrow space of two glass plates, the edges of which are held apart by wax strips, a neutral silver solution is poured in, and a little <term ref="gfa-keywords-9578">glucose</term> is added, or even <term ref="gfa-keywords-8484">gun cotton</term> dissolved in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8786">alkali</term>, so that the shiny metallic silver is deposited on the glass plate. When the process is complete, the liquid part of the solution is poured off, the coating is rinsed with pure water, dried and protected against the effects of air by completely sealing it all around.</p>
                <p>	As an object of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metal</term>, I must also mention the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8501">great organ</term>, since I went to see it being played, which happened frequently. It is 38 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high, 26 feet wide and 23 feet deep and has 5000 pipes, of which the largest is 32 feet and the smallest not quite ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> long and has 80 keys. Incidentally, despite its size it does not occupy much space in these immense rooms. Even its sound, as powerful as it is, soon seems to fade away in the immense space.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's eighth visit, 2 July 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-07-02">July 2nd</date></placeName>. The object that occupied my attention today, after I had consulted Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-02" n="80"><persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName></placeName> earlier, also belongs to the field to which I devote myself out of preference and partly as my own profession, though I find that I go further than I intended, namely, the specimen of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc ore</term>, almost granite-like in appearance, weighing 164 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>, located near the eastern entrance of the transept or nave of the building, <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618557"/> if it can be so called, at the main entrance, which was found close to Earth's surface in "<placeName ref="gfa-places-1664">New-Yersey</placeName>" in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">United States of North America</placeName>.</p>
                <p>	In fact, if one were to add up the weight of all the objects inside and outside the building, and then the weight of the building in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, glass, and wood, it would seem as though the whole world could be balanced against it, and yet <date when="1849-05-01">two years ago on May 1st</date> there was not yet anything of the millions of Centner to which even our antipodians have contributed. Returning to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, as was to be expected, is first among the exhibitors from abroad, both in the number of its objects and their variety in iron, <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9457">scythes</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9458">sickles</term>, all manner of tools, as well as manufacturing, which is represented by the products of my son <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg</persName> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> and various <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> of cast steel, and then those of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-55">malleable Castiron</term>" and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindles</term> by my youngest son <persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold</persName>, whereby I must also mention the very fine products of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1906">Bohemian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9125">glassmaker's art</term>, in which, as with the metals, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">pyrotechnics</term> play a leading role, and before which I stood in amazement. Iron and steel productions, both unprocessed and processed, from my beloved fatherland of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> are insignificant. <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618558"/> However, of great importance are the other products, namely spun cotton, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8817">ribbons</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9452">silk fabrics</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9614">weaving</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9543">embroidery</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay products</term> of a higher quality ("terra cotta") by Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7516">Ziegler-Pellis</persName>, and then <term ref="gfa-keywords-9593">watchmaking</term>, wickerwork and woodcarving etc. Regrettably, nothing was to be found from the <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-1081">Escher Factory</orgName>, which could have claimed so much attention for its achievements and before whose output its rivals in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> would have had to bow. In vain, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electric</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9590">clock</term> in the centre of the transept admonished me to leave soon for home. Of its actual inner mechanism, I know nothing other than that its movement is caused by the alternating forces of <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">magnetic</term> attraction and repulsion and that it was, perhaps, inspired by the low-powered <term ref="gfa-keywords-8485">Zamboni pile</term>. This, too, is a powerful voice hailing the advances of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term>, in connection with <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9302">mechanics</term>, in our present age.</p>
                <p>	I also looked at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9257">copper ores</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1665">Burra-Burra</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-8">South Australia</placeName>, which yield up to 70 pCt.<note>Abbreviation for percent (%).</note> of pure <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, as well as those from <placeName ref="gfa-places-67">India</placeName>, around which countries England equally wraps its tentacles. Its wealth is immeasurable, and yet it has so many poor and miserable people there, not to speak of <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Irland</placeName>, where starvation has become a common occurrence. My every thought is of leaving and, yet, as if in some an enchanted castle, I cannot find my way out. <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618559"/> I also went to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire pump engine</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-76">Canada</placeName> — a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">device</term> of which I have made and repaired so many in my lifetime. Its effectiveness is said to be tremendous and hitherto unknown. Since I could not see its inner workings, nor was it indicated how many men were required to operate it*), it is impossible to calculate whether the information about its effectiveness is accurate. Incidentally, the principle remains forever true that a machine, by and large, only approximates the applied force, and beyond that nothing more can be contrived.  However, it is a different matter when the available force is properly distributed to serve different purposes in one and the same machine, whereby, among those actually in operation at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, I count as one of the most remarkable, one wherein raw <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">cotton</term> is passed from one location to another to be spun immediately, through the artful combination of working parts, into fine yarn. This yarn is threaded onto the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">weaving machine</term> ("powerloom") and, after being crossed in the "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8486">flying shuttle</term> (navette volante"), threaded and threaded again, comes out at the opposite end of the machine as a finished piece of cotton fabric.<note n="*" type="original" place="bottom">Since writing this, I have learned that 40 men are required for this. How all of them can use the moment of force to which they are exposed is beyond me.</note> 
                </p>
                <p><pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618560"/> I also looked for the second time at the great <term ref="gfa-keywords-9380">hydraulic press</term>, this beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8630">invention</term> of the master locksmith <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7517">Bramah</persName>, who lived at the time I was working in London in <ref type="cross" target="../1794"><date when="1794">1794</date></ref>. It was used to lift the pieces of enormous pipes, weighing 42,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> each and that formed the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2157">route</placeName> for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroad</term> between the mainland and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1881">Island of Anglesia</placeName>, up to the tower-like nearly 109-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term>-high stone edifice.
                </p>
            </div> 
            <div type="day">
                <head>London–Birmingham, 3 July 1851</head>
                <p><date when="1851-07-03" type="travelday">July 3rd</date>. At last, thank God! I have finally escaped the tedium of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, having sent Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="81"><persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName></placeName>, who yesterday gave me a coloured <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithographic drawing</term> of his <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1720">extraordinarily large steelworks in Sheffield</placeName></term>, a similar one of my modest <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">steel foundry</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-97">Mühlenthal</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, and left at 11 o'clock in the morning for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="82">Euston</placeName> station ("Terminus"), which is nearly four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my lodging</placeName>, to go from there by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rail</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="83">Birmingham</placeName>, which is 112 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> from London. At quarter past 12 o'clock, the train left. The second-class fare was 15 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> or 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> I appreciated the arrangement that one's suitcase and night bag, provided the former is not too large, are given to the passenger in his compartment and pushed under the bench, which has sufficient space for them. It relieves one of all worries in that regard: <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618561"/> for in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">England</placeName>, no numbers are attached to the items as in Germany, as nothing is weighed, nor any payment required. I arrived in Birmingham precisely at 5 o'clock, stopped at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="84">Stork Hotel</placeName>, which seems a very good <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>, and after lunch and reading the newspapers, took another tour through the streets. I first stood still at a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1739" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="85"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9204">caricature shop</term></placeName>, in front of a caricature that ruthlessly ridiculed the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9206">Catholic</term> Archbishop <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7518">Wisemann</persName> and Lord <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7519">Brougham</persName>, who had spoken somewhat in his favour in the House of Lords.</p>
                <p>The slightest step too far by <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7518">Wisemann</persName> would awaken as yet apparently sleeping British lions, whose claws have something to say. — I was astonished when I visited Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName>, whom I had known from before, at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2002">patent office</placeName> to bring him a greeting from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName> and was asked by his fellow clerk whether I and Mr. Kreeft were <term ref="gfa-keywords-9385">Protestants</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9206">Catholics</term>? Let it not be said that tolerance is generally at home in England, for my business had as little to do with any religious creed as with the man in the moon. It is curious how long political and religious partisanship can remain dormant and then be ignited again by the slightest spark. In that bookstore, there were also scores of <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618562" break="no"/> playing cards lying by the window in an unusually small format. Out of curiosity I enquired about the price, and it was "a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">halfpenny</term>" or 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. I purchased one to assure myself that I had heard correctly. Next door was a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1738" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="86">bookbinder's shop</placeName>, where charming <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Bibles</term> beautifully bound in black <term ref="gfa-keywords-9413">Saffian</term> with gilded edges were displayed in the window. I had no need to ask the price, there were slips of paper (as is often the case in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> with all kinds of merchandise, as they frown upon all manner of questions and answers) for "1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> and two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term>", or 42 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. These two things, playing cards and the Bible, indeed did not belong together, and anyone who knows me can well believe that I am not making light of this. However, I immediately acquired this beautiful edition, although it lacks what I found with surprise in older English Bibles among the apocryphal books and, in my opinion, precisely the best, namely the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8421">Book of Sirach</term>. More, neither <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7592"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7795"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8505">Lord Chesterfield's Letters to his Son</term></persName></persName>, nor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7610"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8487">Knigge's book on human intercourse</term></persName>, nor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7611"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8488">Kampe's Theophron</term></persName> are part of this excellent work, neither in deep knowledge of human nature, nor in practical wisdom, nor in high piety, while <term ref="gfa-keywords-8489">the Book of Solomon</term> — in England, "Song" — has found acceptance and been forced by the theologians into a dialogue between Christ and the Church. <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618563"/> I once conversed with an unmarried Englishwoman, who was a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9365">Pietist</term>, on this subject, and she too was very much enamoured of the Song of Solomon, but could say nothing about the Book of Sirach, of which she had never heard. Since that time, I have asked myself more than once whether the first publisher of the Bible in the English language might well have had a wicked wife to whom, by including this work among the apocrypha, he would have held up a mirror with a rather unflattering reflection.</p>
                <p>	A mere three paces from the bookbinder's shop was an ironmonger, or rather, half and half, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1737" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="87"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9102">quincaillerie</term></placeName>, and at the window <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">medals</term> of lovely white metal, bearing a likeness of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Crystal Palace</placeName>. What does such a medal cost (in size of a standard florin), I asked the gentleman in the store, and behold, the price, which was scarcely to be believed, was 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> or "a half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term>". I took several of them. There were also artificial <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">magnets</term> hanging from the window. I purchased one of not insignificant strength, five <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long, including the anchor, and what did I pay for it? Answer: 18 Kreuzer ("six pence"). It is very nicely made, and what is very understandable, covered down to the anchor with reddish <term ref="gfa-keywords-8490">varnish</term>. Only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> is it possible to buy such metal wares for so ridiculous a price.</p>
                <p>I stayed with this very knowledgeable man, <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618564"/> whose shop is well visited, until it grew dark and told him, as I took my leave, that I would return the following day.	</p>  
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Birmingham, 4 July 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-20"><date when="1851-07-04">July 4th</date></placeName>. As I had promised, I returned <placeName ref="gfa-places-1737" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="88">to him</placeName> first thing next day and brought him a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8522"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">sample of my copper-iron compound</term></term>. He was very surprised by its red colour and by the fact that the metal mixture was so readily attracted by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">magnet</term> and, walking ahead of me, beckoned me to follow. After climbing a long, narrow staircase, we came to two of his storerooms, which were neatly arranged, and then he led me to an attic ("Garret"), where he showed me something that I had really never seen before. Namely, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">rollers</term> 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> long and positioned one above the other, at one end of which there was a crank, and at the axles near the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8957">pivot bearings</term> there were two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur gears</term> of equal size, which interlocked with each other, and then a third parallel roller, which, however, could be positioned higher or lower than one or the other axis of the rollers positioned one on top of the other by adjusting screws, as well as closer or further away from them. When a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">sheet</term> of metal was placed between the first pair of rollers, it was pressed against the third roller by rotating the two rollers and rounded in this ratio to form an almost confluent cylinder once the sheet <pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618565"/> had passed through its entire length, so that if it was made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8638">tinplate</term>, it only needed to be overlapped and soldered together by hand, and if it was made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">iron</term>, it needed only to be crimped. The cylinders were perfectly round and smooth and made with an immense saving of time. After some further conversation, all at once, he put on his black frock coat and said that I should accompany him to one of his friends, who had <term ref="gfa-keywords-9328">coin presses</term> and drop presses and would be delighted to converse with me about stamping. So, we did, and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7522" type="met">Ralph Heaton</persName>, after we had discussed his manufacture, complained terribly about the coin punch he must use, adding that he could not get any steel in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> that was suitable for it and, thus, had to have it sent from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. He showed me pieces that were partly cracked during <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term> and partly with holes and unevenly hardened spots that appeared when they were milled. After inspecting them, I asked if he was minting currency; he led me down a flight of stairs into a kind of cellar, where, in a very narrow space beneath two large presses, each attended by a young boy, money was being minted at great speed by the six-horsepower, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high-pressure steam engine</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587">just as</term> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7523">Watt</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName> had set it up at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636">mint</placeName> in London. I thought at first they were <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">medallions</term>, only he said: No, it is money. I am minting for the <placeName ref="gfa-places-206">Republic of Chilé</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-145">South America</placeName>. And no one <pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618566"/> has stood in his way. It is really very pretty <term ref="gfa-keywords-9258">copper money</term>, having a diameter of <formula rend="inline" notation="tex">\frac{13}{16}</formula> English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>, and an apparent thickness of not quite <formula rend="inline" notation="text">\frac{1}{12}</formula> inch, I say apparent because the rim protrudes on both sides. — It is valued at exactly "½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Penny</term>" of English currency, which is 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of Reichsgeld. As soon as I have the opportunity, I will investigate how many of our oh so delightful Swiss <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">cents</placeName> go into such a coin, about which, regarding <term ref="gfa-keywords-9035">forgery</term>, was warned in vain by those who have acquired some knowledge and experience in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> field, contrary to the conceit of those who believe that with tales and hollow phrases everything is remedied, not to mention the fact that we still sent the money abroad to be manufactured, while our own <term ref="gfa-keywords-9329">mints</term> in Switzerland, indeed, I argue those in <placeName ref="gfa-places-17">Bern</placeName> alone, would have sufficed to meet the demand. For it must be known that each of these two presses supplied 30,000, I repeat, thirty thousand pieces per day.</p>
                <p>This really beautiful money had, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9843">as the figure shows</term>, on its obverse a pentagonal <pb n="80" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618567"/> star and the inscription: <emph rend="italic"><placeName ref="gfa-places-206">Republica de Chilé</placeName></emph>, <emph rend="italic"><date>1851</date></emph>, and on its reverse a laurel wreath, in the middle of which are the words: <emph rend="italic">un Centavo</emph>, and outside the wreath the motto: <emph rend="italic">Economia Es Riqueza</emph>. Not only did this man, whom I had never seen before in my life, show me all of his equipment, including 4 drop presses, under which one presses the beautiful thin <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term> objects, which are then covered with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9137">gold varnish</term>, but he also entrusted me with six pieces of this newly minted money. He hardened all of his coins, as he showed me, under running water, as is necessary for hard steel. He explained that if he were to immerse them at once in water, they would all crack. — As I departed from him, I thought to myself, "There is not a corner of the earth that does not avail itself of the craftsmanship and artistry of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName>. Chilé sends its precious metals to England, and they send <term ref="gfa-keywords-9258">copper money</term> in return." — I lunched with one of the <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7524">Weiss brothers</persName>, to whom I had been referred by my friend Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7525">Escher</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zurich</placeName>, in an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">establishment</term> where there is a table d'hôte of about 20 customers a day.</p>
                <p>— I expressed a wish to visit the once famous <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>, where in <date from="1814-01-01" to="1814-12-31">1814</date> Mr. Walt<note>The person meant is probably Mr. Watt, i.e. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">James Watt the Younger</persName>.</note>, then owner of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1694"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1723"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">this factory</orgName></placeName></placeName>, had shown me so much friendship. I thus arranged for a "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">Cab</term>", and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7524" type="met">Weiss</persName> was good enough to accompany me. He informed me at the outset <pb n="81" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618568"/> that this great machine factory had fallen into decline since the death of Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> and his associate, Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7573">Boulton</persName>, whom I also knew very well. When we arrived, there was not a soul on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1694" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="91">premises</placeName>. Everything in the numerous workshops was empty and desolate. Much of it was in a state of decay. What a difference! to when I first saw this establishment at the height of its splendour and the owners enjoyed such income as not even every prince has. I could never have imagined such a rapid transformation had I not seen it with my own eyes. This place, more than many others, would be worthy of the inscription "Sic transit gloria mundi"<note>Latin for "Thus passes the glory of the world."</note>.</p>
                <p>	Having returned from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName> and taken leave of my two compatriots (Messrs. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7524">Weiss</persName> are from <placeName ref="gfa-places-181">Winterthur</placeName>), I purchased a very good spring balance with which one can weigh up to 45 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pf.</term>, for 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> or 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term> and then proceeded to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="92">my lodging</placeName> to record the events of this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Birmingham–Manchester, 5 July 1851</head>
                <p>	Saturday, <date when="1851-07-05" type="travelday">July 5th</date>. At 10 o'clock, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-471" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="93">Manchester</placeName>. The journey should have been completed in 3½ hours for the 80 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, however, for unknown reasons the "Train" stopped at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1667">Stockport</placeName> for an entire hour and then at another place for half an hour, so that we did not arrive in Manchester until after 3 o'clock.</p>
                <p>How this place has grown in size since I was here in <date when="1827">1827</date>, one can scarcely imagine <pb n="82" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618569"/> without seeing it. Miles of straight and wide streets now define this enterprising city, which owes its present size and prosperity to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8517">invention</term> of a humble barber, <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7535">Arkwright</persName>, who first conceived the idea of spinning <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">cotton</term> by <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">machinery</term>, and the execution of which idea was undertaken by his brother-in-law, a carpenter, with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metal</term> parts made by <term ref="gfa-keywords-9117">founders</term> and locksmiths. The first cylinders were made only of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term>, and for each thread there was a single piece about one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> long. We were still making such things when I worked for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName>, a mechanic in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, in <ref type="cross" target="../1794"><date when="1794">1794</date></ref>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> he obtained for his invention, which was immediately seized upon by the practical spirit of the English, he sold, as Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> told me <date when="1813">some 38 years ago</date>, for such large sums that he obtained an annual income of 10,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term>, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 120,000.</p>
                <p>	Like <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName>, too, is enveloped in a perpetual cloud of smoke. The only difference being that, in the former, only tall chimneys protrude from it, emitting flames from time to time, while in the latter, one also occasionally sees the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term>, 6 to 7 stories high, with their infinite number of windows. These are otherwise quite rare in English private homes, so that in many of their myrmidonian dwellings, per floor, of which there are rarely three, only one mullioned, <pb n="83" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618570" break="no"/> "Sashwindow" of three feet in width is to be seen. One might ask, then, how does light enter these structures? However, the English are no fools and, like <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7459">Paxton</persName> in his <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">glass palace</placeName>, let the light in at the top of the roof, a feature that I believe is not missing from virtually any house. In general, the English architectural style, in this respect, is strange and tasteless. Compare such a house, which looks like a large, partly red and partly black-brown <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">brick</term>, with our friendly farmhouses in various cantons of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, and especially in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-79">canton of Zurich</placeName>, and make your own judgment.</p>
                <p>	After a short lunch, I decided to visit my old acquaintance, Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-6319">Fairbairn</persName>, who has <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7612">a large enterprise</orgName> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboats</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>, but I did not encounter him at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1718" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="94">factory</placeName>. I proceeded to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2080" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="95">his residence</placeName> nearly three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from there, to which a very wide new road led. Here, the, I would like to say ridiculous, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9407">Rococo</term> taste, which has displaced all noble forms and turned everything that exists in this style to eternal dust and cobweb traps, is now visible on the gables of a long row of houses, which are turned at a very acute angle to the street, as now and then in the old imperial cities, and are elaborated with all <pb n="84" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618571" break="no"/> manner of flourishes on the overhanging beams and bows or struts.</p>
                <p>	Many people often do not know what they want, either out of wantonness or laziness. While the French talk too much, the English talk too little, and that is often the source of their eccentric thoughts. Still, in the end, I would rather stick with the English than with vacuous palaver and whimsy.</p>
                <p>	I did not meet Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-6319">Fairbairn</persName> himself, who is presently at a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8497">scientific convention</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1732">Ipswich</placeName> and will return to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> on Tuesday. His son<note>Fairbairn had four sons: Thomas, George, Peter and John. Fischer probably means <persName ref="gfa-actors-7594">Thomas Fairbairn (1823–1891)</persName>, who was <persName ref="gfa-actors-6319">his father's</persName> partner for many years.</note>, with whom I had a very pleasant conversation, gave me his address, so that on my return from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> I may well have the pleasure of seeing my old friend there, whose name is well known throughout England.</p>
                <p>	I must add with regard to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> how immensely well satisfied I was there at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705">Stork Hotel</placeName>. Everything, without exception, was better and nicer than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my lodging</placeName> in London, and at least a third less expensive. In the English countryside, one is delightfully comfortable, but not so in London.</p>               
                </div> 
            <div type="day">
                <head>Manchester–Sheffield, 6 July 1851</head>
                <p>	Sunday, <placeName ref="gfa-places-471"><date when="1851-07-06">July 6th</date></placeName>. After breakfast (half past nine) I went through and arranged my papers, wrote instructions for two of my sons<note>He is referring to <persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">Wilhelm Fischer (1803—1882)</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer (1804—1888)</persName>.</note> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, who also intend to visit <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and packed my things, as the "<term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Train</term>" to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-06" n="96">Sheffield</placeName> was leaving at 3 o'clock, <pb n="85" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618572"/> and I wanted to have lunch beforehand. The journey in second class, which cost 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Sh.</term> and 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, or 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> of our money, for the 40 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, was tedious owing to frequent stops, but interesting on account of the astonishingly varied, hilly country, similar to that around <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Liège</placeName>, where, after passing through a long and densely dark tunnel, one suddenly rolls along over a viaduct (railroad track constructed on piers and arches), which is often at first much higher than the houses standing adjacent to it. A journey with such variety in the construction of <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroads</term> might appear quite enticing to us Swiss, as in our beloved <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">fatherland</placeName> we have plenty of physical-geographical (as well as political) ups and downs. But heaven forbid that we should take on, at least for the time being, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-598">a project for a new railway system</orgName> at the expense of the state: it would bring us ten times the duplicitous blessing of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9773">new coin</term>. — One must have travelled many hundreds of miles, on railways in various countries, to obtain a reasonably clear understanding of the advantages and disadvantages. We are not a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9093">monarchical</term> state. Due to their size in commercial terms, and then due to their neighbours, and as recent times have shown, due to potential domestic political events, monarchical states are compelled to do so. <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, least of all, is to be <pb n="86" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618573"/> taken as a model and pretext for the construction of railways, for even in this country, so rich in industry and population and better equipped than any other in Europe with the means to build them cheaply, some railways have been built that did not bring the kind of return believed possible, though they are otherwise quite reliable here in their calculations. One truth is certain: first of all, that for most of our planned railways there is no absolute necessity, and the temporary delay will and can cause far less damage than haste, of which one has already received clear indications in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> and elsewhere in all manner of cases, especially in political relations. Secondly, one more truth is certain: that with the immense progress of our age, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9302">mechanics</term>, as well as in the technology elevated and supported by these sciences, it is not only probable, but one may say certain, that also the means of transportation, in one way or another, perhaps within a very short time, will be greatly advanced. When battle was fought with bow and arrow as long-range <term ref="gfa-keywords-3945">weapons</term>, no one had the faintest idea of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">battery</term> of twenty-four-pounders and their effect. Once, in our country and elsewhere, innocent witches were burned to death for flying for their own amusement on their broomsticks through the air to <pb n="87" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618574" break="no"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1688">Bloksberg</placeName> on Walpurgis night and, now, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9791">aeronauts</term> soar, unmolested, over land and sea. Not to speak of the speediness of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> and the lightning speed of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">electric telegraph</term>. If someone, inspired by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7552">Athena's</persName> spirit, had foretold at the time these phenomena in their present manifestation, he would have been sent to heaven knows where! But enough of this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer's business visits in Sheffield, 7 July 1851</head>
                <p><date when="1851-07-07" type="travelday">July 7th</date>. This morning my first outing in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> was to Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7536"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1719" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="97">Rodgers and Sons</placeName></orgName>, the most illustrious manufacturers of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlery</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plated</term> goods, not only in this city but, one may say, in all of England, and brought them some <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteor steel</term> I had invented to obtain their opinion of its quality, with the request that I should be able to pick them up again tomorrow, which they promised me. Leaving there, I paid a visit to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1720" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="98">cast steel factory of Mr. Johnson, Cammel and Comp</placeName></orgName>, in which, according to Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName>, 1000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term> are produced weekly, as already mentioned, which is perfectly comprehensible when one sees the extent of the workshops, which are now being increased by a large new building, and when one considers the immense number of locomotive, "Train" and other types of carriage springs, which, as Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName> <pb n="88" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618575"/> informed me, are ordered from them by the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroad companies</term> on a regular basis. In general, they seek their advantage in the quantity of production, which, with their product, is possible by selling, as I have been told, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> of such <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467">spring steel</term> for 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, or 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. They re-acquire the old or otherwise broken <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">springs</term> for a much lower price, making partly cast steel and partly new springs out of it. With such a substantial reduction in the price of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, which is close to 30 pCt.<note>Abbreviation for percent (%).</note> compared to what it was 4 years ago when I was in England and visited their factory, and since the cost of fuel in their highly efficient <term ref="gfa-keywords-8557">bloomeries</term> is so low, it is possible to achieve such a low price.</p>
                <p>	However, it seems to me that they do not do as high-quality work as <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7542">Turton &amp; Sons</orgName>, who also make <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">blister steel</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8508">welded steel</term>, and from the latter, springs. Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName><note>It is not clear whether Thomas or Henry Johnson is meant.</note> had a new spring tested in my presence, which, however, broke long before it had reached its maximum extension through straight compression. In general, since the three gentlemen who make up this company, the third being a German, Gosse, brother-in-law of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName>, spend more time in the office than in the workshops and, therefore, require a "Foreman" for each of their industrial fields, the quality of <pb n="89" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618576" break="no"/> such a foreman is astonishingly decisive. Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName> sent for the smelter, and so we went into one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-88">smelting houses</term>, where 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">furnaces</term> were in continual operation in this one alone and casting took place at all times, since each furnace smelts three times a day. Here, too, as has happened elsewhere, I was asked first by Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName> and then by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting foreman</term>, in particular, how the piping (that is, the gas formation when the steel is poured, and the gas, which remains, adheres, or develops only in the moment of pouring, creates holes of various sizes inside the <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, while no trace of it is noticeable from the outside on the poured bar or the poured object in general) is prevented, whereupon I found it appropriate to simply tell him that "this depends on the conduct of the melting process." He also asked me a question, which appeared to be very simple, but which made me realise at once that he merely sought to determine through this manoeuvre the extent of my experience ("pump me out"). I had no desire for this type of catechism, however, and soon afterward took my leave of these gentlemen, as it was time for lunch.</p>
                <p>	In the afternoon, I went first to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="99">Huntsman's hammer mill</placeName>, where I was well known to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">hammer smiths</term> through Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsmann</persName> himself, and again inspected the facilities <pb n="90" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618577"/> there for heating furnaces and welding ovens. The smaller furnace is heated with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>, the larger one with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coal</term>, and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9731">bellow</term> is used. These fires are far superior to our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">charcoal-fired</term> forges. Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName> himself was, again, unfortunately out of town, and so I continued on from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">Don River</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1677" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="100">West Street</placeName> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-121"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2096" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="101">steel foundry</placeName></orgName></term> of my old friend Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Charles Sanderson</persName>, where I was sorry to hear that he was suffering from podagric<note>Podagra, gout in the foot, especially the big toe.</note> and chiragric<note>Chiragra, gout in the joints of the hands and fingers.</note> pains, as was the case four years ago, but that he was not bedridden. I now had to contend with a walk almost a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">mile</term> to his home, which did not prevent me from visiting him. He received me with great kindness into <placeName ref="gfa-places-2158" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="102">his home</placeName>, where his <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7588">wife</persName> promptly invited me to stay for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, which I accepted with great pleasure, being parched with thirst and feeling unwell myself. Our general conversation, as she is a very intelligent and agreeable woman, revolved for a long while around the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>. It is, at present, the favourite subject of the English, forming the morning and evening entertainment with visitors from abroad, and, indeed, one can hardly blame them for this miracle, which so suddenly unfolded before the inhabitants of our globe.</p>
                <p>	Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Sanderson</persName> afforded me great pleasure by promising, since he has considerable experience in this field, to provide me, as soon as his hand <pb n="91" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618578"/> is usable again, with an accurate report, which I have long awaited, on the minimum of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> required to make from our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8851">bean ores</term>, which he as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-289">mineralogist</term> knows very well, the grey, carbonised <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">pig iron</term> suitable for <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">cupola furnaces</term>, and to enclose a drawing by his own hand for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term> in such small dimensions as the nature of the matter allows. </p>
                <p>We also spoke of a blast furnace, a model of which is at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, that is closed at the top by a valve opened only for filling the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">throat</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-2570">coal</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9027">ores</term>, etc., and then immediately closed again, where the flame and gases are directed sideways through closed tubes for use in other purposes. This furnace has three <term ref="gfa-keywords-9715">nozzles</term>, like <term ref="gfa-keywords-8491">Wilkinson's furnaces</term>, which is certainly the best that can be had. Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Sanderson</persName>, however, had not yet seen it, owing to his indisposition. I also made mention of another far larger model of a blast furnace at the exhibition, with six nozzles, which is probably too many, as it weakens the lining and mantle excessively. More than 50 years ago, <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7541">von Reden</persName>, Minister of Mines, built such a blast furnace in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1962">Harz</placeName> region, with six nozzles, which offered no greater advantage than is obtained with three.</p>
                <p>After conversing for nearly two hours, I departed from this family, which has always shown me great friendship, with the wish that they would also visit me soon in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, <pb n="92" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618579"/> and I ended this long day by writing in my diary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Further business visits in Sheffield, 8 July 1851</head>
                <p>	On <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265"><date when="1851-07-08" type="travelday">July 8th</date></placeName>, I visited the cast steel manufacturers, Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1721">Turton and Sons</placeName></orgName>, with whom I am also on friendly terms, and who, in addition to a very large volume of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term>, also produce a lot of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">springs</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroad cars</term>. The demand for this product is unbelievable! Their springs appeared to me better than <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537">Cammel's</orgName>. These gentlemen do their own work, and the specimens I was shown stood up perfectly to rigorous testing. As the saying goes, "It's the eye of the master that fattens the horse".</p>
                <p>	Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7543">Turton</persName> was not at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1721"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1714" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-08" n="103">Bow Spring</placeName></placeName>, but at the place where they have their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mills</term> and hammers, at what is called the Sheaf works, not far from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">Don River</placeName>, which powers the <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName>'s <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mill</term></placeName>. I never expected to discover such an extensive mill. The number of workshops, including grinders, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mills</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file smithies</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9632">tool smiths</term>, etc., amounts to 73, according to the numbers written on the doors. Several of the offices are staffed by officials.</p>
                <p>	Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7543">Turton</persName> was preparing to leave for London to visit his brother, who was very ill, and, as he passed by, told the "Porter", and no proper factory in England is without one, allow this gentleman, pointing to me, to come and visit <pb n="93" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618580" break="no"/> all the workshops as he pleases. He accompanied me to <placeName type="itinerar" when="1851-07-08" n="105">my lodging</placeName>, where I proceeded to lunch and he to the "Terminus" (train station) for his journey to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. In the afternoon I availed myself of his permission by first visiting the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">hammer mill</term>. The stroke of the hammers is short but very fast, which makes sense, as the heat from the stroke always keeps the steel hot longer under a fast hammer blow than under a slow one, where the hammer is heavier and the stroke longer. Hammers and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8658">anvils</term> are fitted with inserted “crosses” or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9821">hammer faces</term> of "chilld" <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term>. Their drawing furnace did not seem to me as good as <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687">Huntsmann's</placeName>, inasmuch as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> they burned did not reach the same high degree of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9191">ignition</term> as there. I had hoped to go to the "<placeName ref="gfa-places-1680">Potterworks</placeName>", after having made another tour of the rolling mill, but being too tired and the hour too late for such a long walk, I contented myself with writing my notes on the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–Dover, 9 July 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-1265"><date when="1851-07-09">July 9th</date></placeName>. Having finished my business, which could not have induced me to stay longer in any case due to my malaise, I went this morning to the cutlery and plated goods manufacturers <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7536"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1719" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="106">Rodgers &amp; Sons</placeName></orgName> to retrieve my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term>. They provided material for an interesting conversation with one of these gentlemen about the nature of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> in itself, as well as the <pb n="94" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618581" break="no"/> components of <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, and I valued the fact that we both agreed in the opinion that iron is actually only good if it is pure and that every purified iron can thank the manifold (in my experience, fourfold) substances, which are combined with it in flow or in strong and long-lasting <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealing</term>, for its becoming steel. He spoke very favourably about my razor blades and about the natural <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus</term>, the result of the displacement of the crystals<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> in the flow of the molten steel. Time was running short. At 10 o'clock I was due at the train station, from where, after covering 165 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="107">London</placeName> at 3 o'clock in the afternoon. Once there, I called on Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="108"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName></placeName> to discuss various matters with him. In the meantime, I was visited by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544" type="met">Baird</persName>, who had returned from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, where he had assembled the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9429">ship</term> delivered by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7480">Robinson</persName>, and in the evening at 6 o'clock I left for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="109">Dover</placeName>, where I arrived after 9 o'clock, and left at 11 o'clock that night on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">postal steamer</term> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">Ostend</placeName>. If I compared the crossing from Ostend to Dover to a kind of hospice, then by morning I could have described the salon as a battlefield, for the weather was extremely stormy and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasickness</term> had broken out among all the passengers, with the exception of one, who had likely completed long voyages at sea before. <pb n="95" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618582" break="no"/> Immediately on departure from Dover it was so crowded that, foreseeing what was to come, I went onto the deck, despite the storm and rain, borrowed an old blue jacket from a crewman for 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, putting it on over my great coat and taking an old piece of sailcloth as a cover and a piece of rope rolled up in a coil as my pillow, and so in the vicinity of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> on the bare deck took up my bed for the night, which was admittedly not a pleasant stay in the kind of weather I described, but which prevented me from contracting seasickness.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Ostend–Mannheim, 10-11 July 1851</head>
                <p><date when="1851-07-10" type="travelday">July 10th</date>. As the day dawned, we saw the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1681">church tower</placeName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-10" n="110">Ostend</placeName> on the horizon, and I hoped that we would arrive there at 8 o'clock in the morning, according to the printed ticket, to leave as promised with the train to <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cologne</placeName> that was waiting for us, and therefore went down to the salon to fetch my overnight bag and umbrella, which I had left there, onto the deck. Oh, but what a spectacle! Passengers lying around on the floor and benches, afflicted with this disgusting <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">disease</term> and exhausted, overturned candlesticks on the tables from the swaying of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">ship</term>, broken bowls on the floor, soiled clothes, etc. As I said, everything was crowded, and I had to step on the feet of several people to fetch my belongings. <pb n="96" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618583" break="no"/> They drew back only mechanically, without saying a word. The ship was not able to enter Ostend until 10 o'clock in the morning, and so, instead of only four hours in the favourable case, we had needed eleven. I would never again recommend this crossing to anyone going to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> or traveling from there to the mainland. Anyone wishing to travel to England should take the route, with <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cologne</placeName> as the end point of a journey along the Rhine, via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Liège</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName>, and when coming from England, if he does not prefer to travel via <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-470">Strassburg</placeName>, from Calais back to Liège and Cologne. The morning train to Cologne did not wait for our ship, and so I could not leave <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">Ostend</placeName> until 1 o'clock that afternoon, and then took a night train from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-10" n="111">Aachen</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-82" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-11" n="112">Cologne</placeName>, where I arrived early in the morning of <date when="1851-07-11" type="travelday">July 11th</date> and immediately continued my journey by rail to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-11" n="113">Mannheim</placeName>, where I spent the night.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Mannheim–Freiburg–Schaffhausen, 12–14 July 1851</head>
                <p>On <date when="1851-07-12" type="travelday">July 12th</date>, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1123" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="114">Karlsruhe</placeName> around noon, visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547" type="met">Kessler</persName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1722" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="115"><term ref="gfa-keywords-74">machine factory</term></placeName>, and Currency Councillor Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7453">Kachel</persName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1682" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="116">mint</placeName>, and took some orders. In the afternoon at 3 o'clock I left Karlsruhe again and was now able to spend another night in bed in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="117">Freiburg</placeName>, as I had no bed for four nights in a row and was forced to spend one night in the open air and in bad weather.</p>
                <p>On the <date when="1851-07-13" type="travelday">13th</date> in the evening at 9 o'clock I departed from <pb n="97" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618584"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122">Freiburg</placeName>, and on the <date when="1851-07-14" type="travelday">14th</date> in the morning at 10 o'clock, in spite of the hardships that this journey entailed, I arrived <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237"><placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-14" n="118">home</placeName></persName> again, thank God, healthy and happy.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
                <head>Afterword: Thoughts on free trade</head>
                <p>Postscript to my travel diaries.</p>
                <p>	If anyone other than my <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">family</persName> and friends should get hold of this little volume and then ask why its publication, interest in whose contents may have been harmed by delay, has only now taken place, then let me answer very briefly that due to various official and personal business, it was only in <date when="1852-11">November of this year</date> that I was able to complete the copy of the original, which was written mostly in pencil. I would add that, because I wrote it for myself alone, I regard it merely as a picture of that period of my life and, yet, for that very reason, as can be the case with historical paintings on canvas, believe that one or another picture may retain some interest, for as long as the work takes to be published. — And now, in conclusion, the following remarks: while lunching in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, as the inn where I stayed has introduced a kind of table d'hôte on weekly market days, the principal conversation with my fellow lodgers revolved around <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">free trade</term> which was to be instituted and which was embraced by all with whom I spoke, <pb n="98" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618585" break="no"/> without exception. Reflecting on their arguments, and those I heard more particularly from various manufacturers, it became clear to me that only their own interest, they being by far the largest majority, made such a measure urgently desirable, a fact of which I became even more convinced when I considered their enormous factories and their profitability, and came to a conclusion as to the effect this freedom of trade, given such a superiority in technical and pecuniary means and the cheapness of their operating forces, would have, first, on <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">my fatherland</placeName> and then on other nations on the continent, as well.</p>
                <p>	On my way back, I pursued the matter even further. Only some time later, prompted by a newspaper article arguing to the contrary, I committed my views to paper and handed them over to the press<note>The article appeared in two parts in the Tage-Blatt für den Kanton Schaffhausen, nos. 88 and 89, on 15 and 16 April 1852.</note>. I now add them to these notes as well, as they pertain to my interesting<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> remarks in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, of which I made only fleeting and vague references on some of its pages.</p>
                <p>For if one wishes to form an opinion on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">free trade</term>, one must first consider what the duty of self-preservation demands of us, which is of greater importance and more closely related to us than all the spurious theories of freedom, equality and unanimity (the latter term was invented, for <pb n="99" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618586"/> one had to be embarrassed to speak of Swiss harmony), which are so hackneyed that not a grain more can be extracted from them, and after ascertaining the duties towards oneself, one has only to ask quite simply, what is free trade and what does it entail? The answer is, that every person may take the results of his labour, or of his commerce or trade, and sell them wherever he pleases, without being bound by any restriction favouring the labourers or merchants in the country where he takes his goods. Before the consequences of this freedom can be discussed, the question must be posed, Are the peoples of all nations where free trade is to be introduced on the same level of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> as a result of the natural products in their soil at the surface and in the depths of their earth? Or has nature, or have the social conditions and culture of mind based thereon, or to be more precise, the technical skill, created no difference? The answer, which arises from the existing and irrefutable facts, is no!</p>
                <p>If then two nations, or, to bring the matter back to the simplest point, two manufacturers produce the same thing, but the one, through greater skill, supported by local advantages, can produce the needed objects, that is, all goods, in the same quality and, in most cases, even better than the other, <pb n="100" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618587"/> yet at a cheaper price, then one must know nothing of reality to believe that the consumers will not, in all cases, buy from the first and take no notice of the other, whereupon the latter gradually falls into ruin. Whether because he cannot contend with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-161">competition</term> as things stand and must therefore cease to produce, or whether, out of a sense of honour or obstinacy, he nevertheless continues in his occupation, he will just as surely become impoverished. However, one must not believe that this ruin affects him alone, no! In many thousand corollaries of human intercourse and sources of the circulation of money, which, despite our efforts of understanding remain as inscrutable as the thoughts of men, another vein is thereby cut off or clogged, which then, in turn, deprives others of their sustenance, at least in part, and it happens just as when one throws a stone into water, the rings continue to become apparently weaker but obtain greater circumference.</p>
                <p>	The principal question, however, is that which while relevant to the whole world, is to be considered here only specifically in relation to <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">our fatherland</placeName>. What reasons can <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> have to speak out in favour of the free trade system and to set in motion all levers, known and unknown, i.e., those of the press and the influences on individuals it has long successfully used to win others over to its interest, in order to achieve its objective? <pb n="101" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618588"/> The answer is simple, its interest and its interest alone — and one is very much mistaken to believe that, even if there are a few individuals of this nation who are distinguished by true liberality and magnanimity, there is not an equally developed and rigid egotism guiding its <term ref="gfa-keywords-9169">commercial policy</term>, as with any other nation. History provides enough evidence of this, if the <placeName ref="gfa-places-191"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9774">sulphur trade with Naples</term></placeName> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9347">opium dispute</term> with <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">China</placeName> are not proof enough.</p>
                <p>	Anyone looking through his own eyes, and not through the glasses of the theoretician from some attic window onto the continent, at this great work of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">world exhibition of industry</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, which was almost beyond human strength to accomplish in the short period of time in which it was carried out, must admit, by all means, that the English manufacturers in general were allowed to measure themselves against any other similar products, and that anyone who was induced to purchase one thing and another, particularly in the factory towns, was able to see for himself that the English, with the exception of those products which nature denies to their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9216">climate</term> and with the exception of very few objects insignificant as articles of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4336">world trade</term>, produce everything satisfactorily and, generally, in even greater perfection than what could be imported from other countries. <pb n="102" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618589"/> This, in addition to the fact that the prejudice in favour of their own products, which generally prevails among them and is not entirely unfounded, makes them averse to the purchase of foreign products, if not for very special circumstances, such as uncommonly low prices, resulting from the cheapness of the raw materials at the site of the foreign producers, or unattainable perfection, where nature, especially in the case of dyed materials, as a result of the nature of the water or the atmosphere, favours other countries, cause the English to purchase these objects, which are quite insignificant in relation to their export.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="postscript">
                    <head>The importance of free trade for England</head>
                    <p>	If we now further consider that the <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> produce in their country, by contrast, not only everything that human art and human genius can accomplish, so to speak, but that they, favoured by the spirit of perseverance, diligence and industriousness that pervades this nation, and by virtue of their vast experience, or, if you will, by virtue of their abundance of skilful people, of the great capital at their disposal and the tremendous driving force that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> from the bosom of the earth enables them, produce in a given period of time a quantity sufficient for half the world, under which, in spite of all the advantages listed here, they would soon suffocate in no time, if they did not have an outlet to the outside world. Thus, it is clear to see why they so urgently desire <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">freedom of trade</term> and do not want to restrict <pb n="103" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618590"/> the import of their products with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9444">tariffs</term> of any kind. — Should the tariffs remain, they would no longer be able to eradicate the factories of the continent, which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">decree</term> of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon</persName>, whose genius so correctly recognised the true cause of the difference in the industrial conditions of the continent in comparison with <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, had brought about, or if not eradicate at least paralyse them in such a way that their commercial and industrial egotism would continue to enjoy the fruits of its meditations at the expense of the gradually impoverished and exhausted nations. — What England already so severely oppresses, albeit in part still secretly, are her <term ref="gfa-keywords-9443">workers' associations</term>. One need only have been in the factory towns of England and visited this class of society in its low, dark dwellings, and then compare the enormous disparity which the luxury of a comparatively small part of the nation displays to the eye, to arrive at the conclusion that there is nothing in the world which does not have its cause, and that the above phenomena, which may possibly become more glaring in time, or at any rate may continue for some time, are only the burgeoning effects of deep-seated and long-standing causes.</p>
                    <p>	As a result of the aforementioned means employed by it, England produces, in a word, excessively. If it cannot generate profit in this or that way at the expense of other nations, the immediate consequence will be that precisely a part of its poorest inhabitants, <pb n="104" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618591" break="no"/> that is, the factory workers, will be forced to sit on their hands and thus become a burden to the country. Until then, so it seems, the governments of the continent are still very much on their guard to accept the friendly invitation of the English for free trade as quickly and willingly as the latter would like, given the state of affairs. What <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> will do remains to be seen. What we should do, however, can soon be decided upon quiet and uninterested examination. In conclusion, for those who are so fond of giving their money to strangers, I leave the following remarks made to me by the late <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7549">King Frederick of Würtemberg</persName>, so full of wit and profoundly aware of the duties of a regent, when in the <date from="1814-06-01" to="1814-08-07">summer of 1814</date>, during my stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-143">Stuttgart</placeName>, I was summoned to his <placeName ref="gfa-places-1683">pleasure palace "Mon Repos"</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1180">Ludwigsburg</placeName>, in a conversation lasting two hours on various subjects concerning the production and consumption of various articles in my own country, or their procurement more cheaply from abroad. He said (verbatim, I immediately wrote it down in my diary) speaking in reference to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">rifles</term>: "I am taxed for making rifles for my military in my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1684">factory</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1685">Oberndorf</placeName>, each piece of which costs me 6 new <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">Thaler</term>, while I could get them from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Liège</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8411">Louis d'or</term>. However, a monarch or a government cannot calculate like an individual. Though it is also advantageous for them if savings can be made, <pb n="105" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618592"/> if I pay a Louis d'or to England, it is lost forever. If I pay 6 Thaler for a rifle that is made in my own country, 3 go back into my pocket," he said, tapping his hand on his vest pocket.</p>
                    <p>	There is still much left to be said which relates more to particularities, but this little may be regarded here as the reverse side of what the friends of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">free trade</term> parade before the public, and apply to what should be done in Switzerland. I believe that we, as one of the smallest and youngest states, for it is only through the Confederation that we have become one<note>The adoption of the new Federal Constitution of 1848 transformed Switzerland from a confederation into a federal state.</note>, according to the new unified theory, should wait to see what larger established governments will do in the discussed matters and, instead, come to a better understanding with our closest neighbours, from whom we could expect more favourable responses in any case, as the need for commerce is mutual, than from a distant country whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-9169">trade policy</term> ultimately proceeds only from itself and its own advantage and is likewise concentrated there.</p>
                    <p>	The second matter about which I still have something to say concerns the <ref type="cross" target="../1851/36">lithograph</ref> appended to these notes. I regarded it as superfluous to describe the dimensions of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Crystal Palace</placeName>, though it was the main reason for my journey, not only because this had been done much earlier in a number of newspapers, etc., <pb n="106" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618593"/> but also because I was convinced that a mere indication of the length and width of this marvellous building, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> or "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8493">klafter</term>", could hardly give anyone a clear idea of its extent or size, unless some sort of visualization were to be added to it, and so I had the idea, which gave me a great deal of pleasure from the moment it arose: What if instead of these specifications, as if by magic, the Crystal Palace were to be constructed above <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>. I placed the floor plan of the former, reduced to the same scale, on top of the plan of the city, so that one could then see how many streets and public spaces it would cover in length and width, it is useful to achieve the aforementioned purpose to a degree<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note>. Through the kindness of Mr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7550">Peyer</persName>, I received the scaled-down plan of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">our city</placeName>, which his meritorious and highly respected <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-1127">father</persName> had drawn up with great diligence.</p>
                    <p>	To this plan I have superimposed, as I said, the floor plan of the exhibition building and only remark for those who have not read any description of this building that in its length, which is 1851 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">English feet</term>, it would extend all the way from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1686">Schwabenthor</placeName> down to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName> and, with its<note>Erratum from the <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">first edition</ref>.</note> width of 408 feet, would cover several of our main streets, squares and churches. May the execution of this idea, though imperfect, be well received.</p>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-35">The Author</persName>.
                    <lb/>
                <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, <date when="1852-12-21">21 December 1852</date>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="annex">
                <head>Appendix: Ground plan of the Crystal Palace and of the city of Schaffhausen</head>
                <p><pb n="107" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618595"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9844">Ground plan</term> of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Crystal Palace</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="108" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618596"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9846">Ground plan</term> of the city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="109" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618597"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9845">Combination of the two ground plans</term> in the same ratio.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>