<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="6">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1846</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Notes on my Journey via Carlsruhe, Mannheim, Cologne and Ostend to London, Derby, Wingfield, Alfredton and Butterly Ironworks to Sheffield, Liverpool and Back via Sheffield and London to Schaffhausen in late 1846.</titlePart>
                </docTitle> 
                <lb/>
                <byline>by <docAuthor>J. C. Fischer</docAuthor>, Lieutenant Colonel of the Artillery.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Schaffhausen. Printed by J. J. Biegler’schen Buchdruckerei in <docDate>1847</docDate> Schaffhausen.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Title page</head>
                <p> <pb n="1" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734607"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9852">[Titelblatt der Erstedition]</term></p>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Foreword</head>
                <p><pb n="3" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734609"/> The following letter from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Tho. Wm. Brande</persName>, Esqre., Master of the Die Office at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1636">London Mint</placeName></orgName></placeName>, steeled me in my hitherto tentative resolve to once again go to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> this year, my health permitting, of course, which once one has passed one’s seventy-fourth birthday, as have I, is a by no means certain proposition. I had selected <date when="1846-07">July</date> for this journey; but then some official business relating to my administration of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-6116">mines</term> as well as a pleasant family occasion, at which my presence would have been sorely missed both by those most nearly concerned and other family members, detained me here until October, a time of year when one should really <pb n="4" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734610" break="no"/> refrain from travelling, especially if one intends to journey overseas. — What then transpired in connection with my business affairs there, for whose happy outcome I have Providence to thank, will be revealed in the following pages, which obviously cannot possibly be of interest to anyone beyond the circle of those nearest and dearest to me. That the notes I was able to make on the outward, and, even more so, on the return journey have proved so paltry pains me; but one cannot be master of every situation and must content oneself with whatever chance offers, especially on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term>, where one is confined to the inside of a train carriage and the objects flying past outside are hardly sufficient to prompt contemplation, and what little entertainment there is from time to time, both in form, content and timing, tends to be – to put it mildly – quite tedious.</p>
                <p>My grounds for printing these notes, which since they really are quite trivial I did not wish to entrust to the book trade, were the same as those pertaining to last year’s. They are intended at most to be a reminder of me for my family when I myself am no more, <pb n="5" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734611"/> and for those of my friends and acquaintances who are indulgent enough to let my work be spoken for by my good will.<lb/>
                    <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, <date when="1847-05-28">28 May 1847</date>.<note>The journal was printed by <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8309">J. J. Ziegler’schen Buchdruckerei</orgName>, Schaffhausen, in 1847.</note><lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>,<lb/>
                    Lieutenant Colonel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Brande’s letter to Fischer</head>
                <p><pb n="6" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734612"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636">Royal Mint</placeName>. <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, 1 Jan. 1846.<lb/>My dear Sir!<lb/>We have made some trials with the bar of <term ref="gfa-keywords-613"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">Steel</term></term></term> You sent us*)<note n="*" type="original" place="bottom">*) It was dispatched from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> in late 1845.</note>, and are well pleased with it. Will You be so good on the receipt of this to prepare for us two bars of the same quality each 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> square, et two bars 1½ inch square, and forward them to us without delay.</p>
                <p>Will You also inform me who are Your London Agents and to whom I am to pay the amount of our debt to You. I should also wish to make Some arrangement for a further supply of Your steel, which, if You can furnish of the same quality as the sample bar and of such sizes as we require we should use here in preference to any which I have lately been able to procure.</p>
                <p>Pray let me have an immediate answer to this – and if You should come to London let me see You upon Your arrival here.<lb/>
                    Yours faithfully<lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Tho. Wm. Brande</persName>.</p>
                <p>The sizes of the bars to use for our common <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">dies</term> are 1½ inch by 1¼, et and if You can send us some 3 or 4 bars of that size they should be immediately tried. <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734613"/></p>                
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Schaffhausen–Ostend, 15–17 October 1846</head>
                <p><pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734614"/> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1846-10-14" n="1"><anchor/></placeName> On <date when="1846-10-14">14th October 1846</date> I departed shortly after noon on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1618" when="1846-10-14" n="2">Stühlingen</placeName> and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1619" when="1846-10-14" n="3">Lenzkirch</placeName> through the interesting <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1620" when="1846-10-14" n="4">Höllenthal Valley</placeName> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1122" when="1846-10-14" n="5">Freiburg im Breisgau</placeName>, where I arrived around 11 o’clock in the evening, and found very good lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1713" when="1846-10-14" n="6">Gasthof zum Engel</placeName> near the post office..</p>
                <p>By half past six in the morning of the <date when="1846-10-15">15th</date> there was an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> standing in front of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term> ready to take us travellers to the station, whence the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1123" when="1846-10-15T13:00:00" n="7">Carlsruhe</placeName> departed at 7 o’clock, arriving in the said city at 1 o’clock in the afternoon. As one can linger in Carlsruhe for four hours and still arrive in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098">Mannheim</placeName> in time to do some business that same evening, I gladly seized this welcome opportunity to visit the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8336"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1722" when="1846-10-15" n="8">Kessler Factory</placeName></orgName> and Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547">Kessler</persName> himself.</p>
                <p>Anyone who has not seen this factory for some years would be astonished at the extent to which it has grown, as is true of that of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1939"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7525"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-1081">Escher</orgName></persName></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zurich</placeName>, which for its own line of business has set itself an even greater goal, despite one supremely important factor impinging on it, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734615"/> just as it does on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2172"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7893">v. Maffei factory</persName></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName> and the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2173">brass works</placeName></term> of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7774">Beck &amp; Comp.</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1329">Augsburg</placeName> – both of them jewels in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavaria’s</placeName> industrial crown – and on so many other establishments large and small in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, that one major obstacle facing them being their considerable distance from both a sea port and productive <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite mines</term>, in both of which <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> is by nature richly endowed.</p>
                <p>It is remarkable how often a great man, by virtue of his genius, proves capable of transforming the conditions prevailing in half the world, making changes that are more long-lasting and, by their very nature, more likely to spread and consolidate than he could by virtue of the sword, were he to possess both powers in equal measure. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon</persName> demonstrated this, for those who know that prior to his appearance, England’s branches of industry put it far ahead of the Continent and enabled it to capitalise on this lead, and how, faced with such overweaning <term ref="gfa-keywords-161">competition</term> and such nimbleness and perfection in production, no one dared challenge it, will not hesitate for a moment to acknowledge that  Napoleon’s <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">Continental Blockade</term> inflicted a much deeper and more permanent wound on England than that caused by all his victories against the Continental powers; for encouraged by the thought <pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734616" break="no"/> that England need no longer be feared, factory upon factory was founded, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term> in all branches of industry trained, and beneficial and purposeful systems introduced, so that when his power was broken and normal intercourse with England was resumed, those same factories, first and foremost among them the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term>, were so firmly established that even when hit by misfortune (as happens often enough in England, too, incidentally) it could not crush them, still less destroy them. As Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547">Kessler</persName> was confined to his room by a foot injury, I was shown around by Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7938">Rickenbach</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, who is employed in <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8336"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1722">this great establishment</placeName></orgName> as a technician, and after talking to him about a delivery of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rods</term> made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, showed him a specimen of my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">cast bar iron</term></term> (a toothed curve, <emph rend="italics">mangeherz</emph>) which as something hitherto unknown to him piqued his interest. The most remarkable thing about the factory, it seemed to me, having never seen such a thing before, was the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9099">stretching hammer</term> weighing circa 180 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> and driven solely by leather belts running over 2 pulleys; the smaller of these was on or at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">drive shaft</term> itself, where there was a taper-fit wheel with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8889">pegs</term> to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9745">activate the hammer</term>. — Herr Kessler had in the meantime heard of my cast bar iron and had sent word <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734617"/> that I should visit him in his room. He, too, was as yet unaware that steel, like other metals, might be cast in dies and still retain its specific properties, and he wished me all the best for my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term>. — The fast approaching time for my departure and the arrival of the doctor in Herr Kessler’s room put an end to our discussion of other important matters, which I would have very much liked to continue.</p>
                <p>The train set off again from Carlsruhe at 5 o’clock in the evening and we arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1098" when="1846-10-15T20:00:00" n="9">Mannheim</placeName> at 8.</p>
                <p>Having alighted at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1712" when="1846-10-15" n="10">Deutscher Hof</placeName>, which is a very good inn, I went to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2227" when="1846-10-15" n="11"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7457">Eisenhardt</persName></placeName>, who expedites my shipments of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636">mint</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, and as he himself was not there left him the wherewithal for all future shipments. At 6 o’clock in the morning of the <date when="1846-10-16">16th</date>, I embarked on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamship</term> Die Königin and by midday was in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1846-10-16T12:00:00" n="13">Mainz</placeName> and by 9 o’clock in the evening in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1846-10-16T21:00:00" n="14">Cologne</placeName>. The weather was quite good for that time of year, and travelling on a steamer on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName>, especially downriver, is always pleasant if one remains on deck. There one can form a greater or lesser impression of how the cultivation and appearance of the banks of this fine and mighty river have changed since the days of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7514">Julius Caesar</persName> and the somewhat later <persName ref="gfa-actors-7956">Tacitus</persName>, from those who inspired the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9807">Song of the Nibelung</term> all the way down to the nineties of the <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734618"/> century just passed and the early second decade of the present one, when the allied powers vindicated their rights over the same by virtue of the sword.</p>
                <p>In Cologne itself I took lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2174" when="1846-10-16" n="15">Bergischer Hof</placeName>, which had been recommended to me, but which I would not recommend to anyone.</p>
                <p>At 5 o’clock in the morning of the <date when="1846-10-17">17th October</date> I drove from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1846-10-17T05:00:00" n="16">Cologne</placeName> to the station to get the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">Ostend</placeName>.<note>This connection was rendered possible by the opening of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2192">Aachen – Liège</placeName> line on 15 October 1843.</note> So speedy was our journey and so brief the time spent at the various stops en route that I was unable to observe anything particularly worthy of note; the most interesting landmark on this route really is the very long tunnel near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1969">Königshofen</placeName><note>Fischer is probably referring to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2233">Königsdorfer Tunnel</placeName>.</note>. Then came the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8890">lignite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> mines, where there was a cutting rather than a tunnel, and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1" when="1846-10-17" n="17">Aachen</placeName>, where the whole train was hauled <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2194" when="1846-10-17" n="18">over the hill</placeName> by means of a iron wire rope scarcely five quarters of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> thick, or so it seemed to me, which ran on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8958">friction rollers</term> all the way along the track and was kept in motion by a stationary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> on the hilltop. I noticed that many of the steam carriages were fitted with a simple but safe escapement mechanism by which, when travelling downhill, they were raised sufficiently for their wheels to be no longer touching the ground, their place having been taken by skids so that the carriage moved as if on runners like a sleigh.</p>
                <p><pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734619"/>I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1625" when="1846-10-17T20:00:00" n="19">Ostend</placeName> at 8 o’clock in the evening, so that according to the railway register, I had accomplished a 95-hour<note>Presumably <term ref="gfa-keywords-9723">Wegstunden</term>.</note> journey in a single day.</p>
                <p>I turned in for the night at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2228" when="1846-10-17" n="20">Ship Hotel</placeName>, which is very much an English establishment, though the many servants there also speak German and French. The food was good and this, coupled with the very moderate bill, inclines me to recommend it to all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Crossing from Ostend to Dover, 18 October 1846</head>
                <p><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1625" when="1846-10-18T06:00:00" n="21">Shortly after 6 o’clock</placeName> in the morning of Sunday the <date when="1846-10-18">18th</date>, I boarded the official English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamship</term> that takes letters from the Continent along with it and is equipped with two, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">60-horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> with which to defy wind and waves on the crossing to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1846-10-18T13:30:00" n="22">Dover</placeName>, which is located 78 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">hence</placeName>.</p>
                <p>On arriving onboard ship and seeing the haze and the fiery red sunrise with the yellow streaks of a foehn wind, I prophesied nothing good of our journey; nor could the three, long-winged petrels who appeared in the distance once we were at sea induce me to think otherwise. Slowly but surely, the wind picked up, becoming ever stronger so that the two sails that were still up began pushing the ship too far to one side had to be taken in.</p>
                <p>Instead of the 4 hours and 30 minutes that it usually takes to make this <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">crossing</placeName>, we needed 3 hours more, and at about a cannon’s shot distance <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734620" break="no"/> from the shore, the captain signalled that owing to the stormy weather he could not put into port, which is in any case difficult for vessels arriving at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-13">Belgian</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Dutch</placeName> coast; hence the four boats, each of them manned by four sailors, actually pilots, and a helmsman, that pulled up alongside us to fetch the passengers first and later the luggage.</p>
                <p>I arrived at my usual hotel, the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1715" when="1846-10-18T15:00:00" n="23">Gun und Victoria Hotel</placeName>, at 3 o’clock, just in time for lunch, which here is taken earlier than usual on Sundays. And I ate heartily, too, the sea-sickness with which, owing to the swell and the heavy pitching of the ship, I had for once been afflicted, as had many others, having left me quite empty. — As the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153"><term ref="gfa-keywords-522">customs house</term></placeName> to which the boats had brought the travellers’ cases and bags did not open again until 4 o’clock in the evening, I could not leave on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">afternoon train</term> to London, and since the next train to cover the 88 English miles from Dover to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> was not to depart until half past six, arriving there only after 11 o’clock at night, I decided to remain in Dover and to end the day with two letters <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName> to inform <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my dear ones</persName> of my safe arrival, thank God, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer enjoys two “Sandwitchers” in London, 19 October 1846</head>
                <p>Having departed <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1846-10-19T08:00:00" n="24">Dover</placeName> on the second <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> at 8 o’clock in the morning of <date when="1846-10-19">October 19th</date>, <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734621"/> I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1846-10-19T12:00:00" n="25">London</placeName> at around 12 o’clock and again turned into my previous lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1846-10-19" n="26">St. Pauls Family Hotel</placeName>, which although rather dear is very elegant and conveniently situated.</p>
                <p>To return to my journey from Dover, it was with great pleasure that I found myself travelling along the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric railway</term> that already has an operating licence for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">6-mile</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2198">stretch</placeName> on the line from <placeName ref="gfa-places-2188"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1918">Croydon</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName></placeName>, and there is demonstrating in reality what I felt able to predict with some certainty one year ago, namely that even this curious idea of using <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">vacuum</term> for such great purposes is now being put into practice.</p>
                <p>Soon after my arrival in London I went to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1846-10-19" n="27"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582">mint</orgName></placeName> and to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-10-19" n="28"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName>, but finding neither of them there, left my calling card and departed. — I had better luck with my former acquaintance <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-10-19" n="29">Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, who a year ago had furnished me with letters of recommendation for the North of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and it mattered in no small measure to me that I was able to talk to him about <placeName ref="gfa-places-2185">our railway</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> and how favourably it had been spoken of by men who know about such things. I also told him about my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">cast bar iron</term> and about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">cast steel</term></term> with which I have thrice supplied the Royal Mint in London this past year alone. — On returning <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1846-10-19" n="30">home</placeName>, my appetite and curiosity duly whetted, I could not resist the temptation to enter a shop <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734622" break="no"/> where a glass panel inscribed with gold letters offered the hungry and thirsty a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">four-penny</term> (12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>) <term ref="gfa-keywords-9366">pint</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">Old Burton Ale</term>, which assuming it is the real thing is the best in all of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, along with two “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9864">Sandwitchers</term>”, which is to say, two slices of bread smeared with butter and between them some ham. — And it really was all so good that had I not still had the prospect of lunch before me, it being already 4 o’clock by then, I would have taken a second portion and would then have been most pleasurably sated for the remainder of the day.</p>
                <p>I mention this trivial matter merely to prove that although anything that has a whiff of gentility about it in London is very dear, once one knows one’s way around it is possible to live both well and cheaply here. One last curiosity of the times that warrants mention in comparison to the scarcity afflicting the Continent is the low cost of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">four-pound</term> loaf of bread made of the finest wheat flour, which is currently just 8 pence or 24 kreuzers in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9722">Reichsgeld</term>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A visit to the photographic pioneers Willat and Croucher, 20 October 1846</head>
                <p>After two failed attempts to meet Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-10-20" n="31"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName> and an interesting convesation with Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-10-20" n="32"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8263">K. junior</persName></placeName>, which we agreed to continue the following day, I went to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2169" when="1846-10-20" n="33">shop</placeName> of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7967">Willats the optician</orgName> of No. 93, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheapside</placeName>, a seller of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9808">photographic paper</term>, which is chemically prepared paper on which photographs can be brought forth in much the same way as with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7806">Daguerre</persName>, <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734623"/> in order to procure some booklets. These booklets, which vary in format and each contain 8 sheets, are enclosed in black paper sleeves which are actually pasted together to seal them, and are sold in sizes ranging from folded letter format to a half folio at prices ranging from 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> to three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term>. — Such paper, on which light beams, the necessary precautions having been taken, very soon take effect, and which take on the images on which they are laid in various hues or even the spectrum<note>A reference to the light field projected by a camera obscura.</note> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8913">camera obscura</term><note>Here, Fischer describes how a camera works through recourse to methods he is already familiar with.</note>, comes in several different types, which depending on the colours actually attained go by names such as <term ref="gfa-keywords-9811">Chromotype</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9809">Chrysotype</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9810">Cyanotype</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9348">Energiatype</term>. I chose the latter, Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7967">Willat</orgName> having first assured me that it was the easiest one to use and the one most likely to prove successful. As he does not perform the operation himself, I chose to go to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2170" when="1846-10-20" n="34"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName></placeName> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612">Ludgate Hill</placeName> opposite the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2195">Old Bailey</placeName>, who produces such <term ref="gfa-keywords-18">light drawings</term> as well as ordinary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8934">Daguerrotypes</term>, but then has them coloured by a Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8337">Beard</persName>, who is the only practitioner of this art in London, he told me. — The bust portrait of a lady, which, although just 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in height, really does resemble a miniature portrait painting, is certainly outstanding, though it cost me 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L.</term> and 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Sh.</term>, or 16 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> One special advantage of photographic <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734624"/> paper is that the first image, or negative, can later be replicated as often as one wishes on still more sheets of similar paper, as is done with <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithographic</term> transfer or overprinting. — I wanted to have Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName> photograph a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9865"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9065">watercolour painting</term></term> of quite some size, 12 by 16 inches, which <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">our</placeName> skillful Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-439">Beck</persName> had painted to show the inside of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">my foundry</placeName> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">steel-pouring</term> operation. (I should say in passing that the said light drawings, or rather prints, which are created not by the application of mechanical force, as might be concluded from the word “print”, but are solely a result of light taking effect on the paper, are dark brown rather than black.) He demanded just 2 Sh. and 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> or fl. 1. and 30 kr. for the first negatives, that is, the inverted images, and for all the positive images thereafter 1 Sh. and 8 pence or 54 kr. each, for as many as I wished.</p>
                <p>But as he demanded 4 days for this work, whereas I would have liked to be able to show the painting to various people right away, I set the whole idea aside and decided to end this by no means uninteresting day with writing. —</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>“Hochrheinbahn”, steel casting and street paving, 21 October 1846</head>
                <p>Whereas 50 years ago such a long journey would have counted among the imponderables, eight days after leaving <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName><note>A correction of “House” in Fischer’s first edition.</note> I am already a citizen of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, as it were. The day’s business began with a visit to <pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734625"/> Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-10-21" n="35"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName>, as a conveyance to whom I hired a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> at a rate of 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> per hour. — Besides my invention of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">bar iron casting</term></term>, our conversation turned on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1270"><placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Waldshut–Constanz</placeName></placeName> railway that <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> would so much like to have built. He took the view that now that <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zurich</placeName> has been granted a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9251">concession</term> for its <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term>, ours will never actually be built; but this opinion I could not share, for the best route for both goods and passenger traffic to <placeName ref="gfa-places-21">Lake Constance</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2077">Württemberg</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavaria</placeName> and indeed <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> is most certainly along the straight line from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> via Waldshut and Schaffhausen to <placeName ref="gfa-places-455">Constanz</placeName>, and from there straight to <placeName ref="gfa-places-490">Friedrichshafen</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1988">Lindau</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1119">Bregenz</placeName>, and not the circuitous route via <placeName ref="gfa-places-236">Baden</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zurich</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-181">Winterthur</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-994">Frauenfeld</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-955">Romanshorn</placeName>. Zurich can certainly serve as the stockyard for whatever is destined for <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>, since once the Basel– or rather the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122">Freiburg</placeName>–Waldshut railway<note>The <placeName ref="gfa-places-2216">Badische Hauptbahn</placeName> only went as far as Freiburg im Breisgau in 1846. The Freiburg – Basel section was not built until 1846 to 1855.</note> is finished, it is likely that all goods and passenger traffic coming from <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName> will give preference to the right over the left side of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName>. The Basel–Waldshut–Schaffhausen–Constanz railway is a natural route and will therefore win out eventually, if not now, then certainly in the course of time, whereas others that are forced along much less obvious routes will surely disappear again.</p>
                <p>From Mr. Im Thurn I went to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-10-21" n="36"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8263">K., junior</persName></placeName>, who took an avid interest <pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734626"/> in the specimens of cast bar iron that I showed him, among which were some large toothed pieces with peculiar curves to make the circular momentum generated by their rotation produce a straight and incredibly fast forward motion. In the course of our discussion we advanced so far that in my letters home I shall now have considerably more to report on this subject. At last I reached the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1846-10-21" n="37">mint</placeName>, where Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> welcomed me most cordially as an old friend. After agreeing on Friday morning for the settlement of our business transactions, we talked mainly about the inspired Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-439">J. Beck’s</persName> coloured drawings of my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">three works</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-97">Mühlenthal</placeName> and the inside of my <term ref="gfa-keywords-121">steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term> foundry during the pouring of a heavy piece. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9865">This painting</term>, which may well be the only one of this subject, has been widely admired as exceptionally well done, an impression due in large part to the light effects of the dazzling white fire of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">open smelter</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> full of molten steel or bar iron being lifted out of the same, while the stained-glass masks with which the eyes have to be shielded against the heat radiated by the furnace and the intensity of the light make the whole thing resemble the scene of the witches’ brewery in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8711">Macbeth</term>. As to the striking of the raised coin “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term>” into the <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734627" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8342">dies</term> in which the finished and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardened</term> coins will thereafter be <term ref="gfa-keywords-9063">minted</term>, I put it to him that this could perhaps be done warm, which would have the great advantage of sparing the coin punch, and that if the dies were first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9822">galvanically gold-plated</term> to prevent the formation of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9239"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9823">mill scale</term></term> on the surface, the striking could even be done red-hot, whereupon he remarked that it might indeed be worth putting that to the test. — Finally, I told him of my process for tempering <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">coin punches</term> and other heavy pieces made of my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">minting steel</term>, of which he duly took notice.</p>
                <p>So now my business of the day was done, with the exception of a visit to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-18">photographer</term> Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2170" n="38"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName></placeName>, to whom I entrusted the aforementioned painting by Beck for him to treat, it having in the meantime become clear to me that I would have to remain in London until the beginning of next week.</p>
                <p>He promised to make me a photographic original as well as several positive prints of that (negative or inverted) image by Saturday morning.</p>
                <p>Every time I visit London I see them experimenting with some new paving system. Today, for example, my attention was caught by yet another new kind of paving system being installed in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheapside</placeName>, of which I can safely say that it is one of the most <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734628"/> frequented streets in all of London. Half the street, which is very wide, had already been torn up, and there were thousands upon thousands of blocks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term>, cut into very regular parallelepipeds, piled up ready to be laid. I measured some of them with my measuring stick and found them to be 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> thick, 15 inches long and 9 inches wide on average. — The bed into which they are laid, or rather stood upright in the direction of their longest side, consisted of sand with nut-sized gravel tipped on top of it and heavily wetted with water. The stones were lined up cheek by jowl in this bed and the joints on all four sides immediately filled with liquid <term ref="gfa-keywords-8472">hydraulic lime</term>. All this was then covered in sand and the surplus sand swept off again so that the street, when finished, will consist of a single stone arch wedged between the two, somewhat higher, pavements that run parallel to the houses on either side.</p>
                <p>The paving in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName> is certainly very fine, but because the blocks are cubes of circa 9 inches across has the drawback of presenting an excessively large flat surface on which horses can easily slip and fall, which happened to me once with my own horses in Vienna, whereas here, the joints between the stones give them something to grip every three inches.</p>
                <p>If this street does not prove durable, then <pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734629"/> I really do not know how we are to make streets durable at all. I asked a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">worker</term> the price of a single stone, which he could not tell me, remarking only that it would doubtless be similar to the price of the granite blocks used to build <placeName ref="gfa-places-2108">Waterloo Bridge</placeName>, one <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">ton</term> of which, that is 21 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>, delivered franco domicile from <placeName ref="gfa-places-109">Norway</placeName>, had apparently cost 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term>, or 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term> in our money. One really does need Englsh money and English enterprise to execute the feats of which I have just now been talking. — Wherever in the world the English track down something that might be of service to them, it has to be procured. No longitude and no latitude into which man has so far advanced remains closed to them, and because here the whole nation – an enlightened nation, one might add – with the press as its proxy, is constantly sitting in judgment, whatever assets there are, are soon identified and used, while whatever is unusable or even harmful is censured and discarded. — The above notes and a letter home concluded the day’s business.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer inspects the atmospheric railway, 22 October 1846</head>
                <p>Thursday, October 22nd. <date when="1846-10-22">Today</date>, when the weather was often rainy, I again visited Messrs. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-10-22" n="39"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName> and <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-10-22" n="40"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName>, but still had time to go by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2171" when="1846-10-22" n="41">Sydenham</placeName> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1918" when="1846-10-22" n="42">Croydon</placeName> so as to gain access, should that be possible, to the “<placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2196" when="1846-10-22" n="43"><term ref="gfa-keywords-3013">Engine House</term></placeName>” (the building housing the stationary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> with the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term>) from which the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2198"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9704">atmospheric railway</term></placeName> to the <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734630" break="no"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1923">Dartmouth Arms</placeName> is operated, an undertaking for which fortune, it seemed, was on my side. As the train was not departing from the terminus (station) to Croydon right away, I asked a gentleman who happened to be standing next to me if he might tell me more about these most interesting installations, which I wrote about at some length in my <ref type="cross" target="../1845">notes of last year’s visit</ref>. After mentioning some of my friends in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to him by name, among them Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, he gave me a card and said: “If you show this to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7845">Gregory</persName>, the engineer at Croydon, he will let you view the engines in the Engine House there, and perhaps see other things too.” After meeting Mr. Gregory, who instructed the stationmaster there to grant me admittance to the Engine House whenever I wished, I decided that since I still wished to travel ten miles on the atmospheric railway, as far as the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2197">Dartmouth Arms</placeName>, that is, and having already travelled 40 miles on the Croydon railway, I would forego that pleasure on this particular evening, as otherwise I would have had less than a quarter of an hour in which to inspect and ask questions about the most intriguing aspects of this invention, and contented myself instead with viewing the outside installations and the sensible way in which the tubes are assembled. I especially admired the exactness with which they had been cast <pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734631" break="no"/> and the thinness of the walls, which given the many thousands of them that are needed – there were indeed thousands of them lying around – is very important. — The train from Croydon back to London was to leave in a few minutes, leaving me with just enough time for the following notes.</p>
                <p>From the experience so far gained, it appears that the application of a composite of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9554">skid</term> and wax markedly improves the closure – that is to say, the air-tightness – of the valves, which hitherto had been steadily deteriorating as a result of constant use, and that since the very start, even the most serious failure to exclude air had never exceeded two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inche</term> on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8783">pressure gauges</term> at either end of the tube, meaning that there had never been any significant reduction in the speed of the moving <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term>, except during the 5 to 6 minutes at the station where the said error had become apparent, and that if a single additional 2-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> engine is applied to evacuate the tubes all the faster, there is still no noticeable difference in the speed of travel. To this advantage might be added a much greater one, namely that on an atmospheric <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railway</term>, neither the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> nor the carriages that it is pulling can come off the rails, and that since the train is not connected to the stationary engine, <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734632"/> as it would be to the locomotive of a conventional railway, it is not imperilled by a burst boiler either.</p>
                <p>My return journey took me through <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1648" when="1846-10-22" n="44">Southwark</placeName> (a small part of London on the right bank of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>) and over <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1638" when="1846-10-22" n="45">London Bridge</placeName>, the work of that clever architect <persName ref="gfa-actors-7936">Rennie</persName>, to whom I was personally introduced by the famous <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel</persName>, creator of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888">tunnel</placeName>.<note>See the <ref type="cross" target="../1825/65">journal of 1825</ref>.</note> Although very fine and extremely solid, in just 20 years it has turned completely black, as have all the buildings in London. I concluded the day with letters to my grandchildren. Notwithstanding the inclement weather, I had seen and learned a good deal, making this a most satisfactory and memorable day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Brande, the Bank of England and a visit to Old Fenn, 23 October 1846</head>
                <p>After visiting Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-10-23" n="46"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName> and replying to two letters, I called in on Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-10-23" n="47"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, who was so kind as to tell me not only that my invention of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">bar iron for casting</term> was winning recognition, but that he intended to give me letters of recommendation for my planned trip to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2148">Alfredton</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName>, which would certainly be most useful to me. After thanking him profusely for these good offices, it being important to be well-written of in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and discoursing with him further about a soft <term ref="gfa-keywords-8757">cemented</term> casting that he had had made for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887">lathe</term> for sliding tools (burin fixe) <pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734633"/> and the many deep perforations on the support rod, including the extent to which these were a result of the cementation process, he presented me with two more addresses for London’s two largest trading houses for <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9507">steel wares</term>.</p>
                <p>Having received a written invitation, I then went to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName> at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1636" when="1846-10-23" n="48">Royal Mint</placeName>, who after placing yet another order for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">coin punches</term>, the fourth such shipment (which I read as proof of his great satisfaction), afforded me the pleasure of seeing some punches made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">my steel</term> actually struck, that is, the raised embossing on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8342">original punch</term> being transferred to a die turned with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9853">tapered top</term> by means of an incredibly large and powerful screw press (balancier), and so quietly and fast that I could scarcely believe that the die was already finished, though that was indeed the case, for both the motif and the inscription were so sharp that no additional tool could have made them sharper and finer.</p>
                <p>His <term ref="gfa-keywords-9328">press</term> having produced such a consummate piece, he laughingly remarked that “if your punch had not held out, we would have held you personally responsible!” After that, we talked about various scientific matters, most particularly about <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term>, and whether they are pure bodies, and if not, the elemental materials out of which they might consist.</p>
                <p>We were both of the opinion <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734634" xml:id="TB6_p_28"/> that it is easier to imagine them as compounds than as pure bodies; Mr. Brande because they differ so greatly in nature, and I because some among them cannot be chemically – or even mechanically – bonded, which presupposes a high degree of heterogeneity. Furthermore, I repeated a view that I had put to him 20 years earlier, namely that <term ref="gfa-keywords-8741">hydrogen</term> in one or the other form must be a component of metals, “and I believe”, he interjected, “that water itself is a metal”. He then told me the curious tale of a mouse that at a friend of his had fallen into a jar containing a solution of<term ref="gfa-keywords-8643"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9816">copper sulphate</term></term>, and that as a further 8 years had elapsed before this jar happened to be taken down again, it turned out that while the flesh of the mouse had corroded away entirely, the skeleton (the bones) had been transformed into <term ref="gfa-keywords-9259">copper pyrites</term>. I thereupon remarked that this was nothing unusual, since (presumably antediluvian) <term ref="gfa-keywords-9818">ammonites</term> partially transformed into <term ref="gfa-keywords-9817">iron pyrites</term> were indeed found from time to time and that I myself had happened to buy such a one in a batch of old <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9159">casting</term>, and had discovered its true properties only later.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8338">Goodwin</persName>, the secretary, had in the meantime issued a draft for the payment of my steel shipments by the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8302">Bank of England</orgName>, since no payments were made inside the mint itself. After taking my leave, therefore, I took the draft straight to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2199" when="1846-10-23">said goldmine</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734635"/> An extraordinary silence reigns in that place, where day in day out immense sums are taken in and paid out. Even the doorway is constructed so as to prevent any collision between the in-coming and out-going, the hinge being down the middle rather than at the side. While on the outside, the word <emph rend="bold">In</emph> is written in large letters on the right-hand side of the doorway, on the inside it is the word <emph rend="bold">Out</emph>, again on the right-hand side, with the result that two persons wishing to enter and exit in the same instant do not block each other’s way but open their respective doors without so much as seeing each other. — My cheque, or draft, contained not just a number but also the letters <emph rend="bold">A.C.</emph>, and when I entered the room, or rather the large hall, I saw right away the cash or payment counter at which I had to wait, there being similar letters there, again writ very large so as to obviate the need for inquiries and indeed speech generally, to which the English, quite rightly, are so averse. — I mutely handed the cashier my cheque, and, after first entering the number, quantity and amount in his ledger, he asked me only whether I preferred <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9091"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9826">banknotes</term></term>? — “Gold”, I said, and without another word, he counted it out and pushed it towards me on a little shovel, from which I gathered it up in my hands.</p>
                <p>I have spent and received so much money in my life, but none with such pleasure as that I received today, and not only because I myself had earned it, in part with my own hands, <pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734636" break="no"/> but also because England was giving me its money for my product, whereas in all other instances it is the other way round.</p>
                <p>After lunch I went to one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9493">steel traders</term>, in fact in to the same <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2201" when="1846-10-23" n="50">shop</placeName> as the one in which I purchased some steel and assorted tools shortly before leaving London for home <ref type="cross" target="../1794/7">52 years ago</ref>, and there I learned, to my great delight, that the owner Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</orgName>, who back then was very young and had just taken over the business from his uncle, was still alive. He still remembered Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName>, for whom I had been working at the time, and since by then it was already almost dark asked me to return to him at 11 o’clock the next morning. This man, who is uncommonly rich, looked rather sour and serious at first; but the longer I was with him, the more his face brightened so that we parted on quite amicable terms. — The day’s business ended with a long walk to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2169" when="1846-10-23" n="51"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7967">Willats</orgName></placeName> the optician on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheap Side</placeName>, and then with another to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8325">Youle</persName> on <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2200" when="1846-10-23" n="52">Leadenhall-Streel</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer has his likeness taken, 24 October 1846</head>
                <p>Saturday, October 24th. The registration of various objects and copying of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.’s</persName> letters of recommendation as well as his own accompanying letter containing a few suggestions of his having kept me busy all morning, I did not go to see Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2201" when="1846-10-24" n="53"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</persName></placeName> until 1 o’clock. He had become very friendly by then, and, after <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734637"/> seeing the specimen that I had brought with me, declared the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707">casting of bar iron</term> to be most promising, noting that the process was as yet unknown in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. He also mentioned, in the course of our conversation, that English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> was no longer as good as it once was, and as grounds for this gave the great <term ref="gfa-keywords-161">competition</term> between steelmakers, which were now buying up old <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">carriage springs</term> and such like from the railway companies, and without knowing or even heeding their quality were melting them down <emph rend="italic">pell-mell</emph> in order to make cheap <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>.</p>
                <p>We parted from each other with the request that I visit him again on returning from the North of England. A planned visit that I received from Mr. T.<note>Possibly <persName ref="gfa-actors-7543">Thomas Turton</persName>.</note> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, who based on his own quality controls likewise lamented the declining quality of English steel, and who invited me to visit <placeName ref="gfa-places-1721"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">their establishment</orgName></placeName> in Sheffield, promising me something that not everyone in England is afforded, namely that I might see whatever I wished in their factory (comprising, as it does, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cementation</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">foundry steel</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file</term> and locomotive spring factories), took up so much of my time that all that I now had time for was a visit to the photographer <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2170" when="1846-10-24" n="54"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName></placeName>, who does such outstanding work in coloured <term ref="gfa-keywords-8934">Daguerrotyp</term>, to have my own likeness taken, and to the optician I wished to consult on the subject of “dissolving <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734638"/> views” (images that change by “dissolving”). These images, which in German are misleadingly called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9340">Nebelbilder</term> [lit. “fog pictures”], are inserted into a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9824">magic lantern</term> lit up by a flame fed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9825">oxygen and hydrogen gas</term> or illuminated by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7822"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8979">Drummond Light</term></persName>, and are currently all the rage. For the inhabitants of a city as large as this, acquainting oneself as far as possible with whatever the lovers of science are currently bringing to light from the treasure trove of the natural sciences, often with great effort and exertion but no less often through their own perceptive genius, really is instructive and hence very much to one’s advantage; whereas many a person in a small town on the Continent believes he has done his duty to destiny merely by retiring after dinner to a so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffeehouse</term></term> instead of doing something productive and by retaining his frog’s eye view of the world ensures that he and his family are just as clever at the end of the year as they were at the start of it.</p>
                <p>Having decided to travel to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1257">Derby</placeName> on the morrow, and the following day to the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2215">Butterly</placeName>, just 13 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> away near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1877">Altfredton</placeName>, I busied myself with packing my things, because the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> waits for no man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>London–Derby, 25 October 1846</head>
                <p>Sunday, October 25th. I had to be at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1666" when="1846-10-25T10:00:00" n="56">Euston</placeName> Terminus, which is more than 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2231">City</placeName>, where I am <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1846-10-25" n="55">currently residing</placeName>, at 10 o’clock in the morning, or rather quarter of an hour earlier, <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734639"/> and on arrival there paid 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pound</term> and 11 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term>, or 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> and 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> for a first-class seat to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1257">Derby</placeName>, 142 miles hence. This being a Sunday, there were no more seats to be had in second class, for some unknown reason. The seats in first class are arranged three in a row, meaning six per carriage. Each person sits on an excessively wide, fully upholstered armchair, whereas persons in the second-class carriages have to sit five in a row and on wooden benches with wooden backrests. Here we see the base, and one might boldly add, inhumane, spirit of speculation that is addicted only to profits, in all its dreadful colours, especially when compared to those fine furnishings that the governments of <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavaria</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1899">Baden</placeName> have seen fit to install in the same class of carriage for the benefit of the public at large.</p>
                <p>On arriving in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1257" when="1846-10-25T15:00:00" n="57">Derby</placeName> at 3 o’clock in the afternoon, I wrote letters home and to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. At lunch, to which I was summoned at 5 o’clock that evening, I made the acquaintance of a country doctor, who despite being my only table companion did the honours, as is the custom here, meaning that he served me first and as soon as I had finished a portion inquired whether he might serve me another.</p>
                <p>This gentleman, who was doing the rounds of the sick in his district, showed me his travelling apothecary, which was most compendious and, it seemed to me, <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734640"/> very sensibly stocked so that it contained all the medicines most necessary to the needs of the moment; I read the labels on the little crystal flacons: Opium, Camphor, Salmiac, Salpeter, Extr. Hyosciami, and Moschus; then several types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">infusion</term> and little boxes of plasters. The importance of not just medical but also swift pharmaceutical assistance needs no further comment, and many a patient in the countryside has fallen victim to the want of a nearby apothecary or such a dispensing physician as this one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>The Butterley Works and a highway robbery at Alfredton, 26 October 1846</head>
                <p>Just after 9 o’clock this morning I took the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1257" when="1846-10-26T09:00:00" n="58">Derby</placeName> to the station, which is quite some distance away, in order to have myself listed as a passenger on the train to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2076">Wingfield</placeName>, the railway hub nearest to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2215"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Butterly Ironworks</term></placeName>. — As the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> did not depart right away, I had a chance to take stock of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire pump</term> after the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7917">Newsham</persName> system, which differs from the previously known types in respect of the power with which the water is ejected, the purposeful arrangement of the compressor, the simplicity and solidity of the assembly, and the ease with which it can be transported by just a few hands, assuming the distances are not too great. Thus I am persuaded that it will not be so easy to make anything better, as I have said repeatedly in places where it might have been of use, and though experience entitles me to an opinion on ths matter, or so I believe, <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734641"/> it has hitherto gone unheeded. I must also add that one reason this fire pump, which is intended only for the station, seems so extremely expedient, is that it is situated very close to the canal, which flows by just a few <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> further down.</p>
                <p>I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2076" when="1846-10-26T10:00:00" n="59">Wingfield</placeName> just after 10 o’clock and again boarded an omnibus to the little town of <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1877" when="1846-10-26" n="60">Alfredton</placeName> just three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> hence, from which I had but 2½ English miles to cover on foot, there being only a vicinal road to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>. Also on the omnibus were an older man and woman, and then a young woman clad all in mourning, who said not a word as long as the man and woman, with whom I had begun conversing, were present. But as they were going to their farm up in the hills, they soon bade us farewell and alighted, whereupon the young lady, now that we were alone, politely asked whether, since she had four miles to walk to the home of her Mamma and her path would take her past the ironworks that I wished to visit, she might “put myself under your protection”. I gladly assented to her request, although I saw no reason why my protection might be necessary.</p>
                <p>After we had already walked for two miles and I, not knowing this region at all, had let her guide me along many narrow lanes, it seemed to me that <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734642"/> given the direction in which we were going and the length of time that we had been afoot without setting eyes on the ironworks, we must have gone astray. I told her of my concern, which I could see she shared, and suggested to her that we return to the mill that we had shortly before put behind us in order to ask the way. A gentleman in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabriolet</term> that was just then pulling up at the mill told us that henceforth, I would have to take a different route, a lane that veered off at a right angle, while she would take the other. — She implored my pardon for having thus wasted my time, which was indeed annoying, and excused herself for having led us astray on the grounds that she had only once before made this journey. — After a quarter of an hour the gentleman in the cabriolet overtook me and told me to climb in beside him since he would be driving through the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7794">ironworks</orgName></term> whither I was bound, which thanking him profusely, I did. On arriving <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2215" when="1846-10-26" n="61">there</placeName>, I presented my letter of recommendation to one of the owners, a man already advanced in years by the name of <persName ref="gfa-actors-8339">Goodwin</persName>, who promptly appointed a counting-house clerk to show me around. The following are but the more important of my observations, which would have been more interesting and more numerous had not Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7872">Jessup</persName>, the director of the works to whom the letter was actually addressed, unfortunately been absent that day. The young clerk, meanwhile, had no technical knowledge, nor indeed any knowledge at all beyond his own métier, <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734643"/> which made me disinclined to treat what he told me as infallible.</p>
                <p>The three <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnaces</term> that are in operation here are fired with lumps of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">anthracite</term> both small and large up to 50 and 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> in weight. These are cast into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">throat</term>, followed by first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9199">limestone</term> and then the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9027">ore</term>, which is a poor <term ref="gfa-keywords-8653">clay ironstone</term>. Each of these furnaces is supplied with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9706">hot blast</term> from three <term ref="gfa-keywords-9715">nozzles</term>, the hot air having previously been heated to the melting point of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> in the flat, Heber-like, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast-iron</term> pipes of the adjoining stove. The whole furnace shaft measuring fifty and more <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> from bottom to top supposedly holds 100 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term> or 2,100 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> of molten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, as well as all the coal, ore and limestone on top of it, or so my guide told me.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">flame</term> in these furnaces is much larger, whiter and more intense than in furnaces fired with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">charcoal</term>. Yet the immense heat that develops here is lost entirely. The anthracite, which comes from the works’ own mines, is 500 per cent cheaper than what it would cost in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, my guide told me. I had previously asked the gentleman in the cabriolet about the price of coal here in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1925">Derbyshire</placeName> and he had told me that it cost 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> per ton or 21 Centner and 14 shillings per ton of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term>.</p>       
                <p><pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734644"/> The <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term> for large castings is heavily used and there were ten moulds for gas “mainpipes” of 10 feet in length and 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> wide standing upright in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8705">casting pit</term> ready to have the molten iron poured into them. The works itself, incidentally, does not look very inviting and most of the windows are most abominably broken. Likewise the large tools that are used for various operations, since they also build <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamships</term> etc., are not at all remarkable and can certainly not compare with those of Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7525">Escher</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zurich</placeName> or Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547">Kessler</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1123">Karlsruhe</placeName>. — Wishing not to be late, since the train leaves Wingfield for Sheffield at half past four, and having nearly 3 miles to walk back to Alfredton, despite not having eaten anything since that morning, after which I would have a further 3 miles on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> to the station, I politely declined my guide’s invitation to show me a second works, even further afield, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9594">remelting</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9053">refining</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8557">welding</term> are done and where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mills</term> are located. I was already on the road when a man of not the most inviting appearance made to join me; I gave him short shrift, however, and at a bend in the road fell back somewhat. When, later on, a cart approached from a distance, he stepped off the road and disappeared into the undergrowth or bushes, after which I saw nothing more of him. I reached the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term> at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1877" when="1846-10-26" n="62">Alfred<pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734645" break="no"/>ton</placeName> and after having lunch there was again fully restored. Such was the cleanliness of the rooms and the accoutrements, the quality of the meals and the home-brewed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ales</term>, of which the innkeeper was perhaps a little too fond, that it had the comfortable, friendly character of those country inns of Old England that we know so well from the faithful and appealing descriptions of the same to be found in the better sort of novels. One is not surrounded by so many stiff, black-clad, high-collared, lisping waiters, whose economy with words and detached deportment leave one puzzling over whether one is of a higher or lower standing than them. From the innkeeper I learned that just two days previously, a stationmaster had been the victim of a highway robbery in that region, as had a butcher on his way to buy cattle, whereupon I at last understood why the young lady whom I had met that morning had solicited my protection, though she had said nothing of this at the time. As the English are great timekeepers, I arrived at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2076" when="1846-10-26" n="63">Wingfield</placeName> just a few minutes before the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">train</term> roared into the station with sparks flying and boiler hissing, and in just a little over an hour had covered the 31 miles to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1846-10-26" n="64">Sheffield</placeName>, where on alighting I found an omnibus to take me to my usual lodgings at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1846-10-26" n="65">Tontine house</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734646"/> I went without delay to the most famous of all the cutlers, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1719" when="1846-10-26" n="66"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7536">Rodgers and Son</orgName></placeName>, not just to have some of my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> whetted, but also to present them with two new blades made of the same <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">steel</term> as that I use for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">coin punches</term>. These blades, forged, inscribed with my name, and tempered, I had brought with me from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> to have them <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">ground</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polished</term> and encased in Sheffield so as to be able to form a proper judgment of their quality. I was assured that everything would be ready by tomorrow evening.</p>
                <p>Before ending my record of today’s events, I must return again, despite having mentioned it many times before, to the unseemly habit of ostentatious idling, which in Schaffhausen dialect we would call <emph rend="italics">Herumlartschen</emph>, of which it is for the most part members of the genteel classes, or at least those who aspire to become so, who are guilty. For just as I was going down into the dining room to take some <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> and buttered bread, a gentleman at another table – I should add that all the tables in this fine establishment are <term ref="gfa-keywords-8774">mahogony</term> – sat down on a chair and instead of contenting himself with putting his feet up on another chair, which is what everyone else was doing, put them up on the table, remaining in this position, moreover, until the waiter brought him his supper. Only then could he be bothered to take his feet down off the table, <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734647" break="no"/> and then only in order to make room for the tablecloth, plates and dishes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer shows Huntsman a picture of his works, 27 October 1846</head>
                <p>Being in possession of a letter of recommendation for Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537">Cammel &amp; Comp.</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, on finishing breakfast I inquired after the address of the said gentlemen and was told by the waiter that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName> was just then at the hotel and was about to leave. On hearing this I entered the dining room, where he still was, and presented him with my letter. After reading the same, he invited me to leave the hotel with him, which I gladly did. The <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1720" when="1846-10-27" n="67">establishment</placeName> belonging to these gentlemen, which is quite a long way outside the city and close to the station, is very extensive and probably the largest of the astonishingly numerous <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel-makers</term> here. In addition to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, for which they have twenty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">furnaces</term>, each of which supplies three castings a day, there are four large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9629">cementation furnaces</term>, each with a capacity of two hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>, the lighting, firing and cooling of which takes three weeks. They also make <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> as well as <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">springs</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term> and train carriages.</p>
                <p>We went first to the casting house, then to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8626"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file cutter</term></term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9044">file smithy</term>, and then to the spring factory, though in none of these places did I see anything new, except for the one change that has been introduced in the cast steel factory, where instead of placing just one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> in the furnace, as they did before, they now put in two at once. Anyone who does not know the cause of this, <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734648"/> will wonder that their method for so long remained hidden to other nations; for according to the advertisements in <persName ref="gfa-actors-7870">Jars</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9812">metallurgischen Reisen</term>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703">Old Huntsman</persName> chanced on this <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> in the early fifties of the previous century, and the clever <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Swedish</placeName> ironmaster <persName ref="gfa-actors-7955">Eric Th. Swedenstierna</persName>, wrote about it in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9813">account of his travels</term> through a part of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019">Scotland</placeName> undertaken in the years 1802 and 1803:</p>
                <p>“Ehurn jag i Sheffield vid 2. ne särskilta fabriker ägde tilfälle att temligen noga följa giutsstälprocessen, är det alldeles icke min mening, att hwarken här eller på något annat ställe gifva derom en utförlig beskrifning, dels emedan den vi länge ägt, sammanlagd ved hvad vi kenna om naturen af jern och stål är alldeles tillräcklig att vegleda den som har en vis praktisk kundskap i jernhanteringen, dels emedan det kan vara oss till någon förmån, at behålla konsten for oss sielfva då de många misslyckade försök, som blifvit giorda i Tyskland och Frankrike, vittna, at den är ännu okänd der, oaktadt allt hvad lärde och olärde derum skrivit.”</p>
                <p>Which translates as follows: <lb/>“Although I have chance to thank for having been able to observe the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">steel casting process</term> quite closely at two different factories in Sheffield, I would not presume <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734649"/> to provide a detailed description of the same either here or indeed anywhere else, in part because what we have long known, combined with what we now know of the nature of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, is of itself sufficient to point anyone who has some practical knowledge of iron working in the right direction, and in part because it may be to our advantage to keep this art to ourselves, the many failed attempts that have been made in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> being proof enough that it is as yet unknown there, notwithstanding what learned and not so learned people have written about it.”</p>
                <p>One of the gentlemen told me that he had recently been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName> – the <term ref="gfa-keywords-161">competition</term> is so great that they send their agents everywhere in search of sales or go there themselves – and there had seen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> made by my son, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName>, which had been very fine. — He then wished to know the wages paid to my <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term> and miscellaneous others who have a hand in steel-making, and I answered him in some detail, if only to gain the right to ask him questions of my own in return. There was nothing new for me to see in these factories, and I almost regretted having made the journey there, though as my return journey was to take me past Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman’s</persName> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1687" when="1846-10-27" n="68"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mill</term></placeName>, I resolved to inquire after him as well.</p>
                <p>On arriving there, the “porter” told me that <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734650"/> since Mr. Huntsman lived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1806">Attercliff</placeName>, 2 miles from Sheffield, he would not be in the city until 1 o’clock that afternoon. I therefore walked all the way over to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1846-10-27" n="69"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">cast steel</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file factories</term></placeName> of Messrs. T.<note>Almost certainly <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">Thomas Turton &amp; Sons</orgName>.</note> in order to present them with a calling card that one of the gentlemen who had sought me out in London (they are brothers) had given me. But here, too, the gentlemen were absent, and I was told that they would not be in the factories until 4 o’clock in the afternoon. After purchasing some souvenirs to take home with me, I returned to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1687" when="1846-10-27" n="70"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman</persName></placeName>. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">He</persName> and his daughter, a very beautiful young lady, were just then in the factory yard, and once I had introduced myself he was extremely friendly. I told him that I had merely wanted inquire after his health, having not seen him on my previous year’s visit or for twenty years prior to that; and because, contrary to what I had hoped, he had never come to <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, I wanted to at least show him in drawings what <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">my own works</placeName> looks like both inside and out, to which end I had deliberately brought along the three <term ref="gfa-keywords-9065">paintings</term> of it done by our Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-439">Beck</persName>, a drawing teacher and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9371">painter</term> famed for his talent who deserves to be much more widely known.</p>
                <p>Mr. Huntsman was inviting me up to the counting house, when his son rode up on horseback, and, having been introduced to me, shook my hand most cordially and said that he had recently been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, where he had heard my name mentioned. Mr. Huntsman, alongside his son and daughter, then studied the three <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734651" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9065">paintings</term> for some time, most particularly <term ref="gfa-keywords-9865">the one</term> showing the inside of my steel and <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">bar iron foundry</term>, which owing to the figures with masks in front of their faces to shield them from the extreme heat when pouring molten metal and the special light effects is a most audacious work. The English are invariably drawn to such things, especially when there is some truth to them, which is certainly the case with this painting, as with the other two.</p>
                <p>Later, Mr. Huntsman asked me what I was expecting and whether I would like to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mill</term>, an offer which I gladly accepted, especially for the sake of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">heating furnace</term>, which over the past year has undergone all manner of modifications. He and his family left the works with me, though all the while insisting that I must for sure visit him again on my return from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName>, which I had already told him was where I intended to travel on the morrow, God willing, though I would return via Sheffield.</p>
                <p>By now it was almost 3 o’clock and time for lunch, since I still intended to return to Messrs. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1846-10-27" n="71"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">T.</orgName></placeName> at 4 o’clock. That is also what I did, though finding the said gentlemen still not there, I resolved to await their return. The smelter was just then standing in front of the gate to the foundry yard, whereas the other <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term> were having a break inside. He and I – the gentlemen having still not yet arrived – then had a long conversation about the most important aspects of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9502">steel-making</term>, about the rising and subsiding of the steel when pouring, about damaged <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term>, <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734652"/> about the sooting up of the sprues and about so-called “plugs” that block their openings. In the end, he took me into the vaults on which the furnaces are built, and into the workshops where they make the crucibles, and taking a lump of the clay they have on stock actually fashioned one right there and then. With the exception of a single, though not unimportant circumstance, the method was the same as I had seen used by Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1797">Walker and Booth</placeName></orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786">Rotherham</placeName> <ref type="cross" target="../1814/28">32 years previously</ref>. — At last the gentlemen arrived. They had learned of my arrival from their brother in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. We spoke at length about steel-making, and from what they told me, I concluded that my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9686">invention</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">cast bar iron</term></term> was already much talked about in England, though no one had as yet been able to successfully replicate it. — The specimens that I showed them commanded their full attention, and they regretted my not wishing to remain in Sheffield for longer. I believe they would have liked to learn more, this being something new, though I had my own reasons for avoiding that.</p>
                <p>Suddenly it became very bright in the yard, a sign that pouring was about to begin. We went down to watch. They wondered at my prediction, made while the casting of the two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9510">rods</term> was in progress, that the one would rise, having become inflated with air bubbles, while the other would subside (that is, contract), which is indeed what happened.</p>
                <p>I took my leave of them, and although it was by then almost completely dark <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734653"/> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> had long been lit, the older of the gentlemen accompanied me all the way to Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7536"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1719" when="1846-10-27" n="72">Rodgers &amp; Son</placeName></orgName> to fetch the two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> that I had brought with me, forged and tempered from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>. They had turned out splendidly, and I gladly paid the 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> due for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">grinding</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polishing</term> of the blades and for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9023">ivory</term> cases. Mr. T. even accompanied me to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1846-10-27" n="73">inn</placeName>, where I began packing for the following day.</p>    
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–Liverpool, 28 October 1846</head>
                <p>Wednesday, <date when="1846-10-28">October 28th</date>. This morning I left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1846-10-28T09:00:00" n="74">Sheffield</placeName> on the 9 o’clock <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-471" when="1846-10-28" n="75">Manchester</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The countryside between Sheffield and Manchester is rather like <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> in some places, being most similar to the hills of <placeName ref="gfa-places-78">Thurgau</placeName> or the lowlands of <placeName ref="gfa-places-494"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2229">Appenzell</placeName></placeName>, except that one does not see so many fruit trees. An example of the goodwill typically extended to foreigners here cannot go without mention: I had ordered a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term> at my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">lodgings</term> prior to my departure, which was not brought to me straight away. But knowing that the stations in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are very strict timekeepers and that I would have to wait another three hours for the departure of the next train, I became uneasy on account of the delay. Noticing this, a gentleman whom I had never seen before, readily ceded to me the coffee and bread and butter that had already been served to him. I accepted them gladly and would indeed have arrived at the station too late, had I not done so. — I arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1745" when="1846-10-28T13:00:00" n="76">Liverpool</placeName> at around <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734654"/> 1 o’clock and took a room at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2202" when="1846-10-28" n="77">Adelphi Hotel</placeName>. Though I have not seen all the hotels in England, that this is one of the finest, at least from the outside, I am sure no one who knows England would dispute.</p>
                <p>When, soon afterwards, I walked to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2203" when="1846-10-28" n="78">the large iron and steelworks</placeName></term></term> of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7861">Horsefall &amp; Comp.</orgName>, which is 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> from the hotel, I had to marvel at how fine a city Liverpool is compared to many another city, <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> included. This was most apparent in the splendid shops along its straight and wide streets, which also had very wide pavements. Even down at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2011">Mersey</placeName>, the banks of which form the port of Liverpool, they take their place among the countless magazines of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">cotton</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">timber</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-109">Norway</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-145">South America</placeName> and all sorts of other goods etc. Liverpool might almost be viewed as even more a world port than London, and that the first railway for passenger traffic in England was built to connect Liverpool and Manchester makes perfectly good sense, when one sees the merchandise of all kinds and incredible stockpiles of cotton stacked up here.</p>
                <p>One circumstance I must mention, if only to show how cheaply a person who cares nothing for society’s expectations can live here in England, is as follows: <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734655" break="no"/> Because Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8340">Horsefall</persName> was not at home and I was minded to wait and go back again later, I entered a so-called “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Eatinghouse</term>” on the banks of the Mersey, where for the same spread as I had previously enjoyed in London, namely roast beef, potatoes and some vegetables as a side dish as well as bread and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale</term>, which incidentally was the best that I have ever drunk in England, I had to pay just 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, or 27 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreuzers</term>, whereas at my lodgings in London, and other hotels as well, it would have cost almost five times that amount.</p>
                <p>My second attempt to meet Mr. Horsefall having likewise failed, I returned to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2202" when="1846-10-28" n="78.1">my lodgings</placeName> and concluded the day with a letter <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName> and to London.</p>    
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Liverpool’s maritime ironworks, 29 October 1846</head>
                <p>How fortunate many an author wishing to write but finding nothing to write about would consider himself, were he accorded experiences such as I have had <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745"><date when="1846-10-29">today</date></placeName>! Of course I can say this only in relation to those objects that are most of interest to me, though there is always something to discover.</p>
                <p>As I had a journey of 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Engl. miles</term> to Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7861">Horsefall</orgName>, I set off from the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2202" when="1846-10-29T08:00:00" n="79">Hotel Adelphi</placeName>, where I am currently residing, shortly after 8 o’clock, which admittedly is quite early for <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, especially at this time of year, and walked down to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2011">Mersey</placeName>. What I noticed first, which having taken a different route through the town I could not have seen yesterday, <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734656"/> was an uncommonly long <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2205" when="1846-10-29" n="80">building</placeName>, right on the river, which was open on both sides and had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9426">slated</term> roof supported by iron pillars. I counted 52 such pillars, each of them spaced 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> apart, making for a total length of nearly 1,000 feet.<note>Probably <placeName ref="gfa-places-2205">Salthouse Dock</placeName> Warehouse. Fischer’s description might also refer to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2236">Royal Albert Docks</placeName>.</note> The breadth or depth from the street to the walled-up riverbank was 50 feet. The prodigious quantity of commodities from the in-coming and out-going ships, whose masts alone turn the harbour into a dense forest, that are handled here cannot be imagined by anyone who has not seen it with his own eyes. Lining the road, which to judge by its direction would have led to Messrs. Horsefall eventually, were various <term ref="gfa-keywords-1405">iron foundries</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8796">anchor</term> and chain smithies and other such suppliers of marine equipment, though they all had signs on the factory door saying “No admittance except on business”, as is commonly the case in England.</p>
                <p>On passing one <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2204" when="1846-10-29" n="81">anchor and chain smithy</placeName> that happened to be open just then and which above the sign on the door bore the flourish of its owners <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7778">Bettely &amp; Roberts</orgName>, I could not resist standing in the open doors, which were separated from the workshops beyond by a vestibule, in order to observe the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term> at least from a distance. A gentleman I took for the master came out of a side building soon afterwards.</p>
                <p>Taking a chance, I went up to him and asked <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734657"/> whether I might be permitted to view the works? — I was from <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, I told him, where we were not in a position to do such work. — “By all means”, he replied. “Just come along with me.” — We entered a veritable <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcan’s</persName> forge of a place, in which I counted 16 furnaces for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">forging</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8796">anchors</term> and ship’s chains out of heavy <term ref="gfa-keywords-8539">blooms</term> in the first case and <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">rolled</term> rod iron in the second. The weight of the anchors, which for the larger ships can be several thousand pounds, is well known – if only our political <term ref="gfa-keywords-9621">world-improvers</term> in Switzerland had had it in their power to have such an anchor forged to hold fast our storm-tossed Fatherland in these turbulent times! I thought to myself – though what is not so well known is how long and how heavy an anchor chain such as the one then being made has to be. — Mr. Bettely told me that it has to be 300 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8604">yards</term> or 900 feet long! I measured one <term ref="gfa-keywords-9857">link</term> and found it to be 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long on the inside and furnished with a welded-in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9854">crossbar</term>, which is a <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patented</term> invention designed to lend it extra strength. Each link in this chain, incidentally, was 2 inches thick. I asked him the weight of a single link, and since he was unable to tell me exactly, he ordered such a one to be weighed and found it to be 20 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term>. As 4 links with a total length of 3 feet would weigh 80 pounds, <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734658"/> the weight of the whole chain, even without the anchor, would be 300 x 80 = 24,000 = 240 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> – for a single anchor! They have a very ingenious mechanism with which to make these links as fast and evenly as possible. This consists of a rather large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur gear</term>, driven by a small gearwheel, with an extended axle, onto which is mounted an oval that matches exactly the inside of a chain link. Mounted onto the small gearwheel is a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">mandrel</term> for applying the necessary counter-pressure. The white-hot iron rod is clamped between two such mandrels, and as the distance between them remains the same and only the outline has to change from the short to the long diameter of the ellipse, all that is needed to form the link is a single revolution of the large wheel. The link is knocked off the axle while still warm in order to be welded together and the rod returned to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">heating furnace</term> for reheating ready for another such operation. — This mechanism seemed to me so sensible and time-saving, especially as the machinery, even for large ship chains, can be operated by a single man without much effort, that I believe it might be of benefit to us as well, specifically in those <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-9053">refining furnaces</term> give off a lot of free heat to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9135">annealing furnaces</term>, since it would greatly facilitate the fast and regular bending of even small chains <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734659"/> and could be deployed as an alternative to the time-consuming and uncertain process of hammering on an anvil.</p>
                <p>Arriving at Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8340">Horsefall’s</persName> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2203" when="1846-10-29" n="82">works</placeName>, the younger gentleman was very sorry that his older brother had been taken poorly and consequently detained in the city, and that he himself was on the point of leaving for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName>, though he did appoint another gentleman from the counting house to show me around. We went first to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-121">steel foundry</term> and then to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mill</term> belonging to it. This part of the establishment is not yet very extensive and I saw only a single row of 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">furnaces</term> and just one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> in each, whereas there would have been two in most other works. The crucibles are like all other English crucibles in shape, but <term ref="gfa-keywords-9855">with a thicker base than usual</term>, and since they are made wholly of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2066">Stourbridge clay</placeName></term> without any adjuncts, the biscuit is white, rather like <term ref="gfa-keywords-8446">Selters water pitchers</term>.</p>
                <p>Their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">heating furnace</term>, moreover, was not as well set up as that at Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">Huntsman</persName>. The two hammers, the larger of which is quite weighty and both of which are furnished with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9821">crossfaces</term>, are driven by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>, but have one disadvantage compared to water-driven hammers, which is that neither the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9745">stroke</term> nor the speed <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734660" break="no"/> can be changed fast enough, meaning that the hammer has to be halted first.</p>
                <p>Even more interesting than the steel foundry, such foundries being all exactly alike here in England, as I noted in my earlier journals, were the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9439">forges</term> for large machine parts. Among the many hammers being used there were two in which both head and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9524">handle</term> were cast of a piece, each of them weighing 140 Centner. One of them was just then being used to forge a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">drive shaft</term> for a steam engine on a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">warship</term> of 60 Centner in weight, which of course bears no comparison with the drive shaft of the famous steamship <term ref="gfa-keywords-9814">Great Britain</term> that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9815">just recently</term> ran aground off the <placeName ref="gfa-places-70"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2217">Irish coast</placeName></placeName>, whose drive shaft for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9441">Archimedean screw</term><note>That is, the ship’s propeller. The SS Great Britain was one of the first steamships to be driven by screw propulsion.</note> weighing 340 Centner was likewise made in this workshop, which forged it out of single piece. Many fine things are made on the Continent, too, and even Switzerland, as the least favourable of all the many locations, is certainly in the running in some instances; but the fact remains that it is the English that are setting the pace in greatness and excellence in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term>. I also marvelled at the way the heaviest pieces of iron rod, drive shafts and such like weighing many Centners, some of them tapered, some furnished with attachments, were forged with just the same finesse and assurance as much smaller rods, though of course the potential for mechanisation that is applied here helps <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734661"/> enormously. — The more often I come to England and the more I get to know the English, the more convinced I am that the greatness, wealth and might of a nation, and consequently, as we know from the world of commodities, its happiness, too, are not just a product of the number of its inhabitants, but have to do with moral fortitude, the widespread availability of intelligence, and a reasonable degree of freedom, naturally subject to the laws of the land, since the opposite, whether in the direction of the one or the other extreme, is bound to nullify whatever advantages it might promise. It really is astonishing what these people, who are very few in number even in relation to the population of <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>, let alone that of the whole world, are accomplishing, and how they are able to bring their influence and power to bear everywhere.</p>
                <p>Highly satisfied with everything that I had seen and been, I left <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1745" when="1846-10-29T13:30:00" n="83">Liverpool</placeName> at half past one that afternoon on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1846-10-29" n="86">Sheffield</placeName> via <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-471" when="1846-10-29" n="85">Manchester</placeName>. For reasons unknown to me, we had to wait for over half an hour at the last but one station before Manchester, which I believe is called <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2206" n="84">Parkgate</placeName>.<note>Fischer perhaps means <placeName ref="gfa-places-2206">Parkside</placeName> station.</note> Somehow, probably by means of a “pilot”, (a single <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotive</term> that can travel very fast and can be used wherever there is no <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term>, inclining one to call it the railways’ courier), the stationmasters at the terminus in Manchester had been informed of the problem, because the train <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734662"/> to Sheffield waited until we had arrived before departing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A visit to the works of Cammell and Sanderson in Sheffield, 30 October 1846</head>
                <p>Friday, <date when="1846-10-30">October 30th</date>. Having been preoccupied all morning with writing a long letter and then making a copy of the same, I could not go to the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1720" when="1846-10-30T12:00:00" n="87">works</placeName> of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537">Cammel &amp; Comp.</orgName> until around noon. I had reasons for wishing to persuade them that their installations for the manufacture of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> might be still further improved, and also wanted to inform them of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande’s</persName> letter to me. When they told me they had taken out a <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> on a method of converting iron filings into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, I could not help but smile at the money thus thrown away, remarking that in my experience, quite apart from the fact that the large interstitial spaces between the filings made it virtually impossible to get anything like the necessary weight into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>, they would do well to recall what had happened in my case, for since the iron filings they showed me were already completely rusted, the best outcome they could hope for was <term ref="gfa-keywords-9482">brittle red steel</term>. It is curious how quickly the English resort to patenting. A hundred to a hundred and twenty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term> is the absolute minimum due for a patent, and often one has to fight off legal challenges to boot, which is why it is generally better to keep the matter to oneself.</p>
                <p><pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734663"/> After the long walk from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel’s</persName> steelworks I called in first at <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1687" when="1846-10-30" n="88">Huntsman’s hammer mill</placeName> and then at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1846-10-30" n="89">works of Messrs. T.</placeName></orgName>; but since they were not there, I decided to go to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1846-10-30" n="90"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1677">West Street</placeName></placeName>, which is almost as far away again, to my good friends Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName>, who have the largest of all the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">cast steelworks</term> here. But they were not there either, and as I was told that they do not generally return from lunch until after 5 o’clock, I whiled away the time inspecting some of the lavishly decorated shops, lingering longest at a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee shop</term>, which, much to the delight of spectactors, had a very fine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> set up in front of its large mirror-glass window. This runs all day long, grinding coffee that tumbles down in a prodigious torrent into the large chests below. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">half-horsepower</term> engine with a 3½-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> cylinder and 6-inch piston was running quite fast. The design was that of a so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7523">Watt steam engine</persName></term> that works with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8955">low atmospheric pressure</term>. Estimating that this steam engine, which was exquisitely worked and even had Watt’s ingenious <term ref="gfa-keywords-9612">centrifugal regulators</term> mounted on it, must have cost at least 150, if not 200 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds</term>, one soon gets a sense of all the many things that are speculated on in England. I returned to Messrs. Sanderson after 5 o’clock and as usual was welcomed most warmly. After a long and interesting <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734664"/> conversation concerning our factories, and after they had contemplated with pleasure the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9865">drawing</term> of my works, namely the drawing of the interior of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">my foundry</placeName> during the pouring operation, I had to abandon my plan of departing for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> on the first <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> tomorrow morning, as they were very insistent that I should come to them again next day.</p>
                <p>I returned <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1846-10-30" n="91">home</placeName> through long streets and lanes full of smoke and fog. The route was not unknown to me, but I had gone about halfway when, with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> burning so dimly that they could scarcely be seen at all, I took a wrong turn. I soon noticed, however, and a butcher whom I asked for directions kindly left his shop to accompany me a short way. He was relieved by a labourer walking on the other side of the street, who had also heard my inquiry and offered to accompany me as far as <placeName ref="gfa-places-2207">Angel Street</placeName>, where I was once again on the right path to my lodgings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer loses his way in Sheffield, 31 October 1846</head>
                <p>After viewing a few shops and making some purchases, I went to Messrs. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2096" when="1846-10-31" n="92"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587">Sanderson</orgName></placeName> at 11 o’clock, and there was met by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7538">the younger Mr. Sanderson</persName>, who led me to the works where <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> is <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">rolled</term>, which is a long way from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term>. There, alongside the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9135">annealing furnaces</term> belonging to them, are 11 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mills</term> on which very fine rectangular, flat and round steel is rolled without either pits or burrs. — The English never let a thing go until it is exactly right. From there we went first <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734665"/> to Messrs. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1719" when="1846-10-31" n="93"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7536">Rodger &amp; Son</orgName></placeName>, who had reached a very positive verdict on my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term>, and thence to my <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1846-10-31" n="94">inn</placeName>, where we reached an agreement on a matter that was in part the purpose of this trip.</p>
                <p>Before dinner I went to several more shops, the temptation to buy things that for us are difficult to come by and certainly not as cheap for that quality, being impossible to resist. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">Tea</term> of the finest quality, already weighed into packets that are then glued shut, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9299">measuring sticks</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8848">pencils</term> and various trinkets I just had to have, some for my own use, some as gifts for my own dear ones.</p>
                <p>After lunch, by which time it was already dark, I went to Messrs. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1721" when="1846-10-31" n="95"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542">T.</orgName></placeName> in order to take my leave of them. Although it was Saturday evening and a great crowd of people had gathered in the vestibule to receive their week’s wages, the younger Mr. T. took me to the works where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">springs</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term> and heavy <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal waggons</term> are rolled. The toe rods are shoved into an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9135">annealing furnace</term> through an opening that is not much larger than the rod itself, and then, once they are hot enough, passed through a pair of eccentric <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">rollers</term>, first from the one side and then the other, so that starting from the middle, where the rod is at its thickest, it becomes ever thinner, after which the other half is rolled out <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734666"/> in like manner. Emerging still warm from the rollers, they pass under the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8661">shears</term>, which clip the springs evenly and exactly at the front, and then under the perforating machine, which punches the holes that the springs have to have in order to be mounted. Next to this is the proving machine, which tests the quality of the springs after they have been bent and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">tempered</term>. This machine consists of a perpendicular <term ref="gfa-keywords-8878">screw</term>, which at the top is fitted with a rather large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur gear</term>, which, driven by a small gearwheel, produces the very slow motion that turns the screw as well. The rotating screw is pressed down on the middle or the thickest part of the spring, which has previously been laid in an iron trough and coated all over in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">oil</term>, for as long as it takes for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9856">spring</term>, which hitherto had a bend of 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>, to be pressed flat onto the sole or floor of the trough. Once the screw has been raised and the spring, now bent again, has been taken out, it is lain between two pins, which to prove that it did not yield, did not break, it has to touch at either end.  One of the proven springs, made of 15 lamina and measuring 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> end to end, had a curvature of 5 inches and at its thickest point in the middle was 4 inches thick. The other spring had 20 lamina, was 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term> long and <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734667"/> 5½ inches thick in the middle, and had a bend of 9 inches. This is all the work of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high-pressure machine</term> of just 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> with a pressure of 45 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> per square inch, whose cylinder measures just 10 inches across.</p>
                <p>This morning I had to wonder at how little worn the Sandersons’ <term ref="gfa-keywords-2750">boilers</term> seem to be and was told that one boiler attached to a 34-horsepower <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> typically lasts 10 years.— We then went to the shop where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> are tempered. Their method of tempering files to straighten them differs completely from my own in respect of the liquid that is used for this purpose, while the means by which we each enhance the effect of the liquid are very similar. In these factories, too, they have discovered that when two files of the same weight and same length are tempered, of which the one is rectangular and the other flat, it is the rectangular one that is liable to crack, whereas the flat one will remain whole. — The grounds for this phenomenon have not yet been ascertained, and Mr. T. said that while an astonishing number of files used to crack even as recently as seven years ago, this no longer happened.</p>
                <p>I felt their tempering water in a large stone trough and would say that it was 15 to 18° <persName ref="gfa-actors-7935"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8567">Reaumur</term></persName> above 0. The additive they use to make the same more potent, moreover, was revealed to me the instant I tasted it, and is an entirely sensible choice of medium.</p>
                <p><pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734668"/> It was very dark when I went home and I again lost my way amid the eternal fog, in which this whole island is so unrelentingly enshrouded at this time of year. But there being more than enough people still out and about, I was able to obtain directions a-plenty; for to have an idea of what such a factory town in England is like on a Saturday evening when the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">common sort of people</term> have just received their hard-earned wages, one really must have visited such a one in person. Those blessed times when one can fill one’s pipe and light it from time to time such as one has with us, and elsewhere, too, seem not to exist at all over here; nowhere do people with some business to be about, be it high or low, work harder than they do in England. The butchers and bakers are all but besieged and all the passable streets lined with long rows of grocers’ carts.</p>
                <p>Potatoes, which are such an important staple for all households here, are stacked up very exactly according to size and variety; and although they are sometimes sold by quantity, it is more often by weight. There is almost no branch of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> that, assuming it is not already indigenous, the English do not appropriate for themselves, as long as the pursuit thereof seems promising. I had not known until now that England produces <term ref="gfa-keywords-9126">painted glass</term>. But now that the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7381"><placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Emperor of Austria</placeName></persName>, through the artist <persName ref="gfa-actors-7906">Mon</persName>, and the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7515">King</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavaria</placeName> <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734669"/> in his own lands have afforded this ancient art form such support, causing it to rise again like a phoenix out of the ashes, one sees some very pretty things made by so-called “glaziers” here in England, too. I bought a few items, namely the red ones that were valued so highly by the ancients, and then some glasses with added ornaments, all of which were extremely cheap.</p>
                <p>Arriving late at my <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2143" when="1846-10-31" n="96">lodgings</placeName>, I busied myself with a report to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8304">Geological Society</orgName> concerning the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> of a new <term ref="gfa-keywords-9025">rock drill</term> consisting of a hollow cylinder, which instead of a chisel bit or monk’s hood, is fitted with a toothed crown bit, which was to be presented at yesterday’s meeting.</p>
                <p>According to this report, it now takes 22 days to drill down to a depth of 500 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, which using the old method would have taken more than a year. The power of the water squirted into the hollow tube drives the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8853">mud</term> up to the surface of the borehole, while the drill itself is unscrewed only when the bit has to be resharpened or replaced by a new one. Something that has attracted considerable attention, and in some quarters concern, over these past few days is the formation of a “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9443">protection society</term>” by <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term>, actually the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlers</term> who are so uncommonly numerous in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, from several different works. The purpose is to force factory owners to pay them higher wages <pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734670"/> in opposition to that protection society that the masters and capital investors in the factories have set up to shield themselves against excessive demands on the part of the workers. This latter society sometimes has less of a say in England than elsewhere, for the law, which counts for so much in these parts, is applied without mercy whenever things are taken to an extreme. My business here concluded just as I wished, I shall leave Sheffield tomorrow, God willing, though the image of this most industrious and hence wealthy city will certainly not leave me so soon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–London, 1 November 1846</head>
                <p>I left on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1265" when="1846-11-01T08:30:00" n="97">Sheffield</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> at half past eight in the morning. Just as Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName> had predicted, when I told him yesterday of my intention to depart today – “You’ll be creeping along on the road all the day” – the train’s many stops meant that I did not arrive in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1846-11-01T19:00:00" n="98">London</placeName> until 7 o’clock in the evening; and for the greater part of the day, which was in any case almost entirely swathed in fog, I had only myself for company, with the exception of just one gentleman with whom I was able to converse on literary matters for a while. The other passengers were travelling only from one nearby town to another, having had no time to do that during the week, and hence were constantly changing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Technical spectacles at the Polytechnical Institution, 2 November 1846</head>
                <p> I could not possibly leave <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> without once again going to <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734671"/> the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2140" when="1846-11-02" n="99">Polytechnic Institution</placeName>, which always has much that is of interest to me. — An <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> took me to that faraway place for just 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> (18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>).</p>
                <p>The two exhibits that laid claim to my attention <date when="1846-11-02">today</date>, among many other things, were the experiments with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9556">diving apparatus</term> and the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9340">dissolving views</term>”, which in German are inaccurately called <emph rend="italic">Nebelbilder</emph> [“fog pictures”]. — At the rear of the ground-level hall is a walled-in basin of 20 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in diameter and 14 to 15 feet high, which is filled with clear but greenish-tinged water to give it the appearance of seawater. Floating on this ocean was a ship of about three foot in length and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9747">fully rigged</term> etc. just like a large one. When, as a result of the movement of the water, it approached within a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8493">fathom</term> of the edge of the basin, a small, finger-sized, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7780"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve rocket</term></persName> was fired at it, and after passing through wind and water as they say, that is, skimming the surface of the water or a little below the same, pierced the side of the ship so that the water immediately gushed in. As on a large ship, the irregular motion resulting from the uneven filling of the vessel made it keel over until it was lying on its side and presently sank. — Then came the <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734672"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9555">diver</term>, clad entirely in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9556"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">suit of India rubber (“caoutchouc”)</term></term> and on his head an iron helmet with glass windows in front of the eyes. Screwed onto the helmet were two tubes or hoses, also of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">Gummi elasticum</term>, one of which was connected to a suction and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2607"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8978">pressure pump</term></term> consisting of three cylinders (to produce an even air current) set up outside the basin, while the other poked up above the surface of the water. With two men working the pump, one of these tubes supplied the diver with a steady stream of fresh air inside his helmet, while the other discharged the exhaled air. Weighed down with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> weights, the diver descended the iron ladder down to the bottom of the little ocean, and there threaded a thin rope under the hull of the ship, which he then secured in several places. He then climbed up out of the water several times and each time was given several sealed and thin-walled copper canisters, representing buoyancy barrels, which with some difficulty he attached to the rope on either side of the ship. No sooner had he attached the last pair of these than, to the jubilant applause of all those present, the ship rose majestically to the surface and sailed on its way as if nothing had happened. — In token of their satisfaction with this successful experiment, those present threw quite a few coins <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734673"/> into the basin, and these the diver carefully picked up off the bottom, thus proving how useful this apparatus is for working underwater, even at great depths, he having been able to remain there for more than a quarter of an hour.</p>
                <p>Leaving the basin, I went next to the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9340">dissolving views</term>”, the demonstrations of which began immediately afterwards. The completely dark <term ref="gfa-keywords-8793">amphitheatre</term> was large enough to hold several hundred people, five hundred according to one gentleman, and at the end facing the seats had a likewise dark wall illuminated solely by a so-called “Campus visionis”, a circle of light produced by <term ref="gfa-keywords-9825">hydrogen-oxygen gas</term> of a brightness akin to sunlight. The anticipation of the impending apparitions is very great. The name of the object to be represented suddenly appeared in flaming letters at a door in the background that had hitherto gone largely unnoticed, after which the object itself seemed rather to evolve out of an inchoate muddle of colours, eventually reaching a level of perfection in both perspective and in the modelling of the bodies, such as we are accustomed to seeing in a good panorama. — The first was the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2208">bridge</placeName> and the falls, or rather the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName> being forced through its narrow rocky bed, near <placeName ref="gfa-places-991">Lauffenburg</placeName>. It was drawn after the old, no longer so well-known <term ref="gfa-keywords-9867"><term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">engraving</term></term> by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7898">Chr. v. Mechel</persName><note>Mechel was a publisher of engravings. The engraving was after a work by Benjamin-Rodolphe Comte (1760–1851).</note> in <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734674"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, but on a much larger scale. — I was scrutinizing this image carefully, this being a region I have known very well my whole life long (I first crossed the bridge in <date when="1787">1787</date>, when it was undergoing repairs), when as if by magic it became the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1970">palace of Fontainebleau</placeName> with a gendarme riding around the fountain in front of it. Next time, I thought, my senses, or rather my eyes, would not deceive me, whereupon I fixed my gaze on the black head of the horse and the upper half of the rider alone. But what help was that? A momentary, barely perceptible dissolution of the outlines and – look there! – the horse’s head had turned into the bow of a merchant vessel that was just as black as the head had been, while the rider had become the mast, the fountain the ocean, and the palace itself the port of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2009">Marseille</placeName> with its <term ref="gfa-keywords-9271">lighthouse</term> and multitude of ships. I dispensed with all further investigations and contented myself with simply enjoying the ensuing succession of transformations, which consisted of depictions of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2209">Mount Lebanon</placeName> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-6532"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2090">St. Catherine’s Convent</placeName></term><note>St. Catherine’s Monastery is actually on <placeName ref="gfa-places-2091">Mount Sinai</placeName>.</note>, the inside of that church and a procession, then the salt desert, then a royal burial at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2064">St. Denis</placeName>, then an <placeName ref="gfa-places-67">Indian</placeName> temple and ruins etc., and then, as a finale, the most magnificent display of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8863">fireworks</term>, albeit without fire. The principal fire wheel must have been 18 to 20 feet in diameter. Moving inside the same, though in the opposite direction <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734675"/> were still more fireballs in the most beautiful and striking colours, either spraying sparks and flames or attracting sparks from the periphery to the centre, where they were swallowed up as if in an abyss, until suddenly, the inchworming <term ref="gfa-keywords-9193">microbe-like</term> movements ceased, leaving only a many-splendoured wreath, inscribed in the middle of which, in golden letters, were the words: “<orgName ref="gfa-actors-8341">Polytechnical Institution</orgName>, founded in the Year 1837.” Darkness then returned and loud and sustained applause told of how pleased the spectators were with what they had just witnessed.</p>
                <p>These are the advantages for those desirous of learning for which the practical sciences offer such vast scope. For just 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term>, or 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>, one can spend half a day here and from the specially deployed and rigorously instructed attendants learn whatever one wishes to know about the scientific and practical aspects of the various exhibits, which incidentally are numbered according to a catalogue. Nor is that all, for the institution has also hired properly salaried professors whose task it is to hold daily lessons or lectures, which anyone who has paid his one shilling admission may attend; on the morning and afternoon of the day of my visit, for example, the subject was the electrical <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">telegraph</term>, that most curious monument to the inventiveness of our age, <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734676"/> to facilitate a better understanding of which there were demonstrations in small and so-called “working models”.</p>
                <p>As I already mentioned, one might linger here for days and still not get to know all, or, I might say, even the most interesting, of this vast compilation drawn from all the many different branches of human knowledge, since the collection itself comprises over 2,000 exhibits, and if the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9363">physicist</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">mechanical engineer</term> marvel at <persName ref="gfa-actors-7914">Napier’s</persName> new <term ref="gfa-keywords-8813"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9820">printing press</term></term> and the astonishingly powerful <persName ref="gfa-actors-7739"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9819">hydro-electric machine by Armstrong</term></persName>, by means of which steam brought to a head and forced through narrow nozzles to subject it to extreme friction develops a mass and intensity of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">electrical</term> “fluidum”, as also the largest electrostatic generator hitherto known to man, then the physiologist and anatomist will undoubtedly find much to please them in contemplating the two, uncommonly large-scale models (144 times their natural size) of our two most excellent organs of sense, namely the eye and the ear, which can be taken apart to reveal their hidden-most parts and the nerves connected to them by which we receive even the tiniest impressions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer picks up his photographs and meets a new travelling companion, 2 November 1846</head>
                <p>After quite a long sojourn in this most interesting <placeName ref="gfa-places-2140">place</placeName>, I had just enough <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734677"/> time to go to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2170" when="1846-11-02" n="100"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName></placeName> to fetch the coloured <term ref="gfa-keywords-8934">Daguerrotype</term> and the photographic drawings in order to have everything ready for tomorrow afternoon as the time of my departure for home. — The coloured Daguerrotype and my own <term ref="gfa-keywords-2762">portrait</term> were already finished and have turned out very much to my satisfaction. — Had a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9371">portrait painter</term> of old, I am thinking namely of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7941">Rubens</persName>, famed for his diligence and veracity, seen such a portrait but not known how it came about, he might well have imagined the painter to be some otherworldly being, seeing how far the forces and effects of nature outshine all that is made by human hand. — As to the photographic positive printed on so-called “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9348">energiatype paper</term>” showing the inside of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9865"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">my steel foundry</placeName></term>: the negative had come out quite well despite the persistent fog, for given the dull and damp weather, he had given me but little hope of success.</p>
                <p>At 5 o’clock, after leaving Mr. Croucher and calling on Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2201" when="1846-11-02" n="101"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</persName></placeName> on account of some business matters, I again went to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-11-02T17:00:00" n="102"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im Thurn</persName></placeName> that I might travel with him to his home in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2210" when="1846-11-02" n="103">Dulwich</placeName>, which is an uncommonly well situated manor house surrounded by parks, gardens and fields belonging to the estate, some 5 to 6 miles from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2231">City</placeName>, that is. His very amiable <persName ref="gfa-actors-8327">spouse</persName>, <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734678"/> who besides being the mother of four pretty children was very pleasant to talk to, had two Misses Fillis as guests, one of whom Fate had decreed to be my <persName ref="gfa-actors-8305">travelling companion</persName> all the way back to <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>. The said lady had already written to me in both English and French from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, whereupon I had duly answered her in both languages so that all that remained for us to agree regarding my itinerary, which I had planned with a view to speed and from which I had no wish to depart, was the time and place of our meeting on the morrow, which was set for 4 o’clock at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">St. Pauls family Hôtel</placeName>. — Lively table talk made the time fly so fast that I might almost have had to walk all the way back to London. Mr. Im-Thurn, however, among the many other favours he showed me, was so kind as to accompany me the circa 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2211" when="1846-11-02" n="104">Denmarkhill</placeName>, where I was able to catch one of the last <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> back to the City. This took me as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2212" when="1846-11-02" n="105">Grace Church Street</placeName>, whence I could walk what, for London, was the relatively short distance to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1710" when="1846-11-02T22:00:00" n="106">my lodgings</placeName>, where I arrived shortly after 10 o’clock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Last errands and departure from London, 3 November 1846</head>
                <p>I had errands to run from 9 o’clock in the morning until 3 o’clock in the afternoon: to Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2134" when="1846-11-03T09:00:00" n="107"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468">Im-Thurn</persName></placeName> and Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2133" when="1846-11-03" n="108"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8262">K.</persName></placeName>, to take my leave of them and to thank them for the many proofs of their friendship, and then to Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7967">Wulliat</orgName>, <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2201" when="1846-11-03" n="110"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</persName></placeName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7804">Croucher</persName> <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734679"/> for business. — At Mr. K.’s I saw yet another patented product that will certainly be very important for some needs. This was a drawn iron tube of 2½ to 3½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter and barely 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">line</term> thick, which showed no signs of having been either <term ref="gfa-keywords-194">welded</term> or soldered. These tubes are very long and seem to be coated with a kind of extremely durable <term ref="gfa-keywords-8490">glaze</term> to prevent them rusting. The tubes of 2½ inches in diameter cost 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> or 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> per foot, while those of 3½ inches cost half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8586">crown</term> or 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 30 kr. Mr. K. told me that it took immense power to draw such tubes.</p>
                <p>At Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2169" when="1846-11-03" n="109">Wulliat’s</placeName> I bought some <term ref="gfa-keywords-9348">energiatype</term> paper as well as instructions on how to use it to make prints and for the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8913">camera</term>” (the English, economical with words as ever, never add the word “obscura”). The preparation is very easy, even though this is the best, that is, the most sensitive, of all the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9808">photographic papers</term>. — Good white paper is washed in a solution of one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">ounce</term> of distilled water with 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8613">grains</term> of succinic acid, 5 grains of sodium chloride and half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9866">drachma</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3522">gum</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1898">arabic</placeName> added. Once the paper has dried again, the one side is drawn over the surface of a solution of 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9866">quint</term> or 60 grains of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9653"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9459">silver nitrate</term></term> in a shallow dish, but in such a way that the other side is not wetted, as otherwise there will be stains. The paper <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734680"/> is then left in a dark place to dry completely, whereupon it is ready for use. Up to this moment, however, it must be kept covered so as to shield it from light at all times.</p>
                <p>As Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7804"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2170" when="1846-11-03" n="111">Croucher</placeName></persName> had feared, the positive picture, which admittedly was very large, did not turn out well in every respect, only since it was not in his power to remedy that, I could not say anything myself. We departed <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-89" when="1846-11-03T17:00:00" n="112">London</placeName> at 5 o’clock and arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1608" when="1846-11-03" n="113">Dover</placeName> at 9 o’clock, where I wrote up my notes of all that happened today.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Dover–Schaffhausen, 4–8 November 1846</head>
                <p><date when="1846-11-04">November 4th</date>. We sailed for <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1625" when="1846-11-04T14:00:00" n="115">Ostend</placeName> on the Royal Mail <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Steamship</term> <emph rend="italics">Queen</emph> at half past nine in the morning, high tide having not arrived any earlier. The weather was very unpleasant, though notwithstanding the same, we arrived shortly after 2 o’clock, and at 3 o’clock departed on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2007" when="1846-11-04" n="116">Malines</placeName>. En route I was again given reading matter, just such a <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8252">tract</orgName> as the one given me the previous year, which I mentioned in my <ref type="cross" target="../1845/3">travel diary</ref>. (If I am often singled out for this particular happiness, then doubtless because the one or the other such lady seems to have an inkling, for which I give them credit, that I am not yet sufficiently converted and hence am in need of such like.) This one, however, was so insipid and written in an idiom so common and so unworthy of the seriousness and, I might add, guilty reverence <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734681"/> of the subject matter that after reading around half of it, I was glad of the onset of twilight and the opportunity afforded me of returning it without being impolite, for one should not read such stuff merely to laugh at the ridiculous comparisons – “the Saviour knocks on the sinner’s door”.</p>
                <p>In Malines we had to make the journey from the station to the town on foot, in the course of which I had the misfortune to stumble over an iron threshold under a gate, which in the darkness was barely visible, as a result of which I acquired a by no means trivial contusion on my left knee and left side.</p>
                <p>Thursday, <date when="1846-11-05">November 5th</date>. Owing to my contusions on the one hand and a minor happenstance with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> tickets that was resolved only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2071">Vervier</placeName> on the other, the work of conversion, which was not going well at all, was suspended for the whole of the day, which began with our departure from <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2007" when="1846-11-05T08:00:00" n="117">Malines</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cologne</placeName> at 8 o’clock in the morning. We arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-82" when="1846-11-05T20:00:00" n="118">Cologne</placeName> at 6 o’clock and went to visit the world-famous Mr. <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2213" when="1846-11-05" n="119"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7828">Farina</orgName></placeName>, whose water washes away more <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> than did <placeName ref="gfa-places-2184">Pactolus</placeName> for the Ancient <placeName ref="gfa-places-821">Greeks</placeName>, and of course made purchases of the same. — After supper, we boarded the steamer going up the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName>, where the somewhat excessive care taken with <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734682"/> keeping the ticket safe again caused some trouble, though without any further consequences. The Journey</p> 
                <p>on <date when="1846-11-06">November 6th</date> up the Rhine to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1846-11-06T18:00:00" n="120">Mainz</placeName>, where we arrived at 6 o’clock in the evening, was extremely tedious. Luncheon in the crowded and well-served dining hall went some way towards relieving the monotony.</p>
                <p>We departed <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2006" when="1846-11-06T22:00:00" n="121">Mainz</placeName> on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> at 10 o’clock in the evening and arrived in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1098" when="1846-11-07T06:00:00" n="122">Mannheim</placeName> at 6 o’clock in the morning on</p>
                <p><date when="1846-11-07">November 7th</date>. There we took the 7 o’clock train to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1123" when="1846-11-07T10:00:00" n="123">Carlsruhe</placeName>, where we arrived at 10 o’clock. — Nowhere, I believe, to return to Mainz, is the charge for taking one’s effects on the post coach dearer than on that short stretch from Mainz to Mannheim. If I am not mistaken, my travelling companion had to pay between 6 and 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term> for her two cases and two night bags, while I was charged 54 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> for my little valise, for which I had not been charged anything anywhere else. — After visiting Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547">Kessler’s</persName> <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8336"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1722" when="1846-11-07" n="124">establishment</placeName></orgName> in Carlsruhe and the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1682" when="1846-11-07" n="125">mint</placeName>, where I accepted orders for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">punches</term>, we departed on the 3 o’clock train to <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1122" when="1846-11-07T19:00:00" n="126">Freiburg</placeName>, where we arrived at 7 o’clock in the evening, finding good lodgings at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1713" when="1846-11-07" n="127">Engel</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Sunday, <date when="1846-11-08">November 8th</date>. We set off on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> from <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/27734683"/> <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1122" when="1846-11-08T04:00:00" n="128">Freiburg</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> at 4 o’clock in the morning. We had only one travelling companion, a native of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-132">Black Forest</placeName> who has a place in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and who accompanied us only as far as <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1620" when="1846-11-08" n="129">Höllsteig</placeName>. He listened politely to our theological discussions, since my travelling companion was not always of the same opinion as me, until I began speaking to him in German. We breakfasted in <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-1619" when="1846-11-08" n="130">Lenzkirch</placeName>. The time passed quickly. At 2 o’clock I delivered up <persName ref="gfa-actors-8305">Miss Fillis</persName> to <persName ref="gfa-actors-8306"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7968">her people</persName></persName> at the <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2214" when="1846-11-08T14:00:00" n="131">Campagne Berbice</placeName> safe and sound, and then hurried off <placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-131" when="1846-11-08" n="132">home</placeName> to my dear ones, thanking Providence for having afforded me a safe journey.</p>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>