<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="4">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1825–1827</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Fragments from the diary of three journeys to London and various factory towns in England in autumn of 1825, 1826, and 1827.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <lb/>
                <byline>By <docAuthor>Johann Conrad Fischer</docAuthor>, Lieutenant Colonel of Artillery and Cantonal Councillor. Including lithograph.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Stuttgart and Tübingen, in the J. G. Cotta'schen Buchhandlung. <docDate>1829</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Title page</head>
                <p><pb facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589774"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9841">[title page of the first edition]</term></p> 
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Preface</head>
                <p><pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589776"/><placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" notBefore="1825-07-26" notAfter="1825-10-19" n="1"><anchor/></placeName> The <ref type="cross" target="../1825">journey to England</ref> in <date when="1825">summer 1825</date> was hardly over, when as a result of my interests there, I was induced to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">return</placeName> in autumn of the same year, as well as in 1826 and 1827, likewise in autumn.</p>
                <p>These journeys were solely of a professional nature, however, and I was obliged to devote my attention to business matters given the limited time available to me, <pb n="II" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589777" break="no"/> so that I was not at liberty to pursue those things that were actually of greater general interest. However, those that incidentally to cross my path (and this happens quite readily in England) I did not leave entirely unnoticed. Some public papers took from my correspondence home and from our newspaper, which is also accredited abroad, as an excerpt from my diary, a twice repeated story about the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888">Thames Tunnel</placeName> and one about <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkin's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-2856">siderographic</term> works.<note>A report appeared in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9805">"Allgemeiner Schweizerischer Korrespondent"</term>, No. 80, Schaffhausen, 6 October 1827.</note> Various other things, however, remained intertwined and undisturbed <pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589778"/> with the daily entries that were of interest only to me, since I believed, after allowing myself on more than one occasion to share with the public my notes from previous journeys (albeit only fleetingly), that this fragmentary addendum would not be very suited to protecting me from the unjust reproach of superficiality.</p>
                <p>As all my journeys to this strange island have not been without consequence for me and my endeavours, I hope I will be forgiven for my wish to see this epilogue added to the foregoing.</p>
                <p> <pb n="IV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589779"/> If there is something of value or interest in it, then I may rejoice all the more in the fulfilment of this wish. If this should not be the case, then I hope, nevertheless, that the public, which has received the preceding volumes so favourably, will for the sake of the same also graciously receive this later supplement. —<note>The Journal was published by <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8308">J. G. Cotta'schen Buchhanldung</orgName> in 1829.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>First outing to Woolwich, 19 October 1825</head>
                <p><pb n="1" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589780"/> As I would have liked to visit the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1890">armoury and the workshops</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1889" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-19" n="1.1">Woolwich</placeName>, I endeavoured to obtain a letter of introduction, which Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName>, chemist at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7575">Royal Institution of Great Britain</orgName>, had the goodness to provide me to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7754">Barlow</persName>, professor of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematics</term> at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8321"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1891" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-19" n="2">Royal Military Academy Woolwich</placeName></orgName>, who has made a name for himself with an invention that rectifies aberrations of the magnetic needle even at very high latitudes, making them very reliable. —He received me very favourably. To my chagrin, however, I learned from him that without express permission from the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7755">"Ordonnance-Office"</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, which is presided over by the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7756">Duke of Wellington</persName>, foreigners are not allowed access to the <pb n="2" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589781" break="no"/> warehouses and workshops of this institution.</p>
                <p>I inquired about some objects, recent discoveries and improvements in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3945">arms</term> and material, though without receiving a satisfactory reply. He also told of the use of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion locks</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">rifles</term> and large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9070">cannon</term>, though not convincingly, adding that some of the experiments with them had not been quite so successful.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7754">Barlow</persName> generously offered to show me around, if I came back, though I could not do so before Saturday. I had already scheduled my departure for Friday, but still had time to change it. — We also spoke (for he had also worked in it) about <persName ref="gfa-actors-7460">Leibnitz's</persName> so remarkable <pb n="3" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589782"/> yet largely unknown <term ref="gfa-keywords-8695">Arithmetica binaria</term> or dyadica – so worthy of this able <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematician</term> – and its unique attributes, insofar as in multiplication and division with dyadic quantities or signs, namely the 1 and the 0, one does not need to know the multiplication tables at all, as well as about the striking phenomena in the calculation of square roots, where the same often appears already in the square and can simply be read from it, or rather the root, though the quantity itself requires so many signs to be represented, can be deduced at once. He agreed with my conjecture that with even higher powers, as well as with the progression and proportion calculations, which I never had time to perform, similar strange phenomena might occur. —</p>
                <p>With the promise to return on Saturday, I left for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>, from where a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">coach</term> departs for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-19" n="4">London</placeName> every hour. Owing to the extremely <pb n="4" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589783"/> heavy rain, only two people were in it, which is otherwise very rare, namely a couple who had just been married and were returning to London. — On the way, the bride pulled <term ref="gfa-keywords-9864">sandwiches</term> out of her basket for herself and the groom to eat, and I was obliged to partake of them as well, insofar as the genuine, uncompromising good-naturedness of the English required me to do so. This was not the first time, as something similar had happened to me earlier in an encounter with a respected banker in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1644">Lombard Street</placeName>, who offered me in just such a way half of his buttered bread, which he was holding in his hand when I entered his office, and I could see that he was pleased not to be refused. —</p>
</div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Visits on recommendations in London, 20 October 1825</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1825-10-20">This morning</date></placeName> I arranged for a letter of introduction from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1893" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-20" n="5">Swiss Consul</placeName> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7757">Prevost</persName> to <pb n="5" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589784"/> the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7755">"Ordonnance-Office"</orgName>, which I delivered myself in the afternoon.</p>
                <p>I believe I may ascribe to that circumstance, in part, the contents of the Permission, in which the Commandant was instructed to appoint an officer to accompany me, who was to show me whatever I wished to see. In addition, I received through one of my friends a highly favourable letter to two excellent and experienced officers, Colonel <persName ref="gfa-actors-7835">Fryers</persName> and Major <persName ref="gfa-actors-7880">Lane</persName>. The letter from the "Ordonnance-Office" was addressed to General <persName ref="gfa-actors-7934">Ramsey</persName> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8807">Artillerie</term>. From the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1892" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-20" n="6">"Ordonnance-Office"</placeName>, which is in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1894" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-20" n="7">St. James Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1843">Westminster</placeName>, I made the long journey to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1895" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-20" n="8">City-Road</placeName> to obtain from Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2028" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-20" n="9"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7758">Martineau</persName></placeName> an introduction to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel</persName> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1896">Deptford</placeName>, or actually <placeName ref="gfa-places-1897">Rotherhite</placeName>, by means of which I might obtain permission to inspect the works  for the so remarkable passage <pb n="6" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589785"/> beneath the bed of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, he having made for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel</persName> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2607">water pumps</term> which are being used there.</p>
                <p>Since it was already evening and his associate, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7507" type="met">Taylor</persName>, who is the director of a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel works</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1789">Warwikshire</placeName>, was present, we had an excellent conversation over <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast-steel</term> production, which is also carried out in that works. There, I learned, confirming what I already knew from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName>, that not all types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coke</term> can be used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> and ensuring the quality of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, if the smelting is done in sealed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term>, from which it follows that <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">charcoal</term>, in general, if it is not too expensive, is still the best fuel for this method of production. —</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>The tunnel beneath the Thames, 21 October 1825</head>
                <p><date when="1825-10-21">Today</date> I was at the so-called <placeName ref="gfa-places-2111" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-21" n="10">"Tunnel Shaft"</placeName>, not far from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1896">Deptford</placeName>, about 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589786" break="no"/> down stream from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName>, which serves as the entrance to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888">tunnel</placeName> running under the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>. As many remarkable objects as I have had occasion to record in my diary this visit, few seem to me of such general interest. The purpose of this construction is to establish a land connection between the two banks of the Thames by way of a road beneath the river, even further down than has ever been done before, without hindering navigation on the river, for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> is expanding further and further in all directions. The bold idea of a subterranean road has been attempted several times, but never successfully. Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7916"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7771" type="met">Brunel</persName></orgName>, known for his mechanical genius, has now been entrusted with the task of solving this monumental and highly complex problem, and it is highly probable that he will succeed.</p>
                <p><pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589787"/> A tower 90 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high, measured on the inside, and 50 feet wide, with walls 3 feet and 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> thick, is now partially <term ref="gfa-keywords-9082">sunk into the ground</term> and partially above. I say partially sunk, for in the beginning the tower was built on level ground and, as it would have to reach a height of 40 feet (that is how deep, namely 38 to 40 feet, it was known from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8663">mining drill</term> that loose sand ["moving Sand", as Mr. Brunel called it] was present), to dig beneath its foundation and thus cause it to sink. — The clever method employed for this purpose warrants closer description. A ring or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8698">frame</term> of circular <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast-iron</term> segments, which taper towards the bottom in a sharp, wedge-shaped manner, and thus had the shape and effect of a "Spate", and the diameter of which was, in total, somewhat less than that of the tower <term ref="gfa-keywords-9082">to be sunk</term>, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589788"/> was joined together by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8878">screws</term> and also connected to a flat ring made of 10-inch-thick <term ref="gfa-keywords-8983">oak</term>, on which the first layer of the 3-foot, 4-inch-thick brick wall was placed. Every 4 feet, a wooden ring was inserted, but no longer spanning the entire width of the masonry, and connected to the lower one by perpendicular screws going up through the masonry, so that the entire shield can be considered not only bricked, but also joined by screws. This is the most ingenious idea, which can certainly be effectively applied for other purposes, especially when building with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">bricks</term>. After sinking 40 feet, which happened very uniformly, solid ground was reached, a kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8700">pudding stone</term> or scree mixed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8701">clay marl</term>, so that the shield sank no further. The earth was then gradually removed bit by bit until a depth of 90 <pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589789"/> feet, or 35 feet below the deepest ground of the Thames, was reached, and the foundations laid. This method, together with the use of so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8473">"Roman Cement"</term>, or waterproof mortar, which immediately solidifies in water, made it possible to reach the specified depth, at which the tunnel or subterranean passage, over which flows the tide of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> at a depth of 50 feet, is to be constructed over a length of more than 1200 feet.</p>
                <p>One must see this work, however, to appreciate its magnitude and boldness.</p>
                <p>With Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771">Brunel's</persName> permission (otherwise it is quite forbidden) I descended to the deepest point below to the sump, which continues down 16 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> further, is walled and sealed again with a vault that collects the remaining groundwater flowing into it in canals all around.</p>
                <p><pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589790"/> It was there that I was first able to appreciate the remarkable and almost terrifying uniqueness of this enterprise. The shouts of the workers, the rattling of the chains on the hoists, the hissing of the three pumps of 13, 11 and 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter with a 3-<term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term> piston stroke at twenty times a minute, and the rumbling sound of the scooping and emptying of rubble and building materials into the hoisting troughs, all echoed in magnificent cadences in this immense cylinder. Ninety feet above my head, hovering in mid-air in the centre of the shaft, because it was not possible to give it a stable foundation given the constantly changing depth of the tunnel shaft, on rods and chains running in at an angle from the periphery of the shaft, almost connected to each other, and resting on a frame of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term>, was a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9799"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high pressure engine</term></term>, with 2 cylinders of 12 inches in diameter and a pressure <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589791" break="no"/> of 5000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> on the piston surface (45 pounds per square inch), which very sensibly, so that the perpendicular stroke is carried out completely, have an inclination of 45 degrees to each other, and whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rods</term> turn a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2190">crank</term> with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">spiral shaft</term>, to which the gear for the pump mechanism is attached. The shaft itself, which still protrudes somewhat above the earth, is covered with a lightweight <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName>-style roof. To reach the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-21" n="11">tunnel</placeName> below, which will be built in the next few days, a gently sloping spiral staircase (4½ feet across and 100 feet long) or so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8703">rider's staircase</term> without steps will be installed inside the shaft, which will be illuminated with the beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">light</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8704">oil-gas</term>. Of the construction of this tunnel, I note very briefly that it is accomplished by placing <term ref="gfa-keywords-8845">12 iron shields next to each other</term>, each with 3 stories, so that 3 workers are working on top of each other, <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589792" break="no"/> and thus, a total of 36 men day and night. As soon as another foot has been dug out, which the workers can do in utmost safety, the shields with their protruding cutting edges are pushed forward by screws and the wall immediately bricked behind them as they advance. The tunnel itself spans 33 feet wide and is divided into 2 parts for pedestrians coming and going by a 25-foot-high wall in the centre. It sounded like a fairy tale when, in response to my inquiry, Mr. Brunel told me that the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2111">tower</placeName> had been built in 4 weeks. "Or actually in three," he added, "because we gave it a week to dry before we sank it." Behind this tunnel, another is being constructed, 200 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> wide. The one I describe is for pedestrians only.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Guns and grenades in the Woolwich Arsenal, 22 October 1825</head>
                <p><date when="1825-10-22">This morning</date> I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1890" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-22" n="12">Woolwich</placeName> as agreed with Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7754">Barlow</persName>, <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589793" break="no"/> unfortunately, however, I did not find any of the aforementioned gentlemen there. Some of them were absent entirely, others only for a while. — In the meantime, I presented my "Permission" from the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7755">"Ordonnance-Office"</orgName> to the commandant's office, to which Mr. Barlow accompanied me, and an order was immediately issued to Major <persName ref="gfa-actors-7886">Johnson</persName> of the Artillery, who received me very courteously, to provide me with an escort. An officer (of the guard), who was full of good will but very young, was assigned to me.</p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1567" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-22" n="13"><term ref="gfa-keywords-55">casting house</term></placeName> was our first stop. Just then, there were two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9800">Miller</term><note>The name Miller probably refers to Patrick Miller (1731–1815), joint owner of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8647">Scottish cannon foundry</term></placeName> Carron Iron Works, a pioneer in the development of carronades. However, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7779">Robert Melvill</persName> is regarded as the actual inventor of the carronade.</note> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">twenty-four-pounders</term> in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8705">pit</term> ready to be cast using a new system (which I will describe later); 6 others were being moulded. —</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> of their metal consists, <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589794"/> according to the information I received, of 100 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and 11 pounds <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term>. The casting, or pouring, which I enjoyed, is done through a funnel outside of the mould but tightly connected to it, which on the inside opens into a thin, wide mouth. This device not only allows the metal to enter the mould in perfect purity, but, most importantly, it fills the mould very slowly, given the intense temperature they are able to heat it with.</p>
                <p> — From the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term>, we proceeded to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8854">boring workshop</term>. This deserves no special mention; indeed, it is considerably less sophisticated than some of the newer ones.<note>Fischer is probably referring to the horizontal drillt that was constructed by Jan Verbruggen in 1770. At the time of Fischer's visit, the plant was over 50 years old and was not modernised until 1843.</note> However, I must admit that I have never seen anything more beautifully drilled and turned. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8713">bore</term> of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9800">Miller</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8718">twelve-pounder</term> cannon was polished as if by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8720">goldsmith</term>; its base or bottom formed a hemisphere. — The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8560">touch holes</term> are somewhat less narrow than those of the French <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589795"/> Ordnance, but also of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and screwed in. —</p>
                <p>From the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term>, our tour led us to the small fireworks room, where <term ref="gfa-keywords-9144">signal rockets</term> for land and sea forces are manufactured.</p>
                <p>What impressed me was how the sticks and necks were painted with a quick-drying <term ref="gfa-keywords-8490">varnish</term> to protect them from deterioration and moisture. —As they occasionally make very large, very long-range and high-flying ordinary and radial rockets, the latter emitting 22 pieces, I understood, after seeing everything, how <persName ref="gfa-actors-7780">Congreve</persName> conceived the idea of his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8714">rockets</term> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7781">Shrapnell</persName> of his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8721">grenades</term>. From the fireworks room, we arrived at the so-called "Repository", where all manner of implements of war are on display, some in actual size (such as Congreve's rockets) and some in miniature.</p>
                <p>I was most intrigued by <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589796" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8721">Shrapnell's shells</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve's rockets</term>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8728">machine</term> for mixing the different kinds of powder very quickly and uniformly with each other (the government obtains its powder from seven different <term ref="gfa-keywords-8727">powder mills</term> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-402">Kingdom</placeName>, of which no two kinds are perfectly alike); then to see the most remarkable effect of the explosion of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">gunpowder</term> when enclosed in a mere linen bag and attached to walls, gates, or grates, compared with that of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8729">petard</term>; and then to see a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8730">burner</term>, or "Fire-Ship", as they call it, especially in regard to the fillings and construction, as well as the nature and arrangement of their <term ref="gfa-keywords-8731">sulphur candles</term> (fire-lances).</p>
                <p><term ref="gfa-keywords-8721">Shrapnelle's grenades</term>, of which they have different <term ref="gfa-keywords-8873">calibres</term>, and use them both as a projectile for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8732">howitzers</term>, or in connection with the larger types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve's rockets</term>, <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589797" break="no"/> of which they then form the head, as an explosive weapon, are externally and internally no different from ours, except that the hole of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9146">incendiary tube</term> has a sharp <term ref="gfa-keywords-8779">screw thread</term>, which keeps it from falling out and prevents it from being damaged if it were pounded in, and that the grenade is filled with lead or small iron pellets, and then the spaces between them are filled with powder, before the said incendiary tube is screwed in. According to the experienced and rather communicative artillery man (he was in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-87"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8710">battle of Leipzig</term></placeName> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8733">Waterloo</term> as a gunner for a Congreve <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">battery</term>), the amount of powder in these spaces is sufficient to break the grenade into many small pieces and propel the pellets over a considerable distance.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve rockets</term> stood on a wall in order of size <pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589798"/> from the so-called three-pounders to the thirty-two-pounders, the latter of which, since the corpus or cylinder of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">sheet iron</term> is about 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> long and 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter, is said to weigh about 300 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> when filled. — The 12- to 18-foot-long sticks for the larger rockets were not attached to them, though they were to the smaller ones; all are secured to the case by three iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8734">agraffe</term>. Only the larger types are used to ignite ships and buildings, the smaller ones as offensive weapons against enemy troops, especially <term ref="gfa-keywords-9208">cavalry</term>. The larger ones end in a pointed cone, and the rest of its body, about a quarter of the length of the case down, is perforated all around with holes that are covered with parchment and varnish, from which the inextinguishable <placeName ref="gfa-places-821"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8735">"greek" fire</term></placeName>, as they call it, flows out. <pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589799" break="no"/> — Both from the inside and from two channels or closed tubes running up the side, the fuel is ignited by the "impelling power" just as the rocket approaches its target.</p>
                <p>The medium-sized rockets do not end in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">cone</term>, but in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8721">Shrapnell grenade</term>, of which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9146">incendiary tube</term> protrudes sideways near the periphery of the shell and is also ignited by the rocket's fire, which then has the effect described above.</p>
                <p>The small rockets have a solid iron nose in front, elliptical or almost egg shaped. I have been told that the distance of the trajectory traversed by these rockets is 3000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8604">yards</term> for the largest and 1500 for the smallest, a yard being 3 English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, if their ascent occurs at an angle of 45 degrees.</p>
                <p><pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589800"/> I would have liked to inquire about the inner nature of these, in some cases, certainly very effective and useful weapons of war and about the nature of the priming and propelling composition; only I sensed the risk of it and did not want to deprive myself by asking imprudent questions (the general effects of which I was able to deduce from the characters of my escorts) of the opportunity to perhaps accidentally learn more.</p>
                <p>I mention the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8728">machine</term> for uniformly mixing the various types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">powder</term> supplied by the seven mills of the Kingdom partly because of its simplicity and partly because it shows, as is particularly noticeable in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">our country</placeName>our country, how difficult it is to achieve uniformity in this chemical preparation without such a device. <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589801"/> If one can rely on the results obtained by experiments with regard to firing distances and the tables based on them, this would be most necessary.</p>
                <p>On a frame, in a circle, there are seven four-sided, funnel-shaped vessels, open at the top, each of which ends in a rather narrow tube with a slider at the bottom. These tubes almost touch the upper rim of a wide funnel with a relatively large hole at the bottom, which is angled inside, or rather blocked like a basset, and is rotated by a mechanism. At a single pull, all seven sliders open and, hourglass-like but on a large scale, the powder flows out of the tubes and onto the walls of the circulating funnel, where it falls through the hole in its centre into a large container, a thousandfold, but uniformly mixed with each other in the overall proportions. — <pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589802" break="no"/> All the trials with this type of mixture have given the most satisfactory results.</p>
                <p>The effect of the explosion of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">gunpowder</term> when ignited in large quantities without being enclosed in highly resistant receptacles, astonished me. In a plain <term ref="gfa-keywords-9049">linen</term> bag, 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term> of gunpowder was attached to an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> lattice gate made of round rods at least 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> thick, fragments of which were kept and shown to me, and ignited. The explosion shattered the entire gate and crossbars, while a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8729">petard</term> of the larger kind, previously suspended from the same gate and released, made only a round hole the width of the petard's chamber. — Considering that such a tool, together with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8736">board</term> on which it is tied (not considering the cost), requires six men to carry and hang it, while a single man can easily carry a centner <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589803"/> of powder in a sack and place it anywhere at will, this seems to be a not insignificant contribution to the art of war.</p>
                <p>I was very impressed with the design of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8731">sulphur candles</term> (fire-lances), which act in the place of a fuse for firing the gun, because the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8807">gunner</term> can see at a glance how many minutes one will burn and consequently knows how many he will need for a given purpose, or during a campaign that may last for several hours. The lances are wrapped in white paper and then in equal distances, each equivalent to one minute, wrapped with strips of black paper that have the same width as the white intervals, so that neither by day nor by night can he make a mistake about their duration and can even use them as a sort of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">pyrotechnical</term> clock.</p>
                <p><pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589804"/> There were several other curiosities, which, however, since they are mere curiosities and of no essential use, do not deserve any particular mention. — From my escort, whom I probably kept from lunch, I was unable to learn anything about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">guns</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">percussion locks</term>, except that the trials carried out with them were just as unsatisfactory as with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term>. I believe, incidentally, that the difficulty of modifying the gun material would be greater than the technical difficulty of solving this problem.</p>
                <p>It had been the officer's duty, as I later learned, to escort me to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1903" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-22" n="14">rotunda</placeName>, a good quarter of an hour's walk from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1890">arsenal</placeName>. It is an immensely large model room for both bas-reliefs of fortifications, as well as older and newer instruments of war. He alone made himself known at the <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589805"/> sentinel's room and returned the letter from the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7755">Board of Ordnance</orgName> to me, so that I could present it there myself, which I did, but retained it, since the attendant was only in civilian dress.</p>
                <p>On the road leading there, on the large greens in front of the administration buildings, there was a park with twelve six-pounders and the accompanying <term ref="gfa-keywords-8739">caissons</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8737">limbers</term>. Upon superficial inspection, because I was without escort, I could not perceive any substantial differences in construction from <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">our</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">batteries</term>, except that on each <term ref="gfa-keywords-8737">limber</term> on the right side of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8738">pole</term>, at an appropriate distance from it, there was a shaft attached to the guide, so that the off horse was always in a shaft, of which the pole formed the left arm, while the saddle horse, like any other draught horse, had its left side free.</p>
                <p><pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589806"/> This arrangement must have always been that way, for my escort, whom I had asked earlier whether, since they had the improved <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">batteries</term>, anything essential had been changed in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3274">frames</term> or otherwise, told me expressly that nothing at all had been changed.</p>
                <p>In the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1903">rotunda</placeName>, I was once again particularly interested in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve rockets</term>, of which there is a collection both in actual size and in miniature models, together with their <term ref="gfa-keywords-3274">frames</term>, which have been modified from time to time in their fittings and which simultaneously serve as directional tools. Of the large rockets I mention nothing more than the still visible effect of a so-called three-pounder. At a distance of 1500 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8604">yards</term>, it accidentally hit a square oak column 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> thick. It penetrated it completely, but remained stuck there, as the back end had been blown open and was therefore wider. <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589807" break="no"/> There I discovered that there must have been a paper case in it, or rather that the paper rockets are inserted into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">sheet-iron</term> cylinders. I asked the guard if this was the case with all of the rockets, which he answered in the affirmative. This seems to me not entirely irrelevant to understanding their production.</p>
                <p>As I conversed with the guard about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3274">frames</term> for these rockets, a man dressed in civilian clothes, but by all appearances a respectable military officer, approached me and asked very politely if I was Lieutenant Colonel <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName>; I said: yes. Did the officer who was with you at the arsenal not accompany you here? — No. — I am sorry about that; however, he added, introducing himself, this gentleman, pointing to the guard, will show you everything you would still like to see. — It was nearly evening. I stayed, as long as possible, at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8903">rocket frames</term>, <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589808"/> then at an ambulant saddlery and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9793">gunsmith</term> workshop, which is admittedly better suited for the steppes and wastelands of distant parts of the world than for our inhabited region, but which was very ingenious and functional. The frames for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8715">Congreve rockets</term> have limbers and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8739">caissons</term> similar to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term>. The rockets are inserted into these into perforated boards, just as the infantry cartridges were once inserted into the pouch timbers. The poles are tied together below the axis and attached to the same. The frame itself is a false bottom, resting on the axle, and is made of strong planks. In two types of these frames, one has semi-circular and the other triangular <term ref="gfa-keywords-8740">fluting</term> with the tip pointing downwards, but in the third there are <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> tubes that can be placed vertically or in a pyramid shape on top of each other or horizontally next to each other, into which the rockets are then inserted and in most cases fired simultaneously. <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589809" break="no"/> This latter type is the most sophisticated, if only because the sticks are no longer attached to the side, which had made the centre of gravity lie outside the axis of the rocket and consequently also outside the line of direction. Even more sophisticated still, they are now bolted to the solid base and in the centre of the rocket on whose circumference 6 vents are drilled, through which the ignited charge flows out. —For certain purposes, there are also extension tubes to lengthen the centre tube and thus obtain even greater accuracy in hitting the target. Pleased, but not satiated by what I had seen, I walked in the dark of night, unmolested, through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1904" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-22" n="15">"Black heath"</placeName>, which is infamous for robbers. I encountered a patrol there that informed me <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589810"/> that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-23" n="18">Dover coach</placeName></term>, in which I had provisionally reserved a seat in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> to commence the journey back to <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">my homeland</placeName>, would soon arrive in the vicinity of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1905" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-22" n="16">"Morden Colledge"</placeName>, where I had intended to board it, which was to be in a few minutes, so that I would have enough time to spare until we reached <placeName ref="gfa-places-1610" type="itinerar" when="1825-10-23T01:30:00" n="17">Canterbury</placeName>, where a dinner awaited us between 1 and 2 o'clock in the <date when="1825-10-23T01:30:00">morning</date>, to admire the extraordinary amount of material, whose storage places and camps collectively, without exaggeration, occupy an area of several <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English square miles</term> at this single location of this relatively small island alone, and the multitude of people that inhabit it and to seek out the causes that made all this possible <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" notBefore="1825-10-23" notAfter="1826-11-30" n="18.1"><anchor/></placeName>.</p>
</div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Family outing to Burma, Egypt and Mexico, 30 November 1826</head>
                <p><pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589811"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1826-11-30">This morning</date></placeName>, after I had visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName> and spent more than an hour engaged in very stimulating conversation with him in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2324">laboratory</term> of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1703" type="itinerar" when="1826-11-30" n="19">Royal Institution</placeName>, during which we discussed, in particular, the nature of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term> and acknowledged the ignorance in which we still find ourselves with respect to them. He attributed the main cause of this to the impossibility, up to now, of separating them into their basic components, and where I, prompted by certain perceptions, ventured the opinion that <term ref="gfa-keywords-8741">hydrogen</term> in solid form plays a great role in them, to which he replied, which characterizes his modesty equally as much as his general amiability, "I see well You are a practical man and the simple observations of such ones will do often more good to society than all our speculations". <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589812"/> After this conversation, my route took me, accompanied by my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">eldest</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">youngest</persName> sons, to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630" type="itinerar" when="1826-11-30" n="20">Picadilly</placeName>, where I passed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8742">Exhibition of Ancient and Modern Mexico</term>, which <placeName ref="gfa-places-2018" type="itinerar" when="1825-11-30" n="21">building</placeName>, in addition to housing these curiosities, also serves as a repository for some <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egyptian</placeName> antiquities, as well as for the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7909"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8743">state carriage of the Emperor of the Burmese</term></persName>, recently arrived from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indies</placeName> and exhibited here, whose significant empire was forced to submit to the strength and intellectual force (to speak figuratively) of a handful of Britons.<note>In point of fact, the First <term ref="gfa-keywords-8744">Anglo-Burmese War</term> was one of the most costly conflicts of the British <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7942">East India Company</orgName>: the British lost 15,000 European and Indian soldiers, and the British government revoked some of the Company's important privileges owing to the high costs of the war.</note></p>
                <p>This <term ref="gfa-keywords-8743">carriage</term> has a house or small tower in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName> style with a roof that gradually tapers and is decorated with bells on the eaves.</p>
                <p>Everything on it is gilded and decorated with (though likely fake or mostly so) <term ref="gfa-keywords-8982">precious stones</term>. In the house itself is the throne, where the emperor sits, which is made of carmoline-red fabric, <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589813"/> decorated with gold fringes and small gems. Two white elephants are harnessed in front of it, and the handlers on top of them. In front, instead of the footmen, there are two magnificent peacocks, and behind them two of his guards, armed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabres</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8972">daggers</term> and spears. The wheels are made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8745">ironwood</term> and the spokes, in contrast to everything else, are <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver-plated</term>. By our standards, the work, as a whole, is artificial, coarse and tasteless.</p>
                <p>What seems to give this carriage even greater value are the 128 windows, or rather inlays of panes or leaves of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8746">rhinoceros horn</term>, going all the way around it, which have had to be made so thin with special techniques to make them transparent.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-3909">music</term> instruments, mostly metallic, are similar to those of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName>, <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589814" break="no"/> including the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8747">"Tam-Tam"</term>, and differ quite a lot from <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">European</placeName> instruments in the nature and character of their sound.</p>
                <p>Even more conspicuously inferior and puerile, in comparison with ours, are their <term ref="gfa-keywords-3945">hand weapons</term>, designed more to shorten the lifeline of one patiently surrendering in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8748">Seraglio</term>, than for safety and protection. — I walked down from there, my mind full of all manner of thoughts, to the room at ground level, which contains old and new <placeName ref="gfa-places-205">Mexican</placeName> curiosities, collected, as it seemed to me, more out of speculation than for the sake of science, by a certain Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7909">Bullak</persName> during and after the reign of the, one might say, ephemeral Emperor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7868">Iturbide</persName>. — In less than a minute, I was thus transported among objects that in part present the most remarkable, and in grey times, of which history gives no account, the clearly most sacred of a country whose inhabitants, one can say <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589815"/> with some truth, are the antipodes of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1901">Burmese empire</placeName>, which was once scarcely known by name in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. — This sudden relocation made a strong impression on me. — So it is given to you, I said to myself, you earnest, industrious and persevering people, from a small point, from your island full of fog, neighbour of old <placeName ref="gfa-places-1706">Thule</placeName>, to cross the globe as if with a span and to accumulate the commodities of all latitudes and all longitudes among you, and then again through the might of your <term ref="gfa-keywords-3945">weapons</term> or through the advantages of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4336">trade</term> and the fruits of your craftsmanship to be known everywhere, or one might almost say to be everywhere at home. And yet, despite your wealth, you have not yet found the Eldorado of true happiness, any more than others. No ship will deliver it to you from a port, if you do not already possess it, and, as it seems to me, life is happier here, <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589816"/> the simple life, in the convivial circle of congenial fellow citizens or in the beautiful valleys or the open mountains, with the sound of the cowbells and the song of the forest, than in your dark, silent state rooms.</p>
                <p>Surveying the whole of the space, the eye is attracted, though not in a very pleasant way, by three central objects: two hideous colossal idols and the famous <term ref="gfa-keywords-8749">Mexican calendar stone</term>, which seems to bear some resemblance to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1924"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8750">Zodiac of Denderah</term></placeName>.</p>
                <p>Looking at the dreadful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9801">idol</term> of the war goddess <persName ref="gfa-actors-7911">Troyamiqua</persName>, 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high, 4 feet in diameter, carved out of grey <term ref="gfa-keywords-8752">basalt</term>, which only the most degenerate imagination could create (the one of her husband <persName ref="gfa-actors-7865">Huitzilopochtli</persName> is missing), at whose feet, however, there is an effigy in relief of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7902">Mietlanteuchtli</persName> (Lord of the underworld); <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589817" break="no"/> looking at it with its double rattlesnake visage and cruel fangs, with its four hands on the chest, a death head beneath, the belt of a cord of rattlesnakes, and the short feet ending in tiger claws; when one considers how many thousands of slaughtered sacrifices bled on their hideous altars heaped with decaying human bones for the sake of religious delusion and the crassest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8751">anthropophagy</term><note>Fischer's description is based on William Bullock's <term ref="gfa-keywords-9804">exhibition catalogue</term>, which also contains this startling image.</note>, and that still under <persName ref="gfa-actors-7908">Montezuma</persName>, the last of the Mexican rulers, as <persName ref="gfa-actors-7801">Cortez</persName> and the companion of his adventures, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7819">Bernal Dias</persName>, tell us: one is inclined to believe that, since these people were not entirely savages, but, as their writing and language, their sciences and arts and buildings testified, possessed some degree of morality, the exertions of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7913">Ahriman</persName> succeeded in extinguishing and destroying the divine spark in the breast of these unfortunates, <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589818"/> and therewith all sense of humanity and feeling for sublime beauty.</p>
                <p>The second idol is a fragment (only replicated in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9123">gypsum</term>) of a rattlesnake, which, since the body measures about 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in circumference, may have been 70 feet high. It is about to devour a beautifully dressed woman, who has already been gnashed and wounded all over by its teeth.</p>
                <p>The inspection of the great <term ref="gfa-keywords-8749">calendar stone</term> is more pleasant. It was excavated from beneath the paving in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2023">Mexico</placeName> in the direction of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2012">Teocalli</placeName> or Great Temple. It is made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8752">basalt</term> rock and has a circumference of about 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, not counting the section of rock that was left raw, and weighs over a hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term>, so that (just as with the <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egyptians</placeName>) one must wonder about the techniques used by the Mexicans to move such weight, <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589819"/> without knowledge of modern tools.</p>
                <p>In the centre of this great stone tablet, which surpasses the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1924"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8750">Zodiac of Denderah</term></placeName> in size, is the image of the sun, whose rays emanate in the direction of all four cardinal points. All around the head are representations of the seasons in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphics</term>, and the outer circle contains the twenty months of the Mexican calendar, each having eighteen days, which in the computation of time, oddly, corresponds with our own, and this by a people to whom the existence of the other three parts of the world was entirely unknown. — Since the use of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> was unknown in <placeName ref="gfa-places-250">America</placeName> before the European invasion, one must wonder all the more about the means by which these people could have shaped <term ref="gfa-keywords-8752">basalt</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8753">porphyry</term>, and even <term ref="gfa-keywords-8982">gemstones</term>, as they wished. — From the realm of nature there is a bit of everything on display, but essentially nothing new or particularly interesting. <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589820"/> The Mexican man who was there from the village of <placeName ref="gfa-places-2025">Chyula</placeName> not far from <placeName ref="gfa-places-2024">Tezcuco</placeName>, in his national costume, together with his hut of cane and its palm-leaf roof, did not leave a particular impression on me. He seemed too European, in my opinion. By contrast, when I viewed the other objects from the three kingdoms of nature, the same feeling pervaded me as when I viewed the magnificent <placeName ref="gfa-places-22"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8754">Brazilian cabinet</term></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>. They were like strangers from another, or older, unspoiled world.</p>
</div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Perkins' Siderogrpahic Institute, 5 December 1826</head>
                <p><pb n="42" break="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589821"/>I went with my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">eldest son</persName> to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName> at his <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7920"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1849" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-05" n="25">siderographic institute</placeName></orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-05" n="24">Fleet-Street</placeName>, after I had visited him in vain the day before at his former <term ref="gfa-keywords-8944"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1850" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-04" n="23" cert="0">steam engine factory</placeName></term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2027" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-04" n="22">Regents-Park</placeName>, where I learned that he had given it up completely and that another owner continues to manufacture steam engines more or less according to Mr. Perkins' system. <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589822" break="no"/> — He was very pleased to see me again in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and we talked for a while about various things, of which he was most interested in the fact that my son had melted pure <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term> in Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7803"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7758">Martineau's</persName></orgName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2028" cert="0">foundry</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1895">City Road</placeName> in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">furnace</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> designed according to my invention, without additives — of any kind — while retaining its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8980">ductility</term> and its capacity not to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">harden</term> when <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealed</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8755">chilled</term> in water. Already last time, I remarked to Mr. Perkins that molten bar iron, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> that barely preceded it, would be very advantageous for him in his siderographic institute, as he would then not have to revert the plates and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">rolls</term> from <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> first and, after <term ref="gfa-keywords-8756">engraving</term>, change them back into steel, but could carry out the latter <term ref="gfa-keywords-8757">cementation process</term> immediately after <term ref="gfa-keywords-2856">engraving</term>. <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589823" break="no"/> Incidentally, I could not help but give his magnificent invention and the establishment founded on it the praise they deserved.</p>
                <p>If you would like to see this establishment, he said, then my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7915">eldest son</persName> will show you and yours around, and as soon as I have finished a letter that I have only begun, I will follow straightaway myself. With gratitude, I accepted this offer, and we climbed a staircase to the room where the print is engraved on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8758">plates</term> on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8759">rollers</term>, and then transferred from them to plates again. This transfer or impression takes place under a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8772">machine</term> that bears some resemblance to our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8760">wine presses</term>, where a weight (the stone) is suspended at one end of a horizontal <term ref="gfa-keywords-8761">wooden beam</term> and, at the other, the point of rest, while the point of force (the point of pressure) <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589824"/> is as close to it as circumstances permit, thus forming, as it is called in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9302">mechanics</term>, a lever of the second order. This is highly sensible, for in this way, the pressure is constant, which would never be obtainable by means of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8763">adjusting screws</term>. The whole machine is of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term>, both the feet and the extremely thick plate resting on it (the whole being the size of an ordinary card table), as is the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8764">pressing beam</term> above it and about six to eight <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> away from it, which actually consists of two pieces or rails running parallel, which, depending on the width of each plate and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">roller</term>, that must press against each other, and on whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">pins</term> it presses, can be moved apart or closer together, so that the upper part of the roller always runs between the two rails. <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589825" break="no"/> From the end of the arm, a rod, which is also slotted around the pivot on which it is suspended, in order to maintain perpendicularity, and which again has new transverse pivots at the bottom, descends, on which pivot a lever of the second order again presses, one arm of which is very long, and on which, as in the case of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8768">Roman balance</term>, a weight of the desired mass is suspended and moved, and thus by the combination of these levers a pressure of several hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term> can be produced, which would be a device worthy of imitation for our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8760">wine presses</term> and would make them cheaper, in some cases more compact and much less dangerous, than with spindle and stone.</p>
                <p>When the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8771">impression</term> is to be made, the engraved and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardened</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8758">plate</term> is placed on the iron table (everything is perfectly smoothed to ensure that both parts lie flat) and the engraved plate is coated with a bit of fine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">oil</term>. The tempered steel <term ref="gfa-keywords-8759">roller</term>, which receives <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589826"/> the engraving that then appears in relief on it, is now placed between the rails of the pressing arm, which are set at a suitable distance from each other, so that they press on the round parts of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">roller pins</term>, and thus the roller itself on the plate, at one end of which the roller is usually placed. On the round pin there is another extension, rectangular, to which a crank of varying length, depending on whether the roller is large or small in diameter, is attached, and when the weight is in proportion to the depth of the engraving and the surface of the plate in its place to produce the required pressure, the crank is slowly rotated and the roller moved back and forth over the plate until the engraving is completely and perfectly transferred. The same procedure takes place when the relief drawing is to be printed on a hardened roller on a plate of softened steel. <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589827"/> As Mr. Perkins was kind enough to have the whole operation performed repeatedly in front of me, I marvelled both at the rapidity and at the immense precision of it, but I marvelled still more at the efficacy of so simple a machine, when he showed me a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8835">medallion</term> about 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter, representing the three Graces, which were not only engraved with uncommon perfection after the well-known antique <term ref="gfa-keywords-8836">cameo</term>, but had a relief on the cylinder imprinted in the medallion, such as I have yet seen on few medallions of the same size, and the possibility of which I would not have believed, without having seen it myself.</p>
                <p>It was a big mistake, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7915">Mr. Perkins' son</persName> told me, that we took out a <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> only on <term ref="gfa-keywords-613"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8758"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardened steel plates</term></term></term> from which to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8771">print</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-2856">engravings</term> and did not extend it to soft ones as well. <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589828"/> We would have made a lot of money with it, as now many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8837">copper engravers</term> are already beginning to use <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> plates, for though they are not hardened, but only in their natural state, they nevertheless provide a far greater quantity of correct and clear impressions than the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> ones. When I asked him how many impressions one could call good were obtainable from a hardened steel plate, he answered: 100,000 pieces; while from a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">copper plate</term>, hardly 600 to 700, and in the strictest sense probably far fewer, can be made completely flawlessly. Once this plate is worn out, however, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8759">hard steel roller</term> can be used as a prototype, and in a moment, so to speak, a new plate can be printed, whereas if it had to be engraved by hand, it might take months to do so, and despite all efforts, it would not be possible to produce a completely identical one. This is an extremely important advantage <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589829" break="no"/> in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9091">production of banknotes</term>, since the most complicated features and the most obscure inscriptions can be imprinted on the first plate, and one can be sure of obtaining identical plates again and again even after the first one has worn out. — He had three commissions for such banknotes, namely from <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Ireland</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">United States</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1828">Calcutta</placeName>.<note>The order came from the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7942">East India Company</orgName>, which had its government offices in Kolkata.</note> The latter were, which Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName> considers an advantage, also printed on the back side, with different colours and in the three languages spoken in <placeName ref="gfa-places-67">India</placeName>.</p>
                <p>From this workshop, we proceeded to the room where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8813">printing presses</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8771">printing</term> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8758">plates</term> or engravings on <term ref="gfa-keywords-5503">paper</term> are located. There are sixteen of them, and all of them were in operation, which seemed to me the most telling proof of the utility and positive reception of the invention. These presses are also very advantageously arranged, and one can assume that half the time or labour is saved in comparison to ordinary presses. <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589830"/> The upper <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">roller</term> is quite a bit larger in diameter than usual, except that part of it has been cut away, so that the remaining round surface in its development or partial revolution describes only a path or line slightly longer than the width of the largest plates, none of which I saw were larger than about 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long and 9 inches wide.</p>
                <p>Instead of the cross-arm handle on the roller of ordinary presses, here there is an iron wheel about five <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in diameter, on the periphery of which are cast handles spaced at intervals, in the shape of elongated <term ref="gfa-keywords-8808">cane tips</term>, only larger and thicker. This wheel is always to the left of the printer, with never more than one man working at a press. Once the printer has positioned the plate, rubbed it with ink, removed any excess, and passed over it with the ball of his right hand, which he rubs each time on a large piece of <placeName ref="gfa-places-48"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8811">"french chalk"</term></placeName> <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589831"/> lying next to him, in order to remove any grease or dirt from the ink in the latter step. He places the <term ref="gfa-keywords-5503">paper</term> on top, the support above it, and while the upper roller grips the plate and passes it through, he turns the wheel as far around as is necessary to complete the impression. Now, he releases the wheel; a weight over a roller, which has been lifted up by the rotation of the wheel, now causes the wheel to rotate through its descent, and consequently the roller in the opposite direction; so, it automatically returns to the worker, who does not move from the spot, the plate and the printed sheet, which he then lifts off the plate and begins his work anew. — A special feature with great advantage for the inexpensive production of inscriptions or labels for goods and factory items, decorative vignettes and other <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">copperplate engravings</term> for books <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589832"/> whose price is to be kept low, as was the case, for example, with "ABC or Spelling books", which I saw there, is that ten, sixteen or even twenty pieces can be <term ref="gfa-keywords-8771">printed</term> on one sheet at a time and then cut out. The original roll, which is printed from the very first small plate engraved by hand, is, in fact, transferred again to a large plate as many times as space permits, so that on a single plate, as I said, there are then ten to twenty quite identical <term ref="gfa-keywords-8756">engravings</term>, and thus as many copies are produced by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8813">press</term> with a single print.</p>
                <p>About the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8803">softening</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8758">plates</term>, of which the largest type is up to one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> thick, as well as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8759">cylinders</term>, some of which crack during hardening, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName> spoke only with great reserve, nor did he show me the workshop where this procedure is carried out. I could not blame him, since perfecting <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589833" break="no"/> this method is a precondition for the success of the whole enterprise, although with knowledge of the nature of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, and as a result of experiments based on experience in this field, the outcome should be the same everywhere.</p>
                <p>We returned to the first workshop once more, and then to the visitors' room. We were still conversing about steam navigation. Mr. Perkins asserted the principle that no <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> of less than forty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term> could be used with advantage on currents, etc., against the current. According to the latest reports, he said, which I have from <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">America</placeName> (he is from <placeName ref="gfa-places-389">New York</placeName>), there have been great improvements in this regard. The weight of the engine and the water in the boiler has been reduced to almost half. In still water these boats cover fourteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> an hour, or seven miles against the current, if the speed of the latter is seven <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589834"/> miles an hour, and the price of such an engine is about forty-one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term> per horsepower.</p>
                <p>As we parted, he mentioned the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> he had made of a new <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metal</term>, the peculiarity of which is that when it rubs against itself or another metal, it requires no <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">oil</term>, but as it heats up, it becomes smoother, so to speak, and lubricates itself. I did not inquire further; however, my belief is that such can be nothing other than highly over-carbonized <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, almost transformed into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8471">graphite</term>. <date notBefore="1826-12-05T12:00:00" notAfter="1826-12-05T19:00:00">This afternoon</date>, by special favour, I also saw in Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7803"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7758">Martineau's</persName></orgName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2028" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-05" n="27" cert="0">"Experiment room"</placeName> the mach<term ref="gfa-keywords-8788">machine</term>ine, so simple and so useful, for making ice on a large scale at any time and in any temperature of room or weather. Twenty of these machines were ready to be sent to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indies</placeName>, and twelve had already left. <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589835" break="no"/> Then in the same room there was a new <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">mechanical loom</term>, on which all kinds of spun yarns, out of which plain or figured materials can be woven. Tired of walking, watching and writing, I will close my notes for today <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" notBefore="1826-12-05" notAfter="1827-09-20" n="28.1"><anchor/></placeName>.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A Victorian ice machine, 5 December 1826</head>
                <p>It is a well-known fact in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> that when the pressure of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8798">atmosphere</term> on drippable liquids is reduced or even completely eliminated, an ebullition or upsurge occurs in them due to the release of the gas or air they contain, as well as sometimes due to the escape of latent heat, and a significant degree of cold develops due to the strong evaporation that takes place under the above circumstances. Furthermore, the rapid and energetic absorption of water and aqueous vapours by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8640">sulphuric acid</term>, when a large surface comes into contact with it, is known from <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term>. <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589836" break="no"/> The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8788">apparatus for the artificial production of ice</term> is based on these two facts, which, as far as I know, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7888">Leslie</persName> first used only on a small scale and for a scientific experiment, but which English industry, always ready to draw on the whole sum of human knowledge and existing experience, has immediately seized upon to produce a device by means of which one can obtain with ease, safety and in significant quantities, in the hottest zones, at any temperature and at any time of the year, the ice that is so desirable precisely in those regions where the locality completely fails its natural extraction and subsequent storage.</p>
                <p><ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/10">This machine</ref> and its effects I had occasion, as I remarked in my sketches of yesterday, to see in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2028" type="itinerar" when="1826-12-05" n="26" cert="0">"Experiment-Room"</placeName> <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589837" break="no"/> of Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7507"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7895"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7803">Martineau and Taylor</orgName></persName></persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1895">City-Road</placeName> by special favour.</p>
                <p>The device is a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term>, consisting of one or two cylinders, located at the edge of a cast-iron plate about 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> long and 2½ feet wide and fitted with a tube running down the middle of it, which is further divided into two right-angled side tubes located one foot behind the mouth of the main tube. The openings of these tubes project about 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> above the surface of the plate or iron table, which stands on four, low, cast-on feet, and halfway up their projection they are equipped with a spigot. Close to the cylinder or cylinders, and on the central main tube, is screwed a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8783"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9176">siphon barometer</term></term>, which, when the machine is in use, indicates the gradual dilution of the air and when the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8781">mercury</term> in both tubes is at a level <pb n="58a" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589838"/><pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589839" break="no"/> equivalent to the complete <term ref="gfa-keywords-8674">rarefaction</term> of the vessels that are attached halfway up the three tubes.</p>
                <p>The operation of the machine is as follows:</p>
                <p>On each of the three tubes is screwed a metal plate provided with a foot and polished perfectly smooth on its surface as usual. Between the plate and its base (which thus acquires the shape of a salver) there is a tube, also equipped with a spigot, the lower mouth of which has a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8779">screw thread</term>, so that it can be screwed onto the tubes which start from the cylinders and, as has been noted, protrude perpendicularly from the iron table at their ends.</p>
                <p>When the plates are screwed on, they are brushed with a thin layer of lard around their circumference in order to obtain a completely airtight seal for the bell jar to be placed on top of them, the frosted rim of which <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589840"/> is also brushed with lard. Before the bell is placed on the plate, a glass basin about 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> wide and 3 inches high, with a completely flat bottom, is placed on top, two thirds of which is filled with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8640">sulphuric acid</term>. Into this sulphuric acid comes a tripod about 5 inches wide, whose ring is of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> and whose feet are of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9861">glass</term>, which carries an almost hemispherical bowl of fired porous and unglazed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term>, which, when about 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> of water are poured into it, is filled to within a finger's breadth.</p>
                <p>Once all of this is in place, the bell jar is put over it, the plate is rubbed gently, the spigots are opened to establish connection between the bell jar and the cylinder, and the pump starts to operate, with caution. <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589841"/> I say with caution and even with intervals of complete motionlessness, for, since the capacity of the cylinder or cylinders is considerably greater than that of ordinary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pumps</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8674">rarefaction</term> proceeds very rapidly, which causes a violent upsurge of water in the bowl, the overflowing of which and falling into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8640">sulphuric acid</term> below must be prevented in every way to avoid damage and danger.</p>
                <p>After about 10 to 12 minutes of working the air pump, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8781">mercury</term> in the tubes of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9176">barometer</term> is almost level, the boiling or escape of the air and water vapours ceases, and before you know it, at lightning speed, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8838">moire</term> of ice covers the surface of the water, which becomes visibly thicker. —Sometimes it happens, and the causes of this are not yet fully known, that, despite the formation of air bubbles <pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589842" break="no"/> and despite the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8783">barometer</term> indicating the presence of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9597">vacuum</term>, the water still does not freeze. To accomplish this, however, a single small blow with the knuckle of the finger on the bell or the plate, in order to give the water a somewhat <term ref="gfa-keywords-8841">oscillating</term> movement, is sufficient to trigger the formation of the ice, which then tends to form in clouds or patches, and does not appear to emanate from a central point. After a few minutes, when the layer of ice has reached a certain thickness, all the spigots are closed to prevent the outside air from entering, the plates are unscrewed and set aside, so that within an hour at the most, all the water in the earthen bowls becomes ice, which is then removed after the spigot between the foot and the plate has been opened and the bell jar has been lifted. The ice contained therein can be used for a variety of purposes.</p>
                <p><pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589843"/> To avoid losing time waiting for the complete transformation of the water into ice, each machine has several sets of plates, bells, etc. As soon as the instruments that were used for the initial stage of the process have been unscrewed and put aside to complete the formation of the ice, the new ones are screwed onto the table and a new process begun with other bowls of water. This makes it possible, according to the information given to me, that a single man can produce 80 to 100 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> of artificial ice in a day and even more. Once again, we see here the bond of the elements separated by art for the benefit of man. To remove the water absorbed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8640">sulfuric acid</term> in the form of steam and make it suitable for new use, the vessels are exposed to a mild heat, preferably the heat of the sun.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>A diagram of Martineau's ice machine</head>
                <p><term ref="gfa-keywords-9840">Skizze der Eismaschine</term> von <persName ref="gfa-actors-7758"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7803">Martineau</orgName></persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Brunel shows Fischer the leak in the Thames Tunnel, 20 September 1827</head>
                <p><pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589844"/> <date when="1827-09-20">Today</date> I went to the subterranean passage, or so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-7622"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1888" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-20" n="32">"Thames-Tunnel"</placeName></term>, which was built beneath the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> somewhat east of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2089">church</placeName> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1897">Rotherhite</placeName> and which has attracted the attention of the entire educated world both because of its bold and massive construction and because of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8844">incident</term> that occurred there. I was all the more anxious to visit it as I had seen the work <ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/4">when it was begun in 1825</ref> and then again in its progression <date notBefore="1826-11-01" notAfter="1826-12-31">at the end</date> of the year <placeName ref="gfa-places-1888" type="itinerar" notBefore="1826-11-01" notAfter="1826-12-31" n="28">1826</placeName>. A boat took me <placeName ref="gfa-places-1897" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-20" n="30">there</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-20" n="29">London Bridge</placeName> in less than half an hour, and, on arriving at the tower or <placeName ref="gfa-places-2111" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-20" n="31">shaft</placeName>, I was delighted to hear that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7771" type="met">Brunel</persName>, whom I know personally, was present. After I had been announced to him<note>In Fischer's first edition, a word was omitted; this was corrected here.</note>, he was gracious enough <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589845"/> not only to allow me to come down to the entrance of the tunnel where I was, but to permit me to cross the barriers about halfway down the corridor in the western part of the tunnel, which normally prevent visitors from going further, and to go to the very back, to the place where the accident had occurred. No one is allowed to go into the eastern part, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railways</term> are located, on which the carts or so-called dogs, pulled by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9799">steam engine</term> installed at the top of the shaft, run back and forth, supplying building materials, clearing away the rubble and discharging the groundwater, which still flows in from the cave-in of the Thames, in channels along the wall. With astonishment and pleasure, I now saw this tunnel, which had been extended across 565 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, by now already beyond the middle of the Thames, and into its greatest depth, not only completely drained of all water, but every trace of the immense quantity of mud <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589846" break="no"/> that had filled it up before tapering out in a downward slope towards the tower or shaft, had been eliminated on the side walls (which shone once again in their original, grey, marble-like beauty). Not a stone, with the exception of the breach, which I will discuss later, was displaced neither in the tunnels nor in the tower, although the water, reaching the level of the Thames, was 70 feet high within it. The same can be said of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8845">36 iron shields</term> (I would call them <term ref="gfa-keywords-8857">testudo</term> of ancient warfare. Perhaps Mr. Brunel got the idea from them), which together weigh two thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term> and are moved gradually forwards by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8878">bolts</term> attached to the walls of the tunnels, which are always bricked closely behind the advancing shield. Three separate ones had sunk a few inches sideways against the breach. When I expressed my wonder at the short time, relative to the event, within which everything had been restored, Mr. Brunel said to me: "Yes, Mr. Fischer, it was no small matter, between thirty and forty thousand cubic feet of water and mud had to be removed; the latter amounted to about a third of the whole; then the hole in the bed of the Thames had to be plugged. The surface area of this, according to the survey made in the diving bell above it, was about 50 square feet, and the depth of it as far as the tunnel was 36 feet." Mr. Brunel attributes the collapse to a strong current on the floor of the Thames itself, which may have been caused by the ships anchored there for a time in two rows. The workers heard the rolling of the debris above their heads, and the water at first seeped only a little between the end of the wall and the iron frames. When I expressed my <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589847" break="no"/> wonder at the short time, relative to the event, within which everything had been restored, Mr. Brunel said to me: "Yes, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName>, it was no small matter, between thirty and forty thousand cubic feet of water and mud had to be removed; the latter amounted to about a third of the whole; then the hole in the bed of the Thames had to be plugged. The surface area of this, according to the survey made in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8858">diving bell</term> above it, was about 50 square feet, and the depth of it as far as the tunnel was 36 feet." Mr. Brunel attributes the collapse to a strong current on the floor of the Thames itself, which may have been caused by the ships anchored there for a time in two rows. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">workers</term> heard the rolling of the debris above their heads, and the water at first seeped only a little between the end of the wall and the iron frames. <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589848"/> They recognized the warning sign and happily made their escape. Immediately thereafter, the water blasted away two layers of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">bricks</term> across their entire width and filled the tunnel and tower like a forest stream. Indeed, it takes the genius and strength of mind of a man like Mr. Brunel, and the perseverance of the English, not to tremble in the face of such calamity, but rather, with all the force of the human spirit, all the advantages of their art, all the resources of money, despite apparent danger to their lives, to overcome it and to render it impotent, down to its last consequences. Already, beneath the twenty-two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8866">archways</term>, whose pillars form the partition between the two tunnels for those coming and those going, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas flame</term> of the fixed installation erected by the factory itself burns from double-armed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">candelabra</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term>, which are spaced every 18 feet apart from each other, while in the rearmost parts <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589849"/> of the tunnel, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8704">oil-gas</term>, compressed in the usual portable vessels, is still being used. Mr. Brunel plugged the breach, as he told me, with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8868">sandbags</term> and short, thin, leafy tree branches and oily <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> (<term ref="gfa-keywords-8869">fire-clay</term>). The little water that trickles in around the iron shields at the back, where I was, is removed merely by hand pumps, and coming Monday, the <date when="1827-09-24">24th</date> of this month<note>"of this month". The word "month" was erroneously omitted.</note>, construction will begin again and the tunnel will be driven forward. Everyone is eagerly awaiting the success, as one can easily imagine. Before the catastrophe, there was not a single accident during this dangerous and complicated construction, neither during the sinking of the tower, which had previously been built on the ground and whose load was calculated at 1000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term> or 20,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term>, nor up to the sinking of the shaft to its greatest depth, to which, until the provisional staircase structure <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589850" break="no"/> was installed, one could only descend on vertical ladders. Later, a man drowned in the tunnel where the boat carrying the directors to investigate the breach overturned, because, as Mr. Brunel explained to me, the mud was littered with scaffolding timbers that had been completely shattered by the force of the water. Another accident occurred with the compressed gas. A vessel filled with it fell from the top of the shaft and burst. By chance, this happened near a light, so that the escaping gas formed an enormous flame and severely burned a nearby worker.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Father and son visit the Woolwich Arsenal, 26 September 1827</head>
                <p>After I had received permission from the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7755">Board of Ordnance</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-25" n="33">London</placeName> <date when="1827-09-25">the day before</date> through the efforts of the Swiss chargé d'affaires, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7757">Prevost</persName>, I went with my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">eldest son</persName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1889" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-26" n="34">Woolwich</placeName> to see the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1890" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-26" n="35"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8804">arsenal</term></placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1567" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-26" n="36"><term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term></placeName>, <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589851"/> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8854">boring mill</term> and the model halls, all of which I already knew, but to which I wished to give him access, thinking it might be of use to him in two ways, as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9112">rifle manufacturer</term> and as an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8807">artillery officer</term>. After I had presented my permit to the commandant, General <persName ref="gfa-actors-7832">Fischer</persName>, I was again assigned an officer to accompany me, as in the past. As we descended from the office toward the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1567">foundry</placeName>, we heard the firing of heavy <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">artillery</term>, whereupon I inquired of our escort if they were practicing or conducting manoeuvres. He said no, these were only experiments to determine the usefulness and practicability of an idea of General <persName ref="gfa-actors-7833">Foad</persName>, concerning the extent to which the section of a fortress, which might be particularly exposed to the fire of besieging artillery, could put up sustained resistance if protected by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8872">revetment</term> of a double layer of forged <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron rods</term>, <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589852"/> each 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter, which were affixed to it and positioned closely together and crossed at right angles. The experiments were also to test the extent to which this iron cladding, 3 inches thick as a whole, would withstand the effects of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8873">heavy-calibre</term> artillery. Since I was very interested in this demonstration, I asked him to take us there, a request with which he readily complied.</p>
                <p>There were three iron twenty-four-pounders in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">batteries</term> and bolted onto them, as they have it almost everywhere, were <term ref="gfa-keywords-8874">locks</term>, the strikers or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8875">triggers</term> of which were released by means of a rather long cord when the officer commanded fire.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8876">cartouche</term> were of canvas and probably soaked in an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8785">alum</term> solution to make them less flammable. The load consisted of ⅓ <term ref="gfa-keywords-9149">ball weight</term> or eight <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">powder</term>. <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589853"/> The canister shot (very round) was loaded without fixing (which is anyway dispensable with the small margin of error that the English have with their accurate drilling and excellent ammunition) and without wad, as they were fired somewhat downhill. The wad, which we also saw, incidentally, was bunches of unravelled mooring rope.</p>
                <p>Instead of the gnat or fly that we use for aiming on the front of our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term>, here, as on the metal cannon of all <term ref="gfa-keywords-8873">calibres</term>, there was a notch in an oblong square surface slightly raised above the muzzle, which is much better for accurate aiming when the hit is what matters, since the shot cannot easily cause a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8861">parallax</term>, or even cover the target. The distance the shot was to travel <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589854" break="no"/> was 630 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8604">Yards</term> or 1890 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> to the rampart, which was specially built of earth, covered with hewn stones and then with the aforementioned iron rods. The cladding was not more than 8 feet in length and 6 feet in height and was hit very frequently.</p>
                <p>Two of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term> fired so accurately that their shots often hit the target right next to each other; one went mostly left and high. The shots, when they hit the iron, shattered into many pieces, although they were of excellent material, of which I took a fragment after obtaining permission. The front iron bars took the impact of the shot deeply and were mostly also shattered; the rear ones, however, remained unharmed, with the exception of a single one, which was also blown in two by the impact, but, nevertheless, retained its position unchanged.</p>
                <p>I was unable to stay until the end of these experiments, for which "50 rounds", or 250 <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589855"/> shots, were scheduled for today, as I had to return to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. On the following day, the plan was to bombard the object even closer by half; however, what I saw convinced me that, even if it should finally be completely demolished, an even stronger covering of this kind for a rampart located at the weakest point of a fortress would certainly provide great protective defence.</p>
                <p>I made the usual rounds again with my son through the two model halls, and then in the casting and drilling workshops. In front of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8321"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1903" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-26" n="37">rotunda</placeName></orgName> lie a quantity of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term> captured from various countries, which are kept for their beauty or peculiarity in construction and, it pleased me to see, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9802">two immensely large mortars</term>, cast in 1726, by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7373">Schalch</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, who, because he predicted that an accident would happen, which then <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589856"/> did when his warning went unheeded, was promoted from young journeyman <term ref="gfa-keywords-9117">foundryman</term> to the position of royal foundryman in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1890">arsenal at Woolwich</placeName>, a position he held with distinction, acquiring considerable wealth, until a ripe old age. — I saw nothing particularly new in the rotunda since I reported on my visit there two years ago, which notes are now at the beginning of <ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/6">these collected notes</ref>, other than a model of a device by Colonel <persName ref="gfa-actors-7780">Congreve</persName> to conduct the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8864">hydrogen gas</term> that escapes during the <term ref="gfa-keywords-544"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8905">charring of wood</term></term> for coals for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">gunpowder</term> underneath the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8882">retorts</term>, in order to use it again as fuel by igniting it. This idea, incidentally, as far as I recall, had already been proposed and implemented much earlier by the meritorious Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7879">Lampadius</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1108">Freiberg in the Ore Mountains</placeName>. What truly caught my interest were two forged <term ref="gfa-keywords-8883">swivel guns</term>, or small iron cannon, shooting about <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589857"/> three quarters of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>, which the English had taken from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1901">Burmese</placeName>, along with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8743">state carriage</term> of their sovereign.</p>
                <p>These two small pieces are really remarkable. On the one hand, they prove to the connoisseur how far this nation, which is, incidentally, not uncivilized, still lags behind its conquerors in technical skills and, on the other hand, how much, based to the peculiarity of their construction, the striving of the human spirit for perfection and embellishment is to be remarked here as well, even if only in crude and artless contours. The need to be able to load heavy artillery from the rear was, as it seems, felt just as keenly in distant <placeName ref="gfa-places-7">Asia</placeName> as in war-hardened <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName>. From all that I have already seen in this respect and as far as I am able to judge, I would consider this <pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589858"/> Burmese idea, which they have certainly not borrowed and which I regard as new and belonging to them, at least at as good as any known to me, if not give it preference, since these cannon have the peculiar and certainly good thing, even if they are already loaded from the rear, of nevertheless possessing a whole and solid base piece.</p>
                <p>The device consists of the following: the part of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">gun</term> called the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8885">vent field</term> is significantly thicker than in ordinary artillery, and its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8873">calibre</term> is proportionally much wider inside. The upper half of it, however, is cut away on the longitudinal axis, so that it forms only a semi-circular hollow channel into which the short <term ref="gfa-keywords-8886">reinforce</term> is inserted, on which there is a hand lever shaped like a thin dolphin and which only contains the charge along with the shot. This reinforce is tapered, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">conically</term> pointed, from the front and around the outside, <pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589859"/> but only very briefly, so that it fits into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8713">bore</term> of the cannon starting at the end of the hollow, which also has a corresponding conical widening where the reinforce is to fit, and at the rear it locks with its base to the part of the base of the large cannon, as much of it as is left standing. As irregular and crude as these cannon are finished, for one can certainly say that every stroke of the hammer on them is Indian, the craftsman, nevertheless, made an effort to work the nose of this gun into a flower similar to an open <term ref="gfa-keywords-8862">lotus</term>.</p>
                <p>I called these cannon <term ref="gfa-keywords-8883">"swivels"</term> because there is a handle, or fork, around the two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">trunnions</term>, which ends in a point at the bottom. To plant the piece, it is driven into the ground or a piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-544">wood</term>.</p>
                <p><pb n="80" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589860"/> In the model room of the arsenal, since I saw it and mentioned the most remarkable pieces it contained in the <ref type="cross" target="../1825-1827/6">fragments from my diary of 1825</ref>, nothing special had been added, except a machine made by the custodian of the same on a large scale and already put into use, in order to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8896">strike</term> a dozen of the ordinary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8714">rockets</term> at once and, more importantly, quite uniformly. One must really be surprised that this simple idea has, as far as I know, not yet been implemented anywhere else. It consists only in a wooden frame in which twelve wooden hammers are set in motion by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">shaft</term> fitted with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8889">cams</term> that project to a suitable length (in order to provide sufficient fall) and are turned by hand with a crank, and by means of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8899">stamp</term> on which they fall, they move the set in the shells that are fixed in the rockets also mounted on the frame. <pb n="81" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589861"/> I must also mention a very carefully considered and clever arrangement for the production of all kinds of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8863"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">fireworks</term></term> and ammunition. Namely, that instead of building large pyrotechnical facilities, as is done elsewhere, where in the event of an accident the damage and destruction is great due to the number of workers and the combustibles and explosives, here, everything is done in individual, very small wooden houses, painted with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9087">oil paint</term> and situated in a wide area at a considerable distance from each other, in each of which there is room for two workers at most. As a result, the destruction of a whole establishment within merely minutes, as has otherwise already happened, is impossible.</p>
                <p>In the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1567"><term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term></placeName>, compared to other such workshops, there is nothing particularly remarkable, even their <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">melting furnaces</term> are not extraordinarily large, <pb n="82" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589862"/> which I consider quite good, however, as through this and through the great heat that can be obtained in such a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberating furnace</term> with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal flame</term>, the fusion of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> (<term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>) and the resulting higher density of the metal, which contains (and which is certainly also very good), judging by the colour, somewhat more tin than the French composition, can be more fully achieved.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8398"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8852">boring machine</term></term>, on the other hand (there are actually two of them, the long one for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannon</term> and the short one for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8881">mortars</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8732">howitzers</term>), deserves the attention of every connoisseur, who will leave the workshop astonished, where the gun is given the highest, especially intricate perfection with such simple tools.</p>
                <p>While here in <placeName ref="gfa-places-402">Albion</placeName>, so rich in art and gold, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metal</term> are, in fact, wasted on thousands of machines <pb n="83" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589863"/> and other objects, these boring machines, which, as everywhere, are also <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887">lathes</term>, are made solely of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8983">solid oak</term>, and only in those places where it is necessary are iron rails screwed on (on the two so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9153">cheeks</term>, namely, to form the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8963">groove</term> in which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9155">boring bar</term> runs), which, as is also customary elsewhere, is gradually advanced by the worker with the help of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9156">gear</term>.</p>
                <p>First, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8906">hand brace</term> is used to make a small opening or recess in the centre of the gun for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9158">point drill</term>, and the same is used to drill about three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> into the hole. Then, with a specially made <term ref="gfa-keywords-3153">boring tool</term>, the hole is made perfectly round and to the width so that the first <term ref="gfa-keywords-9803">spoon bit</term>, which is semi-circular at the front and in its lower surface, can be inserted, <pb n="84" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589864" break="no"/> with which the gun is then bored to the very end.</p>
                <p>When this first hole is finished, the successive flat rail-drills follow, at the front end of each of which there is a steel ring of the same width as the previous drill, which must serve as a "Guide" for the latter, so that the hole becomes perfectly straight and concentric. Finally, the reamer, or polishing drill, is used, which differs from the other in that it no longer has a guide ring but is rounded at the front, since the chambers of English cannon and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8881">mortars</term> always form a hemisphere, which is certainly advantageous, as nothing of the cartridge can remain stuck and it is also easier to clean; it is also honed in such a way that only the side adjacent to the half rounding in front, against which the cannon moves as it rotates, cuts, while the opposite side has a rounded <pb n="85" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589865"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9236">polish-steel-like</term> edge, which indeed suits this purpose to the highest degree.</p>
                <p>To prevent every kind of "Shakes", which are copied on the metal in a most unpleasant, though often essentially not harmful way, this last drill not only shaves away an extremely thin <term ref="gfa-keywords-9239">layer</term>, but on its upper and lower surface are screwed two half-round pieces of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8865">boxwood</term> about 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long, underlaid with playing cards, which completely fill the hole of the gun, are lubricated with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">oil</term>, and thus also help to perfect the polish.</p>
                <p>What struck me about this <term ref="gfa-keywords-8852">boring machine</term> was that I did not see any so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9241">slides</term> ("Sliding-tool; burin fixe") but noticed that the gun was turned from the rough with very simple <term ref="gfa-keywords-3153">lathe</term>, which the worker only placed on a wooden <term ref="gfa-keywords-9514">trestle</term> ("Support"), <pb n="86" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589866"/> and then finished with flat, right-angled polished rails. The contour of the gun was, incidentally, formed using a perfected iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-9242">template</term>, which the worker placed on the back and front of the circle, which had already been preliminarily set to the appropriate diameter for this purpose.</p>
                <p>This way, as the worker said to me, with whom I conversed for a long while, we can finish a piece of artillery faster than with the slide, which we also have, but which, as you can see, stands there unused. For the boring of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8881">mortars</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8732">howitzers</term>, which are processed like guns for the initial opening, I saw a tool that I had never seen before, with which every <term ref="gfa-keywords-8873">calibre</term>, whether large or small, can be brought to the appropriate width.</p>
                <p>On the flat plate of the drill, whose diameter <pb n="87" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589867"/> is such that one can almost finish the smallest calibres with it and which, in addition to the half rounding at the front, also has a ring attached as a guide, there is a piece of steel rotating around a pin on the plate and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8880">bent down</term> over the bar like a <term ref="gfa-keywords-3153">turning tool</term>, on which an upright <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> is riveted, which, because the hole of its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">pin</term> is countersunk, can nevertheless turn, and through the transverse hole of which, projecting about one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> from the upper part of the plate, passes a round rod, equipped with a double attachment (so that it cannot rotate forwards or backwards, but rather in the hole of the piston), which exceeds the length of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9155">boring bar</term> somewhat and which is equipped at the back of the end of the boring bar with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8779">screw thread</term>, which passes through a lug with the same thread, which forms a part of the end of the boring bar. The outermost end of this <pb n="88" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589868"/> regulating rod, which is parallel to the boring bar, has a square <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">pin</term> to which a key is attached in order to turn it as desired and, depending on whether this is done with the left or right hand, the aforementioned bent turning tool of the axis of the boring bar is brought closer to or further away from it, fixed at the desired, or required, point and, thus, the width of the hole to be made is determined for each round of boring until the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9070">gun</term> has its proper width. This has the immense advantage that instead of the large drills comprised of one single piece, only a small part must be fabricated, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardened</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">finished</term>, and that, however it may be finished, the tool retains its usefulness to the full, since whatever length may be lost from the axis of the boring bar when the part is removed is restored with a slight turning of an adjustable <term ref="gfa-keywords-8878">lock</term>; and thus the <pb n="89" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589869"/> diameter of this (universal I would like to call it) drill with variable dimensions can be brought precisely and consistently to the desired point each time. As for the drilling of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8560">touch holes</term>, the rounding of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8766">trunnions</term> and the formation of their surfaces and lugs, the former is done in the usual way and the latter as well, namely by means of a hollow cylinder into which the cutters are inserted.</p>
    </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Perkins demonstrates the high pressure steam engine, 27 September 1827</head>
                <p>When I wrote in the <ref type="cross" target="../1825">diary</ref> of my second journey to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> about the inventor of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8877">steam gun</term>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName>, based on what I believe I was able to gather from his physiognomy at our very first acquaintance (p. 54), that the realm of knowledge would be indebted to him for more than one discovery and that it seemed to me that the pursuit of great ideas occupied him more than the dusty <pb n="90" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589870" break="no"/> acquisition of earthly possessions, I might well believe that I was not mistaken about him. For in this short period of time, he has indeed again made such essential improvements to his type of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9094">steam engines</term> (which are always distinguished above all others by the immensely <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high pressure</term> he imparts to the steam and by the fact that, despite this, he has never had an accident), or rather he has invented new ones, so that one cannot but admire his genius in this physicotechnical subject. It is not only in view of the very small space which his machines occupy in relation to their efficiency, but also because of the perfect safety of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8937">steam apparatus</term>, although the pressure in it is brought up to 800 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">square inch</term>, and of which one is inevitably convinced when observing it, notwithstanding his public announcement of it, <pb n="91" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589871"/> and the testimony of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9092">engineers</term> given about it in pamphlets. It will hardly fail to happen that in the end, for his own efforts and the exertions of his genius, he will also be awarded a prize of honour, which, as it seems, they want to deny him in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, and not entirely without fervour, whereas, if he were in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9093">monarchical</term> state, where such acknowledgements emanate from the sovereign, he would already have received it.</p>
                <p>I visited Mr. Perkins twice: the first time alone (he now lives in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2112" type="itinerar" notAfter="1827-09-26" n="38">Grays-Inn Road</placeName>), where in a few months he had erected a new building and a <placeName ref="gfa-places-2095" type="itinerar" notAfter="1827-09-26" n="39" cert="0"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8944">steam engine factory</term></placeName> (he had ceded the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1850" cert="0">previously owned</placeName> ones in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2027">Regents Park</placeName> to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7846">Gurney</persName>), which would have taken years to build on the continent, and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2095" type="itinerar" when="1827-09-27" n="40" cert="0">second time</placeName> with my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">eldest son</persName>, since I thought it was worth the effort <pb n="92" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589872"/> that he should also see these beautiful, small and efficient machines.</p>
                <p>Mr. Perkins gave me the details of these machines verbatim and also gave me the details regarding the advantages of the latest improvements, of which I omit the following statement from the last paragraph, which, if its correctness were proved by experiments and counter-experiments, would bring about an important amendment in the laws of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term>, but will in any case greatly attract the attention of natural scientists.</p>
                <p>He said: "By experiments I have found that the heating material is ponderable matter and obeys the laws of gravity, and by virtue of this property I have managed to bring it down from the flues and back into the furnace, thus saving a considerable amount of fuel."</p>
                <p><pb n="93" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589873"/> Since Mr. Perkins will not be exempted from proving this assertion, which, incidentally, he would be able to do at any moment, since the furnace and the machine are ready and in full swing, I will, without entering into any further discussion, only mention what he has told me about the price, size, weight and efficiency of the same, and I will only remark that even in these newest machines – which still have the peculiarity of having no <term ref="gfa-keywords-3213">eduction valves</term> and whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">pistons</term>, which he showed me, are of a metal mixture that, as he claims, do not require <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">lubrication</term>, and in general are very useful because of their permanent connection to the cylinder, while he is also impressed by the speed of the machine, which, even when it must bear the applied load, functions with 100 strokes per minute, is incomparably constructed, being made of two rings, <pb n="94" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589874" break="no"/> one above the other, cut open at opposite points and therefore resiliently expanding and aconcentric in their thickness – I say that in this newest machine of the largest type thereof, he has made the improvement of giving it two cylinders, one larger and one smaller, where then the steam, when it has functioned in one, passes over into the other, and when it has also done its work there, is then fed to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8954">condenser</term>, a new device by which advantages are obtained in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high-pressure steam engine</term> that were not had before.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, which by all appearances does not quite suit him, will now likely lose him forever, as I heard from him that he was willing to go to <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I received the following information from him about his latest steam engines with two <pb n="95" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589875"/> (unequally wide) cylinders, which he had set up at the place mentioned above and which I saw in operation.</p>
                <p>Firstly. Such a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">30-horsepower</term> steam engine costs only two-thirds of the amount one has to pay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> for an equally powerful and well-manufactured one.</p>
                <p>Secondly. It occupies an area of only 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">square feet</term>, that is, 6 feet long by 5 feet wide, and its entire height, including the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8956">flywheel</term>, which is 5 feet in diameter, is not more than 9 feet.</p>
                <p>Thirdly. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">piston</term> makes 120 strokes per minute. The construction and arrangement of the steam pipes, which have to withstand a pressure of 5 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8962">atmospheres</term> (= 750 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">square inch</term>) when the machine is in operation, is such as to preclude any danger of bursting. <pb n="96" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589876"/> The machine, incidentally, is so simple that its size and weight is only a fourth of that of an ordinary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8955">atmospheric</term> one.</p>
                <p>Fourthly. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName> is inclined to give not only the authority but also the necessary instructions to those <term ref="gfa-keywords-8944">steam engine manufacturers</term> who would be willing to enter into an agreement with him.</p>
                <p>Since Mr. Perkins was kind enough to share with me the metal mixture from which he made his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8951">pistons</term> (which I saw myself, and which, despite their friction against the inner walls of the cylinder and their rapid movement, require no <term ref="gfa-keywords-8952">lubrication</term>) and which consists of twenty parts <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and four and a half parts English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term>, so it would be important to apply them also to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8957">journal bearings</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8958">friction rollers</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8959">grooves</term> (coulisse) and other similar objects to see how useful they would be there, <pb n="97" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589877"/> for which purpose I also mention this composition here.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Peruvian steel and a visit to Sanderson and Huntsman, 5 October 1827</head>
                <p>After a bad <date when="1827-10-05">night's</date> sleep, as is the case when travelling, and a breakfast in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1807" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="41">Nottingham</placeName>, which again was much more like a lunch, in that in addition to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term> and eggs and butter, there was poultry and three kinds of meat, I was glad to find myself in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal district</term>, which bestows life and wealth to this region, but especially to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>. Not only are the coals very good, but the two layers above each other, of which the lower is, as usual, the better and more powerful, are extracted with little effort, mostly by hand, and sometimes only with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8939">horse-engines</term>. Equally interesting to me were two other objects on the long stretches that I travelled through in all haste, <pb n="98" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589878" break="no"/> namely the castle of the former Lord <persName ref="gfa-actors-7793">Byron</persName> on the left side of the road on a hill in a charming area before <placeName ref="gfa-places-2036" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="42">Nottinghamshire</placeName>, built in a rather ancient style and inhabited by him before he met his fame and his misfortune, called <placeName ref="gfa-places-2019" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="43">Newstead Abbey</placeName>. Then, also to the left of the road, there was <placeName ref="gfa-places-1961" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="44">Hardwik Castle</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1925" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="45">Derbyshire</placeName>, in which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7824">Elisabeth</persName>, acting as a woman and not as a queen, but abusing her authority as Queen, imprisoned her more beautiful rival, the unfortunate <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7894">Mary of Scots</persName></placeName>, for a long time. This historically peculiar castle, which is also beautifully situated with a lovely view, now belongs to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8079">Duke of Devonshire</persName>, on whose fair <persName ref="gfa-actors-8080">wife's</persName> eyes an honest sailor once tried to light his <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipe</term>, of which the short story goes as follows:</p>
                <p>The Duchess once stood still in an open <term ref="gfa-keywords-8961">calesche</term> near Tower-Steiers, <pb n="99" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589879" break="no"/> to await someone. A sailor, walking very close to her carriage, gazed up at her with unblinking eyes. At last, with her customary affability, she asked "my friend do you want something?" "Nothing Madam," he replied, "but to light my pipe at Your eyes". Smiling, she pulled out her purse and gave him a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8536">guinea</term>, saying that this would not do and that he had better get a lighter elsewhere.</p>
                <p>"Flatter me as you may," she often said to the distinguished gentlemen in her company, "yet none of you can pay me so fine a compliment as this person has done."</p>
                <p>Approaching <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="46">Sheffield</placeName>, one sees only a single, massive cloud of smoke which would be equally as much trouble for Dr. N.<note>It is not known for whom this abbreviation stands.</note> <pb n="100" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589880"/> to blow away as would be the fog that constantly envelops <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, for whose removal he patented a method.</p>
                <p>Since I found that I would, in any case, arrive too late in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> to see anything important or be able to visit anyone, and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> has many and varied attractions for me, I decided to stay there and to investigate, in particular, where or by whom the so-called Imperial or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9096">Kaiser</term>, and then again <term ref="gfa-keywords-9097">Peruvian steel</term> (two quite new phenomena in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel fabrication</term>) are made, but first of all to visit and greet my old acquaintance, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">cast steel manufacturer</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName>. When I arrived at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2096" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="47">factory</placeName></orgName>, he was having dinner in town, and I was told that he would be back later. I thought that I might be able to find out where the above types of steel were made at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="48" cert="0">Tiltinghouse</placeName> (<term ref="gfa-keywords-9099">steel drawing mill</term>), <pb n="101" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589881" break="no"/> since they would have them <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">drawn</term> there, and so I went to the mill.</p>
                <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9100">hammersmith</term> had an octagonal bar under the hammer, which had not been cast smoothly at all, having a great many transverse cracks, so he forged it again on the corners, but then put it down next to a similar one lying on the ground with the remark, "it won't do". — "No it won't do," repeated a gentleman standing next to him, "It's no good." "Can you not tell me, good friend," I now interjected, "where to obtain <term ref="gfa-keywords-9096">Imperial</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9097">Peruvian steel</term>?" "No," said the gentleman who answered instead of the hammersmith, "of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9096">imperial steel</term> I know nothing at all, Peruvian is made by Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7866">Bixley and Green</orgName>, but it cannot be worked, as you see, like this one I have made. My name is <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName>, and I make the best <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> here, and if you would only come to me at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1806">Attercliff</placeName>, <pb n="102" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589882"/> where I have my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1805">manufactory</placeName>, I would show you the like, which cuts <term ref="gfa-keywords-9861">glass</term>. This one I have only made for trial with ores brought me by a gentleman from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indies</placeName>. They make <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> with it there, but it is no good, and there is nothing better for our steel than good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">Swedish iron</term>". I watched them <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">draw</term> for a while, looked again attentively at their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">warming furnace</term>, which I described earlier and whose suitability for their fuel I must again fully acknowledge, and then went to Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8081"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7844"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7866">Bixley and Green</orgName></persName></persName>. When I tried to buy Peruvian steel in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2097" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="49">store</placeName>, I was not given any, but was directed to the office, where I was told to come back at eight o'clock, as they did not have any on hand at the moment.</p>
                <p>103
                    I then hurried to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7945">Sanderson</persName><note>Corrected from "Sanders" in Fischer's first edition.</note> in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2096" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="50">cast steel factory</placeName></orgName></term> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1677" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05" n="51">West Street</placeName>, which was quite a distance away. He was in the office <pb n="103" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589883" break="no"/> and received me very kindly, as did his two associates, to whom he explained who I was and offered me lodging in his apartment if I should wish to stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, which I declined. After some conversation about steel manufacturing, I departed, and he accompanied me. Instead of going to the door, he first took me to the coal warehouse and showed me their beautiful (light) <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">cokes</term> and then, to my amazement, to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> works, which was in full swing. I watched the melting and casting for a while and then proceeded to the cement works, where they <term ref="gfa-keywords-8757">cement</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-8989"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">Swedish iron</term></placeName>, known as <term ref="gfa-keywords-9101">Hoop L</term> because of the sign (L), which is the best, and then turn it into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>. Their <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term> is really excellent and burned as uniformly as one could wish. I told him what I do with the overpour steel so as to make the best use of it, <pb n="104" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589884"/> which interested him very much, since they have also accumulated a large pile, and, finally, my thoughts about <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8469">steel</term>, supposedly produced from East Indian ores, which I judged by external characteristics to be badly imitated <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteor steel</term></term>, and added, I believe the gentlemen in Sheffield also plow with my oxen. "I see well," he replied smiling, "they can't throw any dust into your eyes."</p>
                <p>Friendly, though competitors, we parted company.</p>
                <p>In the <date when="1827-10-05T20:00:00">evening</date> at eight o'clock I returned to Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7844"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8081"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7866"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2097" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-05T20:00:00" n="52">Bixley and Green</placeName></orgName></persName></persName>, but again I was unable to obtain any <term ref="gfa-keywords-9097">Peruvian steel</term>. They said they would send it to me in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. I recognized, however, that they were simply unwilling to give me any. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-8081" type="met">Bixley</persName>, meanwhile, invited me to join him upstairs and took me to his warehouses, six of which, <pb n="105" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589885"/> one more precious than the other, were filled with metal and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9102">iron goods</term> of all kinds, which <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> supply, by which I also mean <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plated</term> work, and each time I entered, as if by a stroke of magic, with the turn of a switch, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lights</term> glowing on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9105">crystalline</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9104">lustres</term>, like fireflies, were raised to blazing flames, spreading daylight over the shiny objects. Of the many beautiful and fine things, I only regretted not being able to buy one thing, as I was traveling through <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, namely a beautifully lacquered <term ref="gfa-keywords-9560">tea tray</term> of virtually the largest kind embellished with gold plating, which cost only 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> or about 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Guld.</term> 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term> Before departing, I courteously purchased a handsome and well-crafted pair of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8661">scissors</term>, whereby he then gave me two <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">copper engravings</term> of his warehouse as seen from the inside and then, with great devotion, <pb n="106" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589886" break="no"/> took a flat box from a glass cabinet, which had a steel frame and a glass lid and was divided into seven gilded compartments on the inside. These compartments contained <term ref="gfa-keywords-9106">cupro-nickel</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8919">chrome-ironstone</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platina</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8855">borax</term>, and burnt <term ref="gfa-keywords-8785">alum</term> (the latter both in pieces, which made them recognizable). "You see," he said, "we make the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9097">Peruvian steel</term> you asked for, which is incomparable, with these materials. We do not sell it, however, but use it only for articles of our own manufacture." With equal devotion and admiration, I returned the sacred object to him and thanked him for the gracious explanation. I wanted to make the most of my time in Sheffield, where many an altar exists for the worshippers of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcan</persName>, and, though it was very late, returned first to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9244">drawing mill</term> and then to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term>, since both are in operation day and night. <pb n="107" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589887" break="no"/> In the drawing mill, I examined the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9246">warming furnace</term> once more and for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">sixpence</term> got the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9099">hammer</term> stopped, so that I could talk to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9100">hammersmith</term> about it. This furnace, simple as it is, proves that the English know how to overcome so many difficulties arising from the nature of their burning material.</p>
                <p>In the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">steel mill</term>, the thing I wanted to see most was the disposition of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8740">fluting</term> and the successive application of them to the piece to be <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">drawn</term>, so that in the last cycle, where it is flattened, there are no <term ref="gfa-keywords-9247">burrs</term> on the sides, as there used to be, and where the whole secret lies in the fact that the bar is so large that the narrow sides are not flattened at the edges, but remain somewhat half-round.</p>
                </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Short visit to the Gott family in Leeds, 7 October 1827</head>
                <p>This <date when="1827-10-07">morning</date><note>Fischer must already have been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-07" n="53">Leeds</placeName> on this day.</note> I talked with the young Mister <persName ref="gfa-actors-7842">Gott</persName> about the change in customs and <pb n="108" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589888"/> habits that had taken place over the past thirty years even in the North of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, despite its still greater remoteness from the rest of <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europe</placeName> and the more limited contact with the continent, and, in particular, about how much the once so frequent "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8859">Boxing matches</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8922">Cocks-fightings</term>" had diminished. He absolutely confirmed this, but he said to me: Only recently I witnessed how far this devotion can yet go with some individuals (as far as fist fights are concerned, they have now been completely relegated to the lowest classes of society, as you yourself will have had occasion to notice on your journey, but not so the cock fights), in that a certain Lord Davy still maintains 300, say three hundred, such fighting cocks at great expense, and where an opportunity presents itself, has them fight against others, and that with the betting of large sums of money.</p>
                <p><pb n="109" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589889"/> As a great honour (for no one is otherwise allowed into the barracks of this bird militia, in which twelve persons keep watch day and night, so that they are well looked after and nothing dangerous or poisonous may be thrown to them), I was permitted to behold them in the morning at 4 o'clock, before the owner had even awakened, and to be present when they were given their food. "They were indeed highly fed," he continued, which contributes a great deal to the fact that they usually win.</p>
                <p>Also the traditional (by the way substantial) pomp at some banquets continues to take place among wealthy landowners, who in their way of being and thinking may be compared to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8930">country squires</term> of bygone days, of which a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9089"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8084">Tom Jones</persName></term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9090"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7817">Joseph Andrews</persName></term> and other books give us an impression. At one such gathering, given by a certain Watson Taylor, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9279">"Cup-Board"</term> <pb n="110" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589890" break="no"/> was displayed, consisting of a silver and gold-plated <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">tin</term> 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> long. I would hardly dare to mention it, if several public papers had not done so as well.</p>
                <p>If, however, the so-called refinement of customs in the countryside does not always keep pace with that of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">metropolis</placeName>, the spirit of improvement cannot be ignored even in the meanest farm implements. Just as, on the one hand, the equally rapid and uniform distribution of liquid <term ref="gfa-keywords-9088">manure</term> while driving up and down over the field or meadow, in so far as it comes from a barrel loaded on a cart to which a closed, square, wooden pipe equipped with many taps is attached transversely at the bottom, serves the goal of improvement, so too is the painting of these and all other field implements, including wagons and carts, with oil or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9087">tar paint</term>, of which I will speak shortly, expedient <pb n="111" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589891"/> to protect them against the effects of weather and rapid rotting, and is also proof of this spirit of improvement that prevails everywhere.</p>
                <p>This tar paint consists of a mixture of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9561">coal tar</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9085">ochre</term>, has a not unpleasant green olive colour, and is very economical, given that these two materials cost almost nothing, and is very durable and weather resistant. In general, the English not only always ask what can be gained from this and that, but they ask just as often what can be saved, which has just as positive a benefit, as success is always certain, but the profit is determined by sales.</p>
                <p>All very heavy or solid objects, such as fences, wrought-iron gates, etc., are painted with this green paint. Objects, on the other hand, that are small and light, as well as all plows <pb n="112" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589892"/> that are left standing alone in the field, are painted red, which is very clever, for not only can they be recognized at great distances but even the smallest <term ref="gfa-keywords-9239">chip</term> of them betrays the thief.</p>
                <p>As I pondered the quantity and inexpensiveness of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coals</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1789">Warwickshire</placeName> up to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2078">Yorkshire</placeName>, independent of their enormous consumption, Mr. Gott showed me a map of the coal deposits, just as far as they were drilled in these districts and then calculated their cubic content, out of which, based only on what is known with reliability so far, a supply results, which will last for a thousand years with a continued, uniform consumption as at present.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer procures specialist literature, 10 October 1827</head>
                <p>In a bookstore on <placeName ref="gfa-places-2098" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-10" n="54">Pater Noster Row</placeName> <date when="1827-10-10">today</date> I purchased <persName ref="gfa-actors-7961"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9084">Uré's chemical dictionary</term></persName>, which is excellent in its way and especially richly furnished with tables and many drawings, and then several issues of the weekly register for mechanics, <pb n="113" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589893"/> actually the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9798">Register of the arts and sciences</term>. As far as I know, there is still no book on the continent that is comparable to this one, neither in terms of cost nor of usefulness, though it is sometimes referred to in many <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">German</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName> technical publications, and rightly so.</p>
                <p>It would be a highly commendable work, and would certainly pay off, if any bookstore in Germany would publish a faithful and comprehensible translation from its earliest beginnings until now, furnished in the same manner with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithographic</term> drawings. Since, with the otherwise high price of books in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, such a booklet or number costs only 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> or about 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term>, it would probably be even more economical to produce in Germany, and if it were published in one or more capitals and residential cities, <pb n="114" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589894" break="no"/> where there are many craftsmen, artists and students, a much larger and more varied mass of knowledge about English <term ref="gfa-keywords-14">engineering</term> would at once be available among these people and, what is more important, about the spirit and genius of the English <term ref="gfa-keywords-9083">mechanics</term>, their prudence, their rationality and their tools, which in general can be better understood and learnt from their own experience than demonstrated ad oculos, as with methodical textbooks, where too much attention is paid to theory to be generally understandable and engaging, or by isolated descriptions intermingled with pictures of unfamiliar objects, as they occur in periodical writings, and the benefit would become conspicuously apparent in no time at all. The booklets I bought contained, among others, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8651"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9094">Perkin's latest steam engine</term></term></persName> with two unequal cylinders, <pb n="115" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589895" break="no"/> the injection tube, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8954">"Condensator"</term> and "Steamchamber", and then the two latest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8943">steam carriages</term> from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7846">Gurney</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2027">Regents Park</placeName> and from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7910">Mosley</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1648">Southwark</placeName>. Both of these carriages, meanwhile, suffered accidents during their first trials. Mosley's, which had rented a special enclosed meadow for the test, had its boiler burst, and several people were injured by off-spray of the boiling water, and Gurney's broke a wheel after driving down the rather steep incline called <placeName ref="gfa-places-2099">Highgatehill</placeName>, whereas nothing at all had happened on the way up, which was more to be feared. Incidentally, no one was harmed in this accident, and I must be mistaken if the steam carriages were not as perfect and safe as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboats</term>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Tour of the Hammersmith Bridge and a visit to the theatre, 11 October 1827</head>
                <p>Having read in the public papers that the new <pb n="116" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589896"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9081"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2100" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-11" n="55">chain bridge at "Hamersmith"</placeName></term> was now quite finished and open for passage by wagons and on foot, I went with my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">eldest son</persName> to see it. The first impression it made on me was not entirely the most pleasant, inasmuch as the massiveness of the bars, or chain links, seemed to me too thick and clumsy for its length, especially in comparison with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7905"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2101">those constructed by Baron v. Mitis</placeName></persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>. Indeed, their thickness seemed to me excessive still in that four double rows of such chains, of which the inner row consists of six adjacent ¾ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> thick and 5 inches high rails, and the outer row, which carries the walkway for pedestrians, consisting of three such rails, run parallel to each other on both sides. It is admittedly true that Mr. v. Mitis had the excellent idea, after he had previously investigated the different <term ref="gfa-keywords-9080">cohesive forces</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> compared to each other by his ingenious machine, <pb n="117" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589897"/> and had arrived at the extraordinary, previously unknown result that the strength of ordinary steel to that of good iron is at least about 9 to 4, and therefore it would be possible to make the links thinner with the greatest certainty, if not by half, then at least by a third, and thus in the total construction costs, since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9079">abutments</term> could also be lighter, an advantage would be obtained over an iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-9081">chain bridge</term> in a ratio of 16 to 11; that is, if a bridge of iron costs 16,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term>, one of steel costs only 11,000 Gulden. The bridge in Hamersmith, incidentally, comprises two arches, one of which has a length of 400 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> and 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>, and the other 140 feet, while in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> itself, which was, in fact, very sensible and advantageous, a large stone pier is erected, where the two arches unite, <pb n="118" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589898"/> and, since they rest on top of it, only press perpendicularly on it, while their two other ends run into the piers on land in the usual way and are connected to it. The width of the bridge, including the two sidewalks, is 46 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, and according to a construction supervisor who was present, it required 350 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term> or 7000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term> of iron. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, a similar bridge was to have been built over the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2062">Seine</placeName> not long before, but it seems that the master builder did not properly calculate the load that the piers would have to bear. For when it was finished, they were already torn down by the weight of the chains and, since the poor wretch, the master builder, was thus taken from the world, everything now remains abandoned. The French journals, however, were quite silent about the incident. The durability of the bridge at Hamersmith was tested by eight wagons, <pb n="119" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589899"/> each loaded with 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term>, which were placed on it and then trotted over it in close succession.</p>
                <p>As my way home led me straight past <placeName ref="gfa-places-2103" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-11T19:00:00" n="56">Haymarket</placeName> and it was <term ref="gfa-keywords-9790">theatre</term> time (7 o'clock in the evening), I went <placeName ref="gfa-places-2102" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-22T19:00:00" n="57">in</placeName>. It must be said that, although the entrance fee is considerably higher than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, one gets something for his money, almost too much. For not only were three plays performed, two operettas and one comedy, but also "Sundry Entertainments", among which mainly the dancing and singing of the quite pretty Madame <persName ref="gfa-actors-7962">Vestris</persName>, who was much discussed in the theatre world, was to be counted, and who, as a fly-whisk seller from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2039">Odenwald</placeName>, and in local costume, fascinated and amused with her expressive and ambiguous "buy a broom".</p>
                <p>As the English place great value on time in all things and the exertions of the orchestra, <pb n="120" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589900"/> which certainly cannot be compared with those on our best German stages, as it seemed to me at least, appear to them to be entirely secondary, the curtain fell both during the transition from one act to the next, as well as from one piece to the next, so to speak, only to be raised again. With all this almost uninterrupted playing, it was nevertheless past one o'clock in the morning before everything ended, and I now had the pleasure of walking more than two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2104" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-12T02:00:00" cert="0" n="59">home</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, I was again delighted, as before, by the so natural and unforced acting of the performers and their mostly natural, or only very slightly tinged, complexion, which contrasts very much with the affectation and ultra-declamation of the French actors and their, one might say, heavily applied make-up. I will not mention anything about the costume, <pb n="121" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589901"/> because one can well imagine that in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold-rich</term> England <term ref="gfa-keywords-5503">paper</term> and tinsel are taboo.</p>
                <p>On this somewhat moonlit, yet cold and foggy October night, I met several individuals, in particular, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2098" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-12T01:00:00" n="58">Pater-noster-Row</placeName>, a woman with four children lying on the pavement in front of a house door, where they spent the whole night. Such a thing seems almost unbelievable to us, but if the reliable <persName ref="gfa-actors-7798">Colqhuon</persName>, who knew <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and its size and its misery better than almost anyone, says somewhere that about 30,000 people wake up in London every day, who do not know where they will lay their heads in the evening, then what I have just mentioned no longer provokes anyone's notice. I must also mention the tragicomic story of young <persName ref="gfa-actors-8110">Grimaldi</persName>, which was the talk of the day in London, and because he amuses the public very much on the stage as a clown or buffoon, has also been mentioned frequently tonight. In addition to the fact that it may, <pb n="122" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589902"/> at the same time, be regarded as a contribution to the moral history of London, I will mention it. He had a love affair with a theatre maid, but her name was not Agnes. He grew tired of her and bid her farewell. She, in rage and despair, takes poison on the spot. The symptoms of its effect appear, she says what she has done. Medical help is summoned, but she lies hopelessly prostrate. Grimaldi learns of it, goes to see her, and also in desperation, and to obliterate the impression made on him by the situation of his former lover, he drinks two bottles of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8860">brandy</term> in succession. He achieved his purpose entirely, for he became a fool immediately thereafter. "It turn'd about bis brains", was the expression of the newspapers reporting about it immediately. This is how both of them might well have ended; however, the efforts that were made on both their behalves were not fruitless, <pb n="123" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589903"/> for it is now generally assured that she is out of danger again and that he has come to his senses.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>London Steelworks and a so-called tobacco dispenser, 12 October 1827</head>
                <p>This <date when="1827-10-12">morning</date> I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-2106" type="itinerar" notAfter="1827-10-12T12:00:00" n="60">London Steel-work</placeName>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">foundry</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9056">iron forge</term> owned by Messrs <persName ref="gfa-actors-7885"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7958"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-8111">Thomson and Johnson</orgName></persName></persName>, situated on the left bank of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, not far from <placeName ref="gfa-places-2107">Vauxhall Bridge</placeName>, to have the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> I had made in Mr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7758">Martineau's</persName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-127">Russian</placeName> iron in direct smelting, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">drawn</term>, for, in addition to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term>, these gentlemen also have a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8540">lift-hammer</term>, which weighs 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term>, or 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term>, with a cast <term ref="gfa-keywords-9524">shaft</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9515">bush</term>, or rather <term ref="gfa-keywords-9529">"warts"</term>, and two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9099">draw hammers</term>, all driven by one and the same <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>. In addition to the above-mentioned products, they also manufacture the material for carriage and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">chaise</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">springs</term> by welding together so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8668">"German Steel"</term> (low-iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term>). <pb n="124" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589904"/> Here, too, the new, splendidly devised <term ref="gfa-keywords-8557">welding</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9282">annealing furnace</term> is used for this purpose, and they make dripping heats from 12 to 16 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long. It is quite certain that the English are our masters in all kinds of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">pyrotechnics</term>, which refer to boiling, <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealing</term> (and that under the most varied, and most importantly, precisely controlled degrees of heat), <term ref="gfa-keywords-9073">firing</term> (<term ref="gfa-keywords-9575">pottery</term>, etc.) and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">melting</term>. But one also finds so many advances and techniques applied, which have their basis in <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term>, which in any case can soon be regarded as only one science, that one has to admire the spirit of observation and the thoughtfulness of these people very much, indeed. For precisely these advances, which can be proved, were mostly invented only by common workers, to whom the theoretical knowledge in the above sciences, especially in any context and connection, was completely foreign. <pb n="125" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589905" break="no"/> Why this drive for improvement is nowhere to be found on the continent, and especially in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, but why most people prefer to remain in the rut as they have learned it, may be due in part to wanderlust (which is very different from sensible and expedient travel) and then also in the fact that, on the one hand, the master, who does not know much better, instead of consulting others, especially in the case of an important or new task, only wants to assert his master's right and infallibility and, on the other, the brother in <placeName ref="gfa-places-497">Hamburg</placeName> and the brother in <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName> do not want to let their glories be diminished by objections from their perhaps younger, but nevertheless more experienced director. What I have said here, incidentally, is not taken from thin air but is based on my own experience.</p>
                <p>While my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">steel</term> was being <term ref="gfa-keywords-9098">drawn</term>, one of the workers, who already knew <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">my son</persName>, <pb n="126" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589906"/> came to me and, assuring me that he knew every single facility of this factory, attempted to persuade me to take him with me to the continent. To some, such a request might have been very welcome, but not only would I not have wanted to take a worker from a factory where the owners showed me goodwill and trust, but one must be careful, in general, in our country to hire a so-called Englishman, which we consider pretty much synonymous with nonplus ultra. For they cost a great deal of money, since the proper and at the same time skilled ones always earn a good living in England, are often drunkards, and they seldom, even if they really know the whole of fabrication, which, incidentally, is very rare and can only be expected from a good so-called "Foreman", meet the expectation, because they have to deal with different material <pb n="127" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589907"/> and with different people than they have in their own country.</p>
                <p>On our way <placeName ref="gfa-places-2104" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-12" n="63" cert="0">home</placeName>, we caught sight of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> which makes the daily (and I believe several times) trip between <placeName ref="gfa-places-2045">Richmond</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. It is the smallest and sweetest thing I have ever seen and covers the distance, 15 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term>, I am told, in barely 5/4 hours. This is already very fast, but not nearly as fast as the steamboat Caroline, which runs regularly between London and <placeName ref="gfa-places-2008">Margate</placeName> and is said to cover this distance of 100 English miles in six, and if the wind and tide are favourable, even in five hours. To get to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1648" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-12" n="62">Southwark</placeName>, I crossed <placeName ref="gfa-places-2108" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-12" n="61">Waterloo Bridge</placeName>. This bridge is very solid, but in my opinion, not in good taste. Such a pure and sublime style, as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2109"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2109">Börse</placeName></placeName>, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName> <pb n="128" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589908" break="no"/> at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2015"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9790">theatre</term></placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2013">Glyptothek</placeName>, or in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName> and several other <term ref="gfa-places-35">German</term> residential cities on so many new structures, I have not encountered in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, to the extent that I have seen, on any public structure. The mechanics, on the other hand, have also contributed their share to this bridge. Since pedestrians have to pay a <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">toll</term> and pass through a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9281">turnstile</term>, but the owner of the toll employs only one person, an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9280">indicator</term> is connected to it in the inner room, which shows the number of people who have passed through or back over a period of days, weeks and months. This calculating or, in this case, price-determining device is also used in other, truly amusing ways, much to the chagrin of tobacco smokers who would like to smoke a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">pipe</term> for free in the pub. In England, in fact, only foreigners smoke, <pb n="129" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589909"/> and then only military personnel, seafarers, and those of the lower classes. It is not done in the better <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">coffee houses</term>, but in the lesser ones, where there are separate smoking rooms for this purpose. However, people do not carry pipes and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9072">tobacco</term> with them as they do in our <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">country</placeName>. The pipe (white earthen) is obtained from the landlord, but the tobacco is on the table in a sealed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8638"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9233">tin can</term></term>. For the innkeeper it would be much too far and unreliable to collect from the consumer the amount for each pipe that is filled, which amounts to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term> or three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. The tobacco box thus has a special compartment with a hole, like a paupers' box, into which just one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term> goes. In the inside, opposite the hole, is the arm of a lever, the other end of which is connected to the latch that closes the <pb n="130" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589910"/> lid of the tobacco box, and its length is calculated in such a way that only the weight of a penny and nothing less can open it. If one now wants to stuff his pipe, one tosses in a penny, the lid pops open, and the smoker has what he needs. If someone thinks he can get away with a half penny, the deception is punished immediately, as the box, because the weight is too light for the lever, remains inexorably closed, and he must add another whole penny, because a second half is not enough to open the box, since the first half does not remain on the lever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Journey home via Paris, 13-21 October 1827</head>
                <p>Having finished the main item of my business today, I had no reason to remain in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> any longer, and so, in order to gain time, I decided to get a seat on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">coach</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" notBefore="1827-10-13T17:00:00" notAfter="1827-10-13T23:59:00" n="64">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" n="65">Dover</placeName> in the evening. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> the Sovereign brought me to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-14" n="66">Calais</placeName> on the <date when="1827-10-14">14th</date> <pb n="131" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589911"/> amidst <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">heavy winds and thunderstorms</placeName>, and the courier from there to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1605" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-15T12:00:00" n="67">Amiens</placeName> on the <date when="1827-10-15T12:00:00">15th</date> at noon and to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-16T04:00:00" n="68">Paris</placeName> on the <date when="1827-10-16T04:00:00">16th</date> at 4 o'clock in the morning.</p>
                <p>In order to attend to some business, I remained there the <date when="1827-10-16">16th</date> and <date when="1827-10-17">17th</date>, and had the pleasure of making the acquaintance of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7816">Delessert</persName>, Banquier of Paris, one of the most distinguished <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> residents of that city, to whom, incidentally, I did not have an introduction at all, but only verbal communication from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7753">Perkins</persName>, to see in the most glaring light the contrast in urbanity with the dirtiness of a money trader in London, who, incidentally, is not English<note>Fischer means <persName ref="gfa-actors-8295">Nathan Mayer Rothschild</persName>, whom he met on 24 und 27 September 1827.</note>, and to whom I was able to pass a few lines from one of his friends. On the <date when="1827-10-17T18:00:00">17th</date> in the evening at 6 o'clock I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-17T18:00:00" n="69">Paris</placeName>, on the <date when="1827-10-18T12:00:00">18th</date> at noon I was in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1915" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-18T12:00:00" n="70">Chalons sur Marne</placeName>, on the <date notBefore="1828-10-19T16:00:00" notAfter="1828-10-19T23:59:00">19th</date> in the evening in <placeName ref="gfa-places-470" type="itinerar" notBefore="1828-10-19T16:00:00" notAfter="1828-10-19T23:59:00" n="71">Strasbourg</placeName>, on the <date when="1827-10-20">20th</date> passing through <placeName ref="gfa-places-10" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-20" n="72">Basel</placeName> until 9 o'clock at night, <pb n="132" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589912"/> where on the way I very miraculously escaped a great accident caused by the carelessness of the coachman, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1817" type="itinerar" when="1827-10-20T21:00:00" n="73">Stein near Säkingen</placeName>, and on the <date notBefore="1827-10-21T12:00:00" notAfter="1827-10-21T19:00:00">21st</date> in the afternoon thank God happily and well <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237"><placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" notBefore="1827-10-21T12:00:00" notAfter="1827-10-21T19:00:00" n="74">at home</placeName></persName>.</p>
                <p>With difficulty I will return to that country which I have so recently left and in which I have seen and learned about so many things. Two things, however, as the results of my repeated observations, will continue to occupy my mind even at a distance.</p>
                <p>First of all, by what causes and by what means not <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term> but the spirit and mind for industry and its nature and methods has developed there (political and pecuniary power alone do not ensure this; <placeName ref="gfa-places-138">Spain</placeName> never had it, even if at one time the sun never set in the lands of its sovereign), and how, now, however, as nothing human remains unchangeable, the culmination point <pb n="133" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16589913" break="no"/> in this respect seems to have already occurred in England itself. For Providence, as the educator of the human race, has so willed it, as a consequence of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">Continental system</term>, that the continent has come to realize its own strengths and, wherever they are nurtured and nourished, that which the necessity of life demands and that which adorns and delights it is produced from its own bosom with greater success every day.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>