<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="7">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Traveljournal 1851</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="jcf">
                    Handschriftliche Widmung durch <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Conrad Fischer</persName>
                </handNote>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle><figure xml:id="fig0">
                    <graphic url="images/JCF1851-Titelblatt.jpg"/></figure>
                    <titlePart type="main"><pb n="I" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618482"/> Journal of a trip to the Exhibition in London and to some industrial cities in England in the summer of 1851.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <lb/>
                <byline>By J. C. Fischer, Lieutenant Colonel. With appended lithographic illustration.</byline>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint>Schaffhausen. Printed by Murbach &amp; Gelzer. <docDate>1853</docDate>.</docImprint><note>Im Exemplar des Tagebuchs, das als Vorlage für die Edition dient, steht folgende Widmung in Fischers Handschrift: «Seinem wehrten Reisegefährten zur Industrie–Ausstellung nach London, und zum Andenken, dem Herrn Kantonsrath Amman von Ermatingen. der Verfasser»</note>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="content">
                <head>Titelseite</head>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Gedanken zur Weltausstellung in London 1851</head>            
                <p>Foreword.</p>
                <p><pb n="III" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618484"/>Anyone who, for 60 years, through more or less active involvement in the technical field, combined with observation of what has newly emerged in the areas of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term>, finds himself in the position of being able to make a comparison between what existed in <date to="1791-12-31" from="1791-01-01">1791</date> and what presently exists in <date to="1851-12-31" from="1851-01-01">1851</date>, he must, in observing the progress made in this period relative to what happened in earlier periods of the same duration, be astonished, one might say dumbfounded, by what the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">world's fair in London</term></placeName> presents to us this year; and one is compelled almost involuntarily to exclaim "Enough, now; stop at once, human spirit, to work as you do; repose, and savour, as well, the fruits of your so manifold endeavours, for everything is transitory, after all!" — But that <pb n="IV" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618485"/> is the nature and the prerogative of the eternally prevailing human spirit, emanating from the Creator and moving through both passing and future generations, to produce again and again in greater perfection, or in some alternative way, what the ravages of time devour from the earthly. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">glass palace</placeName>, with its thousand glories, will disappear again from the Earth, leaving no trace of its existence, yet only to make way, once again, for something new. These simultaneously exhilarating and disheartening reflections by no means exclude the homage that must be paid to the present with its achievements and to this world exhibition, in particular; and I, whose record of it is contained in these pages (kept, admittedly, for frequent lack of time, sometimes only sparsely), do not regret this trip in the slightest; no one, however, should expect to find here an index or catalogue or, much less, a systematic description of even a fraction of the exhibits; this is simply my diary, the account I give to myself of how I spent my time. Illustrated and non-illustrated papers will provide enough coverage of the exhibition, without exhausting it, while my final verdict, after having observed <pb n="V" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618486" break="no"/> and repeatedly observed, is that one can describe, another can listen to or read the description, but will, insofar as I infer from my own experience, never have or be able to obtain a genuine impression of this extraordinary event, if he has not seen it for himself. — As satisfied as I am with the outcome of what I had hoped to see and saw, limited as it was to just a few things, and also with the verdict I reached on the small and inconspicuous things I sent to the exhibition, which I perhaps owe only to the circumstance that they were objects of a peculiar kind, I was even more satisfied with the results of my stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, as well as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, and some pages of my diary filled up in an interesting way that quite deeply imprinted in my memory for recollection, and I close the same with thanks to the Highest that only a few weeks before my <date when="1852-09-14">seventy-ninth birthday</date>, in full strength, I was able to undertake the journey to this <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">remarkable island</placeName> and to add these notes about it to those from earlier times.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, <date when="1852-07-21">21 July 1852</date>.<note>Das Tagebuch wurde 1853 bei <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7553">Murbach &amp; Gelzer</orgName> in Schaffhausen gedruckt.</note>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">I. C. Fischer</persName>.
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Schaffhausen–Freiburg, 12. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="1" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618488"/> On <date when="1851-06-12" type="travelday">June 12th</date>, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="1">Schaffhausen</placeName> at 1 o'clock in the afternoon, via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1618" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="2">Stühlingen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1619" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="3">Lenzkirch</placeName>, for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="5">Freiburg</placeName>. Regardless of the weather conditions, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1620" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="4">Höllenthal</placeName> always remains a most fascinating natural phenomenon. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9069">geognosist</term> must ask himself what tremendous forces created this deep and vertical cleft to form the bed of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1621">Treisam</placeName>? — The most striking scenes are visible only on a moonlit night, as was the case today. How must it have been for the solitary wanderer in earlier times, as he left this yet uninhabited realm of shadows and entered, full of awe, the lowlands of paradise? — This, as did a little later the so daringly constructed and artificially perforated <placeName ref="gfa-places-1622">tower</placeName> of the minster in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122">Freiburg</placeName>, which stood out just as peculiarly, and has defied the force of the elements in unshakeable solidity for almost a millennium, made an immense impression on me. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1848"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8770">pyramids</term></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName> do not withstand comparison, neither in craftsmanship nor in beauty, with this magnificent structure, which was born of the old German spirit. — These were my thoughts, more or less, <pb n="2" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618489"/> and with far fewer resources than we have at our disposal today, this miracle could be accomplished, as we stopped in front of the post office in Freiburg around 11 o'clock and took up our quarters for the night at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1713" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-12" n="6">Engel</placeName>, amazed to find no strangers there at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Freiburg–Mannheim, 13. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>I say we, for I had as traveling companions two other <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName>, a worthy compatriot, Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName>, and Cantonal Councillor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">Ammann</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-984">Ermatingen</placeName>, on whom the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7451">current President of France</persName> often called when he was still living in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1165">Gottlieben</placeName>. On the <date when="1851-06-13" type="travelday">13th</date>, they accompanied me on the rather monotonous journey from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="7">Freiburg</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1123" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="8">Carlsruhe</placeName>, where we parted ways, as they also undertook an excursion to <placeName ref="gfa-places-47">Frankfurt</placeName>.</p>
                <p>	I had enough time in the afternoon to visit Director <persName ref="gfa-actors-7452" type="met">Ziegler</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7453" type="met">Kachel</persName> Currency Councillor. From the former, I learned of important developments that were to compel the member states of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8307">German Custom's Union</orgName> to raise <term ref="gfa-keywords-522">tariffs</term> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, which, however, as clear as the reasons for this appear to be, are not being duly observed in <placeName ref="gfa-places-17">Bern</placeName> for reasons that cannot be discussed here. From the latter, I learned that the renowned <persName ref="gfa-actors-7960"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8437">Uhlhorn press</term></persName> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9063">minting currency</term> (which I had already seen in operation in <placeName ref="gfa-places-98">Munich</placeName>) was victorious at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">London exhibition</term> for its efficiency over the one displayed there by the excellent mechanic Maudsley<note>Als ausgezeichneter Mechaniker und Begründer des englischen Werkzeugmaschinenbaus gilt <persName ref="gfa-actors-7454">Henry Maudslay (1771–1831)</persName>. Fischer bezieht sich hier sehr wahrscheinlich auf seine Söhne, die das Familienunternehmen nach dem Tod des Vaters weiterführten. Welchen der beiden Söhne Fischer hier meint, ob <persName ref="gfa-actors-7896">Thomas Henry Maudslay (1792–1864)</persName> oder <persName ref="gfa-actors-7897">Joseph Maudslay (1801–1861)</persName>, kann nicht eruiert werden.</note> that operated by a different system. <pb n="3" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618490" break="no"/> It was even viewed with pleasure by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen Victoria</persName> and the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7456">Duchess of Nemours</persName>. At 4 o'clock, I left again by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="11">Mannheim</placeName>, visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7457" type="met">Eisenhardt</persName> there, and after dinner at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1712" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-13" n="13">Teutschen Hof</placeName>, wrote these lines.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Mannheim–Köln, 14. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>	The <date when="1851-06-14" type="travelday">14th</date>. Although there is much to enjoy about a journey on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhine</placeName> by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="14">Mannheim</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-82" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="15">Cologne</placeName>, owing to the ever-changing and remarkable view of the shoreline in fine weather, which not only permits a stay on the deck but even invites one to do so, it becomes rather tedious when one is confined to the cabin or the so-called salon by cold, storm or rain, as was the case today in contrast to yesterday's beautiful, warm, though somewhat windy day. Also, for me at least, there was no one to engage in instructive or interesting conversation among the few educated passengers, so I was able to recover some sleep, which I had lost the two previous days by going to bed late and getting up very early; <persName ref="gfa-actors-35"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">we</persName></persName></persName> arrived in <note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> Cologne at 7 o'clock in the evening, where I took up my quarters at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1711" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-14" n="17">Kölnischer Hof</placeName>.</p>  
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Köln–Ostende, 15. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>The <date when="1851-06-15" type="travelday">15th</date>. Today was far more interesting to me, with respect to various observations, than was yesterday, though the speed of the journey by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rail</term> hardly allows for the observation of any objects <pb n="4" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618491"/> outside it. — I was attracted, first, by the generally so very sectioned terrain, and then by the excellent cultivation of the soil, the further along one progresses, until finally entering <placeName ref="gfa-places-1623" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-15" n="18">Flanders</placeName>. The horticultural crops, particularly the vegetables, seem to be far more advanced than our own, but even more interesting to me was the number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">factories</term> of all kinds, whose existence, as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, is indicated by the high chimney stacks, and also by the numerous shipments of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> parts, as well as by the quantity of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> ores and the pure zinc derived from them.</p>
                <p>There may come a time when the discovery will be made why <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> has not become wholly <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, or iron, in a given case, has not become either <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> or zinc, since I have much reason to believe that the primary matter of these three <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term> is one and the same — A hypothesis about this, if it were in itself as simple as nature in its workings, could perhaps make one ridiculous, and yet I want to cite a case that would seem to give some support to my conjecture. As is well known, iron and copper, especially when they are melted together in fairly equal quantities, do not combine even in the highest flux, but instead, regardless of whether the mixture is poured into moulds or allowed to cool in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>, <pb n="5" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618492"/> separate distinctly from one another like oil and water, and only a small percentage, due to <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">stoichiometric</term> relationships, is absorbed by one from the other, yet the essential character of both metals remains. However, I had already accomplished this bond in various ratios in <date from="1814-01-01" to="1814-12-31">1814</date>, and I made it known under the name "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8522">yellow steel</term>" in the <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-2.xml">diary of my trip to England in 1814</ref>, published in <date from="1816-01-01" to="1816-12-31">1816</date> by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7458">H. Remigius Sauerländer</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-2">Aarau</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If one did not know that this was a metal compound, or so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term>, one might say: it is not <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, because it has a yellow colour and a different <term ref="gfa-keywords-9116">specific gravity</term>, while another might say: but it is also not <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, because it is yellow and is drawn by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">magnet</term> like iron, and it is also not <term ref="gfa-keywords-3405">gun metal</term>, and not <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term>, because, when thrown red-hot into water, it becomes hard, almost like <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>. However, the art to the formation of this metal, which I will call <emph rend="italic">a</emph>, is to add something that is lacking in each of the two individual substances; if that something, or these new basic elements, were not added, ♀ + ♂ would not = <emph rend="italic">a</emph>, and so iron will neither become copper nor zinc, nor will zinc become iron, if these essential additives, which enable their transformation, are missing. As I should have noted at the outset, my better understanding <note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> in the meantime <pb n="6" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618493"/> has led me to believe, in contradiction with general opinion, that these metals are not simple bodies, though I readily admit that my above hypothesis concerning the existence of multiple basic elements of these metals does, indeed, have its weaknesses. However, the fact itself, of transference from one matter into another, still remains, and as long as we do not know the manner of formation of the metals, the bonding agent of their various atoms and the stoichiometric relationships necessary for this purpose, the dispute as to whether they are simple or compound will remain unresolved.</p>
                <p>With these thoughts, not knowing how better to occupy my time on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">train</term>, I arrived at the station in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1624" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-15" n="19">Ghent</placeName>, where the immensely light, yet solid construction of the two buildings whose columns of great height and width are made entirely of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and whose roofs are composed only at the bottom of a single band of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">zinc</term> and, then, up to the top, entirely of glass, captivated my full attention, so that I also invited <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">my two traveling companions</persName></persName>, who arrived with me in <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cologne</placeName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-47">Frankfurt</placeName>, to view this graceful and peculiar building. — I wondered, is it the case, here, that the architect of this station in Ghent<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note>, earlier, and <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7459">Paxton</persName>, who built the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Glass Palace</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, later, had similar ideas without knowing of one another; as <persName ref="gfa-actors-3060">Newton</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7460">Leibniz</persName>, where, <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618494"/> while the former invented his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8439">fluxions</term>, the latter founded the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8440">doctrine of calculus infinitorum</term>?</p>
                <p>	I had continued to hope that it would still be as before that a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboat</term> would leave <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-15" n="20">Ostende</placeName>, where we arrived in the evening after 7 o'clock, for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> the following morning, so that I could get a full night’s rest instead of the few hours I had slept the previous three nights, especially as I was, in fact, still a kind of convalescent, and my doctor had, perhaps only semi-voluntarily, released me from his care to make this strenuous journey. Alas, it was to be a true night of suffering, such as I had never experienced on my frequent sea voyages. It had been windy all day, but towards evening it became much stronger and mixed with rain. After a short dinner in Ostende, my two travel companions and I boarded the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8441">Royal Mail Steamship</term>, which, according to a new schedule, sets sail every evening at 10 o'clock. We had taken our places on the first available seat or in the salon, and as long as the ship was still in the harbour, the passengers passed to and fro, there might have been 20 to 24 of them, and all were in good spirits. In the meantime, I delighted in the small round windows, of which there were only five on either side along the entire length of the salon and which resemble those on our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8946">Schaffhausen steamship</term> to a hair's breadth, spreading in the daytime <pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618495" break="no"/> just the same pleasant darkness so beloved by the English in their meditations and which might well inspire us to meditate too: yet, alas, it was to be otherwise. No sooner were we at sea than the violent swaying of the ship and the jolts made it clear that it was quite unsafe out there, and those with more sensitive natures soon began to suffer from <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasickness</term> in its full, ravaging form. My fairly good constitution withstood it for a long time, however, with the swaying of the ship, which became more violent from hour to hour, combined with repulsion at the effects of this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">disease</term>, which is similar to cholera for its rapid spread among the passengers lying about in every direction, and their groaning and moaning, I could no longer endure it, and I do not recall ever having suffered so much during the at least four-hour duration of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Ankunft in Dover, 16. Juni 1851</head>
                <p> On <date when="1851-06-16" type="travelday">June 16th</date>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName>, who could no longer bear to remain in the salon, which looked more like a death chamber, remained on deck from 3 o'clock in the morning on, despite the storm and rain, and today he reported to me, as we recounted our tales of woe, which even afterwards imposed on us a strict diet, that in that same hour the waves had become so high that they sometimes reached the helmsman at his post, who then quite phlegmatically shook the water off his coat of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">Indian rubber</term>. After 9 o'clock in the morning (the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8441">steamboat</term> was unable to land at low tide, <pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618496" break="no"/> so remained on the high seas), we were picked up by smaller boats, and soon after were able to have our belongings, of which the night bags were not inspected at all, and the suitcases only superficially, taken to the inn. As a comment on the fact that nothing, not even misfortune, can be had cheaply in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, I will add that the waiter on the steamboat, who had the courtesy to provide the victims of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">disease</term> with the necessary basins, of which there was at most one, for every two persons, was paid 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> or 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term>. of our money per person; then it cost another 36 kr. per person to get from the steamboat, which should have but failed to taken us, to shore on the other boat, and finally I had to pay 36 kr. to the porter, who carried my suitcase and the night bag to the inn, which was only the third house from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153">customs office</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If, by chance, anyone should be bored by this tale of woe, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">my two aforementioned traveling companions</persName></persName> will confirm word for word, then rightfully so, for so too am I. Only once was I compelled to laugh in the midst of all the misery, when the thought occurred to me, if only a skilled caricaturist were at hand to depict all the postures<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> and expressions of this heap of suffering humanity with the brush of a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7461">Hogarth</persName>. —</p>
                <p><pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618497"/> Of the ladies on board there is nothing to be said. The door to their salon remained closed, as is only proper; certainly, however, there will have been no lack of genuine sentimentality among them. Somewhat restored at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1715" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-16" n="21">inn</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7462">Hippgrave</persName>, after having written a letter <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">home</persName> and inviting them to join me, I walked around the town with my two traveling companions to see if they were satisfied by the first impression this, one might say in some respects, wonderland had made on them.</p>
                <p>	Aside from the picturesque setting of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, we admired the lavishly decorated<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> stores and the generally accomplished works displayed therein, and lastly, the inviting <term ref="gfa-keywords-9449">seaside resorts</term>, so appropriately designed. Weary from the previous night's events, and weary from writing, I will retire for the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Dover–London, 17. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>	<date when="1851-06-17" type="travelday">June 17th</date>. After a delightful night's sleep, and some notes taken after breakfast, I left for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="23">London</placeName> by <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rail</term> at a quarter past 9 o'clock.</p>
                <p>	Inside the barbarous wooden boxes of the second-class carriages, which reveal this island's ferociously speculative spirit, we were joined by two Englishmen and the daughter of one of them, a young woman of about 14 years of age. Her father told me that she had already been with <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618498"/> relatives in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName> for 6 years and spoke German, which was, indeed, the case and superbly so. I have often remarked that children learn foreign languages much quicker than adults do, though the mental powers of the latter are more developed. Whoever wants to teach his children the knowledge and practice of other living languages at an early age should rather employ child caretakers and maids (the so-called governesses are usually too precise and, at least in their imagination, too learned) as teachers of those foreign languages than a professor with his<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> syntax and grammar, who has perhaps been torturing students with it for thirty years, and yet cannot himself speak any of the languages he teaches.</p>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-7450"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">My two traveling companions</persName></persName> were pleased to be able to converse with her, and through her with her father, who, as he informed me, was a landowner in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1627">York</placeName> but lived in London. He was a highly educated and well-travelled man, spoke French and German<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> in addition to his mother tongue, and perhaps it is due to the fact that I conversed with him in all three languages, in turn, that when I took leave of him at the train station in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, he pulled out his wallet and presented me with his visiting card, which read, "Mr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7463">Minet</persName>, 19, Old Quebeckstreet, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1717">Oxfordstreet</placeName>, near the marble arch," <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618499" break="no"/> together with an invitation to certainly pay him a visit. While the invitation from an Englishman who hardly knew me was extraordinary to me, I will accept it.</p>
                <p>	In the hustle and bustle of collecting<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> our baggage, which is not assigned numbers as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, and for which, even if heavy and numerous, one never pays anything, I lost my two traveling companions, who, by the way, had to take a completely different route to their lodging than I did to mine.</p>
                <p>	Upon arriving at the same, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="24">St. Paul's Family Hotel</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1700">St. Paul's Churchyard</placeName>, I certainly would not have been given a room, since there has been another owner there for 4 years now, if the head waiter had not fortuitously recognized me straight away and promised to find me a room in the house, or elsewhere if no one left, by evening. Since it was barely 1 o'clock, and dinner is not until after 4 o'clock, I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1615" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="25">Newgate Street</placeName> to visit the ironmonger Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2201"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7546">Fenn</orgName></placeName><note>Beide Brüder, Samuel und Daniel Fenn, hatten ihr Geschäft an der Newgate Street. Es ist unklar, welchen Herrn Fenn Fischer besuchte.</note>, with whom I had already become acquainted in <date when="1794">1794</date>, when I was then working for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName>, a mechanic in London, but did not find him at the shop, and bought various things for my wardrobe, which I had not wished to carry with me from home.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="day">
                <head>Das Ausstellungsgelände: Erster Eindruck, 17. Juni 1851</head>
                    <p>After dinner I immediately boarded an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> to be taken for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term> (this is the fare from the area where I am staying) <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618500" break="no"/> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition building</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="26">Hyde park</placeName>, a little over 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> away: — not to go inside, but only to get a first impression of its position, circumference, style and execution, so that it would be independent of the interior, as the soul of the entirety. I was convinced that this impression must be different from the one conveyed by drawings, since the latter encompass neither foreground nor background, just as little as the side walls, of any importance to convey the proper scale of the whole, which even a linear scale, incidentally, would not provide. I have just had an idea, and <ref type="cross" target="TB7_p_107">at the end of this volume</ref>, I will attempt to establish a scale, at least for the citizens of my beloved <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">hometown</placeName>, that will produce a fairly accurate estimate of the extent of this building, and that will make the numbers comprehensible.</p>
                    <p>	The building is positioned rather low on the landscape, very close to the bank of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1628">Serpentine River</placeName>, and the main façade is often obscured by oak trees, some of which stand very close to it, which greatly diminishes the impression that this palace, if free of this environment and standing on some elevation, would otherwise make. The choice of this building site was, however, an unavoidable necessity that cannot be faulted; however, one is mistaken to imagine this glass palace as transparent, like a lantern. Of the high, narrow window frames formed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast-iron</term> columns, 24 are filled with an uninterrupted series of planed wooden boards, painted light brown, to the left and right of which 4 such frames are filled with glass. The <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618501" break="no"/> description I provide here applies only to the ground floor; I can say nothing about the superstructure, which, along with the roof, is completely covered with glass. I walked around the entire building, which is surrounded, as it seems to me, too closely and at an oppressive distance, by a heavy iron fence, which forms between the two only a narrow alley that is filled with all manner of woodwork and broken boxes, among which, in turn, individually submitted objects of lesser importance, which were not brought into the building, because they could not be disassembled, such as, for example, on the northern side a large stone crucifix from <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>. An exception to the above is the southern wall or the short side of the building, from which the aforementioned iron fence stands at a greater distance, forming a beautiful space or courtyard, on which can be found <term ref="gfa-keywords-9575">earthenware</term> in dimensions likely never before produced, for use as vessels for chemicals, as well as other receptacles; crooked and straight pipes of stoneware for conducting water and other liquids, and thus coated neither inside nor out with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9129">glaze</term>, but glazed, like a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8446">Selters mineral water jug</term>, by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9218">salt vapours</term> produced in the kiln; immensely heavy <term ref="gfa-keywords-8796">anchors</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9285">ships</term> and equally immense blocks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coal</term>; <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618502" break="no"/> then a column made from a single piece of cut and polished <term ref="gfa-keywords-8507">granite</term>, 20 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high and without a capital; large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9426">slate</term> slabs; a wall of hollow bricks, of which I had already conceived and for whose production I had received an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8447">imperial license</term> in <date when="1826">1826</date> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>; beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8830">sculptural</term> objects, along with several other striking sculptural and architectural ornamentations; as well as interesting lifeboats, etc., about all of which the catalogues report far better than is possible for me to do in so brief an overview.</p>
                    <p>	It was interesting to see the crowd walking to and fro, since it was already about 7 o'clock in the evening. Riding, it would seem, is fashionable again among the women; I observed several, each accompanied by her cavalier, riding up and down the avenue along the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1629">New river</placeName> side; they wore dark blue long riding dresses, and, as if by agreement, small round felt hats, like the so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8448">Hecker hat</term>", though I believe, as daughters of Eve, their thoughts under these hats are less revolutionary than lustful. The calmness and decency among this crowd was remarkable, and it did not seem to me at all that I had seen any arrested expressions as those that appear in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> on the eve of a revolution, or after it has already broken out. <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618503" break="no"/> The police are not at all bothersome; one is pleased to see them, as they are not mouchards<note>Franz. umgangssprachlich für «Spione».</note>, but rather polite and eager to serve. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gaslights</term> were already beginning to burn in the stores, which prompted me to return to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-17" n="26.1">my lodging</placeName> to write the foregoing and retire for the day at 11 o'clock in the evening.</p>    
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers erster Ausstellungsbesuch, 18. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>	The <date when="1851-06-18" type="travelday">18th</date>. At the usual time in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, namely after 10 o'clock in the morning, I commenced my daily business, visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7863" type="met">Howard</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7468" type="met"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2134" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="28">Im Thurn</placeName></persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469" type="met"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1703" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="29">Faraday</placeName></persName>, for whom, since he had gone out, I left my card, and then went from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-18" n="30"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, where I stayed until 6 o'clock in the evening.</p>
                <p>	From the outside, as I already thought to myself yesterday, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">building</placeName> did not make the extraordinary impression on me that I had expected, and the reasons for this are as follows: first, for its immense length, it has no corresponding height, though the transept from the ground to the highest point of the semicircular vault measures 108 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">English feet</term>. In this case, however, it was wise to concentrate on the special requirements of the situation, rather than follow standard protocol. Secondly, due to its proximity to the trees and its somewhat low position, the building cannot be viewed as a whole. Yet, upon entering, one has no choice but to be astonished by the very idea of it. How so many nations of the world, and in such different ways, have paid homage to it, and how these various displays, <pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618504" break="no"/> despite their variety of material and form, have been so judiciously united into a whole — and to think that all this, including the colossal structure itself, was erected in such an incredibly short and strictly defined period. It would be a conceited, one might say quite ridiculous, undertaking to describe even a few of these multitudinous objects in any detail. The catalogues, public newspapers, and men of letters who have already written about this subject, or who will write about it in the future, say enough on this subject. However, one item particularly attracted my attention today, whose beauty must certainly be admired by all, and whose absolute uniqueness — namely the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8450">fountain</term>, which, by my estimation, has a height of 30 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, all parts of which are made of the most beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9105">crystal glass</term>, weighing almost 90 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>, and over whose uppermost bowl or basin the water falls, first, as a large veil and then, further down, in beautiful cascades, which, in the absence of flowing water, can be immediately transformed into the most dazzling and largest <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">candelabra</term> in the world. There are several other fountains of various kinds in the building, including one whose stone basin measures 36 feet in diameter, yet in these immense spaces is neither disruptive or conspicuous.</p>
                <p>The second thing that captured my attention for some time <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618505"/> were the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8502">wax figures</term>, life-size and adorned with their ornaments, of an Indian and his wife from the primeval forests of <placeName ref="gfa-places-250">Amerika</placeName>, the redskins, as they are called. Such a race of humans still exists, in contrast to those of the most advanced culture. One recognizes at first sight that they are quite faithful reproductions, and without being a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7882">Lavater</persName>, one sees in the exceedingly pronounced features, hardened by toil, exertion, and even the highest indifferentism, a coarseness, cruelty, and then again languor, and yet they too are human beings!</p>
                <p>	I note only in passing that in no country in the world would it have been possible to compile such a collection of the most remarkable things that the savage, semi-savage and highly civilized peoples have produced in art and craftsmanship, as is the case here. — Anyone who has seen this exhibition will carry the impression of it with him for the rest of his life, yet one must never expect anything but a fragmentary account of it.</p>
                <p>	Around 7 o'clock in the evening, I went to supper in a neighbouring, very nice <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">dining establishment</term>, where many of the gentlemen and ladies who had also come from the exhibition were present in several rooms, and lived, while enjoying everything in equal quality, 50 percent cheaper than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my hotel</placeName>, which is located in the city, where everything is much more expensive.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head> Fischers zweiter Ausstellungsbesuch, 19. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618506"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-19">June 19th</date></placeName>. After having gone early in hopes of visiting Dr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7470" type="met">Bolley</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471" type="met">Colladon</persName>, our two <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioners at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> (both staying in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="31">Finsbury Square</placeName>, a place, in fact, for its great distance from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition hall</placeName> not at all convenient for the duties of their office) and encountering neither, I was given a warm and cordial reception by England's first chemist, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName>, at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7575"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1703">Royal Institution</placeName></orgName>, and I was amply compensated for the long journey from Finsbury Square, where the above-mentioned compatriots are staying, to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1696" type="itinerar_London1851" when="1851-06-19" n="33">Albemarle Street</placeName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="34">Picadilly</placeName> by the most fascinating conversation I had with him.</p>
                <p>After almost an hour of discussion concerning primarily <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">pyrotechnical</term> objects, as well as the articles I had sent to the exhibition in response to a request I had received <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">at home</placeName>, I returned to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="35">exhibition</placeName>, which was not very far away (about half an hour). The thousands of echoes from the newspapers of all civilized countries will, without ever being able to exhaust the subject itself, describe it. I have already said how ludicrous it would be for a single individual to attempt anything remotely of the sort, and so I shall not, however many times I should go there, comment at all at length on what I have seen and admired.</p>
                <p><pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618507"/> <date when="1851-06-19">Today</date> I devoted myself first and foremost (it is forgivable for a father) to the search in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austrian</placeName> department for the submissions made by two of my sons who are established in that beautiful country, so richly endowed with natural treasures of all kinds.</p>
                <p>	Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8272"><persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName></orgName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName> delivered six tableaux of the most diverse assortment of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> and a seventh of samples of cast steel rods, the quality of whose shape, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">cut</term> and grade is to be judged by the jury at a later point in time, and Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-6330"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold Fischer</persName></orgName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-158">Traisen</placeName>, an exceptional collection of articles from the field of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-56">malleable Castiron</term>," which, though manufactured in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> earlier, albeit under a veil of secrecy, I also invented, and for which I was once awarded exclusive <term ref="gfa-keywords-8447">privilege</term> in <date when="1829">1829</date> by His Majesty the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7381">Emperor Francis</persName>. These articles of malleable cast iron were complemented by a number of beautifully crafted <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindles</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mills</term> from his factory. On my remark to one of the custodians, who are distributed throughout the building in small offices, that the labels ("tikets"), that is, the small plates bearing the name of the exhibitor and the number assigned to his products in the catalogue, were missing, I was given permission with the greatest generosity to add anything I should think appropriate in this regard myself. However, since these articles <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618508"/>  had been placed under Austrian protection, I thought it appropriate not to preempt but to inform the I &amp; R Commissioner, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472">v. Buschek</persName>, of the matter by letter.</p>
                <p>	Altogether, one notices a great obligingness towards all strangers everywhere, and especially among the police, as well, and how so much attention is paid to everything without one being aware of it. The following may serve as evidence. Among the articles in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9828">my shipment</term> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, of which I had an illustration made <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">at home</placeName> by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-404">Beck</persName>, the drawing teacher, an engraving of which I commissioned in <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, there were also two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8971">daggers</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteoric steel</term> of very beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damask</term>. Upon looking after my things at the exhibition, these daggers, which had been placed in a rather exposed location, had gone missing.</p>
                <p>	I was nearly convinced that they had vanished, and so I inquired with an official. The latter immediately sent a policeman to another official, who, as would be the case, had been entrusted with the supervision of the articles of the Swiss department. He arrived forthwith and retrieved them from behind a large piece of meteoric steel, where they had been placed for greater security. They were then given a more suitable place for viewing.</p>
                <p>	Thousands and thousands of objects, each of them peculiar in its own way, remain unobserved, depending on the character of the observer, <pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618509" break="no"/> yet, for one thing the industrious and ingenious country of England has compelled the attention of every visitor, and this is that in which it also claims highest rank in the world, namely, the quantity of its curious machines; they produce all manner of things before the spectator's very eyes. Here, they artfully <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">weave</term> beautiful and complex designs. There, they print; there, they <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">spin</term>; there, hundreds of the most sensible machines and tools are displayed, all designed to save time and serve perfectly the needs of life, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agriculture</term>, luxury and the arts, and in the very midst of these various machines, at the side of a fountain, of which there are many in the building, in general, providing ample water for cooling and drinking, a millstream rushes in perpetual flow from the opening of an upright parallelepiped (tall narrow box), as if from a monstrous gullet, 10 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high, and in a width of approximately 6 feet, into a relatively large basin. One cannot see where the water comes from, one cannot see where it goes, like the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8454">Danaids' barrel</term>, the basin never fills.  I wondered why, so as to make the whole thing still more imposing, they had not enclosed this surprisingly prosaic box with planks of imitation rock? In <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">Frankreich</placeName>, where they well-versed in the wrapping of everything in a pleasing manner, they would certainly <pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618510"/> have done something of the sort, and in <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>, where they still delight in miracles, they would perhaps even have added a <persName ref="gfa-actors-8265">Moses</persName> with a staff. The English have not yet reached the zenith of figurative poetry. According to my calculation, I had covered eleven <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> on foot between 9 o'clock in the morning and after 5 o'clock in the evening on my long walks, and now faced the bleak prospect of making yet another considerable journey to the city, as all the carriages from the exhibition building were occupied. At the far end of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="36">Picadilly</placeName>, I was fortunate enough to be able to occupy a seat vacated by another passenger on an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term>, and to have my highly afflicted body brought to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-19" n="37">my lodging</placeName>, to finally have supper at about 7 o'clock, and to write down the foregoing ruminations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Über das Leben in London, 20. Juni 1851</head>
                <p>	<placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-20">June 20th</date></placeName>. The big cities are, with few exceptions, unpleasant and ruinous for those condemned to spend their entire lives there; they are veritable dungeons! Happy is he who is permitted to pass his days in honourable employment in our beautiful <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">fatherland</placeName>! — Londoners are never, or only very rarely, smiled upon by a sky as clear as our own, or rather, nearly the whole year through, they see nothing but the pall of smoke and dust spread so abundantly and vaporously over the metropolis. They do not behold the beautiful meadows, the running brooks, the green <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618511"/> forests, much less the silver crown of our <placeName ref="gfa-places-5">Alps</placeName>! — Grey and black-brown rows of houses without end, the ceaseless sound and noise of innumerable carts, laconic conversation or complete silence in the dining rooms of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inns</term> and even common taverns, where each of the arrivals first looks around in search of an unoccupied table, and as quickly as possible barricades himself behind an excessively large newspaper. This is but a brief, and certainly unexaggerated, sketch of London life, on the whole. — The bright side of all this, however, is that they are far more for domestic life than their neighbours across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">channel</placeName>, and that their quietude, and the spirit of study and advancement thus cultivated, applied even to the most inconspicuous of things, renders them capable of the astonishingly great things which they have already accomplished, and continue to accomplish. To these thoughts and comparisons, I was prompted by the various activities of the day, which I began and ended with difficulty, though it became interesting enough to me through an encounter with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9502">steel manufacturer</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1631">Newcastle upon Tyne</placeName>. I could not go to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, nor to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8455">Chinese collection</term>, which is not far from it, and made no other acquaintance than that of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-20" n="38">the banker where I withdraw the money</placeName> I need, and much is needed, indeed. It is good to have earned it in advance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Der «Fünf-Schilling-Abend», 21. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618512"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-21">June 21st</date></placeName>. After a few outings very early in the morning, that is, in these late summer days at half past 7 o'clock, when most shops are still closed and there are not very many people or carriages on the street, I went to the counting house of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-21" n="39">bank Paynes &amp; Smith</placeName>, for which I had received a cheque (payment order) of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L.</term> 30 yesterday, so that if someone else should present it for payment, I would not be obliged to honour it. However, only a few subordinates were there, who undertook to carry out my request, but told me that I would have to come back at 9 o'clock, as payments would not be issued until such time. The situation was as follows: The night before, while I was away, my tailor came to collect my coat for altering, however, in that very coat was my purse containing the cheque. I did not return home that evening until after 9 o'clock, by which time there was nothing I could do. <date when="1851-06-21" type="travelday">This morning</date>, after leaving the bank, I went directly to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1736" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="40">fabric shop</placeName> where I knew the tailor was working. — If, said the owner, the purse was in your coat, you will certainly get it back and whatever may be in it, upon which he went immediately to the tailor himself and brought back the purse and its contents in no time at all. In <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, there is much deceit, but also much honesty, I believe more of the latter than of the former. In this city, the drink in particular makes <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618513"/> people poor and unhappy. The latter among all classes.</p>
                <p>	Regarding punctuality in all those businesses where, to a certain extent, mathematical precision prevails, which certainly has its advantages, I would like to add that when I returned to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7583"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1632" type="itinerar" cert="0" when="1851-06-21" n="41">bank</placeName></orgName> a little before 9 o'clock, I was asked to take a seat on a <term ref="gfa-keywords-4350">bench</term> opposite the table at which the five cashiers conduct their business. About five minutes before 9 o'clock, the official to whom I was to present the payment order arrived. I held it in my hand and showed it to him, but he said not a word. Instead, he emptied several sacks of gold into a drawer together with the familiar shovel used to scoop it out again, and did nothing more.</p>
                <p>	At the stroke of 9 o'clock, however, he asked me only, Do you prefer <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9826">banknotes</term>? I replied gold. Without even counting (there were whole and half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8456">sovereigns</term>), he poured the gold into the pan and out of it onto the table without taking any further notice of me. I counted it anyway, and it was quite correct. — In order to know where Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7473">Wilson's</persName> office in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="42">glass palace</placeName> (one could not have chosen a better name) might be, I asked a "policeman" when I arrived there where I might find it, and he pointed me to a completely different, very distant side of the building. I found it <pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618514"/> all right, but did not encounter the man himself. About half an hour had passed since I decided to go home, when a police officer approached me quite some distance away from the spot. I thought to myself, What does he want? You have not done anything unlawful, after all. Then he stopped me and asked politely if I had found the office, to which I replied that I had, but this was proof to me of how carefully they observe people, for I was dressed in English style, that is to say in black. From him I first learned that the exhibition would remain open until the <date to="1851-10-31" from="1851-10-15">end of October</date>, which I was glad to hear, since <persName ref="gfa-actors-148"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">two of my sons</persName></persName>, who are established in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, were also planning to visit <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> later. I have already said how humble and polite these "policemen" are. They are all handsome, well-chosen people with dark blue tail coats, on the collar of which is embroidered the number under which the officer is registered, dark blue pantaloons, fine round hats, white gloves and, under their arm, a rolled-up overcoat of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8442">Indiarubber</term> (caoutschouc)" for dubious weather, but neither <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">tobacco pipe</term> nor <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre</term>, nor moustache. Well acquainted with the great city, or at least with the district assigned to them, anyone unsure of his bearings can obtain better information from no one, which they willingly give, even accompanying you for a distance, provided <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618515"/> that you speak English. — Today, being Saturday, the entrance fee, instead of 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term>, was now 5 shillings, like all Fridays and Saturdays. The rooms, however, were quite empty and, as I noted earlier, realized that, just as those less fortunate, richer people can grow equally accustomed to paying only a shilling for the same thing rather than five.</p>
                <p>	I remarked something else on this five-shilling evening, which was attended almost exclusively by people in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">equipages</term>, in proof of the great backward stride of the English in complying with the spirited catechism of the radicals. They still remain devoted to the so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8458">Zopfthum</term>" (whether this scurrilous term is of German or Swiss origin I do not know) among the general public in their country, by holding on to the good things from earlier times that have been recognized by experience, without making their eradication a popular idea to the general population, which then has the good fortune to be declared emancipated for the moment, in the form of brass music and chorale singing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Ein erfüllter Sonntag mit Schreiben, 22. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-22">June 22nd</date></placeName> Today, being Sunday, I began writing early, having stopped yesterday owing to genuine fatigue. Later I walked through the beautiful, rather extensive, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-22" n="45">Cheapside</placeName>, and would have liked to go into a "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Coffeeroom</term>" for a glass of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale</term> or claret, but apart from the fact that all the stores were hermetically sealed, so too were the doors. Even at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my inn</placeName>, the exterior door <pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618516"/> was closed, and only those who knew the secret could open it by turning the knob, otherwise one had to ring the bell. Returning to the inn, I asked the innkeeper, since I was in the habit of paying by the day, to bring me the bill, but he politely asked me to wait until morning. Whether this is the case at all inns, or whether he is some kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9456">sectarian</term>, I do not know, but I do know that on the mainland they are more willing to take whatever money falls into their hands, they are not so particular about it, so as not to deter visitors. However little the Sabbath observance is to be despised, but rather to be honoured in the highest degree, if it comes from a sincerely thankful heart, where then every day becomes a Sabbath day, Christ Himself taught us the best lesson about it, when the Pharisees, whom those of our days resemble to a hair's breadth, asked Him for His opinion on it. An English woman spoke very earnestly to me about the fact that Parliament allows <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cabs</term> ("cabriolets") to drive around town on Sunday and that <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroads</term> are allowed to operate, citing the God-fearing principles that have been practiced in her family, in that, when her dear father died and the funeral took place on a Sunday, the body (one does not carry it in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, one drives it to the churchyard) was not conveyed by her own horses, but by <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618517" break="no"/> hired ones. — I thought to myself, so it is they who are compelled to commit the sin of desecrating the Sabbath to spare her own from punishment. — In a province neighbouring the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">canton of Schaffhausen</placeName>, one often sees painted on the farmhouses a burning house, and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7474">St. Florian</persName> in immense proportions beside it with a bucket of water, which he pours over the flames. Beneath one such painting, a jester wrote, "O great, holy Florian, save my house, set others on fire." — Is that not a fitting passage for this story?</p>
                <p>	I spent the rest of the day writing to my youngest son <persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold</persName>, who, like his two older brothers<note>Gemeint sind <persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">Wilhelm Fischer (1803–1882)</persName> und <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer (1804–1888)</persName>.</note>, has also earned his living and reputation in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> through diligence and skill. For all three of them, the Horatian saying "Ubi bene, ubi patria"<note>Eigentlich «Ubi bene, ibi patria» (Wo es mir gut geht, da ist meine Heimat). Das Zitat wird nicht Horaz, sondern Cicero zugeschrieben.</note> remains true to this day, even though the true <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> man, in almost all cases, is drawn back to his birthplace in later years. Among other things, I told him in my letter: "Yesterday I visited my old inn, where I used to live, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1695" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="43">Cross Keys</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1726">Wood Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheap Side</placeName>, and the alley, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-21" n="44">Shoe lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet Street</placeName>, where I worked for the mechanic <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName> <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-1.xml"><date when="1794">57 years ago</date></ref>." — London does not change the way other cities do, it merely grows larger. Its brick houses always remain black, sad and monotonous; — Everything in the <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618518"/> world has two sides! England has its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition of industrial diligence</term>, which is temporary, and we have that, which nature in so manifold a way and in ever-renewing beauty, spreads out before us in all the glory of its creative power.</p>   
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers vierter Ausstellungsbesuch, 23. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-23">June 23rd</date></placeName>. This morning, in the interest of my son, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName>, I wrote a letter to the Austrian commissioner in question, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472">v. Buschek</persName>, to acquaint him with the matter and to ask for redress, as a truly significant error had taken place regarding <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8272">his submission</orgName> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, both with regard to the omission of the display in the official catalog and in the name of the exhibitor on the objects themselves. Afterwards, I visited Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-2134" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="46"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7468" type="met">Im Thurn</persName></placeName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName> on private business. In the course of our conversation, we came to speak of a Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7475">Spencer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1631">Newcastle upon Tyne</placeName>, with whose <persName ref="gfa-actors-7476">son</persName> I had become acquainted a few days ago, and he told me that he had recently won his case for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9469">spiral springs</term> vs. <term ref="gfa-keywords-8932">cylinder springs</term>, for the so-called buffets on <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, which, following the sale of his patent right to five other persons, secured him an annual income of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L. St.</term> 1900, or about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 23,000 of our money. Only in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are inventions, the offspring of observation, <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618519"/> contemplation, and experiment to attain certainty, so highly valued in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term>. It is a pity that this mistaken country values only the practical and useful, while the doctrine of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9157">fundamental rights</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, of the learned professors and attorneys (who, for the sake of science, did not allow even a speaker, let alone a writer, the slightest grammatical mistake or, anything in their view, a formal error) has once again so quickly foundered. My transport from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-22" n="48"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, it almost bordered on a miracle, did not last more than two minutes for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> This time the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibus</term> drove on the opposite side of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1628">Serpentine River</placeName>, which is really only a rather large pond, like one of the smallest Swiss lakes, but which looks very impressive on the beautiful grounds of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698">Hyde park</placeName>, and pleasure boats with sails and "rigging" of not insignificant size sail around on it. After I had delivered a supplementary manuscript to the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7473"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="49">office of Professor Wilson</placeName></persName>, providing details concerning my submission to the exhibition, I re-entered the building. The more one becomes acquainted with it, the more, I would say, one's senses dull to all that one sees and the less one desires to say anything about it, given the absolute impossibility <pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618520"/> of any coherent description. Today I had a special purpose. In the entire catalogue, I found only one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre</term> listed among the items from <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName>; and in my shipment, there were articles of true Damascus, or as I call it, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">meteor steel</term>. Unfortunately, my wish to compare the Damascus was not fulfilled, for the sabre was hung too high and, moreover, was still in its sheath. I did see the three Egyptian commissioners, however. Two of them had the mixed features of the Negro and the Caucasian races, both in colour and in the restless, not very congenial gaze. The third, probably an Egyptian <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">German</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">French</placeName>, stood out among them, like the modern, silver <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">candelabras</term> among the other, equally precious, genuine Egyptian products in their display. — One of the real Egyptians, (all three of them wore European attire, with the exception of their red hats with black tassels) had a five-pointed golden star on a golden chain, and below it the <placeName ref="gfa-places-148">Turkish</placeName> crescent, a curious emblem, to which our European diplomats might justifiably take exception. I stayed in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">exhibition building</placeName> until half past six in the evening, without having enjoyed a single thing that morning, but before leaving I viewed quite attentively the celebrated diamond <term ref="gfa-keywords-8459">Kooh-i-Noor</term>, or Mountain of Light, which is the property of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indian</placeName> prince <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618521" break="no"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7477">Runject Singh</persName>, and whose (presumed) value, judging by the calculation and estimation hitherto used for smaller diamonds, amounts to 2,000,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">L. Sterling</term>, for it would be a shame not to have seen this magnificent jewel the size of Earth, to which, if I were hungry, I would have preferred half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> of bread. Going by general opinion, everyone is disappointed by this piece, and I would not give a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kreuzer</term> to see it again. Even the women, who are otherwise not impervious to diamonds, walk away unmoved. A large rectangular railing encloses a similar pedestal. Inside this railing, which is equipped with a door, there are always two police officers. On the pedestal lies a blue-velvet cushion covered by a large dome-like cage of round, gilded iron bars. On two very small columns, also gilded and barely 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> high, rests now in a casing lying diagonally on top of it this wonder of the world, to which neither the foggy atmosphere of London, nor the genius of the English, who otherwise know how to effect many things, could give this white piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9227">carbon</term> the appearance that (according to the explanation of our <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemists</term>) it should have by covering it with boards and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas light</term>. As I said, it was already half past six o'clock. The people employed <pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618522"/> in the building for this purpose covered the objects displayed on the stands with cotton cloths, and visitors walked quietly and without crowding towards the doors. Fortunately, among the many thousands hurrying home, I found a spot in an omnibus that took me all the way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-23" n="50">Cheapside</placeName> to an excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">tavern</term>, where I was able to eat enough to make up for my forgotten lunch.</p>
 </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers Highlights der Ausstellung, 24. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-24">June 24th</date></placeName>. As an addendum to <date when="1851-06-23">yesterday’s</date> thoughts on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, there remains for me, as certainly for many thousands and thousands of visitors, aside from those things of general interest, namely the idea of this undertaking and its splendid execution, only a relatively very small part, for the sake of which I can be pleased to have witnessed this spectacle, for that is what I would like to call it, as regards both objects and people. Four main things, however, will remain in my memory as products of artistic creation. Namely, the portrait of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">queen</persName> on a life-size <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porcelain tablet</term>, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7478">Louis Philippe</persName> commissioned at the time of the<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8461">Entente cordiale</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1635">Sevres</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>; then, the large, absolutely flawless <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror made from a single cast</term>, 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high and 10 feet wide; furthermore, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8450">crystal fountain</term> of which I have already made mention. All three of these objects are the greatest triumph of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8462">halurgy</term>, to which, to a degree, the porcelain<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> must also be counted, and then, fourthly, the triumph of the <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618523"/> spirit, which controls the elements and natural forces according to its will and shows itself in all its power in the totality of the present machines and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>, which even have <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">rails</term> beneath them on which to run and for whose operation only a slight movement of the finger is required to transform its latent energy in the blink of an eye into powerful propulsion. These are the general impressions that can never be gained in such a way anywhere else. Of a thousand and one other things piled up here, the shop floors in great cities, especially in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> itself, offer a daily exhibition. One can say entire magazines of luxury articles and precious fabrics are veritable shops of the exhibition, namely glass cases, far larger than those of many stores in reality, where the objects contained therein can be viewed, but not touched. Nothing comes into being in the world at once in all its potency, yet it is astonishing how quickly in the course of time the current needs of society in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are provided for, from which the Englishman, and he is quite right, for this is the only true means of prolonging life, reckons chiefly the profit of time.</p>
                <p><date when="1851-06-24">Today</date>, because I now had at my disposal every means of transportation required <pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618524"/> to do a great deal in less time, I travelled and did business from 10 o'clock in the morning until 4 o'clock in the evening, which astonished even me. — A <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">cab</term> that I hired by the hour, for which I had to pay 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> each, took me first from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1700" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="51">St. Paul's Church</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="52">Finsbury Square</placeName> to the two <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioners, from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="53">Mint</placeName> by the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1727">Tower</placeName>, and then to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="54">Billeter Square</placeName>, and yet, after a rather long conversation with him, I was at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="55">London Bridge</placeName> by 2 o'clock. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9829">Since yesterday evening at 3 o'clock</term>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-1221">fire</term> had been raging on the opposite bank, which had broken out in a paper factory and enveloped several <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hop</term> warehouses. In today's newspapers, the damage to the various <term ref="gfa-keywords-237">insurance companies</term> was already estimated at 200,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">P. Sterling</term> or 240,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term>. Aside from the firemen and the police, no one was bothered about this fire, except to linger a little out of curiosity. It was strange that when the first and second warehouses were burning with a vehemence that made it almost impossible to approach them, and the third warehouse had been saved from the fire completely, that it suddenly broke out in the fourth. The English expression for it was, "It was the fiend who did it," which suggests arson. Fiend is synonymous with Satan. On the banks of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, I purchased a ticket for one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">steamboats</term> leaving every quarter of an hour from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639">Greenwich</placeName> and <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618525" break="no"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1640">Gravesand</placeName>, which for the 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="56">Greenwich</placeName> cost 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term>, or 12 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> and in half an hour I was there, and a willing Englishman immediately called a carriage driver, who after collecting the tax of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term> (3 kr.), guided me across the very wide Thames, where I arrived in a very short time at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8969"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7479"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7480"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7569"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1702" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="57">steamship factory of Misters Robinson &amp; Rüssel</placeName></orgName></persName></persName></term>. At the desk, I asked for Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544">Baird</persName>, who, according to his earlier calculations, should have been back in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> long ago from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, where he had assembled the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8946">steamboat</term>, but this was not the case, as I was able to infer from a letter I received <date when="1851-06-23">yesterday</date> suggesting that not everything was in order there yet. I found it conspicuous that one of the gentlemen immediately asked me if I was a partner, to which I replied no, I was co-owner of another steamship. After some conversation, which seemed a bit suspicious to me and which did not quite correspond with the remark Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544">Baird</persName> once made to me in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, "You are my only friend", I was soon on my way. Again, a boat picked me up at the shore, and in the middle of the ever-turbid Thames, delivered me to the fast steamer Najade for the return trip, whereas the Sybille<note>Die Dampfschiffe Najade und Sybille, die Fischer erwähnt, sind im «Lloyd's Register of British and Foreign Shipping 1850 &amp; 1851» nicht verzeichnet. Dies deutet darauf hin, dass es sich um kleinere, unter 100 Bruttotonnen schwere Themse-Fährdampfer handelte.</note> had brought me. Every quarter of an hour, one is sure to encounter a steamboat going down to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1640">Gravesand</placeName>, <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618526"/> which is 22 miles from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName>, or up to London.</p>
                <p>	In the evening by 4 o’clock, I was back in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="58">my quarters</placeName>my quarters. This is the great savings in time I spoke of earlier. Later, I went to a nearby dining establishment, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1709" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-24" n="59">Metropolitan Tavern</placeName>. In elegance of tableware, it surpassed those at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">my hotel</placeName>, and the price of everything, and equally good, was ¼ less than at my lodging, though it only went by the name of tavern, and not hotel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer und seine Ausstellungsobjekte, 25. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-25">June 25th</date></placeName>. This morning I went for the third time to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1697" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-25" n="60">Finsbury Square</placeName> to our <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Swiss</placeName> commissioner Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471" type="met">Colladon</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1196">Geneva</placeName> and found him at home. From him I learned that Prof. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7470">Bolley</persName>, his colleague, had gone home and was unlikely to return. It also seems to me that one commissioner is sufficient, since everything is so well organized, and there is a clerk <persName ref="gfa-actors-7481">Steiger</persName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">glass palace</placeName> every day, who speaks all three languages, German, English and French, has lived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> for 16 years and can<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> provide any necessary information. A good deal of money could have been spared in Switzerland, but this has probably happened to other governments as well; for the near future, expenditures in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are not to be spared, and the most regrettable thing is that they will hardly benefit those <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618527"/> who made them in any way, neither the governments nor the individuals. Nevertheless, I would have had no occasion for this visit had I not already made the acquaintance of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471">Colladon</persName> <date when="1825">26 years ago</date> at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8103">Swiss Natural Historical Society</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1271">Solothurn</placeName>; incidentally, this is the place to say it, as a Swiss it was also agreeable to him that the little that I contributed to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> was there only by itself. Namely, my <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus meteor steel</term></term> and objects made from it, as well as the samples of the alloy of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> in various proportions that I invented, which was previously considered impossible. Be the verdict of the jury of its day what it may, I can testify that I was initially reluctant to send anything to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, as I considered my achievements in this case too insignificant for a jury that was meant to judge, so to speak, the industry of all four regions of the world, and that I only did so after our first magistrates at the time requested that I do so. They wished to see something to represent the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">canton</placeName> and trusted that I would be willing to do so, though I had no hope of success.</p>
                <p>	From Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7471">Colladon</persName> I proceeded to my old and highly esteemed friend, Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483" type="met">Brande</persName>, Director of the Stamp Office at the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7582"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1636" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-25" n="61">Mint</placeName></orgName>. — The English have a good memory for friendship, this I have <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618528"/> still found to be true. In our conversation about the nature of metals, we both remained static at the boundary that it had so far implacably set for our research. I reiterated my old idea that water in some form or another acts as a bonding agent for metal atoms. I said that I had told him the same thing <date when="1826">25 years ago</date><note>Compare journal 1825—1827 p. <ref type="cross" target="TB4_p_32">32</ref> and journal 1846 p. <ref type="cross" target="TB6_p_28">28</ref>.</note> and that he had corrected me when I used the expression water and had noted that it was not water but <term ref="gfa-keywords-8741">hydrogen</term>. I now have reason to believe, however, based on my observations that at least another third form than water, which is a compound, and hydrogen, which, on the other hand, is believed to be a simple body, must exist. He neither contradicted nor confirmed, the way the English do, who prefer to be rather too silent than to talk too much, which is the most sensible thing even in politics, where, on the other hand, our beloved youth (jeunesse), who endeavour to improve the world, speak out in volumes, but who, once dependent on the crutch and the armchair, will likely change their tune.</p>
                <p>	If only I could tap the sources of knowledge that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7469">Faraday</persName>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7483">Brande</persName>, and <persName ref="gfa-actors-5424">Liebig</persName> have given us! — The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> invented by me, of which I have already spoken above, and the samples of which I presented to him consisted of 8 parts old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and 3 parts <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, interested him very much as a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8917">chemist</term>, <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618529" break="no"/> and it seemed to me that it almost made him disbelieve certain theories contained in the books, since here we have an indisputable fact. He took me into the mint, where he showed me an almost unbelievable break in a press frame of immense thickness and quite sound casting, and then into the water tower, which contains, at a height of 70 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in an iron basin of 50,000 cubic feet, the best drinking water, drawn from a tapped spring by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>, serving equally well for consumption and to extinguish fires. We also visited the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling mill</term>. It is almost unbelievable what long sheets of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> lie about waiting to be processed there, or perhaps only understandable, since this little <placeName ref="gfa-places-402">Albion</placeName> dominates the world far more than <persName ref="gfa-actors-7451">Napoleon</persName> or his predecessors ever did by conquest.</p>
                <p>	When I consider, as I write this, that it is only the twelfth day since I left home, that I have travelled through so many countries, have had such a stormy sea voyage, and have already seen so many astonishing things, and think back to the times of my first journey on foot to <placeName ref="gfa-places-10">Basel</placeName>, in <date when="1787">1787</date>, and how everything was then, bad and narrow roads, only footbridges instead of bridges over the two, often so torrential, forest waters of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1642">Wutach</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1643">Steinach</placeName>, I can hardly recognize myself in the drive that has been given to the human spirit since then: will it continue like this, <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618530"/> where will we end up!? And who will guarantee that the idea does not arise, if the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8464">aether</term> be suitable for respiration, or if a surrogate is found, <term ref="gfa-keywords-6029">to establish contact with other worlds</term>, which, I might add, the Creator makes quite easy for us through something that is generally avoided like a bitter medicine, namely, through the simple medium of death, "where (as <persName ref="gfa-actors-7947">Schiller</persName> so beautifully expresses it) the spirit is stripped of the earthly, separates itself in flames from its shell, and drinks the pure air of the aether!"<note>Fischer zitiert in abgeänderter Form Friedrich Schillers Gedicht «Das Ideal und das Leben».</note></p>
                <p>	One would have enough to write about in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> if limited to only the new things that happen every day, yet they accumulate so quickly as to become immediately obsolete and easily forgotten. Who would not have stopped to watch a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9829">burning fire</term> that had already been raging for two days, which, as already mentioned, I myself witnessed yesterday on my way to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> to embark for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1639">Greenwich</placeName>, or rather who would not have watched it for a long time? Yet, as I said, this was not the case. People were going back and forth across <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> with their usual alacrity, and I, too, spoke to my fellow passenger on the steamboat about it only as long as we were in its vicinity.</p>
            </div>   
                <div type="day">
                    <head>Fischers Spaziergänge durch London, 26. Juni 1851</head>
                    <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-26">June 26th</date></placeName>. Devoting myself quite early to some business, before intending to go to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="66"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, as the former might lead to some interesting remarks <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618531"/> in the future and confirm that the straightest and clearest path in business always leads most surely to the goal. — If I were a writer of novels, instead of giving an account to myself of the time I have spent, and if I had the talent for it, I could write a rather thick book with truths from my experiences, which would look quite like a novel. So much for all that. Before I went to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, I was curious to know, since my way led me through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1644" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="63">Lombard Street</placeName>, coming from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="62">Billeter Square</placeName>, what had become of my two traveling companions, Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7450">Hug</persName> and Cantonal Councillor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7449">Ammann</persName>, whom I had only met once by chance in the Crystal Palace, but although they were staying in this street, I could not find the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1708">City Hotel</placeName>. An old woman instructed me to go to St. George’s Court<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note>, and there, in the rearmost part of it, was their lodging, called <placeName ref="gfa-places-1689" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="64">St. George and Vulture</placeName>, but they had already departed. The building is not so terrible and seems to be frequented mostly by Germans, among whom are probably a number of refugees. In London, however, they do not make their fortune with their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9830">beards</term>, just as little as with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9635">cigars</term>, and I appeal to all those who have been in London to say whether they have ever encountered a single person out of a thousand people in the street <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618532"/> with a cigar or a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">pipe</term> in his mouth. Time has too great a value in England for this pastime.</p>
                    <p>	The English commoners have not yet entirely abandoned their intolerance of foreign manners, dress and coiffure. When I worked in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> fifty-seven years ago, anyone with foreign attire very soon had what they call "a mob at ones heels", and the honorific name they attached to such an individual was generally "french Dog", insofar as in the great generality the geographical knowledge of this mob extended only to French, and Dutch, inhabitants of <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-105">Holland</placeName>; but on this day, <date when="1851-06-26">June 26th 1851</date>, I read in the morning in the eminent newspaper <term ref="gfa-keywords-8465">Morning Chronicle</term>, a very general article about the reactionary policy of <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName>, in which the large number of troops, which this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9093">monarchy</term> still has standing on its feet in the face of gloomy financial conditions, is criticized, but it is partly excused by the political behaviour of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1566">Preussen</placeName>, which is not called by any nice name, and adds that the same (i.e., number of troops) is necessary owing to the garrisons that <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austria</placeName> must keep in its large cities, such as <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-251">Prague</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1909">Brixen</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1965">Hohenlinden</placeName> (I read the words for the third time). Incidentally, it is known, insofar as it was published in the newspaper, that, when the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1728">Scheldt</placeName> was opened under his <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618533"/> administration, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7503">the great Pitt</persName><note>Sehr wahrscheinlich <persName ref="gfa-actors-7503">William Pitt der Ältere</persName>. Die Scheldefrage und der Zugang zur Flussmündung für den Handel war eine internationale politische Angelegenheit. Der Zugang zum Fluss war Gegenstand eines kurzen Konflikts während des Kesselkriegs von 1784 und kurz danach während der Französischen Revolution. Im Jahr 1792 wurde der Fluss wieder geöffnet. Es kann aber nicht ausgeschlossen werden, dass sich Fischer auf den Sohn, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7931">Pitt den Jüngeren</persName>, bezieht. Denn auch zu dessen Amtszeit war die Scheldefrage noch immer aktuell.</note> asked, "where is that d. Escaut?" — Where is that damned Scheldt? Just as in <date when="1814">1814</date>, when I came to England, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9301">customs officer</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, to whom I said that I was from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> in Switzerland, asked me in all seriousness whether missionaries also visited us. In the <ref type="cross" target="TB2_p_203">diary of my travels at that time</ref>, I immediately recorded this question and my answer to it, which can still be found in print. The English hunger for newspapers must be fed every day, and, for the same price, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7504">John Bull</persName> is fed just as great a variety of stories as a stranger who ventures haphazardly into this or that <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">eating-house</term> in London. To come back to the subject of all manner of foreigners' beards and how repugnant they are, as it seems, to the English commoners, I read <date when="1851-06-26">on the same day</date> in the newspaper <term ref="gfa-keywords-8466">Punch</term>, which otherwise treats no one with mercy, a complaint about the English commoners and their ragamuffins, of whom, by the way, one sees less than in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, that they have carried their insolence against Germans with beards so far as to run after them in the vicinity of the exhibition building and to present them with old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> in mockery.</p>
                    <p>	This tendency to imitate the custom of times long past in beards and frumpy old German attire, which good taste rejects, will hardly last long, however.</p>
                    <p><pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618534"/> Many times, as I walked down <placeName ref="gfa-places-1644">Lombard Street</placeName>, a narrow and not very long street, where several bankers and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9064">money changers</term> reside, I have stopped in front of the currency exchange house <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7581"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1704" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-26" n="65">Spielman &amp; Comp.</placeName></orgName>, as almost everyone does who has not yet discovered the displays in its windows of large pans, filled mostly with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> and then covered with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9091">banknotes</term> and other paper money, and, in addition to these riches, layers of gold bars weighing 4-6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> and more. Today, however, I was particularly attracted by a pan of <placeName ref="gfa-places-629">Californian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">wash gold</term>, and I am certainly not exaggerating when I estimate the weight of gold contained in this pan to be about 40 pounds, and thus worth at least 30,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term>. As gold it is of no interest to me, but immensely so for its form. The general character is as follows: flat, mostly elongated round leaves, approximately as thick as a playing card and even thicker, up to the size of a fingernail. This, however, is not the marvellous thing, but rather the conglomeration, the fusion of these leaflets without any apparent gangue ("Lode"). They can be best compared to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> flakes that are formed when (in our country at least) young women (sometimes also unmarried older ones) observing the usual traditions, pour liquefied lead into water on <term ref="gfa-keywords-9746">St. Andrew's Eve</term>, in order to discern from its shape <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618535" break="no"/> whether they will soon find a husband.</p>
                    <p>	I have devoted so much time to studying <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">metals</term> in regard to their formation and destruction, I deliberately use these unscholarly expressions, that I was quite disturbed by the sight of these peculiar formations today. Something else struck me about this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term>, namely its reddish, somewhat dingy colour, in contrast to the otherwise solid gold that has accumulated into its natural state, of which I own a beautiful specimen from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1645">Calandaberg</placeName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-57">Grisons</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>	Following the advice of the synopsis enclosed with the catalogue, I devoted my attention today more to the individual objects of particular interest to me than to wandering around in the extensive halls, looking at everything and seeing nothing, and recorded what I thought worthy of later recollection. In the end, I recorded a far larger inventory than I had assumed and will probably write several pages at another time than at this late hour (half past midnight) about the observations I made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Über den englischen Absatzmarkt, 27. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-27">June 27th</date></placeName>. Today, a full day of business, was a very tiring one for me, although important in its consequences, insofar as I will have to stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> probably longer than I had intended. <pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618536"/> I went first to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="67"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7505" type="met">Cammell</persName></placeName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, the largest steel manufacturer in England, whom I had met before, and who, in his conversation with me, declared that his business had expanded to the extent that he was now making 50 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9078">tons</term> a week of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">casting</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467">spring steel</term>, that is, over 1000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term>. Then I went to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="68">Billeter Square</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1646">Fenchurch Street</placeName> and from there to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1647" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="69">Phoenix Foundry</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1648">Southwark</placeName>, far across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>, where I watched the casting of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8468">bearings</term> (a kind of bushing for the axles of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">locomotives</term>), consisting of a patented white and soft material, which I know, and discovered some ingenious devices for it. About the properties of these bearings, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7506">Dewrance</persName>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9026">inventor</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">patent</term> owner, told me that they perform quite well over not too great distances, but turn into a kind of "Decomposition" of black sludge when the friction is sustained for too long a period over great distances, such as from London to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1937">Edinburgh</placeName>.</p>
                <p>	My business was concluded in a further conversation with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505" type="met">Cammell</persName> at his office in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-27" n="70">Barge Yard</placeName>, near the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1650">Mansion House</placeName>, whereby I merely remark that only as the English have the whole world as a market for their manufactured goods, their immense turnover makes it possible for them to offer everything so cheaply and, thereby, to crush other <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618537" break="no"/> manufacturers, where they are not subjected to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9444">tariffs</term> in other countries. For one must know that, for example, in the case of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9502">steel production</term>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName> sells his rolled spring steel for 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term> or 7½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money. If we assume that he has only half a Kreuzer of pure profit on each <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term> after deducting all expenses (<date when="1826">25 years ago</date> the steel manufacturers in England still calculated a profit on 3 Kreuzer per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>, as Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7507">Tailor</persName>, then director of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7508">iron and steel works "at the seven Oaks,"</orgName></term></term> informed me), then there still remains a net profit of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 833 per week, or 40,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">Gulden</term> for the whole year, for large-scale production. Manufacturers on the mainland cannot emulate this, as under no circumstances (I am referring to the production of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> here) is it possible to make a profit that even approaches a fiftieth of a percent. Incidentally, what we have just said can be applied to almost all types of products. So much for today. Later, perhaps only after my return, I will come back to this subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Ausflug in die Badeanstalt, 28. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-28" type="travelday">June 28th</date></placeName>. One often plans to do something in the morning, and by evening, nothing has come of it. Since in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> on Saturday afternoon and on Sunday one is to a certain extent quite left to oneself, the freedom to think only of oneself is considerable, and I therefore had in mind for these two days and Monday to head for <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618538"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, or at least for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1651">Brighton</placeName>, whose <placeName ref="gfa-places-2029"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9449">seaside resorts</term></placeName> are inviting enough in the current heat. However, my business in the morning and writing a letter <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">home</persName> in the afternoon delayed my departure in order to reach either of these places in time, so I decided to go to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1652" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-28" n="71">Leicester Square</placeName>, where I was told there was a bathhouse. From the outside it looks quite respectable, and there are four doors, the first and second for ladies of the first and second classes. A similar partition was provided for the gentlemen. I went to the first class bureau and was given two towels and a coin, marked first class, but I immediately lost all desire to enter when asked to pay no more than six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> (18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term>). I was then directed to a narrow gallery, which had equally narrow baths and where about 30 people sat in a queue on benches against the wall, who in the order in which they arrived were directed to a bath as soon as one was vacant. By my calculation, I would have had to wait another 1½ hours, and so I returned my coin and towels, and received, contrary to expectation, my money back. Too overheated from all the walking, I entered a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8920">chemist's</term> to drink a jug of natural <term ref="gfa-keywords-8446">seltzer water</term>, which, since he told me about it, I followed up with a portion of an artificial one, <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618539" break="no"/> which I thoroughly enjoyed for its plentiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9226">carbonation</term>. Regarding it as unhealthy, the "Chemist" was reluctant to give much approval to so-called "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9194">Gingerbeer</term>," of which I had already partaken in the morning, as it has an extremely pleasant taste, and which is frequently consumed in summer.</p>
                <p>	On my way home, I encountered two street sweepers in operation, each of which was drawn by a horse. In these devices, too, which do the work of 20 maids, we see the spirit of the English. On a two-wheeled cart is an oblong wooden box open at the top, at the rear of which, at a suitable distance, an iron axle passes through a cylindrical brush of about 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in length and 2½ to 3 feet in diameter. It has two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur gears</term> that interlock with the spur gears of the same size attached to the inner of the two hubs, so that when the horse advances, the broom, which has just enough slack as to always rest on the street, also rotates from back to front, sweeping the street and pushing the collected matter in front of it. When a quantity of refuse has been collected, the driver stops, scoops it into the box and continues his journey.</p>
                <p>As an addendum to my remarks, referring mainly to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> objects <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618540"/> mentioned at the end of my notes from <date when="1851-06-26">June 26th</date>, which I was prevented from writing by fatigue and the late hour I would have had to devote to them, I mention, first of all, a collection of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1938">East Indian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, known as "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8469">Wootz</term>," from <placeName ref="gfa-places-397">Bombay</placeName>, and then the unshaped <term ref="gfa-keywords-9497">steel blooms</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1729">Golconda</placeName>, which <persName ref="gfa-actors-7609">Tavernier</persName> mentions in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8470">records of his travels</term>. This wootz consists of small lumps or "<term ref="gfa-keywords-9249">Reguli</term>," almost always of the same weight, which were cooled in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>. I still possess a fourth of such a lump, which was given to me by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7509">Bréant</persName>, Inspecteur des <placeName ref="gfa-places-1934">Essais</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, in <date when="1826">1826</date>. A whole lump of this kind commonly weighs ⅞ of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>. This steel is hard, very difficult to <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">forge</term>, it hardens, yet, at least in <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">Europa</placeName>, does not produce long-lasting cutting instruments. The latest opinion about this steel, albeit erroneous, is that it consists of "<term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">magnetic iron</term>". More accurately, one might say it is made of magnetic ironstone. The Golconda lumps are thin and wide, often very porous, and such a lump, which is usually broken into four parts, yields four beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damascus</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9412">sabre blades</term>, however, often with what the English refer to as "Flaws." I would also mention that this steel is very durable and of excellent quality. Among the stone-cutting tools, I saw a useful device for the hammers, which we call two-pronged hammers, namely steel spikes, which are pointed at the top and bottom and serve two <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618541" break="no"/> purposes; they are simply inserted into the iron hammer, which has a rectangular conical hole. If a man has a dozen such spikes, he can work for days without having to run to the blacksmith again, and that is enough for today.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Weitere Highlights der Ausstellung, 29. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-29">Sunday, June 29th</date></placeName>. In my daily entries, for which I often, even in the height of summer, had to spend hours of the night, I touched on some things only briefly, or not at all, in the hope of mentioning them at a more convenient time. For these things, Sundays in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> are quite suitable if one does not travel and, therefore, the following addendum.</p>
                <p>I have already remarked in my earlier notes that nothing would be easier than to report something new, or never before seen, every day. Yet, how the various forms of charlatanism, which at bottom is so contrary to the serious and scrutinizing character of the English, though it does not seem to fail in its intended effect and can flourish alongside the genuinely new, good and interesting, is almost incomprehensible and must surely derive from the surprisingly one-sided education of the people. Every day, on my way to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, in the high streets of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, but especially in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Piccadilly</placeName>, one of the broadest and most beautiful streets of London that leads to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1698">Hydepark</placeName>, I saw six shabby fellows on the sidewalk ("Flags") walking back and forth in procession, one behind the other, all day long. <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618542"/> Each of them carried a large wooden frame attached to a flat pole on the paper cover of which was advertised in large red letters, where one might see a view of the "Holy land" and acquire a faithful image of the city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1768">Jerusalem</placeName> at the time of our Saviour for 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> (six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>). Anyone who knows the history of the terrible destruction of that city 70 years after Christ (fulfilling the prophecy), as it was handed down to us by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7510">Flavius Josephus</persName>, would be astonished at such deception of the public. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1653"><placeName ref="gfa-places-491">Rheinau Monastery</placeName></placeName> also boasts such an ancient <term ref="gfa-keywords-9776">illustration</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1768">Jerusalem</placeName>, that is, unless it has been stolen from it, like another precious picture book depicting the traditional dress (if I am not mistaken) of the 13th and 14th centuries, at a time when its true owners had no control over their library. However, that illustration is rather more a city plan bearing its location from later times than an illustration like the one above and, in any case, does not bear this presumptuous inscription.</p>
                <p>	When circa 2000 years ago the famous <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematician</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7511">Archimedes</persName> (whose tomb in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1730">Syracuse</placeName>, already overgrown with weeds, was renovated and restored by the equally famous <persName ref="gfa-actors-7576">Cicero</persName>, during his time as proconsul in <placeName ref="gfa-places-434">Sicily</placeName>), after having made the great discovery of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9116">specific gravity</term> of bodies in the bath and, thereby, exposing the fraud of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8720">goldsmith</term>, who substituted alloyed <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618543"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term> for the pure gold that the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8276">king</persName> had given him to make the royal crown, repeated his joyful <emph rend="italic">ἑvϱεκα!</emph> <note>Korrekte Schreibweise: ηὕρηκα.</note>( I have found it!), he could hardly have imagined that some two thousand years later, in the far north, in the vicinity of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1706">Thule</placeName>, in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tinlands</term> (what is today England) a tailor would adopt his exclamation regarding the men's dress shirts he manufactures, in order, by means of this enigmatic word, to demonstrate to the gullible London public, who are, in fact, not very well versed in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-821">Greek</placeName> language, that he alone had discovered the one true cut for men's dress shirts.  — And, yet it is so — and in several of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">coaches</term>, which travel daily to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term>, one finds this Greek tailor's pronouncement on a large advertising leaflet. I have already said it repeatedly, and I will say it again, the charlatanry in England is beyond belief, and it seems that they love it for it appears in such great variety.</p>
                <p>	Indeed, it is astonishing how people in this cosmopolitan city resort to the most incredible things to earn money or to acquire things, and yet the people of the lower classes, despite all manner of industriousness, are not one whit better off than they are in our own country, or rather, not even as well off as those in our own. They have nothing to cultivate. Forests, fields and pastures, not to speak of vineyards, <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618544"/> remain unknown to many, who, it is said, never get out of London their whole lives. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName>, who has offices here, as well as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-497">Hamburg</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-389">New York</placeName>, proclaimed with great chagrin upon seeing a coloured illustration of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967"><placeName ref="gfa-places-97">my steelworks in the Mühlenthal</placeName></placeName>: "I want to live there! I'll not stay in London! — The bustle is too great, and nothing but wear and tear." Last week's newspaper reported 870 deaths, and this week's just 100 more, namely 970.</p>
                <p>	Again, in one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> that travel daily to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName>, there was a rather large coloured <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithograph</term> print at the front, inside, depicting a beautiful young woman and an elder gentleman. Half of the young woman’s hair was in its natural colour, namely an garrish red, while the other half was a glossy raven black, and the gentleman, half of whose hair and Van Dyke beard, was more white than grey, with the other half transformed into a beautiful nut-brown, what the English call "auburn", by virtue of the artistry of the hair dresser, whose address in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Picadilly</placeName>, where he lives, was appended to the lithograph.</p>
                <p>My visits to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term> on several days <pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618545"/> only taught me that, if visiting it is to be of use to anyone with a specific purpose in mind, one must, apart from the most prominent and generally admired objects, turn away completely from the superfluity of what is there and limit oneself only to what can serve this purpose to the greatest extent possible, and that is why I only note, in these leisure hours and later, those things that particularly interested me, as I write first and foremost only for myself, knowing that <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">my family</persName> and few friends will gladly make do with what is sufficient for myself. These pages are, as usual, only an account I give myself for the purpose of recollection.</p>
                <p>	In view of my limited leisure time, I devoted my attention almost exclusively to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-289">mineral</term>, and, in conjunction with these, <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgical</term> objects and their processing, as well as the machines and tools available for this purpose. As a result, the notes I took there and then, which constitute the synopsis in hand, were unfortunately almost too brief and catalogue-like to be instructive or engaging for anyone but myself by way of recollection.</p>
                <p>Specimens<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8471">plumbago</term> from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1654">Borrowdale pit</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1655">Cumberland</placeName>, this curious mineral, which in the great heat of our <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618546" break="no"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelting furnaces</term>, when pulverized, does not even agglutinate, are the richest in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9227">carbon</term>, the analysis yielding 90 parts in 100, and only the 10 remaining parts consist of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9212">silicon</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8654">iron oxide</term>, interested me as <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term> material, as well as various specimens of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8472">hydraulic lime</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8473"><placeName ref="gfa-places-608">Roman cement</placeName></term>, of which the basic constituents are as a rule always <term ref="gfa-keywords-9212">silicon</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8785">alum</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">lime</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8832">magnesia</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9002">siderite</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9460">soda</term>. I passed by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">hard coal</term> samples of all kinds and sizes only with regret, as the various and weak veins in <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">our canto</placeName>n (we cannot even apply the term "coal field") only seem to tantalize, and even to date in the whole of <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, which seems to be situated at too high an altitude for a coal field, though they also occur in England not far from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1656">Ashford</placeName> in a tunnel 300 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> above the sea. Cut into standard sized pieces, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1657">Stavely</placeName> coals are said to be twice as useful both as fuel and as ship's ballast, since they leave no empty spaces between them when loaded.</p>
                <p>	Samples of artificial fuel, meaning solid lumps produced by strong pressure and mixed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9561">tar</term> from coal residue and the like, can be put on a par with so-called <placeName ref="gfa-places-127">Russian</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8475">carboline</term>, and under certain circumstances can be regarded as a worthwhile product. Whether or not <term ref="gfa-keywords-2570">coals</term> prepared from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8476">tanbark bricks</term> are worthy of interest can only be determined by use and <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618547" break="no"/> comparison of their effect with other fuel, just as little can be said about the various types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ores</term>, the majority of which belong to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8653">clay ironstones</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8654">hematites</term>, the latter of which are added to the former, as they are poorer in content, to improve yield. <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Steel</term> samples from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1658">Ulverstone</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">Ironworks</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlery</term> made from this steel, made by direct <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term> (red bloodstone, which is very fine in the quarry, something not entirely desirable), interested me very greatly. Finely ground samples of this ore, with which they <term ref="gfa-keywords-8757">carburize</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> in England, are also on display here. This is nothing new, however; to date, the product has always been unreliable when produced in an open fire of any kind. To be done successfully, the only reliable method for this procedure is in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible</term>; however, only very rich iron ores, yielding 60 to 70 pCt.<note>Abkürzung für Prozent (%).</note>, are suitable for this. We have such ores in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1659">Bella Luna</placeName>, but, to my knowledge, they do not occur in England. The model of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnace</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">throat</term> of which is closed after each charge with a valve-like lid, and the flame emitted through a side furnace to be used for special purposes, was also not without interest to me. However, I was not able <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618548" break="no"/> to learn anything of the results obtained with it.</p>
                <p>	The large <term ref="gfa-keywords-8479">silver</term> cake, weighing just over 7½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> and worth <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 40,000, obtained using <persName ref="gfa-actors-7577"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8478">Mr. Pattinson's process</term></persName>, is remarkable for its size and the manner in which it was displayed. By means of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8477">segregation process</term>, or rather skimming off the still liquid <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> with a perforated shovel from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> that has already solidified in the melting pot, it is melted again in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberatory furnace</term>, and the residual lead is oxidized (a kind of abrasion process), leaving silver of great purity.</p>
                <p>	I spent some time examining the various <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">alloy</term> samples from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7512">Stirling and Morriss</persName>. I first need to know more about their success in application before I will comment on their merits or shortcomings.</p>
                <p>	Their patented so-called “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8481">Patenttoughened</term>" iron<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> consists of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8508">puddled iron</term> into which, while still liquid in the furnace, chunks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9012">wrought iron</term> are thrown in – a product, which owing to the insufficient fusion, as the latter chunks do not turn into liquid, could only be extolled as excellent by a patent-addicted Englishman.</p>
                <p>	Malleable bell metal is ludicrous. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9133">Bells</term> are cast, not forged. It is well known that the hardest bell metal <pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618549" break="no"/> always produces the most beautiful tone. Their union metal appears to be a mixture of six parts <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> and one part <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term>, which, if not invented by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7513">Rinnmann</persName>, was first described by him in his history of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. In the samples of copper-iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">compound</term> there is evidence of free iron that has separated from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, which happens very easily if the proper techniques are not carefully practiced.</p> 
                <p>After lunch on this leisurely Sunday, I walked from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-29" n="73">my lodging</placeName>, not always in the mood to write, from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612" type="itinerar_London1851" when="1851-06-29" n="74">Ludgate Hill</placeName>, partly as a shortcut, but primarily out of curiosity, through the narrow, crooked side streets to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-29" n="75">Blackfriars Bridge</placeName> to observe life and the hustle and bustle on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName>. Good God, I thought, whoever is condemned to spend his life in these dingy black buildings in the middle of the city, as it were, with their sparse, dusty windows and dark, cheerless rooms, must have grown accustomed to them from his youth. Only the conveniences to be found within the least of them offer some little compensation. Bread, meat, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term>, milk and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> are brought into the house. Water is in the kitchen and light in the room, for, to produce light, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas flows out of the pipe</term> as soon as a valve is turned and ignites with a small bang when a burning piece of paper is held up to it. <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618550"/> One needs neither <term ref="gfa-keywords-8867">lamp</term> nor <term ref="gfa-keywords-8593">wick trimmer</term>, though the gas flame does blacken, and everything in these dwellings is so dark and gloomy that one is glad only to see the open sky again and be out in the fresh air again.</p>
                <p>	Having arrived on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661">Blackfriars Bridge</placeName>, I could not without repeated astonishment, though I had seen it before but not to such a degree, contemplate the number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">passenger steamers</term> moving up and down every second of the day, as they are the real <term ref="gfa-keywords-9698">omnibuses</term> on water. At one moment I counted 12 moving between <placeName ref="gfa-places-1661">Blackfriars</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1638">London Bridge</placeName> alone and, on the whole, some 30 going up and down within a little less than an hour. What struck me, and it is likely the latest design, were the low and narrow smoke-free funnels on a few of them, while others were still emitting thick black clouds of it. These new boats were also not exceptionally long, but narrow, and cut across the bow and built with a very tight curvature. The speed of the wheels, and thus of the ship, was quite fast, which is easier to achieve with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">high-pressure steam engines</term> than with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8955">atmospheric</term><note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> ones. It is quite mind-boggling to think how the immense capital for everything one sees could have been raised.</p>
                <p><pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618551"/>Yet, it is more the circulation than the amount of money that is visible here. Each new generation inherits from the preceding one its debts and its money, then, generally speaking, continues its activity for 30 years before stepping down again from the stage to make room for a new one.</p>
                <p>	Anyone who has seen the cottages of the inhabitants of our northernmost regions can imagine at best, albeit without certainty, how it might have looked here nearly 2000 years ago, when <persName ref="gfa-actors-7514">Julius Caesar</persName> undertook his march to Britain, and not far from this place cut his pile bridge across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1641">Thames</placeName> (some of these piles were excavated about 50 years ago and preserved in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1662">Leverian Museum</placeName>, where I saw them. They are of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8983">oak</term>, but black through and through like <term ref="gfa-keywords-8981">ebony</term>, and just as hard).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischer über den Besuch der Matrosen, 30. Juni 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-06-30">Monday, June 30th</date></placeName>. Last week, at her expense, the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen</persName> had her own <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7578">sailors</orgName>, namely those who are exclusively on duty on the two royal yachts, brought to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">exhibition</term></placeName> on a special train on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">railroad</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1663">Spithead</placeName>, where, if I am not mistaken, these ships are docked. They all appeared in their blue jackets, white "Trousers" and simple oilcloth hats with wide brims, very handsome, indeed. Many still adorned with cords for good behaviour. This seems to me an excellent idea to encourage emulation. <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618552" break="no"/> Corporals, sergeants and sergeant majors must be in every company, even if there is not an excellent man among them, and they have their badges of distinction, as is quite respectable. <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">Medals</term> are also awarded, especially in wartime, for special service, though it is not always wartime, in which case they seem to be appropriate for good conduct in peacetime, as well. The <persName ref="gfa-actors-7455">Queen's</persName> idea of making the exhibition accessible to her <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7578">sailors</orgName> has since been extended to other persons unable to visit the exhibition for reasons of duty, of their distance from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, or want of funds. Orphans and boys from seminaries have also been admitted, and today, while I was sitting at breakfast, there passed by my windows five wagons decorated with tree branches and flags, some of which were designed only for people to stand in so-called "Vans" and others for people to sit in, and each <term ref="gfa-keywords-9277">wagon</term> drawn by four horses, all five of which could together hold well over 300 people. They were the workers from two factories. This example will now, for better or worse, have to be imitated by many others, which will significantly increase revenues for the exhibition. In the end, <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> always finds the greatest part of its resources in itself, for when one considers the costs of this undertaking, which have already been incurred <pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618553"/> and are yet to be incurred, then what the foreigner contributes is, in fact, virtually nothing, for he can have his fill of the exhibition four days a week from 10 o'clock in the morning until 7 o'clock in the evening for 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shillings</term> or 2 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term></p>
                <p>	Before leaving for the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="78">exhibition</placeName> on this foggy, mid-summer morning, I paid a visit to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7463" type="met">Mind</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1717" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="76">Oxford Street</placeName>, who received me hospitably, and also introduced me to his wife and elder daughter, as his and his younger daughter's traveling companion from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> to London. After that I headed to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7472" type="met">v. Buschek</persName>, Imperial <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Austrian</placeName> Commissioner, at his office, 43 <placeName ref="gfa-places-1731" type="itinerar" when="1851-06-30" n="77">Clarges Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Picadilly</placeName>, in order to discuss important matters regarding the oversight in the catalogue concerning the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-6330">exhibits of my son</orgName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-59">Hainfeld</placeName>.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers siebter Ausstellungsbesuch, 1. Juli 1851</head>
                <p><date when="1851-07-01" type="travelday">July 1st</date>. In anticipation of soon leaving <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, so that I might travel to the north of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> before my journey <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>, I spent the whole day in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-01" n="79">exhibition halls</placeName>, where one can refresh oneself as necessary, without having to leave the building.</p>
                <p>For myself, as well as for those who may get hold of this little manuscript some day, I will include the things that were most interesting to me today in pencil, comparing them with the suggestions in the synopsis, and then I will stop; after all, one can never really be finished.</p>
                <p><term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">Files</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9458">sickles</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9457">scythes</term> with mostly <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618554"/> riveted<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> handles are available from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> in great quantity, as well as steel samples of all kinds, of which, however, I noticed a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9510">cast bar</term> ("Ingot"), of which, as usual, the upper part was cold formed, but which also contained the bubbles (holes inside from gas that is not expelled or absorbed by means of additives), which they call "Piping", so common in English castings.</p>
                <p>	Also on display are <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">stamps</term> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">medals</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8756">engraved</term> in the usual way, but whose lower half contains either welded <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, or the whole cylinder or truncated <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">cone</term> in a ring of welded <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bar iron</term>, proving how the English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, as a result of its lower resistance to contraction during extinguishing and cooling in water, in comparison with several types of cast steel from the continent, tends to crack during <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term>, as sadly demonstrated by the precious <term ref="gfa-keywords-8342">master stamp</term>, made in English steel, of our <term ref="gfa-keywords-9773">Swiss V-franc coins</term>, which had been so excellent in its intended conception and design.</p>
                <p>	The beauty of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-16"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8498">Berlin cast-iron wares</term></placeName>, which in my opinion are produced most exquisitely in <placeName ref="gfa-places-247">Vienna</placeName>, also evoked much enthusiasm here. This was magnified by the completed masterpiece of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8499"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1210">Bavarian lion</placeName></term> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8642">bronze</term>, which enabled those who had not enjoyed the great pleasure of seeing the colossal <term ref="gfa-keywords-8500">statue of the Bavaria</term> <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618555"/> for themselves in the beauty of its form and the art of its casting, to imagine what a magnificent monument of taste and art <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7515">King Ludwig</persName> must have erected during his reign.</p>
                <p>	Returning to the subject of iron casting in <placeName ref="gfa-places-16">Berlin</placeName>, I note from my own experience that a small addition of English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term> to the cast iron gives it a similar disposition to take on the finest contours of the mould when cast, as does the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> from phosphoric <term ref="gfa-keywords-8483">marsh ore</term>, which, it is believed, is the preferred casting material in Berlin.</p>
                <p>	Because it is, to an extent, related to <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgy</term>, and inasmuch as these natural substances are used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-18">photography</term>, I mention a new improvement that has come about in that field, namely that the so-called negative paper (the paper which receives the first or reverse impression of the chemical light rays in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8913">camera</term> [the English never say camera obscura]) is now substituted by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">mat-ground</term> glass plates, which, as is never mentioned, however, must, of course, be covered with a similar coating that is receptive or sensitive to light rays, as the so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9348">energiatype</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9808">photographic paper</term>.</p>
                <p>	Also very interesting is a true <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver plating</term> of glass, instead of coating it with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8781">mercury</term> and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin foil</term>.</p>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <p>
                    <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618556"/> Zwischen dem engen Raum von zwei Glastafeln, deren Ränder durch aufgelegte Wachsstreifen von einander gehalten werden, wird eine neutrale Silberauflösung hineingegossen, und etwas <term ref="gfa-keywords-9578">Traubenzuker</term> hinzugefügt, oder auch <term ref="gfa-keywords-8484">Schiessbaumvolle</term> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8786">Alkali</term> aufgelöst, wo dann das Silber metallisch glänzend sich auf die Glastafel niederschlägt. Wenn dieses vollständig geschehen ist, wird der flüssige Theil der Solution abgeschüttet, die Bedekung mit reinem Wasser abgewaschen, getroknet und durch gänzliche Verkittung ringsherum, gegen die Einwirkung der Luft geschüzt.</p>
                <p>Als Gegenstand von <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">Metall</term> muss ich auch der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8501">grossen Orgel</term> erwähnen, da ich zu selbiger hingieng als gerade darauf gespielt wurde, was öfter geschah. Sie ist 38 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fuss</term> hoch, 26 Fuss breit und 23 Fuss tief, und hat 5000 Pfeiffen, wovon die grösste 32 Fuss, und die kleinste nicht gar ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term> lang ist, und 80 Tasten hat, übrigens troz ihrer Grösse in diesen ungeheuren Räumen keinen grossen Plaz ausfüllt, auch ihre Töne, so stark sie sind, in denselbigen bald zu verhallen scheinen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers achter Ausstellungsbesuch, 2. Juli 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1851-07-02">Den 2. July</date></placeName>. ln das Fach, dem ich mich eben aus Vorliebe, und zum Theil als eigenen Beruf dazu aufgefordert, widme, gehört auch womit ich mich heute beschäftigte, nachdem ich vorher bei Herrn <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-02" n="80"><persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName></placeName> einsprach, obschon ich finde, dass ich weiter gehe als ich mir vornahm, die nahe beim östlichen Eingang von dem Transept oder Schiff des Gebäudes, wenn man
                    <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618557"/> es so nennen kann, in dem Haupteingang liegende Stufe von <term ref="gfa-keywords-9636">Zinkerz</term>, fast granitähnlich im Aussehen, 164 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> schwer, die in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1664">New-Yersey</placeName> in den <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">Vereinigten Staaten Nordamerika’s</placeName>, nahe an der Oberfläche der Erde gefunden wurde.</p>
                <p>Wenn man in der That das Gewicht aller der Gegenstände, die in- und ausserhalb dem Gebäude sich befinden, und dann das Gewicht des Gebäudes an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">Eisen</term>, Glas, und Holz dazu, zusammenrechnet, man sollte denken, man könnte die ganze Welt damit aufwiegen, und doch war <date when="1849-05-01">vor zwei Jahren am 1. May</date> noch nichts von den Millionen Centnern vorhanden, zu welchen selbst unsere Gegenfüssler<note>Umgangssprachlich für Antipode: Person mit völlig gegengesetzter Einstellung und Geisteshaltung.</note> beigetragen haben. Um auf die <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">Metalle</term> zurükzukommen, tritt <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Oesterreich</placeName>, wie zu erwarten war, unter den auswärtigen Sendern, in die erste Linie ein, sowohl durch die Zahl seiner Gegenstände und ihrer Vielartigkeit in Eisen, <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahl</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9457">Sensen</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9458">Sicheln</term>, allerlei Werkzeugen, sowie Productionen, die durch die Fabrikate meines Sohnes <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg</persName> in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">Gussstahl</term> und vielerlei <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">Feilen</term> von Gussstahl, und dann derjenigen von <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">Weicheisengiesserei</term> (malleable Castiron) und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">Spindeln</term> von meinem jüngsten Sohn <persName ref="gfa-actors-1203">Berthold</persName> repräsentirt sind, wobei ich noch der ganz ausgezeichnet schönen Artikel der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9125">Glasmacherkunst</term> aus <placeName ref="gfa-places-1906">Böhmen</placeName>, bei welcher, wie bei den Metallen, die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8901">Pyrotechnik</term> die Hauptrolle spielt, und bei welchen ich mit Verwunderung stehen blieb, erwähnen muss. Eisen- und Stahlproductionen, unverarbeitet und verarbeitet, aus meinem lieben Vaterland der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName> sind unbedeutend;
                    <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618558"/> aber von hoher Bedeutung sind die anderweitigen Fabrikate, nämlich die der Baumwollgespinnste, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8817">Bänder</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9452">Seidenstoffe</term>, der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9614">Weberei</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9543">Stikerei</term>, der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">Thonarbeiten</term> höherer Art, (terra cotta) von Hrn. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7516">Ziegler-Pellis</persName>, und dann der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9593">Uhrenmacherei</term>, Strohgeflechte und Holzschnizarbeiten etc. Leider war aus der <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-1081">Escherschen Fabrik</orgName>, die so grosse Ansprüche auf Beachtung ihrer Leistungen hätte machen können, und vor deren Produktion wohl auch Rivalen aus <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> hätten zurüktreten müssen, nichts vorhanden. Die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9753">elektrische</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9590">Uhr</term>, die im Mittelpunkt des Transepts aufgestellt ist, mahnte mich zu baldigem Zuhausegehen, aber umsonst. Von ihrer eigentlichen inneren Einrichtung ist mir nichts anderes als das bekannt, dass ihr Gang durch abwechselnde anziehende und abstossende Kraft von <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">Magneten</term> bewirkt wird und wozu vielleicht die schwache <term ref="gfa-keywords-8485">Zambonische Säule</term> die erste Idee dazu hergegeben hat. Auch sie ist eine laute Stimme über die Fortschritte der <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">Physik</term>, in Verbindung mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">Chemie</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9302">Mechanik</term>, in unseren gegenwärtigen Tagen.</p>
                <p>Noch betrachtete ich die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9257">Kupfererze</term> von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1665">Burra-Burra</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-8">Süd-Australien</placeName>, die bis 70 pCt.<note>Abkürzung für Prozent (%).</note> reines <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">Kupfer</term> liefern, und ebenfalls die aus <placeName ref="gfa-places-67">Indien</placeName>, über welche Länder England gleichmässig seine Polypenarme schlingt. Sein Reichthum ist unermesslich, und doch hat es auch so viel arme und elende Menschen dort, von <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Irland</placeName>, wo das Verhungern practisch geworden ist, nicht zu reden. Alle Augenblike will ich fortgehen und komme wie aus einem bezauberten Schloss nicht
                    <pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618559"/> heraus. Ich besichtige auch noch die <placeName ref="gfa-places-76"><term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">Feuersprize aus Canada</term></placeName> — ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">Werkzeug</term>, wovon ich so viele in meinem Leben gemacht und reparirt habe; deren Wirkung eine ungeheure, bisher nicht bekannte sein soll. Da ich die innere Einrichtung nicht sehen konnte, auch nicht angezeigt ist, wie viel Mann dabei angestellt werden können*), so ist die Berechnung darüber, ob die Angabe von dem Effekt richtig sey, unmöglich. Uebrigens bleibt der Grundsaz ewig wahr, dass eine Maschine, in der grossen Hauptwirkung, nur die angewendete Kraft annähernd zeigt, und darüber hinaus nichts erkünstelt werden kann. Eine andere Bewandtniss hat es mit verständiger Vertheilung der disponiblen Kraft, wenn sie in ein und derselben Maschine für verschiedene Zweke wirken muss, worunter ich unter denen, die in der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">Ausstellung</term> wirklich arbeiteten, als eine der merkwürdigsten rechne, wo die rohe <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">Baumwolle</term> denselben an dem einen Ort übergeben und sogleich durch die künstliche Combination der arbeitenden Theile, zu feinem Garn wird. Dieses Garn zieht sich auf die <term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">Webemaschine</term> (powerloom) und kommt durch das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8486">fliegende Schifflein</term> (flying Shuttle), (navette volante) gekreuzt, durchschossen und wieder durchschossen, an dem entgegengesezten Ende der Maschine, als fertiges Stük Baumwollzeug heraus. 
                    <note n="*" type="original" place="bottom">Seitdem ich dieses geschrieben, vernahm ich, es seyen 40 Mann dazu erforderlich. Wie alle das ihnen zukommende Moment von Kraft in Anwendung bringen können, ist mir unbegreiflich.</note></p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618560"/> Noch warf ich zum zweitenmal einen Blik auf die grosse <term ref="gfa-keywords-9380">hydraulische Presse</term>, dieser schönen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8630">Erfindung</term> von dem Schlossermeister <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7517">Bramah</persName>, der zu der Zeit lebte, wo ich <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-1.xml"  ><date when="1794">Anno 1794</date></ref> in London arbeitete. Sie wurde gebraucht, um die Stüke der ungeheuren Röhren, deren Gewicht sich auf 42,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> jede belauft, und den <placeName ref="gfa-places-2157">Weg für die <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term></placeName> zwischen dem festen Land und der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1881">Insel Anglesia</placeName> bilden, um selbige auf ihre thurmgleichen an die 109 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fuss</term> hohen gemauerten Lager, hinaufzuheben.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="day">
                <head>London–Birmingham, 3. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1851-07-03" type="travelday">3. July</date>. Endlich bin ich, Gottlob! dem langweiligen ermüdenden <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> entronnen; nachdem ich dem Herrn <placeName ref="gfa-places-1649" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="81"><persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName></placeName>, der mir gestern eine kolorirte <term ref="gfa-keywords-2840">lithographische Zeichnung</term> von seinem ausserordentlich <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1720">grossen Stahlwerk in Sheffield</placeName></term> gegeben, und eine ähnliche von meiner bescheidenen <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">Stahlgiesserei</placeName> im <placeName ref="gfa-places-97">Mühlenthal</placeName> bei <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, zugesendet hatte, und um 11 Uhr Vormittags nach dem nahe an 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">meinem Logis</placeName> entlegenen Bahnhof (Terminus) von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1666" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="82">Euston</placeName> fuhr, um von dort auf der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahn</term> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="83">Birmingham</placeName>, das 112 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">englische Meilen</term> von London entfernt ist, zu gehen. Ein Viertel nach 12 Uhr fuhr der Train ab. Das Fahrgeld zweiter Klasse beträgt 15 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> oder 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> Wohl gefiel mir die Einrichtung, dass dem Reisenden Koffer und Nachtsak, wenn Ersterer nicht gar zu gross ist, in die Abtheilung wo er ist, mitgegeben und unter die Bank geschoben werden, die Raum genug dafür hat. Man ist dann aller Sorgen, die man sonst dafür haben
                    <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618561"/> muss, enthoben: denn in England werden keine Nummern an die Gegenstände angeklebt wie in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Teutschland</placeName>, weil nichts gewogen, aber auch nichts dafür bezahlt wird. Präzis um 5 Uhr langte ich in Birmingham an, nahm meine Einkehr im <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="84">Stork Hôtel</placeName>, das ein sehr guter <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Gasthof</term> zu sein scheint, und machte nach vollbrachtem Mittagessen und Zeitungslesen, noch eine Tour durch die Strassen. Ich stund zuerst bei einem <placeName ref="gfa-places-1739" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="85"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9204">Carricaturladen</term></placeName> still, wo der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9206">katholische</term> Erzbischof <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7518">Wisemann</persName>, und Lord <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7519">Brougham</persName>, der einigermassen zu seinen Gunsten im Oberhaus gesprochen hatte, auf unbarmherzige Weise mitgenommen werden.</p>
                <p>Der mindest zu weit gehende Schritt von <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7518">Wisemann</persName> würde den jezt noch scheinbar schlafenden brittischen Löwen aufweken, und seine Krallen haben etwas zu sagen. — Ich war erstaunt als ich auf dem <placeName ref="gfa-places-2002">Patent-office</placeName>, als ich den Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7520">Poole</persName> besuchte, den ich schon von früher her gekannt, und ihm einen Gruss von Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName> brachte, von seinem Mitbeamten gefragt wurde, ob ich und Herr Kreeft <term ref="gfa-keywords-9385">Protestanten</term> oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-9206">Katholiken</term> seyen? Sage man nur nicht, dass die Toleranz im Allgemeinen in England zu Hause sey, denn mein Geschäft hatte mit irgend einem Glaubensbekenntniss so wenig zu thun, als mit dem Mann im Mond. Es ist merkwürdig wie lange politischer und religiöser Parteigeist schlafen kann, und dann unvermuthet sich wieder von dem geringsten Funken entzündet. ln diesem Carricaturladen lagen auch <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">französi<pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618562" break="no"/>sche</placeName> Kartenspiele am Fenster von ungemein kleinem Format haufenweise. Aus Neugierde frug ich nach dem Preis, und der war a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">half-penny</term> oder 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> nach unserem Gelde. Ich kaufte eines um mich zu überzeugen, dass ich recht gehört habe. Nebenan war ein <placeName ref="gfa-places-1738" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="86">Buchbinderladen</placeName>, wo am Fenster niedlich in schwarzen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9413">Saffian</term> gebundene <term ref="gfa-keywords-8828">Bibeln</term> stunden, mit vergoldetem Schnitt. Da brauchte ich nicht um den Preis zu fragen, es lagen Zettel dabei (wie dieses in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> häufig der Fall bei allerhand Waaren ist, da sie Feind von allen vielen Fragen und Antworten sind,) zu 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> and two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Pence</term>, oder 42 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> unseres Geldes. Diese zwei Sachen, Kartenspiel und Bibel gehörten in der That nicht zusammen, und wer mich kennt, wird wohl glauben, dass hier kein Spott zum Grunde liegt, aber diese schöne Edition kaufte ich sogleich, nur mangelt in derselben, was ich mit Verwunderung auch in ältern englischen Bibeln so gefunden, unter den apocryphischen Büchern, nach meinem Urtheil, gerade das Beste, nemlich der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8421">Jesus Sirach</term>, und weder des <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7592"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7795"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8505">Lords Chesterfields Briefe an seinen Sohn</term></persName></persName>, noch das <persName ref="gfa-actors-7610"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8487">Buch von Knigge über den Umgang mit Menschen</term></persName>, noch <persName ref="gfa-actors-7611"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8488">Kampes Theophron</term></persName> reichen, weder an tiefer Menschenkenntniss, noch praktischer Lebensweisheit, noch hoher Frömmigkeit an dieses vortreffliche Werk hinauf, während das hohe <term ref="gfa-keywords-8489">Lied Salomonis</term> — in England Song benannt — Aufnahme gefunden hat, und von den Theologen in eine Unterhaltung zwischen Christo und der
                    <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618563"/> Kirche hinein gezwängt worden ist. Da ich einmal mit einer unverheirateten Engländerin, die eine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9365">Pietistin</term> war, über diesen Gegenstand sprach, so war auch sie für das hohe Lied sehr eingenommen, wusste aber über den Jesus Sirach nichts zu sagen, da sie sein Buch nicht kannte. Es ist mir seither schon mehreremal zu Sinn gekommen, ob nicht etwa der erste Herausgeber der Bibel in englischer Sprache, eine böse Frau gehabt habe, der er eben durch Aufnahme dieser Schrift in oberwähnte Bücher, keinen angenehmen Spiegel würde vorgehalten haben.</p>
                <p>Nur drei Schritte von diesem Buchbinderladen war ein Eisenhändler, oder vielmehr, halb und halb, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1737" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-03" n="87"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9102">Quincaillerieladen</term></placeName>, und an dem Fenster <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">Medaillen</term> von hübschem weissem Metall, mit der Abbildung des <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Cristallpalastes</placeName>. Was kostet eine solche Medaille, (in der Grösse wie ein Vereinsgulden), frug ich den Herrn im Laden, und siehe da der Preis, der fast unglaubliche, war 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> oder a half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">penny</term>. Ich nahm mehrere davon. Ferner hiengen am Fenster künstliche <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">Magnete</term>. Ich kaufte auch einen von nicht unbedeutender Kraft von fünf <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term> Länge sammt dem Anker, und was musste ich für diesen bezahlen? Antwort: 18 Kreuzer (six pence). Er ist sehr nett gearbeitet, und was sehr verständig ist, bis gegen den Anker hinunter mit rothem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8490">Firniss</term> überzogen. Nur in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> ist es möglich, gewisse Metalwaaren um einen solchen Spottpreis zu kaufen.</p>
                <p>Ich blieb bei diesem sehr unterrichteten
                    <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618564"/> Manne, der vielen Zuspruch hat, bis es dunkel wurde, und sagte beim Abschiednehmen, ich werde den folgenden Tag wiederkommen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Birmingham, 4. Juli 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-20"><date when="1851-07-04">Den 4. Juli</date></placeName>. Wie ich versprochen, so gieng ich auch zuerst wieder <placeName ref="gfa-places-1737" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="88">zu ihm</placeName> hin, und brachte ihm zugleich ein Muster <term ref="gfa-keywords-8522"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">meiner Kupfer-Eisenverbindung</term></term> mit. Er war sowohl über die rothe Farbe als darüber, dass der <term ref="gfa-keywords-2766">Magnet</term> dieses Metallgemisch so willig zog, sehr verwundert, und indem er vor mir her ging winkte er mir, ihm zu folgen. Nach dem Ansteigen von einer langen schmalen Treppe kamen wir in zwei seiner Magazine, die ordentlich ausstaffirt waren, und dann führte er mich noch in eine Dachstube (Garret), wo er mir wirklich etwas zeigte, das ich in der Art noch nie gesehen; nemlich ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">Walzwerk</term> mit 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fuss</term> langen über einander liegenden <term ref="gfa-keywords-8767">Walzen</term>, an deren einem Ende eine Kurbel, und an den Achsen bei den <term ref="gfa-keywords-8957">Zapfenlagern</term> zwei <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">Stirnräder</term> gleicher Grösse waren, die ineinander griffen, und dann noch eine dritte parallel laufende Walze, die aber durch Stellschrauben höher oder niederer, als die eine oder andere Axis der auf einander liegenden Walzen, und auch näher oder entfernter von denselben gestellt werden konnte. Wurde nun ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">Blech</term> zwischen das erstere Walzenpaar gebracht, so stiess es sich bei dem Vorrüken, durch Umdrehen der zwei Walzen an der dritten Walze an, und rundete sich in diesem Verhältniss zu einem beinahe zusammengehenden Cylinder, wenn das Blech in seiner ganzen Länge
                    <pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618565"/> durchgegangen war, so dass es, wenn von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8638">Weissblech</term>, nur gar von Hand übereinandergestossen, und zusammengelöthet werden konnte, und wenn von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">Eisenblech</term>, bloss gefalzt zu werden brauchte. Die Rohre waren vollkommen rund und glatt, und mit ungemeiner Zeitersparnis angefertiget. Nach etwelcher weitern Unterhaltung zog er auf einmal seinen schwarzen Frak an, und sagte, ich solle mit ihm zu einem seiner Freunde gehen, der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9328">Münzpressen</term> und Fallwerke habe, und gerne mit mir wegen Stempeln reden würde. Dieses geschah, und Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7522" type="met">Ralph Heaton</persName>, nachdem wir uns über seine Fabrikation besprochen, klagte sehr über die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">Münzstempel</term>, die er bedürfe, und sagte, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> bekomme er gar keinen Stahl, der gut seye für dieses, er müsse ihn von <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> kommen lassen, und zeigte mir Stüke die theils im <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">Härten</term> zersprungen, theils mit Löchern und ungleich harten Stellen, die sich beim Abdrehen gezeigt, behaftet waren. Nachdem ich selbige angesehen, so frug ich ihn, ob er denn Geld mache; da führte er mich eine Treppe hinunter in eine Art Keller, wo in sehr engem Raum, unter zwei grossen Pressen, bei deren jeder ein junger Knabe war, mit grosser Schnelligkeit durch die sechs Pferde starke <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">Hochdrukdampfmaschine</term>, ganz nach <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587">der Art</term>, wie Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7523">Watt</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName> sie in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1636">Münze</placeName> in London eingerichtet hatte, Geld geprägt wurde. Ich glaubte zuerst, es seien <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">Medaillen</term>, allein er sagte : Nein, es ist Geld, das ich für die <placeName ref="gfa-places-206">Republik Chilé</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-145">Südamerika</placeName> präge, und kein Mensch
                    <pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618566"/> legt ihm etwas in den Weg. Es ist wirklich sehr schönes <term ref="gfa-keywords-9258">Kupfergeld</term>, hat 1<formula rend="inline" notation="tex">\frac{3}{16}</formula> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term> englisch Mass Durchmesser, und nicht gar <formula rend="inline" notation="text">\frac{1}{12}</formula> Zoll scheinbare Dike, ich sage scheinbare, weil der Rand auf beiden Seiten vorsteht. — Der Werth davon ist genau auf ½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">Penny</term> englisch Geld gestellt, was also 1½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> Reichsgeld ausmacht. So wie ich Gelegenheit habe, werde ich untersuchen, wie viele von den, das <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweizerland</placeName> so beglükenden Cents auf ein solches Stük gehen, vor welchen, wegen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9035">Fälschung</term>, vergebens von Leuten, die sich etwelche Kenntnisse und Erfahrungen im <term ref="gfa-keywords-97">metallurgischen</term> Fach erworben haben, gegen die Einbildung von denen, die da glauben, mit Geschwäz und hohlen Phrasen sei alles ausgerichtet, gewarnt wurde, abgesehen davon, dass wir für die Fabrikation derselben das Geld noch in das Ausland schikten, während unsere vorhandenen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9329">Münzstätten</term> in der Schweiz, ja ich behaupte die in <placeName ref="gfa-places-17">Bern</placeName> allein, ausgereicht hätten für den Bedarf; denn man muss wissen, dass jede dieser beiden Pressen 30,000, sage dreissigtausend Stük per Tag lieferte.</p>
                <p>Dieses wirklich schöne Geld hatte, wie Figura zeigt, auf dem Avers einen fünfekigten
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <graphic url="images/JCF1851_1_Muenze.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                    <pb n="80" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618567"/> Stern und die Umschrift: <placeName ref="gfa-places-206">Republica de Chilé</placeName>, <date>1851</date>, und auf dem Revers einen Lorbeerkranz, in Mitte dessen die Worte: un Centavo, und ausserhalb des Kranzes der Wahlspruch : Economia Es Riqueza, sich befinden. Nicht genug, dass mir dieser Mann, den ich in meinem Leben nie gesehen, alle seine Einrichtungen zeigte, worunter auch 4 Fallwerke, unter denen man die schönen dünnen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">Messingsachen</term> stanzt, die man nachher mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-9137">Goldfirniss</term> überzieht, sondern er verehrte mir noch sechs Stük von diesem neuen Gelde. Seine Stempel härtete er, wie er mir zeigte, alle unter dem Strom, was für den harten Stahl nothwendig ist. Er sagte, wenn er sie glühend ins Wasser werfen würde, so würden sie ihm alle springen. — Als ich von ihm wegging, sagte ich zu mir selbst: «Es ist doch kein Winkel der Erde, der nicht an den Gewerb und Kunstfleiss der Engländer Anspruch macht. Chilé schikt seine edlen Metalle nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, dass man ihm <term ref="gfa-keywords-9258">Kupfergeld</term> dafür übersende.» — Mit einem der Herren <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7524">Gebrüder Weiss</persName>, an die ich von meinem Freund, Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7525">Escher</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-154">Zürich</placeName>, eine Empfehlung hatte, ging ich in ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Haus</term> zum Mittagessen, wo sich eine Table d’Hôte von etwa 20 täglichen Kunden befindet.</p>
                <p>— Ich wäre sehr gerne in das ehemals so berühmte <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName> hingegangen, wo mir <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-2.xml"><date from="1814-01-01" to="1814-12-31">1814</date> Herr Walt</ref><note>Gemeint ist vermutlich Herr Watt, d. h. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">James Watt der Jüngere</persName>.</note>, der damalige Eigenthümer <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">dieser Fabrike</orgName>, so viele Freundschaft erwiesen. Ich nahm desshalb ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-8909">Cab</term>, und Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7524" type="met">Weiss</persName> war so gut, mich zu begleiten. Er sagte mir zum Voraus,
                    <pb n="81" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618568"/> diese grosse Maschinenfabrik seye seit dem Tod des Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>, und dem seines Associé Herrn. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7573">Boulton</persName>, den ich auch sehr gut kannte, ganz herunter gekommen. Als wir anlangten, war kein Mensch auf dem <placeName ref="gfa-places-1694" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="91">Comptoir</placeName>. Alles in den vielen Werkstätten leer und öde; vieles schon zerfallend. Welcher Unterschied! wo ich dieses Etablissement in seinem höchsten Glanz sah, und die Eigenthümer ein Einkommen genossen, wie nicht jeder Fürst ein solches hat. Eine solche schnelle Aenderung hätte ich mir nie vorgestellt, wenn ich sie nicht mit Augen gesehen hätte. Hier mehr als an manchem andern Ort würde die Inschrift «Sic transit gloria mundi»<note>Lat. für «So vergeht der Ruhm der Welt».</note> anzubringen seyn.</p>
                <p>Zurük von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>, und von meinen beiden Landsleuten (die Herren <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7524">Weiss</persName> sind von <placeName ref="gfa-places-181">Winterthur</placeName>) mich beurlaubend, kaufte ich noch eine sehr gute Federwage mit welcher bis auf 45 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pf.</term> gewogen werden kann, für 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Shilling</term> oder 36 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kr.</term> und ging dann in mein <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-04" n="92">Logis</placeName>, um die Ergebnisse dieses Tages aufzuzeichnen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Birmingham–Manchester, 5. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Sonnabends den <date when="1851-07-05" type="travelday">5. July</date>. Um 10 Uhr verreiste ich von <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-471" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="93">Manchester</placeName>. Die Fahrt hätte für die 80 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> in 3½ Stunden zurükgelegt werden sollen, allein aus unbekannten Ursachen blieb der Train bei <placeName ref="gfa-places-1667">Stockport</placeName> eine ganze Stunde, und dann noch an einem anderen Ort eine halbe Stunde liegen, so dass wir erst nach 3 Uhr in Manchester ankamen.</p>
                <p>Wie dieser Ort seit <date when="1827">1827</date>, <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-4.xml">als ich dort war</ref>, an Umfang zugenommen hat, kann man sich,
                    <pb n="82" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618569"/> ohne ihn zu sehen, nicht wohl einen Begriff machen. Meilenlange gerade und breite Strassen bilden jezt diese gewerbsame Stadt, die der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8517">Erfindung</term> eines armen Barbierers <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7535">Arkwright</persName> ihre gegenwärtige Grösse und ihren hohen Wohlstand zu danken hat; denn er war es, der die erste Idee hatte, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">Baumwolle</term> mittelst <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">Maschinen</term> zu spinnen, und die Ausführung davon übernahm sein Schwager, ein Tischler, und liess was von <term ref="gfa-keywords-4347">Metall</term> war, bei <term ref="gfa-keywords-9117">Giessern</term> und Schlossern machen. Die ersten Cylinder waren nur von <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">Messing</term> und für jeden Faden ein einziges Stük von circa ein <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">Zoll</term> lang. Als ich <ref type="cross" target="reisetagebuch-1.xml"><date when="1794">1794</date></ref> bei Herrn <persName ref="gfa-actors-7395">Rhé</persName>, Mechanikus in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, arbeitete, machten wir noch dergleichen. Sein für seine Erfindung erworbenes <term ref="gfa-keywords-239">Patent</term>, deren sich der praktische Geist der Engländer sogleich bemächtigte, verkaufte er, wie mir Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> <date when="1813">vor 38 Jahren</date> erzählte, um so hohe Summen, dass er es auf ein jährliches Einkommen von 10,000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">Pfund Sterling</term>, oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 120,000 brachte.</p>
                <p>Auch <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> ist, wie <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, in eine beständige Rauchwolke eingehüllt, nur mit dem Unterschied, dass wenn in lezterer Stadt nur hohe Kamine, von Zeit zu Zeit Flammen emittirend, daraus hervorragen, in ersterer, noch nebst denselben, sich die 6 bis 7 Stokwerk hohen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">Spinnereien</term>, mit ihrer unendlichen Fensterzahl, die sonst in den englischen Privathäusern so spärlich ist, von Zeit zu Zeit kund geben, so dass in vielen ihrer Myrmidonenwohnungen, sich per Etage, deren selten dreie sind, nur ein Kreuz<pb n="83" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618570" break="no"/>stok mit einem Sashwindow (Schubfenster), von drei Schuh Breite, zu sehen ist. Man wird fragen, wie kann aber Helle in diesen Häusern seyn? Da geniren sie sich aber gar nicht, und lassen dieselbe, wie <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7459">Paxton</persName> in seinem <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Glaspalast</placeName>, oben zum Dach hinein, eine Vorkehrung, die wie ich glaube fast in keinem Hause mangelt. Ueberhaupt ist die Bauart der Engländer in dieser Beziehung unheimlich und geschmaklos. Vergleiche man nur ein solches Haus, das wie ein grosser theils rother theils schwarzbrauner <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">Ziegelstein</term> aussieht, mit unseren freundlichen Bauernhäusern in verschiedenen Kantonen der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName>, und namentlich im <placeName ref="gfa-places-79">Kanton Zürich</placeName>, und fälle dann ein Urtheil.</p>
                <p>Nach einem kurzen Mittagessen wollte ich noch meinen alten Bekannten, den Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-6319">Fairbairn</persName>, der ein grosses <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7612">Etablissement</orgName> für <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Dampfboote</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">Dampfmaschinen</term> hat, besuchen, traf ihn aber nicht mehr in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1718" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="94">Fabrike</placeName>. Ich gieng nach seinem beinahe drei <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> davon entfernten <placeName ref="gfa-places-2080" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-05" n="95">Wohnhaus</placeName>, wohin eine ganz neue, sehr breite Strasse führte. Hier ist nun der, ich möchte sagen absurde, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9407">Rococogeschmak</term>, der alle edlen Formen verdrängt, und alles was in demselbigen vorhanden ist, zu ewigen Staubwinkeln und Spinnewebenbehältern macht, an den Giebeln der Häuser, die nun, wie hin und wieder in den alten Reichsstädten, unter einem sehr spizigen Winkel gegen die Strasse gekehrt, und an den vorstehenden Balkenhöpfen, und Bügen oder Stre<pb n="84" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618571" break="no"/>ben, in allerlei Schnörkel verarbeitet sind, in langer Reihe zu sehen.</p>
                <p>Viele Leute wissen eben öfter aus Uebermuth oder langer Weile nicht was sie wollen. Was die Franzosen zu viel schwazen, reden die Engländer zu wenig, und daher kommen öfter ihre excentrischen Gedanken: doch würde ich mich am Ende immer noch lieber auf die Seite der Engländer halten, als zu leerem Geschwäz und Wetterfahnengesinnung.</p>
                <p>Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-6319">Fairbairn</persName> selbst traf ich nicht, er ist gegenwärtig bei der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1732"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8497">wissenschaftlichen Versammlung in Ipswich</term></placeName>, wird aber am Dienstag wieder in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> seyn. Sein Sohn<note>Fairbairn hatte vier Söhne: Thomas, George, Peter und John. Vermutlich handelt es sich hier um <persName ref="gfa-actors-7594">Thomas Fairbairn (1823–1891)</persName>, der als langjähriger Partner des <persName ref="gfa-actors-6319">Vaters</persName> bekannt war.</note>, mit dem ich mich sehr angenehm unterhielt, gab mir seine Adresse, so dass mir bei der Rükkehr von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> noch wohl das Vergnügen zu Theil werden kann, diesen alten Freund, dessen Name ruhmvoll in England bekannt ist, dort zu sehen.</p>
                <p>Noch muss ich wegen <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> nachtragen, wie ungemein wohl ich daselbst im Wirthshaus <placeName ref="gfa-places-1705">Stork Hôtel</placeName> zufrieden war. Alles, ohne Ausnahme, besser und schöner als in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1710">meinem Logis</placeName> in London, und wenigstens um ein Dritttheil wohlfeiler. Auf dem Lande in England ist einem herrlich wohl, aber in London nicht.</p>
                </div> 
            <div type="day">
                <head>Manchester–Sheffield, 6. Juli 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-471"><date when="1851-07-06">Sonntag den 6. July</date></placeName>. Nach dem Frühstük (halb 10 Uhr) durchging und ordnete ich noch meine Schriften, schrieb Instructionen für zwei meiner in <placeName ref="gfa-places-113">Oesterreich</placeName> etablirten Söhne<note>Gemeint sind <persName ref="gfa-actors-7384">Wilhelm Fischer (1803—1882)</persName> und <persName ref="gfa-actors-148">Georg Fischer (1804—1888)</persName>.</note>, die <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> auch besuchen wollen, und pakte zusammen, da der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Train</term> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-06" n="96">Sheffield</placeName> um 3 Uhr
                    <pb n="85" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618572"/> abging, und ich vorher noch zu Mittag speisen wollte. Die Fahrt, die für die 40 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term> 9 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">Sh.</term> und 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, oder 3 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">fl.</term> 18 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">kr.</term> unseres Geldes, in zweiter Klasse kostet, war eine langweilige, wegen öfterem Aufenthalt, aber eine interessante wegen dem erstaunend abwechselnden Hügelland, dem um <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Lüttich</placeName> herum ähnlich, wo man dann, wenn man durch einen langen, und dicht finstern Tunnel gefahren ist, plözlich über einen Viaduct (auf Pfeilern und Bogen gebauten Schienenweg), der öfter viel höher ist, als die zunächst dabei stehenden Häuser, dahin rollt. Eine Fahrt mit solchen Abwechslungen im Bau der <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnen</term>, könnte für uns Schweizer sehr einladend erscheinen, weil wir in unserem lieben <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Vaterland</placeName> im Physischgeographischen (wie im Politischen) genugsam mit Berg auf und Bergunter bescheert sind; aber bewahre uns der Himmel von Zuhandennahme, wenigstens für jezt noch, bei einem <orgName ref="gfa-actors-598">projectirten Eisenbahnnez</orgName> auf Staatskosten: es würde uns den zehnfachen Segen bringen von der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9773">neuen Münze</term>. — Man muss viele hundert Meilen, und in verschiedenen Ländern, Eisenbahnen bereist haben, um zu einer etwelchen klaren Ansicht des Für und Wider zu kommen. Wir sind keine der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9093">monarchischen</term> Staaten. Dort sind wegen der Grösse in kommerzieller Hinsicht, und dann wegen den Nachbarn, und wie die neuesten Zeiten nachgewiesen haben, wegen möglichen politischen Vorfallenheiten im Innern, dieselben in diese Nothwendigkeit versezt. Am allerwenigsten muss
                    <pb n="86" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618573"/> man aber wegen der Eisenbahnen England zum Muster und Vorwand nehmen, denn selbst in diesem, so gewerb- und volkreichen, und mit den Mitteln, Eisenbahnen wohlfeil zu bauen, besser als in keinem Land von Europa ausgerüsteten <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> sind schon wieder welche eingegangen, die sich gar nicht in der Art rentirten, wie man glaubte, wo man doch sonst in diesem Lande ziemlich sicher rechnet. Eine Wahrheit steht fest, erstlich dass bei den meisten unserer projectirten Eisenbahnen noch keine absolute Nothwendigkeit vorhanden ist, und der einstweilige Verschub weit weniger Schaden bringt und bringen kann, als die Uebereilung, wovon man in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> und anderwärts in allerhand Vorfallenheiten schon deutliche Fingerzeige, namentlich auch in politischen Beziehungen bekommen hat; und zweitens steht noch eine Wahrheit fest, dass bei den ungemeinen Fortschritten dieser Zeit, in der <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">Physik</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">Chemie</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9302">Mechanik</term>, und der durch diese Wissenschaften gehobenen und unterstüzten Technik, es nicht nur wahrscheinlich, sondern man darf sagen gewiss ist, dass auch den Transportmitteln, in dieser oder jener Art, und vielleicht innert sehr kurzer Zeit, grosser Vorschub geleistet werden wird. Als man noch, um ferntreffende <term ref="gfa-keywords-3945">Waffen</term> zu haben, mit Pfeil und Bogen zu Felde zog, hatte Niemand die Idee von der Wirkung einer <term ref="gfa-keywords-8821">Batterie</term> von Vierundzwanzigpfündern, und als man noch bei uns und anderwärts die armen Hexlein verbrannte, wenn sie angeklagt wurden, auf einem unschul<pb n="87" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618574" break="no"/>digen Besenstiel zu ihrem Vergnügen in der Walpurgisnacht durch die Lüfte auf den <placeName ref="gfa-places-1688">Bloksberg</placeName> gefahren zu seyn, so schweben nun hingegen heutigen Tages die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9791">Aeronauten</term>, unmolestirt, über Lander und Meere, der Eile der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">Locomotive</term> und der Blizesschnelle der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9562">elektrischen Telegraphen</term> zu geschweigen. Hätte einer, von <persName ref="gfa-actors-7552">Athenens</persName> Geist beseelt, in jener Zeit diese Erscheinungen in ihrem gegenwärtigen Vorhandenseyn vorausgesagt, er wäre weiss der Himmel wo! hingekommen. Doch genug von diesem.</p>   
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Fischers Geschäftsgänge in Sheffield, 7. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1851-07-07" type="travelday">7. July</date>. Diesen Morgen war mein erster Ausgang in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> zu den Herren <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7536"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1719" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="97">Rodgers und Sons</placeName></orgName>, den berühmtesten Fabrikanten nicht nur von dieser Stadt, sondern man kann wohl sagen von England, für <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">Messerschmied</term>- und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plattirte</term> Waaren, und gab ihnen einige <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">Rasiermesser</term> von dem von mir erfundenen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8453">Meteorstahl</term>, um ihre Meinung über die Qualität dieses Stahls zu vernehmen, mit dem Wunsch, sie morgen wieder abholen zu können, was sie mir versprachen. Von ihnen weg besuchte ich die <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1720" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="98">Gussstahlfabrike von den Herrn Johnson, Cammel und Comp.</placeName></orgName>, in welcher, nach der Angabe von Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammel</persName>, wöchentlich, wie schon erwähnt, 1000 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">Centner</term> an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">Gussstahl</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">Cementstahl</term> dargestellt werden, was auch begreiflich ist, wenn man den Umfang der Werkstätten, die nun durch einen neuen grossen Bau noch vermehrt werden, sieht, sowie die immense Anzahl von Locomotiv-, Train- und andern Arten von Wagenfedern, die ihnen, wie mir Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7606">Kreeft</persName>
                    <pb n="88" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618575"/> sagte, von den grossen <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahngesellschaften</term> beständig bestellt sind. Ueberhaupt suchen sie ihren Vortheil in der Menge der Production, was aber in Beziehung auf ihr Fabrikat in solcher Weise möglich ist, indem sie, wie ich berichtet worden bin, das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">Pfund</term> von solchem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467">Federstahl</term> um 2½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, oder 7 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> unseres Geldes verkaufen. Sie kaufen die alten oder sonst gebrochenen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">Federn</term> wieder um weit geringern Preis auf, machen theils Gusstahl, und theils auch wieder neue Federn daraus, und da bei dem abermaligen so bedeutenden Abschlag von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term>, der nahe an 30 pCt.<note>Abkürzung für Prozent (%).</note> gegen das, was sie vor 4 Jahren, als ich in England, und auch bei ihnen war, beträgt, und der Brennstoff namentlich in ihren so vortheilhaften <term ref="gfa-keywords-8557">Schweissheerden</term> (Schweissöfen) darum so wenig kostet, so ist dieser niedrige Preis möglich.</p>
                <p>So gute Arbeit aber wie bei den Herren <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7542">Turton &amp; Sons</orgName>, die auch <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">Cementstahl</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">Gussstahl</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8508">Schweissstahl</term>, und aus diesem leztern Federn machen, scheint mir hier nicht angefertigt zu werden. Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName><note>Es ist unklar, ob es sich um Thomas oder Henry Johnson handelt.</note> liess eine neue Feder in meiner Gegenwart probiren, aber weit früher als sie das Maximum ihrer Ausdehnung durch Geradedrüken erreicht hatte, brach sie. Ueberhaupt da die drei Herren, die diese Gesellschaft bilden, der dritte ist ein Teutscher, Gosse, Schwager von Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7505">Cammell</persName>, mehr in der Schreibstube als in den Werkstätten sind, und für jedes ihrer Industriefächer einen Werkführer (Foreman) haben müssen, so kömmt auf die Eigen<pb n="89" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618576" break="no"/>schaft eines solchen erstaunend viel an. Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName> liess den Schmelzer holen, und so gingen wir in eines der <term ref="gfa-keywords-88">Schmelzhäuser</term>, wo 24 <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">Oefen</term> nur in diesem in beständiger Thätigkeit waren, und alle Augenblike gegossen wurde, weil täglich in jedem Ofen dreimal geschmolzen wird. Auch hier wurde ich, wie es schon anderwärts geschehen, zuerst von dem Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7593">Johnson</persName> und dann nachher noch von dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">Schmelzmeister</term> ins Besondere gefragt, wie auch das Piping (das will sagen die Gasentwiklung, wenn der Stahl gegossen wird, und wo das zurükbleibende, adherirende, oder erst noch im Augenblik des Giessens sich entwikelnde Gas dann Löcher von verschiedener Grösse inwendig im <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahl</term> bildet, während an der gegossenen Stange oder überhaupt dem gegossenen Gegenstand von Aussen keine Spur davon bemerkbar ist) verhütet werde, worauf ich angemessen fand, ihm blos zu sagen, «dieses hange von der Führung des Schmelzprozesses ab.» Er that auch noch eine, dem Anschein nach sehr einfältige Frage an mich, die mich aber mit einemmal durchbliken liess, er wolle durch dieses Manoeuvre nur ausforschen, (pump me out) wie weit meine Erfahrungen gehen. Zu diesem Catechisiren hatte ich aber keine Lust, und empfahl mich bald nachher diesen Herren, da es Zeit war zum Mittagessen zu gehen.</p>
                <p>Nachmittags ging ich zuerst in Herrn <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="99">Huntsmans Hammerschmiede</placeName>, in welcher ich durch den Hrn. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsmann</persName> selbst den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">Hammerschmieden</term> wohl bekannt war, und beaugenscheinigte nochmals
                    <pb n="90" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618577"/> die dortigen Einrichtungen für Wärmfeuer und Schweissheerd. Der kleinere Ofen wird mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term>, und der grössere mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> geheizt, und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9731">Gebläse</term> wird angewendet. Diese Feuer sind unsern Essfeuern mit <term ref="gfa-keywords-8697">Holzkohlen</term> weit vorzuziehen. Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName> selbst war leider wieder nicht in der Stadt, und so ging ich den weitern Weg vom <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">Donfluss</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1677" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="100">West Street</placeName> zu meinem alten Freund Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Charles Sanderson</persName>, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-121"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7587"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2096" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="101">seine Stahlgiesserei</placeName></orgName></term>, wo ich mit Bedauern vernahm, dass er an podagrischen<note>Die Podagra (Gicht im Fuss, besonders im grossen Zeh) betreffend.</note> und chiragrischen<note>Die Chiragra (Gicht in den Hand- und Fingergelenken) betreffend.</note> Schmerzen leide, was auch vor vier Jahren schon der Fall gewesen, indessen doch nicht bettlägerig seye. Ich hatte nun fast noch eine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meile</term> weit nach seiner Wohnung zu gehen, was mich aber nicht abhielt, ihn zu besuchen. Mit vieler Freundschaft empfieng er mich in seinem <placeName ref="gfa-places-2158" cert="0" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-07" n="102">eigenen Hause</placeName>, wo seine <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7588">Gemahlin</persName> mich gleich zum <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">Thee</term> einlud, was ich wegen brennendem Durst und Unwohlseyn mit grösstem Vergnügen annahm. Unsere allgemeine Unterhaltung, da sie eine sehr verständige und angenehme Frau ist, drehte sich lange um die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">Exhibition</term>. Sie ist gegenwärtig das Lieblingsthema der Engländer, und die Morgen- und Abendunterhaltung mit Fremden, und sie sind in der That über dieses Wunder, welches sich so plözlich vor den Bewohnern unseres Erdballs entfaltete, nicht zu verdenken.</p>
                <p>Eine grosse Freude gewährte mir Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Sanderson</persName> durch das Versprechen, da er darin sehr grosse Erfahrungen hat, mir, sobald seine Hand
                    <pb n="91" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618578"/> wieder brauchbar seye, eine genaue Mittheilung, wornach ich schon lange gestrebt, über das Minimum von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term>, zu machen, um aus unseren <term ref="gfa-keywords-8851">Bohnerzen</term>, die er als <term ref="gfa-keywords-289">Mineralog</term> sehr wohl kennt, das graue überkohlte, für <term ref="gfa-keywords-238">Cuppoloöfen</term> taugliche <term ref="gfa-keywords-9011">Roheisen</term> zu erschmelzen, und noch eine eigenhändige Zeichnung für einen <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">Hochofen</term> in solchen kleinen Dimensionen, als es nur auch die Natur der Sache erlaube, beizufügen.</p>
                <p>Wir sprachen auch von einem Hochofen, dessen Modell auf der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">Ausstellung</term> sich befindet, der oben durch ein Ventil geschlossen ist, welches nur für Füllung der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8797">Gicht</term> für <term ref="gfa-keywords-2570">Kohlen</term> und <term ref="gfa-keywords-9027">Erze</term> etc. geöffnet und dann gleich wieder geschlossen wird, wo dann Flamme und die Gase seitwärts durch geschlossene Röhren geleitet und zu andern Zweken verbraucht werden. Dieser Ofen hat drei <term ref="gfa-keywords-9715">Düsen</term> (Formen), wie die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8491">Wilkinson’schen Oefen</term>, was gewiss das Beste ist, was man haben kann. Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7538">Sanderson</persName> hatte ihn aber wegen Unpässlichkeit noch nicht gesehen. Ich erwähnte auch noch eines anderen weit grösseren Modells von einem Hochofen auf der Exhibition, mit sechs Düsen, was wohl zu viel ist, weil es Futter und Mantel zu sehr schwächt. Schon vor mehr als 50 Jahren richtete der Berghauptmann <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7541">von Reden</persName> einen solchen am <placeName ref="gfa-places-1962">Harz</placeName>, mit 6 Düsen vor, ohne grösseren Vortheil als durch dreie erhalten wird.</p>
                <p>Nach beinahe zweistündiger Unterhaltung verliess ich diese Familie, die sich immer so freundschaftlich gegen mich beweist, mit dem
                    <pb n="92" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618579"/> Wunsch, sie möchten mich auch bald in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName> besuchen, und endete diesen langen Tag mit Schreiben.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Weitere Geschäftsgänge in Sheffield, 8. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Den <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265"><date when="1851-07-08" type="travelday">8. July</date></placeName> ging ich zu den Gussstahlfabrikanten, Herren <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7542"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1721">Turton und Sons</placeName></orgName>, mit denen ich ebenfalls in freundschaftlichen Verhältnissen stehe, und die nebst einer sehr grossen Menge <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">Feilen</term>, auch viele <term ref="gfa-keywords-9074">Federn</term> für <term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Eisenbahnwägen</term> machen. Man glaubt gar nicht, was für ein Consum in diesem Artikel ist! Ihre Federn schienen mir besser als die <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7537">Cammel’schen</orgName>. Diese Herren sind selbst bei der Arbeit, und die mir vorprobirt wurden, hielten die starke Probe vollkommen aus. Das Auge des Herrn macht das Pferd fett! Sprichwort.</p>
                <p>Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7543">Turton</persName> war nicht in der <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">Giesserei</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1721"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1714" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-08" n="103">Bow Spring</placeName></placeName>, sondern da, wo sie die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">Walzwerke</term> und Hämmer haben, in den sogenannten Sheaf works nicht weit von dem <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">Donfluss</placeName>, der dem <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsmann</persName> sein <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">Hammerwerk</term></placeName> treibt. Ich hätte nicht gedacht, ein so ausgedehntes Werk zu finden. Die Zahl der Werkstätten, worunter Schleifen, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">Hammerwerke</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">Feilenhauereien</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9632">Zeugschmieden</term> etc. sich befinden, beläuft sich nach den an der Thüre angeschriebenen Nummern auf 73. Mehrere Comptoirs sind mit Beamten besezt.</p>
                <p>Herr <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7543">Turton</persName> wollte gerade abreisen, um seinen sehr kranken Bruder in London zu besuchen, und da sagte er im Vorbeigehen dem Thürsteher (Porter), und ohne einen solchen ist kein rechtes Werk in England, so wie dieser Herr kommt, auf mich zeigend, so möge er un<pb n="93" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618580" break="no"/>gehindert alle Werkstätten besuchen. Er begleitete mich noch zu <placeName type="itinerar" when="1851-07-08" n="105">meinem Logis</placeName>, wo ich zum Mittagessen und er zum Terminus (Bahnhof) für die Fahrt nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> ging. Nachmittag machte ich nun wirklich Gebrauch von seiner Erlaubniss, und ging zuerst in die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">Hammerschmiede</term>. Der Hub der Hämmer ist klein aber sehr geschwind, was sehr verständig ist, weil unter einem schnellen Hammerschlag durch Erhizung vom Streich der Stahl immer länger warm bleibt, als unter einem langsamen, wenn der Hammer schon schwerer, und der Hub höher ist. Hämmer und <term ref="gfa-keywords-8658">Ambose</term> haben eingeschobene Kreuze oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-9821">Bahnen</term> von abgeschrektem (chilld) <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">Gusseisen</term>. Ihre Strekfeuer schienen mir nicht so gut wie die von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1687">Huntsmann</placeName>, insofern die eingeschobenen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">Coke</term> nicht den hohen Grad von <term ref="gfa-keywords-9191">Ignition</term> erreichten, als wie dort. Ich wollte noch nach den <placeName ref="gfa-places-1680">Potterworks</placeName>, nachdem ich noch eine Tour durch das Walzwerk gemacht hatte, allein zu müde und zu spät für diesen weiten Gang, begnügte ich mich die Notizen von heute noch einzutragen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Sheffield–Dover, 9. Juli 1851</head>
                <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-1265"><date when="1851-07-09">Den 9. Juli</date></placeName>. Meine Geschäfte beendiget, die durch Unwohlseyn ohnedies mich nicht zu längerem Verweilen hätten veranlassen können, ging ich diesen Morgen noch zu den Messer- und plattirten Waaren-Fabrikanten <orgName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7536"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1719" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="106">Rodgers &amp; Sons</placeName></orgName>, um meine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">Rasiermesser</term> abzuholen. Dieselben gaben Stoff zu einer interessanten Unterhaltung mit einem von diesen Herren über die Natur des <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">Eisens</term> für sich, als auch als Grund<pb n="94" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618581" break="no"/>lage des <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">Stahls</term>, und ich sezte einen Werth darauf, dass wir beide in der Ansicht übereinstimmten, dass eigentlich das Eisen nur darum gut seye, wenn es rein seye, und dass jedes gereinigte Eisen den mehrfachen (nach meinen Erfahrungen viererlei) Stoffen, die damit im Fluss oder bei starker und lange anhaltender <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">Glühhize</term> verbunden werden, sein Stahlwerden zu verdanken habe. Ueber meine Rasiermesser sprach er sich sehr vorteilhaft aus, so wie über den natürlichen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8452">Damast</term>, Folge verschobener Crystallisation<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> des im Fluss gestandenen Stahls. Die Zeit drängte. Um 10 Uhr musste ich im Bahnhof seyn, von wo ich, nach zurükgelegten 165 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">Meilen</term>, Abends um 3 Uhr in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="107">London</placeName> anlangte. Dort angekommen, ging ich noch zu Hrn. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1637" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="108"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7606" type="met">Kreeft</persName></placeName>, um verschiedene Angelegenheiten mit ihm zu besprechen. In dieser Zwischenzeit besuchte mich Herr <persName ref="gfa-actors-7544" type="met">Baird</persName>, der von <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> zurükgekehrt war, wo er das von Hrn. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7480">Robinson</persName> gelieferte <term ref="gfa-keywords-9429">Schiff</term> zusammengesezt hatte, und Abends um 6 Uhr verreiste ich nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-09" n="109">Dover</placeName>, wo ich nach 9 Uhr anlangte, und um 11 Uhr Nachts mit dem <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Postdampfschiff</term> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">Ostende</placeName> abgieng. Wenn ich die Ueberfahrt von Ostende nach Dover einer Sterbeanstalt verglich, so hätte ich, als es gegen den Morgen gieng, den Salon, wegen äusserst stürmischer Witterung, und der davon unter allen Passagieren, mit Ausnahme von einem Einzigen, der wahrscheinlich schon weite Reisen zur See gemacht hatte, ausgebrochenen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">Seekrankheit</term>, für ein Schlachtfeld ansehen kön<pb n="95" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618582" break="no"/>nen. Gleich bei der Abfahrt von Dover war derselbe so gedrängt voll, dass ich, was sich ereignen werde, voraussehend, mich ungeachtet von Sturm und Regen auf das Verdek begab, von einem Matrosen um 6 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> eine alte blaue Jake entlehnte, selbige über meinen Ueberrok noch anzog, ein altes Stük Segeltuch zur Deke, und ein spiralförmig zusammengerolltes Stük Tau zu meinem Kopfkissen machte, und so in der Nachbarschaft der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">Dampfmaschine</term> auf dem blossen Verdek mein Nachtlager einnahm, was freilich bei oberwähnter Witterung kein angenehmer Aufenthalt war, aber mich vor der Seekrankheit schüzte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Ostende–Mannheim, 10./11. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1851-07-10" type="travelday">10. Juli</date>. Als der Tag anbrach, erblikten wir ganz am Horizont den <placeName ref="gfa-places-1681">Kirchthurm</placeName> von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-10" n="110">Ostende</placeName>, und ich hoffte, dass wir nach dem gedrukten Fahrtenzettel um 8 Uhr dort anlangen würden, um versprochener Massen mit dem auf uns wartenden Bahnzug nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cöln</placeName> abgehen zu können, und ging deshalb in den Salon hinunter, um vorläufig meinen dort zurükgelassenen Nachtsak und Regenschirm auf das Verdek zu holen. Aber was war dieses für ein Spektakel? Auf dem Boden und den Bänken herumliegende Passagiere, mit dieser ekelhaften <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">Krankheit</term> belastet und erschöpft, umgestürzte Leuchter auf den Tischen wegen dem Schwanken des <term ref="gfa-keywords-8801">Schiffes</term>, zerbrochene Schüsseln am Boden, beschmuzte Kleider etc. Es war wie gesagt alles gedrängt voll, und ich musste, um meine Geräthschaften zu holen, mehreren auf die Füsse treten; sie zo<pb n="96" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618583" break="no"/>gen sie nur mechanisch zurük, sagten aber kein Wort. Erst Vormittags um 10 Uhr konnte das Schiff in Ostende einlaufen, und so hatten wir statt im günstigen Fall nur vier, eilf Stunden gebraucht. Keinem Menschen, der nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> geht, oder von dort nach dem festen Lande reist, würde ich diese Ueberfahrt mehr anrathen. Wer nach England gehen will, der nehme den Weg, wenn <placeName ref="gfa-places-82">Cöln</placeName> der Endpunkt einer Rheinreise ist, über <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Lüttich</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName>, und wenn er von England kommt, falls er nicht vorzieht, über <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> und <placeName ref="gfa-places-470">Strassburg</placeName> zu gehen, von Calais wieder nach Lüttich und Cöln. Der Morgenzug nach Cöln wartete nicht auf unser Schiff, und so konnte ich erst Nachmittags um 1 Uhr von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1625">Ostende</placeName> weg, und dann mit einem Nachtzug von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-10" n="111">Aachen</placeName> nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-82" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-11" n="112">Cöln</placeName>, wo ich den <date when="1851-07-11" type="travelday">11. Juli</date> früh Morgens eintraf, und gleich wieder auf der Eisenbahn nach <placeName ref="gfa-places-1098" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-11" n="113">Mannheim</placeName> verreiste und dort übernachtete.</p> 
            </div>
            <div type="day">
                <head>Mannheim–Freiburg–Schaffhausen, 12.–14. Juli 1851</head>
                <p>Den <date when="1851-07-12" type="travelday">12. Juli</date> langte ich gegen Mittag in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1123" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="114">Karlsruhe</placeName> an, besuchte Hrn. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7547" type="met">Kessler</persName> in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1722" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="115"><term ref="gfa-keywords-74">Maschinenfabrike</term></placeName>, und Herrn Münzrath <persName ref="gfa-actors-7453">Kachel</persName> in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-1682" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="116">Münze</placeName>, und nahm etwelche Bestellungen auf. Nachmittag um 3 Uhr verliess ich Karlsruhe wieder, und konnte nun wieder eine Nacht in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-12" n="117">Freiburg</placeName> im Bette zubringen, da ich vier Nächte hintereinander eines solchen entbehren und unter denselben eine Nacht unter freiem Himmel und bei schlechter Witterung zubringen musste.</p>
                <p>Den <date when="1851-07-13" type="travelday">13.</date> Abends um 9 Uhr verreiste ich von
                    <pb n="97" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618584"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1122">Freiburg</placeName>, und langte den <date when="1851-07-14" type="travelday">14.</date> Vormittags um 10 Uhr, unerachtet der Strapazen, die diese Reise mit sich brachte, gottlob gesund und vergnügt wiederum <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237"><placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1851-07-14" n="118">zu Hause</placeName></persName> an.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
                <head>Gedanken zum Freihandel als Nachwort</head>
                <p>Nachschrift zu meinen Reisenotizen.</p>
                <p>Wenn etwa ausser den <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">Meinigen</persName>, und meinen Freunden, Jemand dieses Büchlein in die Hände bekommen und dann fragen sollte, warum diese, dem etwaigen Interesse daran, durch Verspätung nachtheilige Herausgabe erst jezt stattgehabt habe, so diene ganz kurz zur Antwort, dass wegen vielerlei Amts- und eigenen Geschäften, es mir erst im <date when="1852-11">November dieses Jahres</date> möglich geworden, die Copia von dem, meistens mit Bleistift geschriebenen Original zu vollenden, und dass, weil ich es nur für mich geschrieben, ich es auch nur als ein Gemälde von jenem Zeitabschnitt aus meinem Leben betrachte; und aber, gerade um dessentwillen, wie es der Fall mit historischen Gemälden auf Leinwand seyn kann, eint und andere Bilder, so lange als das Büchlein dauert, etwelches Interesse behalten dürften. — Und nun noch zum Schluss folgende Bemerkungen: während dem Mittagessen in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, weil in dem Gasthof, wo ich wohnte, an den Wochenmarkttagen eine Art Table d’hôte eingeführt ist, drehte sich die Hauptunterhaltung mit meinen Nachbarn um die einzuführende <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">Handelsfreiheit</term>, die von allen, mit denen ich sprach, ohne Aus<pb n="98" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618585" break="no"/>nahme in Schuz genommen wurde. Beim Nachdenken über ihre Aeusserungen, und denen, die ich noch particulariter bei verschiedenen Fabrikanten vernahm, wurde es mir klar, dass eben nur das eigene Interesse derselben, von weitaus der grösten Mehrheit, eine solche Massnahme dringend wünschbar mache, wovon ich mich dann noch mehr überzeugte, als ich ihre ungeheuren Produktionen, und die Wohlfeilheit derselbigen ins Auge fasste, und den Schluss zog, welche Wirkung diese Handelsfreiheit, bei einer solchen Ueberlegenheit an technischen und pecuniairen Mitteln, und der Wohlfeilheit ihrer bewegenden Kräfte, zunächst auf <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">mein Vaterland</placeName>, und dann auch auf andere Nationen des festen Landes, haben möchte.</p>
                <p>Auf meiner Rükreise verfolgte ich diesen Gegenstand noch weiter, brachte aber meine Ansichten darüber, erst geraume Zeit nachher, ausführlicher durch einen Zeitungsartikel, der im entgegengesezten Sinn abgefasst war, dazu veranlasst, zu Papier und übergab sie der Presse.<note>Der Artikel erschien in zwei Teilen im «Tage-Blatt für den Kanton Schaffhausen», Nr. 88 und 89, am 15. und 16. April 1852.</note> Ich füge dieselben nun darum diesen Notizen ebenfalls bei, da sie zu meinen interessanteren<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> Bemerkungen in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> gehören, von denen ich auf einigen Blättern derselben, vorläufig nur schwache Andeutungen machte.</p>
                <p>Denn wenn man über den <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">Freihandel</term> urtheilen will, so ist zuvörderst zu erwägen, was die Pflicht der Selbsterhaltung von uns verlangt, die höher steht und uns näher ligt, als alle Spreutheorien von Freiheit, Gleichheit und Einheitlichkeit (man hat lezteres Wort erfunden, weil
                    <pb n="99" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618586"/> man sich doch schämen musste, von der Schweizereinigkeit zu reden), die so abgedroschen sind, dass nicht ein Korn mehr herauszubringen ist, und nach dieser Feststellung der Pflichten gegen sich selbst, hat man nur ganz einfach zu fragen, was ist der Freihandel und worin besteht er? und die Antwort ist, dass ein jeder die Ergebnisse seiner Arbeit, oder seines Verkehrs oder Zwischenhandels, dahinbringen und absezen kann wo er will, ohne durch irgend eine Restriction zu Gunsten der Arbeitenden oder Verkehrenden, in dem Lande, wo er seine Waare hinbringt, gebunden zu seyn. Ehe nun auf die Folgen von dieser Freiheit eingetreten werden kann, muss man fragen, stehen denn alle Völker auf der gleichen Stufe von <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">Industrie</term>, durch die natürlichen Erzeugnisse ihres Bodens auf der Oberfläche, und in der Tiefe ihrer Erde, wo der Freihandel sollte eingeführt werden? oder hat die Natur, oder haben die gesellschaftlichen Verhältnisse und die darauf beruhende Geisteskultur, oder in näherer Bestimmung, technische Geschiklichkeit, keinen Unterschied begründet, und die Antwort, die sich aus den bestehenden und unwidersprechlichen Thatsachen ergibt, ist Nein!</p>
                <p>Wenn also zwei Nationen, oder um die Sache auf den beschränktesten Punkt zurükzuführen, zwei Fabrikanten das Gleiche hervorbringen, der Eine aber durch grösseres Geschik, unterstüzt durch Lokalvortheile, die Gegenstände der Bedürfnisse, das will sagen alle Waaren, von gleicher Güte, ja in den meisten Fällen noch besser, hervorbringen kann, als der Andere und
                    <pb n="100" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618587"/> aber um wohlfeileren Preis, so muss man von der Wirklichkeit nichts kennen, um zu glauben, dass die Käufer nicht durchaus bei dem Ersten zusprechen, und sich um den Andern nichts bekümmern werden, wo denn der Leztere nach und nach zu Grunde geht, seye es nun dass er, weil er die <term ref="gfa-keywords-161">Concurrenz</term>, so wie die Sachen liegen, nicht bekämpfen kann, und desswegen aufhören muss zu produziren, oder dass er, wenn er aus Ehrgefühl oder Eigensinn dennoch in seiner Beschäftigung fortfährt, eben so sicher verarmt. Man muss aber nicht glauben, dass dieser Ruin nur allein auf ihn einwirkt, nein! in vielen tausend Verzweigungen des menschlichen Verkehrs, und den Quellen der Circulation des Geldes, welche, troz aller Bemühungen, so unerforschlich sind wie die Gedanken der Menschen, wird dadurch wieder eine Ader abgeschnitten oder verstopft, die dann auch wieder Andern ihre Alimentation, wenigstens zum Theil entzieht und es geschieht gerade das, wie wenn man einen Stein in ein Wasser wirft, die Ringe werden nach weiterhin scheinbar schwächer, aber erhalten grössern Umfang.</p>
                <p>Die Hauptfrage ist nun aber hauptsächlich die, die einerseits zur Weltfrage wird, aber hier nur speciell in Bezug auf <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">unser Vaterland</placeName> zu berüksichtigen ist. Welche Gründe kann <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> haben, dem Freihandelssystem nun so das Wort zu reden, und alle Hebel, bekannte und unbekannte, das heisst die der Presse, und die von ihm schon lange mit Erfolg gebrauchten Einwirkungen auf Individuen, die es für sein
                    <pb n="101" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618588"/> Interesse gewinnen möchte, in Bewegung zu sezen, um das Ziel, dem es zusteuert, zu erreichen? Die Antwort ist ganz kurz, sein und nur sein eigenes Interesse; — und man täuscht sich sehr, wenn man glaubt, dass, wenn schon einzelne Individuen dieser Nation durch wahre Liberalität und Magnanimität sich auszeichnen, nicht ein eben so ausgebildeter und starrer Egoismus seine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9169">Handelspolitik</term> leitet, als nur bei irgend einer andern Nation. Die Geschichte kann genugsam Blätter dafür aufweisen, wenn der <placeName ref="gfa-places-191"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9774">Schwefelhandel mit Neapel</term></placeName>, und der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9347">Opiumstreit</term> mit <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">China</placeName> keine Belege dazu lieferten.</p>
                <p>Wer mit seinen eigenen leiblichen Augen, und nicht etwa durch die Brille des Theoretikers von einem Dachstübchen auf dem Kontinent herunter dieses gross gedachte, und für die kurze Spanne der Zeit, in welcher es ausgeführt werden musste, menschliche Kräfte fast übersteigende Werk der <term ref="gfa-keywords-8436">Weltindustrieausstellung in London</term> gesehen hat, der musste durchaus zugeben, dass die englischen Produktionen in der grossen Allgemeinheit, sich neben jeden andern ähnlichen messen durften, und wer veranlasst war Eint und Anderes, namentlich in den Fabrikorten, selbst zu kaufen, der konnte sich überzeugen, dass die Engländer mit Ausnahme der Produkte, die die Natur ihrem <term ref="gfa-keywords-9216">Klima</term> versagt, und mit Ausnahme von sehr wenigen, als Artikel vom <term ref="gfa-keywords-4336">Welthandel</term> unbedeutenden Gegenständen, Alles genügend, und meistens in noch grösserer Vollkommenheit hervorbringen, als was von andern Ländern einzuführen wäre, abgesehen davon,
                    <pb n="102" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618589"/> dass das im Allgemeinen bei ihnen vorherrschende und nicht ganz unbegründete, Vorurtheil zu Gunsten ihrer eigenen Fabrikate sie für den Einkauf von fremden abgeneigt macht, wenn nicht etwa ganz besondere Verhältnisse, als ungemeine Wohlfeilheit, bewirkt durch die Wohlfeilheit der Urstoffe an Ort und Stelle der fremden Produzenten, oder unerreichbare Vollkommenheit, wo die Natur, namentlich bei gefärbten Stoffen in Folge der Beschaffenheit des Wassers oder der Atmosphäre, andere Länder mehr begünstiget, und sie zu Anschaffung dieser, im Verhältniss aber zu ihrem Export ganz unbedeutenden Gegenständen veranlasst.</p></div>
                <div type="postscript">
                    <head>Die Wichtigkeit des Freihandels für England</head>
                <p>Und wenn man nun in Fernerm betrachtet, dass die Engländer hingegen nicht nur so zu sagen Alles im Lande produziren, was menschliche Kunst und menschliches Genie hervorbringen kann, sondern dass sie, begünstiget durch den Geist der Beharrlichkeit, des Fleisses und der Arbeitsamkeit, der diese Nation durchdringt, durch die Masse der Erfahrungen, oder wenn man will, durch die Masse geschikter Leute, durch die grossen Capitalien, die ihnen zu Gebote stehen, und die ungeheuer bewegende Kraft, die ihnen die <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">Steinkohlen</term> aus dem Schooss der Erde bieten, in einem gegebenen Zeitraum eine Menge hervorbringen, die der halben Welt genügt, und unter denen sie bald, troz aller Vortheile, die hier angeführt sind, in kurzer Zeit erstiken müssten, wenn sie keinen Absaz nach Aussen hätten: so liegt hier klar vor Augen, warum sie nun die <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">Handelsfreiheit</term> so dringend wünschen und durch keine <term ref="gfa-keywords-9444">Zölle</term> die Einfuhr
                    <pb n="103" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618590"/> ihrer Fabrikate beschränken möchten. — Bleiben die Zölle, so können sie nicht mehr die Fabriken des Continents, welche das <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Dekret von Napoleon</persName></term> hervorrief, und dessen Genius die wahre Grundursache des Unterschiedes der gewerblichen Zustände von dem Continent im Vergleich zu <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> so richtig erkannte, ausrotten, oder wenigstens so paralysiren, dass ihr Handels- und Gewerbsegoismus die Früchte seiner Meditationen auf Unkosten der nach und nach verarmenden und ausgesogenen Nationen fort und fort geniesst. — Das was England jezt schon so schwer, wenn auch zum Theil noch verheimlicht, drükt, das sind ihre <term ref="gfa-keywords-9443">Arbeiter-Associationen</term>. Man muss in den Fabrikstädten von England gewesen sein und diese Klasse der Gesellschaft in ihren niedrigen dunkeln Wohnungen besucht haben, und dann den ungeheuern Abstand, den der Luxus eines verhältnissmässig kleinen Theils der Nation dem Auge vorführt, dagegen vergleichen, um zu der Ansicht zu gelangen, dass nichts in der Welt ist, das nicht seinen Grund hat, und dass obige Erscheinungen in der Zeit, die möglicher Weise noch greller hervortreten oder jedenfalls noch eine Zeitlang fortdauern können, nur die aufkeimenden Wirkungen von tiefliegenden und schon lange vorhandenen Ursachen sind.</p>
                <p>Mit einem Wort, England produzirt in Folge Eingangs erwähnter und in Anwendung gebrachter Mittel zu viel. Kann es sich nicht in dieser oder jener Weise auf Unkosten anderer Völker Absaz verschaffen, so ist die unmittelbare Folge davon, dass gerade ein Theil seiner ärmsten Be<pb n="104" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618591" break="no"/>wohner, das heisst die Fabrikarbeiter, die Hände in den Schooss legen müssen und dann dem Land so sehr zur Last fallen. Bis dahin, scheint es, sind die Regierungen des Festlandes noch sehr auf ihrer Hut, der freundlichen Einladung der Engländer für den Freihandel so schnell und geneigt Gehör zu geben, als dieselben nach der Sachlage wünschen möchten. Was man in der <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Schweiz</placeName> thun wird, steht dahin; was man aber thun soll, ist bei ruhiger und uninteressirter Prüfung bald entschieden, und als Schluss möge denen, die ihr Geld so gerne an Fremde geben, Nachfolgendes, was der so geistreiche und die Regentenpflichten tief erkennende, verstorbene <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7549">König Friedrich von Würtemberg</persName> gegen mich äusserte, als ich im <date from="1814-06-01" to="1814-08-07">Sommer 1814</date> während meines Aufenthalts in <placeName ref="gfa-places-143">Stuttgart</placeName> zu ihm auf sein <placeName ref="gfa-places-1683">Lustschloss «Mon Repos»</placeName> bei <placeName ref="gfa-places-1180">Ludwigsburg</placeName> berufen wurde, in einem über mancherlei Gegenstände bei zwei Stunden dauernden Gespräch, bezüglich auf die Fabrikation und den Verbrauch verschiedener Artikel im eigenen Lande, oder deren wohlfeileren Bezug aus der Fremde. Er sagte nemlich (und es ist wörtlich, ich zeichnete es sogleich in mein Tagebuch auf), als die Rede von <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">Gewehren</term> war: «Man taxirt mich, dass ich in meiner <placeName ref="gfa-places-1684">Fabrik</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1685">Oberndorf</placeName> Gewehre für mein Militär machen lasse, wovon mich das Stük auf 6 neue <term ref="gfa-keywords-8409">Thaler</term> zu stehen kommt, während ich dieselben von <placeName ref="gfa-places-1311">Lüttich</placeName> oder <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> um einen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8411">Louis d’or</term> bekommen könnte; allein ein Monarch oder eine Regierung kann nicht rechnen wie ein Partikular. Es ist zwar auch für selbige gut, wenn etwas erspart werden kann;
                    <pb n="105" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618592"/> wenn ich aber einen Louis d’or nach England bezahle, so ist er auf ewig verloren. Gebe ich aber 6 Thaler für ein Gewehr, das im eigenen Lande verfertigt wird, so kommen wieder 3 in meinen Beutel,» wobei er mit der Hand auf die Westentasche klopfte.</p>
                    <p>Es wäre noch manches übrig zu sagen, das sich mehr auf Partikularitäten bezieht, allein auch dieses Wenige mag hier als die Kehrseite von demjenigen gelten, was die Freunde der <term ref="gfa-keywords-9052">Handelsfreiheit</term> dem Publikum zur Schau vorführen, und darauf antragen, was in der Schweiz geschehen sollte. Aber ich glaube, dass wir als einer der kleinsten und jüngsten Staaten, denn erst durch den Bund sind wir, nach der neuen einheitlichen Theorie, einer geworden<note>Mit der Annahme der neuen Bundesverfassung von 1848 wurde die Schweiz vom Staatenbund zum Bundesstaat geeint.</note>, warten sollten, was grosse festgestellte Regierungen in den besprochenen Beziehungen thun werden, und uns lieber mit unsern nächsten Nachbarn in besseres Einverständniss sezen, von denen wir jedenfalls vortheilhaftere Erwiederungen zu erwarten hätten, weil das Bedürfniss von Verkehr gegenseitig ist, als von einem entfernten Land dessen <term ref="gfa-keywords-9169">Handelspolitik</term> am Ende nur von sich und seinem Vortheil ausgeht, und auch wiederum dahin sich concentrirt.</p>
                    <p>Der zweite Gegenstand, über den ich noch etwas zu sagen habe, betrifft das diesen Notizen <ref type="cross" target="TB7_p_107">beigefügte lithographische Blatt</ref>. Ich betrachtete es nämlich als ein überflüssiges Geschäft, die Dimensionen des <placeName ref="gfa-places-1701">Glaspalastes</placeName>, wenn schon derselbige Hauptveranlassung meiner Reise war, zu beschreiben, nicht nur weil solches viel früher in einer Menge Zeitungen etc. geschehen,
                        <pb n="106" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618593"/> sondern weil ich überzeugt war, dass nur eine blosse Angabe von Länge und Breite dieses Wundergebäudes, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">Fussen</term> oder <term ref="gfa-keywords-8493">Klaftern</term>, schwerlich jemand eine bestimmte Idee von dessen Umfang oder Grösse geben könne, wenn nicht eine Art von Versinnlichung damit zu verbinden seyn möchte, und so kam ich auf den Gedanken, der mir gleich bei seinem Entstehen viel Vergnügen machte, wenn anstatt dieser Angabe, wie durch einen Zauber, der Cristallpalast über <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> hergestellt würde, ich den Grundriss dessselben, auf den gleichen Masstab reduzirt, auf den Plan der Stadt hinlegte, damit man sehe, wie viele Strassen und öffentliche Pläze er in Länge und Breite überdeken würde, es zwekdienlich seyn möchte, um Besagtes einigermassen<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> zu erreichen. Durch die Güte von Herrn <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-7550">Strasseninspector Peyer</persName> erhielt ich den verkleinerten Plan von <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">unserer Stadt</placeName>, den sein verdienstvoller und hochachtungswerther seliger Hr. <persName type="actor" ref="gfa-actors-1127">Vater</persName> mit so vielem Fleiss aufgenommen hatte.</p>
                <p>Diesem Plan passte ich, wie gesagt, den Grundriss des Ausstellungsgebäudes an, und bemerke nur noch für diejenigen, die etwa keine Beschreibung dieses Gebäudes gelesen haben, dass er in seine Länge, die 1851 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">englische Fuss</term> beträgt, gerade vom <placeName ref="gfa-places-1686">Schwabenthor</placeName> bis an den <placeName ref="gfa-places-272">Rhein</placeName> hinunter reichen, und es in seiner<note>Errata aus <ref target="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618594">Erstdruck</ref>.</note> Breite von 408 Fuss mehrere unserer Hauptstrassen, Pläze und Kirchen überdeken würde. Möge die Ausführung dieser Idee, wenn auch unvollkommen, wohl aufgenommen werden.</p>
                <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Der Verfasser</persName>.
                    <lb/>
                <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName>, den <date when="1852-12-21">21. Christmonat 1852</date>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="annex" xml:id="TB7_p_107">
                <pb n="107" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618595"/>
                <head>Anhang: Grundrisse des Crystal Palace und der Stadt Schaffhausen</head>
                <figure xml:id="fig2">
                    <graphic url="images/JCF1851_2_Palastskizze.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <pb n="108" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618596"/><lb/>
                <figure xml:id="fig3">
                    <graphic url="images/JCF1851_3_Stadtplan1.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <pb n="109" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16618597"/><lb/>
                <figure xml:id="fig4">
                    <graphic url="images/JCF1851_4_Stadtplan2.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>