<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" n="2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Traveljournal 1814</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main"><pb facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557503"/> Diary of a Journey undertaken in 1814 via Paris to London and various factory towns in England, with particular attention to technological aspects.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <lb/>
            <byline>By <docAuthor>Johann Conrad Fischer</docAuthor>, Lieutenant Colonel of Artillery.</byline>
            <lb/>
            <docImprint>Arau <docDate>1816</docDate>. Heinrich Remigius Sauerländer.</docImprint>
           </titlePage>
         <div type="content">
            <head>Title page</head>
            <p><pb facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557503"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9838">[title page of the first edition]</term></p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>Fischer’s interest in technical progress</head>
            <p><pb n="1" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557507"/> Foreword.</p>
            <p>Not a year and a half ago, I resolved to take a journey via <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and various factory towns in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, in order, insofar as the limitations of my time permitted, to become acquainted firsthand with the progress that has been made in iron and steel production over the last twenty years since I visited the country on my return from <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName>.</p>
            <p><pb n="2" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557508"/> Particularly favourable circumstances gave my observations a greater scope and significance than I myself believed at the outset.</p>
            <p>Given the diversity of things I experienced there, I thought it better not to entrust everything to memory but to record all that I saw each day in writing and, so, this travel diary came into being, which I wrote in language unadorned and intended only for myself. After all, my intentions on this journey were strictly my own and for no other purpose.</p>
            <p>After my return, however, a number of my friends were keen to learn of what I had seen on <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">the island</placeName> and, so, to comply with their wishes, I was obliged to circulate my diary both here and abroad. It was only
               <pb n="3" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557509"/> recently that it was returned to my possession, with the request from many that its contents, which proved not uninteresting, be made more generally known in print.</p>
            <p>Although it is quite different to write only for oneself or one’s friends, on whose indulgence one can rely, than for an audience that is entitled to stricter demands, in which respect some things would have required a more careful selection or more complete elaboration, I nevertheless prefer to leave it as it was from the beginning, with the wish that it may also be received favourably in this form. Lastly, I would like to add that, <pb n="4" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557510"/> as extraordinary as the description of one or the other object may be, especially regarding the size and extent of various manufactories, everything is based on fact, on what I saw or heard while there. I have included the exceptional things in these pages all the more gladly, so that they may serve as example and encouragement to myself of how far diligence and perseverance can take one, even in initially small enterprises.</p> 
            <p><persName ref="gfa-actors-35">The author</persName>.</p> 
            <p><placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName>, <date when="1816-01-28">28. January 1816.</date><note>The Journal was published in 1816 by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7458">Heinrich Remigius Sauerländer</persName> in Aarau.</note></p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Schaffhausen–Basel, 7 August 1814</head>
            <p><pb n="5" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557511"/> On Sunday, <date when="1814-08-07">August 7th</date>, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-07" n="1">here</placeName> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-10" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-07" n="2">Basel</placeName> in the company of my young friend <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484">Ringk von Wildenberg</persName>, who, coming from <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>, also intended to travel to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, in order to continue the <date when="1814-08-08">following day</date> with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">courier</term> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1583">Belfort</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>. However, the route had not yet been re-established since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9831">peace</term>, so we were forced to take the detour via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1584">Colmar</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1154">Nancy</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Basel–Paris, 8–14 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the evening of the <date when="1814-08-08">8th</date>, we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1584" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-08" n="6">Colmar</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1585" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-08" n="4">Hüningen</placeName><note>A year later the fortress was stormed and razed to the ground by the Austrian army led by Archduke <persName ref="gfa-actors-5937">Johann of Austria</persName>. Johann Conrad Fischer maintained regular correspondence with the Archduke.</note> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1586" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-08" n="5">Mühlhausen</placeName>, without, to my surprise, being asked for our <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passports</term> at the border, and on the morning of the <date when="1814-08-09">9th</date>, after passing through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1587" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-09" n="7">Schlettstadt</placeName> during the night, we arrived in the <pb n="6" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557512"/> commercial town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1588" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-09" n="8">Sainte-Marie-aux-Mines</placeName>, at the foot of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2072">Vosges</placeName>.</p>
            <p>It was strange to me to hear from the local people that this vital <term ref="gfa-keywords-9353"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2222">mountain pass</placeName></term> had never been occupied by the French in <date when="1813">1813</date> and that the first resistance had only taken place on the other side of the mountains at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1589">St. Dié or St. Diez</placeName>. In the night of the 9th, or rather in the morning of the <date when="1814-08-10T02:00:00-01:00">10th at two o’clock</date>, we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1154" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-10T02:00:00-01:00" n="9">Nancy</placeName>, where we had the pleasure of first having to arrange lodging, as the place where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> stopped, having reached its destination, did not accept foreigners.</p>
            <p>After hearing in the morning that seats in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">stagecoach</term> from Nancy to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> would not be available for another two days, and then not with certainty, we decided, together with two <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8277">French officers</orgName> and a <pb n="7" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557513"/> serviceman who had served under <persName ref="gfa-actors-7485">Davoust</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-497">Hamburg</placeName>, to hire a private coach, whose owner promised, and committed himself in writing, to deliver us to Paris by the afternoon of the <date when="1814-08-14">14th</date> (with the same horses, of course). On the evening of the <date when="1814-08-10T16:00:00-01:00">10th at four o’clock</date>, we left <placeName ref="gfa-places-1154" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-10T16:00:00-01:00" n="10">Nancy</placeName>, and in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1590" type="itinerar" n="11">Toul</placeName> something happened, which we had already foreseen, namely that one of our horses had broken down and had to be left behind.</p>
            <p>The coachman, a German, drank himself into a stupor out of vexation over it and continued by night and fog <placeName ref="gfa-places-1590" type="itinerar" n="12">out of the gate</placeName>. Seeing him in this state, I feared he might topple over and, so, joined him in the driver’s box to avert the danger. He remarked to me, however, that I may remain calm, as God never forsakes a German, that he had been in this ..... country for twelve years and had always managed to get along quite well, except that <pb n="8" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557514"/> two years ago his wife, a Parisian woman, had taken the eight hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> he had saved and run off with his two horses and her lover, so that now he was obliged again to work in the service of others for wages, whereas before he had been his own master. I admired his philosophical equanimity, but, nevertheless, expressed some doubt that, judging by the condition of the horses, we would be in Paris on the <date when="1814-08-14">14th</date> as his master had promised. He assured me, however, that it would most certainly be done, and, indeed, we arrived at the preappointed stages on the <date when="1814-08-12">12th</date> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1591" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-12" n="13">Epernay</placeName> and on the <date when="1814-08-13">13th</date> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1592" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-13" n="14">La-Ferté</placeName>, albeit, not without leaving a horse behind at each night’s quarters. In Epernay, we saw ample traces of those events wherein German strength conquered French arrogance and where the first generals became the first heroes.</p>
         </div>        
         <div type="day">
            <head>Arrival in Paris, 14 August 1814</head>
            <p><pb n="9" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557515"/> Early in the morning of the <date when="1814-08-14">14th</date>, while driving, our driver suddenly sprang from the box shouting, <emph rend="italic">Arrête, femme!</emph>, to run after a woman holding a handkerchief in front of her face, abandoning us to our fate and the horses to their will. The horses, however, were not at all inclined to take to their heels, and so we were able to watch at our leisure as our coachman caught up with the fugitive about four hundred paces behind the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">carriage</term>, brought her back after some lively gesticulations, half voluntarily, half under duress, and introduced her to us as his runaway wife. He placed her next to him in the driver’s box with immense satisfaction. She, however, did not appear to take nearly as much pleasure in this game of chance and, probably out of delicate shyness, covered her face entirely with her husband’s cloak, <pb n="10" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557516"/> as we did, in fact, enter <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-14T15:00:00-01:00" n="16">Paris</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-14T15:00:00-01:00">three o’clock that afternoon</date>. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484">Ringk</persName> and I were happy to take leave of our present traveling party, from whom we had heard nothing but praise – first in verse, then in prose – for <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">their former lord and master, who now resided on Elba</persName>. Incidentally, I took an interest in the fate of a <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8277">French officer</orgName> who we met along the way, carrying his haversack, and to whom we offered a seat in the carriage as a courtesy. According to his discharge papers, he was thirty-six years old, had thirty-two years of service (campaigns count double) and nine wounds. He had done tours of duty in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-138">Spain</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-127">Russia</placeName> and, despite all that, remained a second lieutenant. Not an educated man, but a very good soldier apparently. He complained bitterly that others had been given preferential treatment and that <pb n="11" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557517"/> he had been undeservedly disadvantaged. — I took up quarters at the Hôtel des Ambassadeurs, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1593" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-14" n="17">rue Helvetius</placeName>, with which I was already familiar, and as the evening was fine, I took another walk through the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1594" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-14" n="18">Palais-Royal</placeName> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1595" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-14" n="19">Tuileries</placeName>. </p>
         </div>        
         <div type="day">
            <head>The Vendôme Column and a visit to the theatre, 15 August 1814</head>
            <p>On <date when="1814-08-15">August 15th</date>, on account of the Feast of the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary, no one in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> was available for business, and the shops were closed. Nevertheless, in the morning I visited <persName ref="gfa-actors-7662" type="met">Häring</persName>, an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9755">optician</term> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1594" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-15" n="20">Palais-Royal</placeName>, where I tested an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8431"><term ref="gfa-keywords-7442">achromatic telescope</term></term> on the battlements of his house and inspected his machine for drawing the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9306">brass</term> or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">plated-copper</term> extension pipes for the tubes (when soldered together) round and straight over steel cylinders through corresponding rings, a process that facilitates the assembly of optical instruments greatly by ensuring that the axes fall into one another properly, thus, improving the concentricity of the glasses. <pb n="12" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557518"/> The machine is simple and effective, and the cylinders move vertically instead of horizontally through the rings to save space in the narrow room. The mechanism is the same as a winch, except that it is fitted with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8956">flywheel</term> (which moves too slowly to be of use). A chain, connected to the hook of the winch and passing over the rollers, pulls the cylinders through with the tubes placed over them.</p>
            <p>After taking down some useful addresses from Mr. Häring’s address book and buying a map and description of Paris, I set out to visit the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1596" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-15" n="21">museum</placeName>. In the eleven years since I had last seen it, it had grown considerably, especially regarding the number of magnificent statues. <pb n="13" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557519"/> I estimated the number of visitors at a minimum of two thousand, yet there was no crowding in the least. There were especially many English visitors. It gave me pleasure to hear again the sound of a language that I have missed for some twenty years and that I hold in high esteem for its richness and enthusiasm. After a dreadful and expensive lunch at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1594" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-15" n="22">Palais-Royal</placeName>, I climbed to the top of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8432">memorial column</term> on <placeName ref="gfa-places-1597" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-15" n="23">Place Vendôme</placeName> erected by <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon</persName> in honour of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8277">great army</orgName> for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8433">campaign of 1805</term> and cast from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8642">metal</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8435">captured cannons</term></term>. Its height, including the pedestal and without the twenty-two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high statue of the emperor, which has now been taken down, is still one hundred and eleven Parisian <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, and its weight forty thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>. Two hundred and seventy-six bas-reliefs provide a visual chronology of this three-month campaign, beginning with the departure from the camp at Boulogne and ending with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8435">Battle of Austerlitz</term>. <pb n="14" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557520"/></p>
            <p>A lapidary-style Latin inscription above the metal door reads: <emph rend="italic">The exalted Emperor Napoleon dedicated this column to the glory of the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8277">great army</orgName>. It was made of the metal he seized during the German war, which ended under his leadership within <date to="1805-12-26" from="1805-09-25">three months in 1805</date></emph>.</p>
            <p>Within the column, one hundred and seventy steps lead to its capital, which is surrounded by a metal gallery. A brief inscription on the dome (calotte), or cylindrical dome, with a paraboloid roof cast in a single piece, which was once the base of Napoleon’s statue, states that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7626">Denon</persName> (famous for <placeName ref="gfa-places-3"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9832">his work about Egypt</term></placeName>) had supervised its construction, based <pb n="15" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557521"/> on the drawings of the architect <persName ref="gfa-actors-7627">Lepere</persName>.</p> 
            <p>This <term ref="gfa-keywords-8432">work</term>, which has few equals in its purity of taste and none in its art, was begun in <date when="1807-08">August 1807</date> and completed in <date when="1810-08">August of 1810</date>.</p>
            <p>Not until nightfall did I descend from this remarkable monument to make my way to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9790"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1598" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-15" n="24">Théatre des Variétés</placeName></term> to see <persName ref="gfa-actors-7487">Brunet</persName>, who was famous and popular with the Parisian public for his calembours and witty opinions. The three pieces performed there were of little importance, and the one entitled Le Cocq was modelled entirely after <persName ref="gfa-actors-7625">Schubart’s</persName> <persName ref="gfa-actors-8274">German Michel</persName>. The actors’ costumes, judging from the available <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">copperplates</term>, were quite similar to those of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7488">Moliere’s</persName> time. It was congruous with the coachmen and their oversized bagwigs, as well as <pb n="16" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557522"/> the officers in shoes and stockings, which one frequently sees nowadays, for, as it would seem, in order to please the court, everything old is once again en vogue.</p>
         </div>       
         <div type="day">
            <head>An outing to Chaillot, 16 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-08-16">16th</date>, I went <persName ref="gfa-actors-7776"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2166" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-16" n="25" cert="0">to Mr. Belon</placeName></persName> to present my letter of credit, and then <persName ref="gfa-actors-7489"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2165" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-16" n="26" cert="0">to Mr. Le Page</placeName></persName>, the most famous <term ref="gfa-keywords-9793">gunsmith</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>, to show him some drilled Stutzer and pistol barrels made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, for which he immediately placed an order. He showed me his splendid stock of weapons, among them a large number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9367">pistols</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">his newly developed locks</term>, which are fired without the use of stones and powder by means of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8510">Muriatique oxigénée</term>, which explodes at the mere strike of the hammer. In the depot of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9606"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1599">Versailles arms factory</placeName></term>, I was referred to the director of the manufactory, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7490">Bouty</persName>, at <placeName ref="gfa-places-2070">Versailles</placeName> itself.</p>
            <p>Since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9831">peace</term>, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8255">ser<pb n="17" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557523" break="no"/>vice</orgName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> has been restored, leaving daily at noon or in the evening at eight o’clock, so that one can reach London in four days, at the most, for the sum of one hundred and ten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term>, including the cost of passage across the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">channel</placeName>. After arranging to travel on the <date when="1814-08-18">18th</date>, I left for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1600" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-16" n="28">Chaillot</placeName> after lunch to show <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">my traveling companion</persName> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8520"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1766" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-16" n="29">steam engine</placeName></term> there and the splendid <term ref="gfa-keywords-1405"><placeName type="itinerar" ref="gfa-places-2160" when="1814-08-19" n="30" cert="0">iron foundry</placeName></term> of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7492">Perrier</persName>, whom I already knew personally.</p>
            <p>He was not at home. However, I learned from the secretary that, since the peace, here, as everywhere else, things were going badly for the manufactories.</p>
            <p>The twisting of a long, thin, cylindrical iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rod</term>  between wooden lunettes and wedges inserted between the wooden base <pb n="18" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557524"/> and the use of crochet gave me several good ideas for handling such objects, though the fixing of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3050">moulding sand</term> in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">six-foot-long</term> bottle by means of iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8734">agraffes</term> seemed peculiar to me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Making the acquaintance of Philippe Gengembre, 17 August 1814</head>
            <p>Those who must have their <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passports</term> inspected in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> and who are not keen to travel are condemned to a great deal more walking than is customary. Such was my fate on the <date when="1814-08-17">17th</date>, since <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484">Ringk</persName> had gone out before we had received our passports back from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1604" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="31">police</placeName> for further inspection at the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8301"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2125" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="33">Swiss Embassy</placeName></persName> and the Minister of the Interior, where one had to pay ten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term> for each individual signature, which amounted to almost three and a half hours of walking. After finishing a transaction with a bookseller on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1601" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="34">Quai Voltaire</placeName>, I decided spontaneously to go to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1602" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="35">mint</placeName> to make the per<pb n="19" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557525" break="no"/>sonal acquaintance of the director, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7624">Gingembre</persName>. He received me somewhat coldly at first, having taken me for a traveling salesman peddling my wares. However, I immediately made it clear to him that this was not at all the case, and that I wished to make his acquaintance in a scientific matter, as he had written to me in this regard a few years hence<note>Probably in connection with the competition launched by the “Société d’Encouragement pour l’industrie nationale” in 1808-09: Fischer and Philippe Gengembre were in indirect contact when Gengembre, in his role as Inspector General of Coinage in Paris, examined the steel samples that were submitted by Fischer.</note>. He became very polite, as a result, and in the course of the conversation himself began to ask me about the price of steel and advice on how to obtain it. In the end, I was obliged to give him a piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> from a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9303">medallion</term> I had with me and a sample of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8522">yellow steel</term>, the main components of which are one part <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> and three parts steel, in which he took a particular interest. </p>
            <p>As I was leaving, he begged of me to inquire in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8521">por<pb n="20" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557526" break="no"/>table steam engines with no condenser</term>, as he was currently working on the production of such an engine. My plan to make known in England the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8523">weldable cast steel I had invented</term>, as well as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8467">thin-rolled spring steel</term></term>, with a view to selling it there, he fully approved, convinced that this weldable cast steel was the ideal material for the manufacture of tools. </p>
            <p>As I was indisposed and very tired, I limited myself to visiting a few <term ref="gfa-keywords-9102">quincaillerie</term> and taking an order from Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1594" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="37"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7662" type="met">Häring</persName></placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and concluded my day’s work with a letter <placeName ref="gfa-places-131"><persName ref="gfa-actors-1237">home</persName></placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Visit to the fire brigade and departure, 18 August 1814</head>
            <p>Having learned in passing at a station of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-1354">pompiers</term> on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1603" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-17" n="38">Quai des Orfevres</placeName> that every morning at seven o’clock they manoeuvre with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire engines</term>, <pb n="21" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557527"/> I went there, though still indisposed, on the <date when="1814-08-18">18th</date>. I had expected their equipment would be very good, but my illusions were shattered at first sight. The fire engines are old and dilapidated, and the good discipline and skill of the firefighters, as well as their number (there are forty stations in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>), contribute more to the speedy extinguishing of the fire than does the efficiency of their equipment, which, by design, allows no more than eight men to operate it and sprays a jet of water scarcely eighty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>. The hoses are made of leather and, as I noticed, not lubricated, and therefore bad. I promised the commanding officer (for they are organized like the military and dressed and armed as such) to send a hundred feet of hemp hose, woven without a seam, with which he was not at all familiar and about whose reason<pb n="22" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557528" break="no"/>able price he was surprised, for a trial when I returned <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName>. The fire engine, which used to follow the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">emperor</persName> on his journeys and was operated by soldiers of the guard, was in the same warehouse. It differed from the others only in novelty and in the arrangement of the carriage, which, excluding the space for the pump, which could be loaded and unloaded, still had four seats for the operators. After another trip to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1604" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-18" n="40" cert="0">police station</placeName> for my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passport</term> and a terrible lunch near the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8255"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1770" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-18" n="41">Bureau des Messageries</placeName></orgName>, we left <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-18T13:00:00-01:00" n="42">Paris</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-18T13:00:00-01:00">one o’clock</date> in the afternoon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Paris–Dover, 18–21 August 1814</head>
            <p>Neither our traveling party (which consisted of an ignorant <placeName ref="gfa-places-1019">Scotsman</placeName>, a former sergeant in English service from <placeName ref="gfa-places-60">Hanover</placeName>, a merchant from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607">Calais</placeName>, and a woman from <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>), nor <pb n="23" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557529"/> nor the villages we passed through warrant much mention. I noticed a striking uncleanliness and poor appearance in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1605">Amiens</placeName>, in contrast to which <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne-sur-mer</placeName> stood out quite favourably, be it on account of its proximity to <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and the intercourse with that island or the fact that, in general, the seaside towns of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2021">North Sea</placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">canal</placeName> tend to be considerably cleaner.</p>
            <p>Having travelled day and night, we arrived at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1605" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-19" n="43">Amiens</placeName> on the <date when="1814-08-19">19th</date> in the morning, at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-20" n="44">Boulogne</placeName> on the <date when="1814-08-20">20th</date>, and by <date when="1814-08-20T10:00:00-01:00">ten o’clock that same morning</date> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-20T10:00:00-01:00" n="46">Calais</placeName>, near which, in the little village of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1767" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-20" n="45">Huit-mille</placeName> (so I was told the orthography of that name), was located the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8524">stone tomb</term> of the ill-fated <term ref="gfa-keywords-9791">aviator</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7496">Pilatre du Rozier</persName> and his companions not far from the road where they crashed.</p>
            <p>Despite all earlier inconveniences with our <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passports</term>, we were still made <pb n="24" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557530"/> to pay three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs and fifty centimes</term> in Calais for permission to embark. The embarkation itself took place in the <date when="1814-08-20T15:00:00-01:00">afternoon at three o’clock</date> on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9747">parcel ship</term> Espérance, Capitain Benoit. There must have been some fifty passengers aboard, many of them women. The wind was quite unfavourable, becoming fierce towards evening, and the sea was very rough. This and the frequent tacking of the sails, which caused the ship to sway in the opposite direction, soon caused a generalized <term ref="gfa-keywords-9450">seasickness</term>. Revulsion soon aroused it in me, as well. I lay down on the deck, lamentably covered (because of the rain) with a piece of wet sailcloth that my unfortunate companions snatched from me from time to time, and I did not get up again until we disembarked in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-21T03:00:00-01:00" n="48">Dower</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-21T03:00:00-01:00">three o’clock on the morning of the 21st</date>, after a twelve-hour crossing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Dover–London, 21–22 August 1814</head>
            <p><pb n="25" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557531"/> And so, on <date when="1814-08-21">August 21st</date>, after twenty long years, I set foot once again on <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English soil</placeName>! This time, too, under auspicious circumstances: “Hope” was the name of the ship that brought me there and “blessed one” (Benoit) the name of its captain. — My most urgent business, upon entering the “<placeName ref="gfa-places-1609" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-21" n="49">Paris-Hotel</placeName>” (English name of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>), was to refresh myself again with an English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term>, which was to be followed by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, so that I might sleep soundly, something that these two medicines accomplished perfectly. As the journey was to continue to London on the afternoon of Sunday, <date when="1814-06-21">the 21st</date>, the suitcases had to be inspected first. This presented some degree of difficulty, as one does not gladly conduct business on a Sunday in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. However, this was nothing that a payment of four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9301">customs officer</term> <pb n="26" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557532"/> could not resolve, and at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-21T17:00:00" n="50"><date when="1814-08-21T17:00:00">five o’clock in the evening</date></placeName> we departed for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-22T05:00:00" n="53">London</placeName> via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1610" type="itinerar" n="51">Canterbury</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1319" type="itinerar" n="52">Rochester</placeName> in a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">stagecoach</term>, whose elegance and design would not have disgraced any emissary and arrived at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1726" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-22T05:00:00" n="54">Woodstreet</placeName>-<placeName ref="gfa-places-1611" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-22T05:00:00" n="55">Cheapside</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-22T05:00:00">five o’clock on the morning of the 22nd</date>. We had covered this distance of seventy-two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> in ten hours, stopping for a full two hours at various places along the way. One must behold the beauty and speed of the horses to fully appreciate it (sixty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8536">guineas</term> and above is the going rate for each of them), but even more so the splendour of the countryside and the towns and villages from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> to London. Such a vision of wealth and prosperity is not to be found anywhere else, and it is no wonder that the French were en<pb n="27" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557533" break="no"/>vious of it, for the disparity between this and that country is, indeed, striking.</p>
            <p>The careful, garden-like arrangement of the most extensive <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hop fields</term> and the splendid <term ref="gfa-keywords-9531">sheep farms</term>, where the health and comfort of these animals is assured in every way, demonstrate the amount of attention paid by the English to everything that can bring about the improvement and perfection of anything. Despite my twenty-year absence, I managed to find my way around London. I cannot say that much has improved, and I noticed just as little progress regarding products and stores. Only everything has become tremendously expensive, and some things, including the basic necessities of life, have risen by twenty to fifty percent. I have not yet been able to ascertain the actual reason for this increase. <pb n="28" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557534"/> Perhaps nobody was willing to tell me. However, the effect of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">Napoleonic interdict</term> may have contributed indirectly, and the total disappearance of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9326"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9108">gold</term></term>, which was once so common, and which has now been replaced only by <term ref="gfa-keywords-9826"><term ref="gfa-keywords-5503">paper</term></term>, may also have contributed more directly. The pressure of the times on trade and manufacturing has also been felt strongly by the English, by their own admission, though they now hope the situation will soon improve.</p>
            <p>Having nothing more pressing to do than to make my introductions and renew my acquaintance with Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1800" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-22" n="56"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Y. B.</persName></placeName> Banker of London, I had the opportunity to explore London and discover stores where I might buy a few things. With a visit, which we received late in the evening from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7498" type="met">Schenk</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1803" when="1814-08-22" n="58" cert="0">our apartment</placeName>, and the dis<pb n="29" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557535" break="no"/>patch of a letter <persName ref="gfa-actors-1237"><placeName ref="gfa-places-131">home</placeName></persName>, this day came to a close, in which I had learned a number of things I had wished to know, among which I especially count the prices of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, postage-paid from London at 1 shilling to 1 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>, and the circumstance that, in the whole of England, there are supposed to be no more than three <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">cast steel manufacturers</term><note>The English cast steel producers known to the three Fischers were <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">Huntsman</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1806">Attercliffe</placeName>, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706">Walker &amp; Booth</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786">Rotherham</placeName> und <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8298">P. et C.</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>.</note> and that the production of steel continues to be treated as a secret. I also had the opportunity to become acquainted with the extremely useful, and for the innkeepers immensely beneficial, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8525">device for pumping beverages</term> out of the cellar at a single push of a button and filling the glass directly, and to make a sketch of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>The British Museum, pencils and Shakespeare, 23 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-08-23">23rd</date>, after visiting several stores, I had a long and interesting conversation with a highly reputed  <pb n="30" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557536"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9793">gunsmith</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7683" type="met">Morris</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1612" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="59">Ludgate-Hill</placeName>, during which he firmly maintained, from his own experience regarding the characteristics of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">rifled barrel</term>, that the most accurate shot is always obtained by machining the entire length of the barrel. He completely rejected the new method of firing with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8510">Muriatique oxigénée</term>, for, as he said, the corrosive properties of this <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">powder</term> also damage the inside of the barrel, rendering it unusable in a short time. He sells very strong and fine gunpowder that is neither uniformly large nor round. I arranged with him to test it against the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8526">powder from Bern</term> I had brought with me to England. For he would not yield in his belief that the perfect roundness and uniformity of the grains contributed anything to its quality. On the contrary, he held that the powder containing angular and pointed grains <pb n="31" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557537"/> ignited more quickly everywhere due to the multiple points of contact. This rather far-fetched reasoning, I thought, only stands to show that there is something to be said for everything.</p>
            <p>From Mr. Morris, I proceeded with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484" type="met">Ringk</persName> to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1613" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="60">British Museum</placeName> to visit Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7499" type="met">Planta</persName>, whom I was fortunate enough to find there, as he customarily spends his summers in the country. I informed him of Professor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7685">Müller’s</persName> letter to me and inquired about <persName ref="gfa-actors-7684">Boone</persName>. He was unable to give me any news of him but promised to make inquiries. He took the liveliest interest in the fate of the noble <persName ref="gfa-actors-7500">Johannes von Müller</persName>, who now lives on in his <term ref="gfa-keywords-8430">writings</term>, and remarked that his history of the world would soon be translated into English.</p>
            <p>Mr. Planta was kind enough to open <pb n="32" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557538"/> the museum at my request. However, space does not permit me to give even the briefest of accounts of it here. I only note that it has taken on a completely altered and far more advantageous design in the last twenty years. Many older objects have been altogether removed, and everything has been better and more systematically arranged. An exquisite <term ref="gfa-keywords-9767">mineral cabinet</term> of mainly selected specimens, with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7501">Hauy’s</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7502">Werner’s</persName> classifications, has been added, and what is available of antique busts, bas-reliefs and figures has been displayed in beautiful galleries. The greatest curiosities in antiquarian terms are undoubtedly the artefacts excavated and found in <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName> and then in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1771">Herculaneum</placeName>, among which the celebrated <persName ref="gfa-actors-7867"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8527">Isis tablet</term></persName> most captivated my attention. It is, as far as I know, the only existing monument on which the same object is described in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9178">hieroglyphics</term>, as well as the Coptic and Greek languages.</p>
            <p><pb n="33" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557539"/> After leaving the museum, I visited the best-known <term ref="gfa-keywords-8848"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2164" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="62">pencil manufactory</placeName></term> in London, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7686">Brokman et Langdon</orgName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1772">Great-Russel-Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1801">Bloomsbury-Square</placeName>, after having previously made the acquaintance of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7687">J. Middleton et Comp.</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1493" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="61">Shoe-Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2026">Fleet-Street</placeName><note>The 1814 edition of the Post Office Annual Directory for London states the address as <placeName ref="gfa-places-1777">Vine Street, Piccadilly</placeName>.</note>, whose work is somewhat more refined. As I had the opportunity to watch the production of pencils in both places, I was convinced that their excellent quality depends solely on the attributes of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8471">mineral</term>, which can only be found in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1773">Cornwallis</placeName> and is carefully selected for its greater or lesser hardness.</p>
            <p>A journey of several <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> brought me to Messrs. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1775" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="63"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7688">Bouvie et Antrobus</orgName></placeName>, and from there to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7689">Huber</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1774" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23" n="64">Green-Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1802">Grosvenor-Square</placeName>, whom I should have liked to see before his departure. The hope of welcoming him and his honourable wife in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland </placeName> <pb n="34" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557540"/> diminished to some extent the uneasy feeling of having to do without the company of this gentleman, who could have been so interesting and advantageous to me during my stay in England.</p>
            <p>At <date when="1814-08-23T18:00:00">six o’clock in the evening</date> I found myself at the home of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539" type="met">Yeates Brown</persName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1776">Manchester-Street</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1800" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-23T18:00:00" n="65">Manchester-Square</placeName>, following the invitation I had accepted to dine with him. I was received by him and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7690" type="met">his wife</persName> with the friendship that is accorded to close acquaintances in England, an affection of which I was to receive further confirmation. The splendour prevailing in the house gave clear indication of the wealth of its owner. The sitting room contained a type of low sofa, in addition to the armchairs, in oriental style, all of them covered with precious embroidered <term ref="gfa-keywords-9553">taffeta</term>, and all the furnishings were of the most exquisite, flamed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8774">acajou</term>, or “Mahogany”.</p>
            <p><pb n="35" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557541"/> The bay window facing the garden featured gothic windows adorned with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9126">stained glass</term>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9105">crystal</term> tableware were equally as precious as the rest, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wines</term> even more so. Among them, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9289">Madeira</term> was especially exquisite.</p>
            <p>After the meal and during the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, which took place at about <date when="1814-08-23T22:00:00">ten o’clock</date>, Mr. Brown showed me several splendid works from his precious <term ref="gfa-keywords-1883">library</term>. As a rarity, he owned a copy of the famous “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8528"><emph rend="italic">One hundred merry tales of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7950">Shakespeare</persName></emph></term>”, which had been lost and recently rediscovered by chance. Owing to the peculiarities inherent in the English, only fifty copies of it had ever been printed. While leafing through the book, it struck me that I recognized at once the first three or four tales, and I remembered having read them as a boy <pb n="36" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557542"/> in a very old German book, printed by a certain Hofmann, bound together with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7731"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9833">Aesop’s Fables</term></persName>, and the whole decorated with woodcuts. It would, perhaps, not be unimportant for the philologist to know whether the English or the German edition holds the right of precedence.</p>
            <p>As I was leaving, Mr. Brown was kind enough to invite me to his office for the following day, to furnish me with letters of introduction that would be useful to me on my forthcoming visit to the north of England.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Registration at the Alien Office and a programme for a rainy day, 24 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-08-24">24th</date>, my first order of business was to go to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1843"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1842"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1614" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="66" cert="0">Alien Office, Crown-Street, Westminster</placeName></placeName></placeName>, to have my <term ref="gfa-keywords-9772">passport</term> controlled. Here, as everywhere, I have noticed far more civility towards strangers than twenty years ago, especially as regards re<pb n="37" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557543" break="no"/>primands for taking the wrong or unusual way.</p>
            <p>As an extremely heavy rain, which lasted all day without interruption, prevented me from making any further excursions, I limited myself to collecting the letters of introduction from Mr. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7790"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2224" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="67">Brown et Siordet</placeName></orgName>, visited the eminent optician <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="68"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7545">Dollond</persName></placeName><note>Peter Dollond was the son of the well-known optician <persName ref="gfa-actors-298">John Dollond</persName>.</note>, the tool and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9493">steel merchant</term> <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7546" type="met">Fenn</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1615" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="69">Newgate-Street</placeName>, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cuttler</term> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7551" type="met">Stammers</persName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="70">Strand</placeName>, who makes steel dessert knives <term ref="gfa-keywords-9103">plated</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver</term> on both sides, which gives them a fine, durable edge without the blades tarnishing or rusting.</p>
            <p>As anecdote and final story of the day, I include an account of an incident concerning a young man from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1606">Boulogne-sur-mer</placeName>, who had entrusted himself to unknown persons and, <pb n="38" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557544"/> thus, within the first hours of his stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> was robbed of all his belongings down to the last <term ref="gfa-keywords-8584">coin</term>, with the exception of the clothes on his back. Since he did not understand a word of English, I was able to assist him as an interpreter to the extent that he will be able stay in one place (<placeName ref="gfa-places-1617" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-24" n="71">White-Bear, Picadilly</placeName>) until he can be provided with necessities again from home. Want of time does not permit me to tell this somewhat rambling story in its entirety, now, however, it ought to find its place elsewhere for the purpose of instruction.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Business visits in Cheapside and the Strand, 25 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-89"><date when="1814-08-25">25th</date></placeName>, assuming that I would be able to travel in the evening with one of the numerous <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">stagecoaches</term> leaving daily for <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, I conducted some minor business with <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="72"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7545" type="met">Dollond</persName></placeName>, with whom I discussed, among other things, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror</term> compositions of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7558">Short</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7557">Herschel</persName>, and <pb n="39" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557545"/> the various refractive properties of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8530">Crown</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8531">Flint</term> glasses. He was, or at least seemed to be, of the same opinion as I, that <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> substituted for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, under appropriate control of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">melting process</term>, should give the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8529">mirror</term> greater lustre and whiter colour, since, as is well known, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term> combines with iron equally as well as with copper, and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8805">arsenic</term> can be entirely omitted from the mixture.</p>
            <p>At <date when="1814-08-25T14:00:00">two o’clock in the afternoon</date>, <persName ref="gfa-actors-8104" type="met">Mr. S.</persName>, who had shown my <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484">traveling companion</persName> and me considerable friendship during our stay here, collected us from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1803" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="73" cert="0">our apartment</placeName> to lunch with him <placeName ref="gfa-places-1634" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="76">at the Queens-Arms, Cheap-side</placeName>. Before that, he was kind enough to take me to five different places from which stagecoaches depart for Birmingham, so that I might <pb n="40" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557546"/> reserve a seat; however, all the seats were already taken, and so, for two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term>, I arranged to depart on the following day at four o’clock in the evening.</p>
            <p>In passing by a crucible dealer, <persName ref="gfa-actors-7560">J. Tringham</persName> No. 3, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1669" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="65">Cary-Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1670">Foster-Lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1611">Cheapside</placeName>, into whose store I entered, it was my distinct pleasure to discern that the English black <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> corresponded perfectly in their ratio of capacity to height, width, and thickness with my own, the form of which I had ascertained to be quite different from the German. As to the price of these crucibles, I found it very high, namely two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8585">Mark</term>, or about thirty-two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> of our money for a six-mark crucible, for which we pay fifteen Kreuzer. After dinner we went to the <pb n="41" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557547"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="77">Strand</placeName> to visit Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7561">Berola</persName>, a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9593">watchmaker</term>, with whom I would have liked to make my acquaintance, but he was not at home. I gave two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razor knives</term> from <persName ref="gfa-actors-7562">Kym</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1900">Berlingen</placeName>, which he had made for me from <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474">my steel</term>, which at that time (<date when="1805">nine years ago</date>) I only made in very small quantities, to a <persName ref="gfa-actors-7551"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutler</term></persName> who lived <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="78">next door</placeName> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">sharpening</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polishing</term>, with the request that he do the work himself, so that he could give me his opinion about the quality of the knives and the steel.</p>
            <p>That same evening, I discovered an important <placeName ref="gfa-places-2163" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="79">lathe and tool factory</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1671">Cockspur-Street</placeName> No. 10, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2030">Charing-Cross</placeName>, whose owners, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7563" type="met">Holzapfel and Deyerlein</orgName>, are Germans. — Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7564" type="met">Holzapfel</persName> was very obliging. He showed me his stock of <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887">lathes</term>, the least of which cost thirty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8536">guineas</term>, and the most beautiful, with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8820">basset <pb n="42" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557548" break="no"/> tool</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8546">guilloché machine</term>, two hundred and fifty. Not only did I have the opportunity to admire the beauty of the workmanship thereon, but I also saw two entirely new devices, as simple as they are useful, for turning <term ref="gfa-keywords-8779">screw threads</term> or hollow objects with the greatest of ease, the more detailed explanation of which, however, necessitates a drawing, which I will append to my notes on this subject.<note>The drawing has not survived.</note></p>
            <p>It was still too early to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lights</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1672" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="80">Pall-Mall</placeName>. So, in advance of our visit, we passed by the large <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1673" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="81">Wedgwood tableware factory</placeName></orgName>, near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1674">St. James-Square</placeName> before returning <placeName ref="gfa-places-1803" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-25" n="82" cert="0">home</placeName>, where <persName ref="gfa-actors-8104" type="met">Mr. S.</persName> joined us for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, in the English manner, until <date when="1814-08-25T22:00:00">ten o’clock in the evening</date>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Rolled spring steel from Schaffhausen, 26 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-08-26">27th</date><note>The date was 26 August 1814.</note>, after I had already  <pb n="43" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557549" xml:id="p_43"/> made an early and futile trip to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1675" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26" n="83">Snow-Hill</placeName> to look at a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8669">home brewing apparatus</term> that was thought to be there, but which is now in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1630">Picadilly</placeName> together with its inventor, I set off to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7561"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26" n="84">Berola</placeName></persName> with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9591">rolled steel for watch springs</term></term> that I had brought with me to <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. He was very pleased with it, and after we had <placeName ref="gfa-places-1616" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26" n="85">collected</placeName> the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1900">Berlinger</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razor knives</term>, which received a very favourable review from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7551" type="met">Stammers</persName>, we proceeded to <placeName type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26" n="86">Berolas</placeName>, the watch spring maker, to show him the rolled steel as well. Like most Englishmen, he was at first sceptical of anything foreign. However, when I pointed out to him the advantages of the steel, as well as the laborious, one might even say nonsensical, way in which watch springs are made in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, namely cutting them by hand from thin, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">cast <pb n="44" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557550"/> steel wire</term></term> – the purchase price of which is six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> and eight <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> – and in such a way that each spring must be <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealed</term> six or seven times before it is thin enough, he began to think better of it until, finally, he became so interested that he promised Mr. Berola to start working on springs made of this rolled steel that same day.</p>
            <p>On the way home, I called on the watchmaker’s tool dealer, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2201"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7546" type="met">Fenn</orgName></placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1615" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26" n="87">New-gate-Street</placeName> who, quite enthusiastic about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8467"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9591">rolled steel leaves for watch springs</term></term> I showed to him, as well, confessed that there were none like them in all of England. I would add, the relatively high price of pocket watch springs is evidence of their laborious production in England, where a single spring costs almost as much as a dozen of the same quality in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1360">Locle</placeName> or <placeName ref="gfa-places-1691">Fleurier</placeName>, <pb n="45" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557551"/> i.e. half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8586">crown</term>. — As I was due at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1676" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-26T16:00:00" n="88">At the swan with two necks Inn</placeName> (that was the actual name of the place) by <date when="1814-08-26T16:00:00">four o’clock</date>, from where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">coach</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> departs, I only had enough time to have lunch and pack the most necessary things. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484" type="met">Ringk</persName> and <persName ref="gfa-actors-8104" type="met">Mr. S.</persName> were good enough to accompany me there, and I recommended <persName ref="gfa-actors-7484">my friend</persName> to the latter during my absence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>London–Birmingham, 26–27 August 1814</head>
            <p>My traveling companions in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">carriage</term> interior (the exterior or bonnet was already graced with nine passengers) included: a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8534">type founder</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9735">apothecary</term> from London, and a “Gentleman-Farmer” from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1627">York</placeName> region, who, in spite of the fine handkerchief adorning his frock coat and his <term ref="gfa-keywords-9107">silver-plated</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8535">Spanish cane walking stick</term>, would, whenever necessary, blow his nose into his fingers <pb n="46" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557552"/> in the coach, before retrieving the rest with his handkerchief. That this impropriety was perpetrated by a farmer, who by no means appeared to be a commoner, astonished me, indeed. To my even greater astonishment, however, no one reproached him for it. — As I seemed to gratify the company by engaging in their conversation, I was treated to a tale by the type founder about the ancient history of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1692" type="itinerar" n="89">St. Albans</placeName>, the town through which we were passing, that the houses had been there since the time of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7514">Julius Caesar</persName>, which age, judging by their frailty, I would not dispute.</p>
            <p>As the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">post coaches</term> travel with extraordinary speed to this part of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> (they cover eight to nine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> in an hour, but elsewhere only seven to eight and a half), we arrived quite early in <placeName ref="gfa-places-30" type="itinerar" n="90">Coventry</placeName> a not <pb n="47" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557553"/> insignificant and seemingly quite pretty city, and reached <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-27" n="91">Birmingham</placeName> on the morning of the <date when="1814-08-27">27th</date>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Birmingham’s “Altar to Vulcan”, 27 August 1814</head>
            <p>Anyone repelled by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal steam</term> and thick air of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> need not venture to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>. For the extraordinary number of <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundries</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9112">weapon</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9217">blade manufactories</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelting</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9127">glass furnaces</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9166">hammer mills</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8973">wire drawing</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8843">sheet metal factories</term>, among so many other altars to <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcan</persName>, this city, which is said to have one hundred and thirty thousand inhabitants, is enveloped in a dense cloud of smoke, lasting on average an hour, out of which only the tops of the towers and the high chimneys of the glass and smelting furnaces are visible.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon arrival, I proceeded <placeName ref="gfa-places-1740" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-27" n="92" cert="0">to Mr. H—</placeName><note>Mr. H. is possibly Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7598">Hobday</persName>.</note>, to whom I had been introduced by B — et R<note>It is not known for whom the initials stand.</note>. As he himself owns a shop <pb n="48" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557554"/> filled with the various wares of Birmingham, I was unable to learn from him the names of their actual manufacturers, and as Saturday is the day the English call “a busy day”, I promised to return on Monday. In passing, he showed me, among other precious commodities, a completely steel writing instrument costing fifty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8536">guineas</term>, of which the <persName ref="gfa-actors-8299">Queen</persName> had recently had a similar one made. — Uncertain whether I would be welcomed by Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7573"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7572"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">Boulton et Watt</orgName></persName></persName> with my letter of introduction from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Brown</persName> on this business day in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>, I resolved, nevertheless, to go there, so as not to lose any time and simply to ask when it would be convenient for me to visit. This very significant <placeName ref="gfa-places-1723" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-27" n="93" cert="0">manufactory</placeName> is located four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from Birmingham, and its owners have generated a profit of many millions of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term> for their country through their extremely sensible <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587">im<pb n="49" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557555" break="no"/>provements of the steam engine</term>. For it was from the same epoch, the seventies and eighties of the last century, that the great boom of England’s manufacturing industry dates, when Messrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7523"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7534">Boulton et Watt</persName></persName> showed how their machines could be applied with safety and ease to almost every end of human art.</p>
            <p>Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572" type="met">Watt</persName> received me very politely in the factory’s counting room, after seeing the signature on my letter of introduction. I immediately remarked to him, however, that because I understood the nature of business on Saturdays in England, I wanted only to request half an hour of his time to speak with him on another day. — “If it is convenient for you,” he said, “come and lunch with me tomorrow; <pb n="50" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557556"/> — then we can converse at leisure.” I accepted the invitation without further ado and took my leave. I must attribute this unexpected courtesy more to the signature than to the contents of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Brown’s</persName> letter of introduction; for not only were the signatures in duplicate and two distinctive hands but embellished with a special emblem. All the same, I am no more likely to see the factory than any other. For I have already been informed by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Brown</persName>: “He shows it to no one and has already refused to do so even to highly distinguished persons.” Still, a conversation with such a man is alone worth the journey from London to Birmingham.</p>
            <p>After lunch, I wandered through nearly the whole of <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-27" n="94">Birmingham</placeName> and would like to have entered ten places instead of just one, had it not <pb n="51" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557557"/> been for the commanding “Non admittance” signs posted everywhere. Through the broken windowpanes of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9606">weapons factory</term> (which, I say in passing, is disgracefully common to most factories here, that they have not a single good window) I observed the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8879">honing</term> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9114">gun barrels</term> and admired the skill and uniformity with which the worker let them revolve in his hands, as they were honed crosswise and not lengthwise. Three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> supply power to this factory for the execution of its many types of operations.</p>
            <p>I would also have liked to see the extensive <term ref="gfa-keywords-8973">wire drawing factory</term>, where <term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">iron and steel wire</term> was <term ref="gfa-keywords-633">drawn</term>; however, as with most factories, it was walled off like a monastery. Late in the evening, I chanced to see in an open English <pb n="52" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557558"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9056">refining forge</term>, what they call “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">Puddling-Furnaces</term>”, the very peculiar operation of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8537">refining</term> with flame fire. The process is already known but quite interesting, as the flame from simple <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coals</term> nevertheless yields relatively good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8539">lumps</term> of thirty to forty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> were hammered out by a very weak (since it had no counterblow) T-hammer from the family of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8540">picks</term> in three heatings to short bars, six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">lines</term> thick and four and a half lines wide. I found the method of removing the lumps from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9053">furnace</term> using a thin iron rod, which was inserted and immediately welded in place, very effective, as one does not require tongs and is more a master of the iron in this process, able to draw the lumps uniformly from back to front without having to turn or hammer them. <pb n="53" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557559"/> The hammer, weighing about six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>, was not lifted from the side by the handle, as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>, but by a cast protrusion on its head. As much as I had to acknowledge, at least in this case, the superiority of the German <term ref="gfa-keywords-9165">hammersmiths</term> in skill and strength, I also admired the sensible arrangement of the factory, which fits into the space of one of our ordinary living rooms.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>James Watt gives a tour of his plant and and an invitation to lunch, 28 August 1814</head>
            <p>Sunday, <date when="1814-08-28">August 28th</date>. A certain <term ref="gfa-keywords-9794">tribune of the people</term> of the noble town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> once was meant to make a great speech, whose title he forgot, until, at last, he exclaimed quizzically: “What matter shall I speak to, worthy and trusted fellows, what matter, now?” As no one could tell him, however, <pb n="54" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557560"/> he seized his hat and cane in exasperation and took his leave. — I find myself presently in almost the same position as this honourable gentleman in recording the events of this day, as few have had such a wealth of interesting subjects and, in view of the limited time and the importance of the matter, even I am nearly at a loss as to where to begin.</p>
            <p>At <date when="1814-08-28T14:00:00">two o’clock in the afternoon</date>, after I had spent the morning writing, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-28T15:00:00" n="98">Soho</placeName>, a good hour’s walk away. Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1724" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-28" n="99">Watt’s residence</placeName>, situated in a beautiful and very extensive park, is already distinguished by its construction and by the fact that it is entirely covered with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9426">slate</term> and built of hewn stone, while most other houses in Birmingham and other places in England are constructed of simple <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">red <pb n="55" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557562"/> bricks</term>. The interior, however, displays all the comforts of English life and attests to the wealth of its owner. A servant showed me to the sitting room, into which Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> entered immediately.</p>
            <p>As Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Brown’s</persName> letter had introduced me to him as the director of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8997">our iron mines</term></placeName>, the conversation turned immediately to this subject. Wishing to know the location of the mines and their strike, Mr. Watt produced a very beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-8542">Wyssian map</term> of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">Canton of Schaffhausen</placeName>, on which I complied satisfactorily with his request. After this, the discussion turned to the various types of iron and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>. Quite contrary to my expectations, he led me to the part of his <placeName ref="gfa-places-1723" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-28" n="100" cert="0">factory <pb n="56" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557563"/> in Soho</placeName> devoted to this matter. I was amazed at what I saw there. Any description of it would be inadequate, for it escapes the powers of imagination. I shall merely note that the sheer mass of available <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> alone is immense, not to mention the amount of work put into it. Things that have never been done before are accomplished here, and the erstwhile amorphous compilation of tubes and cylinders we call steam engines is here transformed into an elegant iron structure with columns of Doric and Corynthian order. After viewing a collection of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8989"><placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Swedish</placeName></term>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-2063">Siberian</placeName>, and <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> iron, we were joined by Mr. Watt’s associate, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7573" type="met">Boulton</persName>, for a visit to the lathe and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9439">forging workshops</term>.</p>
            <p>While admiring the exceptionally beautiful, <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">hand-forged craftsmanship</term> in the workshops, I also noticed something seemingly insignificant, but nevertheless <pb n="57" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557564" break="no"/> quite useful. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8544">caulking</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8545">grooving chisels</term> were attached to handles made of hazel rods by being bound together with wire wrapped all the way around them. As a result, there was no need to make a hole in the tool in order to insert the handle, meaning they are much more resistant to breakage and never bounce in the hand. A large stock of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8543">copy milling machines</term>, which they showed me in a storeroom next to the counting room, demonstrated again the meticulousness applied to all operations here.</p>
            <p>The conversation at the table, which, in accordance with English custom, was abundantly furnished with expensive <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wines</term>, became very lively, for they seemed to take pleasure in the fact that I spoke English fluently, which Mr. Brown also remarked in all his letters of introduction, and to which, so it ap<pb n="58" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557565" break="no"/>peared to me, they attached great importance. When the conversation turned to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8787">metal compositions</term> of the ancients, I could hardly avoid mentioning my discovery of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8522">yellow steel</term>. This seemed to be of interest to them, for when I showed them a sample of it, they immediately asked a certain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574" type="met">Murdoch</persName> to join us for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>, of whom they remarked that he had an excellent knowledge of metallurgy and had also worked on this subject for a considerable time. — The dessert, which by English standards was unusually varied, contained, among other things, splendid <term ref="gfa-keywords-9331">muscat</term> and other grape varieties with berries the size of walnuts, the price of which per cluster is never less than half, more often an entire, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8536">guinea</term>.</p>
            <p>Over tea, with which <term ref="gfa-keywords-9197">coffee</term> was served simultaneously, we conversed at length about the metal composition at hand, and Mr. Murdoch proved himself, indeed, to be a <pb n="59" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557566"/> most experienced <term ref="gfa-keywords-9312">metallurgist</term>. However, he had never succeeded in combining anything more than one part <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term> with one part <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>. At the mention of a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">iron works</term> in the vicinity, Mr. Watt said to me: “Mr. Fischer, you can take a bed for the night here, and, presuming you ride, we will visit some of the most interesting factories tomorrow, among others one that employs five thousand workers.” I accepted the invitation with pleasure but, for fear of appearing immodest, declined to spend the night in Soho. After taking my leave, whereby Mr. Watt accompanied me to the gates of the park, I departed for <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-28T11:30:00" n="101">home</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-28T21:30:00">half past nine</date>, fully preoccupied with my thoughts on how far diligence, intellect and perseverance can take a man.</p>
         </div>         
         <div type="day" xml:id="d_29_8">
            <head>Exploring the Black Country on horseback with James Watt, 29 August 1814</head>
            <p>The following day, I was already in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29T07:30:00" n="102">Soho</placeName> at <date when="1814-08-29T07:30:00">half past seven</date> in the morning, after <pb n="60" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557567" xml:id="p_60"/> having ordered <term ref="gfa-keywords-8789">alphabets</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">stamps</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7598" type="met">Hobday</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1740" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="102">Legg-Street</placeName> and covering five <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> on foot.</p>
            <p>While at breakfast, a certain Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7599" type="met">Low</persName> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1741">Trinidad</placeName> arrived, who ordered a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> of fifteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">horsepower</term>, which was to be dispatched with the October fleet. This Mr. Low spoke of the strange <placeName ref="gfa-places-1742">sea of misfortune</placeName> on Trinidad, about which I had read a more detailed account in a recently published travelogue, given to me by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>. Mr. Low left us before long, heading for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8944">steam engine manufactory</term> to make further arrangements with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574">Murdoch</persName>. — “Come,” said Mr. Watt shortly thereafter, “I am never certain that people will wish to speak to me,” and we immediately alighted on horseback, accompanied by a groom and <pb n="61" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557568"/> a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8970">Great Dane</term>. The horses were excellent runners. Mine was called “Jack”, that of Mr. Watt “John”, and the dog was called “Daniel”, after the old gardener of the house.</p>
            <p>After riding for nearly a mile, Mr. Watt stopped suddenly and said, “Where I am about to take you, no foreigner has ever gone before. I therefore implore you not to tell anyone in England, not even Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7539">Brown</persName>, about this, nor should you write letters or make recommendations to me in this regard, as it would be of no use.” — Soon thereafter, we dismounted at a large gateway, after having ridden through a long lane of charming and uniformly built houses, which were all workers’ dwellings, each with its own garden.</p>
            <p><pb n="62" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557569"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1694" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="104">This factory</placeName>, which the Grand Duchess <persName ref="gfa-actors-7600">Catherine</persName><note>The Grandduchess Catherine had visited <placeName ref="gfa-places-84">Fischer’s factory</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schaffhausen</placeName> only a few months previously in <date from="1814-01-01" to="1814-01-31">January 1814</date> with her brother Tsar <persName ref="gfa-actors-3099">Alexander I.</persName></note>, who was as intellectual as she was knowledgeable, considered sufficiently significant during her stay in England as to honour it with an official visit, and to have it shown to her in its entirety by Mr. Watt, with whom she discussed (which he noted with particular pleasure) all of its interesting objects, but especially its <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>, which are so varied in their construction and application. — This factory is located on the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1778">Birmingham Canal</placeName>, which connects to the four main ports of England, namely <placeName ref="gfa-places-1744">Hull</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1743">Portsmuth</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName>. It is surrounded by a high wall and consists of numerous buildings, each several hundred feet in length, among which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundry</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2755">prototype works</term> and <pb n="63" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557570"/> the new workshops are most remarkable. Four furnaces yield enough molten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> to make castings up to a weight of two hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term> in a single piece. Opposite these are the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9584">drying kilns</term>, and the ground between the two quite hollow to mould and cast the largest cylinders aright. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-3050">casting sand</term>, which is somewhat ferruginous and contains a great deal of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8547">mica</term>, is excavated right there on site. Indeed, the whole of Birmingham is erected on this same sand. By my estimates, the other buildings, especially the iron building — I refer to it as such for the floor, stairs and roof are made entirely of cast iron, and the floors and stairs, for that matter, are not smooth, but finely checked like carpets, painted with black paint and kept extremely clean —accommodate working steam engines ranging from six to <pb n="64" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557571"/> fifty “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8588"><emph rend="italic">Horsepowers</emph></term>”, which quietly and uniformly perform the work they were so brilliantly designed to carry out: Stamping money, rolling sheet metal, punching plated tools, moving hammers, turning enormous <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rods</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">spiral beams</term>, and boring out cylinders (a single one of which often takes several months to complete). Thus, they produce more machines of their kind, and much more. Of the dozens of “Boilers” standing around, which are made of two to three layers of thick <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">sheet iron</term> and are excellently riveted together, I noticed that instead of the usual spherical shape, they are now parallel-epipedal with a convex top. All of the workshops, as well as the large open area, are <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">illuminated by gas</term>. Mr. Watt was gracious enough to <pb n="65" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557572"/> show me this lighting system, which was introduced by Mr. Murdoch. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8549">charring</term>, or more precisely, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8549">distillation of the coal</term> takes place in two large furnaces, and in large vessels next to them, the distillation of the gas, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8833">bitumen</term>, and so on. The gas is conveyed from there into a special building with two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8550">iron tanks</term>, which stand in water and are open at the bottom and closed at the top, holding about three thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">cubic feet</term>. From there, it is conducted through pipes into all the buildings of the factory.</p>
            <p>In order to illustrate the effect, Mr. Watt closed the chamber, so that gas burned, with a shining flame and completely odourless, in the glass cylinders of four-armed lamps mounted on the lectern. It remains a secret how to remove the foul odour and the bluish light of the flame from gas. I, however, was able to learn about the procedure.</p>
            <p><pb n="66" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557573"/> From the factory, we proceeded to the neighbouring town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1746" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="105">Smethwik</placeName> to see a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8506"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1747" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="106">steam engine</placeName></term> with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">thirty-three-inch</term> cylinder, which supplies a part of the canals with essential water. From Smethwik, our tour took us to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1748" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="108">Bilston</placeName>, on the great highway to <placeName ref="gfa-places-70">Irland</placeName>, passing <placeName ref="gfa-places-1749" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="107" cert="0">Capon-Fields</placeName>, a very curious point, which is the place where the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1778">Birmingham canal system</placeName> begins. At the highest point of the whole area, near the shaft of an abandoned water-rich <term ref="gfa-keywords-6116">coal mine</term> are two steam engines with fifty-four-inch-wide cylinders, that deliver forty-eight cylindrical feet of water every minute, or double that, if necessary. These supply a large basin from which the deeper channels draw as much water as continuous use requires. The machines are built by Mr. Watt, <pb n="67" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557574"/> and, like all those that originate from him, are especially beautiful. From Capon-Fields across <placeName ref="gfa-places-1748">Bilston</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1750">Wednesbury</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1751">Dudley</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1754">Level-Iron-works</placeName> extends not exactly a valley, but a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1755">basin</placeName> some ten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">English miles</term> long and four, at times six miles wide, quite unique in its kind.</p>
            <p>The land, which is on its surface very barren, but which in its bowels contains an immeasurable wealth of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9199">limestone</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9027"><term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ore</term></term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term>, is littered with buildings, particularly <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9127">glass furnaces</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9454">soap boilers</term>, etc., such that more than five hundred factories can be counted in this district. In the middle of it lies the great <placeName ref="gfa-places-1756"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1752">Wilkinson’s Bradley Iron Works</placeName></placeName>, which employs five thousand workers of the male sex alone, stands out like a crown, and is now, following the death of Mr. <pb n="68" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557575"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7601">Wilkinson</persName> (who, according to his wishes, was laid in a cast iron coffin, over the vault of which is still erected an iron <term ref="gfa-keywords-8770">pyramid</term> weighing four hundred centners), run by a certain Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7602">Ferryday</persName>, who in his early youth was a common coal boy.</p>
            <p>After we had seen in various places, and only in passing, the very distinct manner in which English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8995">iron is manufactured and processed</term>, we set out for the little town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1751" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29T15:00:00" n="109">Dudley</placeName> to have lunch there (it was already <date when="1814-08-29T15:00:00">three o’clock</date>) upon our return from Level-Iron-works, which we had yet to visit, and which is three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> from there. When we arrived at the marketplace, there was a crowd of people, and in the middle of it a huge fire with which the city’s beloved youth proved especially occupied. Upon inquiry, <pb n="69" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557576"/> we were told that a butcher had been selling bad meat, which the magistrate, after notice had been given, had taken away and handed over to the disposition of the thronging public of Dudley. The latter now consigned the corpus delicti to the fire, not at all to the edification of its seller.</p>
            <p>When we arrived at <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7889"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1754" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="110">Level-Iron-works</placeName></orgName>, the owner, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7603" type="met">Gibbon</persName>, not only received us very courteously, but proceeded to show and explain to me all that I wished to know. A somewhat detailed description will be all the more appropriate here, as the mode of operation is roughly the same at all English <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">ore</term> is smelted with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">cokes</term>, and the resulting <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8537">refined</term> with coal flame. Three <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnaces</term> placed side by side, forty-two shaft deep, each yielding from seventy to one hundred <pb n="70" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557577"/> tons or more of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> weekly (which together amounts to six thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>), blow through a single cylinder nine feet in diameter and with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">nine-foot</term> piston stroke, which is set in motion by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">fifty-horsepower</term> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>. Since the cylinder, which delivers its blow into a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9610">iron water regulator</term>, is closed at the top and bottom for double the effect, the amount of air squeezed out per minute is fourteen pistons <formula rend="inline" notation="tex">\frac{9^2\times785\times914\times2^1}{1000} = 15,866</formula> cubic feet. This amount of air is not only sufficient for the three blast furnaces, but also supplies three “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9400"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8552">Refining furnaces</term></term>”, what we would call a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9594">re-melting furnace</term> (one cannot call it a fresh firing). Each of them has three steamers, which incline very steeply, almost like the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8553">Catalan furnaces</term>, over which a gentle stream of water is conducted into the fire to form <term ref="gfa-keywords-8864">hydrogen <pb n="71" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557578"/> gas</term> in order to extract the sulphur from the iron due its greater <term ref="gfa-keywords-8554">elective affinity</term>, thus rendering the iron more suitable for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8537">refining</term>. Over the iron, which is extracted each time in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">two-inch</term> thick plates weighing up to twenty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>, water is run until it cools down completely. It is then broken into pieces of thirty to forty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term>, which are white along the broken edges and have the appearance of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8555">mock steel</term>. Two hundred pounds of this iron at a time are then put into the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">Puddling-Furnace</term>”, which I would rather call a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9053">refining furnace</term>. For, by its nature, it is a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberatory furnace</term> with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9051">a flaming fire</term>, equipped with a chimney about thirty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> high to effect a powerful pull. At the top, the chimney is opened or closed with a lid, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8538">as required</term>. The iron, quickly liquefied by the intensity of the fire, is stir<pb n="72" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557579" break="no"/>red by the ingress of the external air through the open door of the furnace until it separates, then reconstituted, heated anew, stirred again, sprinkled with a small amount of water and, finally, divided into six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8539">lumps</term> inside the furnace itself while in a dough-like state, these lumps, after being subjected to the heat and draught of the external air for some time, are taken out one by one and put under the large hammer. This hammer, cast in one piece with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9524">handle</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9515">grip</term> and weighing about twelve to fifteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>, has neither a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8573">ram</term> nor a hammer-seat. Its two ellipsoidal arms, which are integrally cast in place of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9529">socketed heads</term>, are supported by only two iron trestles. It is, as already explained in an earlier description, lifted at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9516">front at the head</term> by a steam engine, and its shape is also a T <pb n="73" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557580"/> with a surface running along the crosspiece, but lower or deeper than the rest of the channel, so that, even if it falls entirely onto the anvil, there always remains a hollow space of about four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>, in which the lump, which would shatter if the hammer were to strike fully, is first formed and compressed into a short bar. There is also another reason for this space, since the hammer has a strike area of only five inches and the lump can be up to eight inches thick and could, thus, not otherwise be placed beneath the hammer. Once the lump is compressed from four and a half inches to one and a half to an oblong piece, it is called a “Bloom” and then put into the “Bloomery”, or stretching and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8557">welding furnace</term>, which is also a very effective <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberatory furnace</term>. Here, several pieces are <pb n="74" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557581"/> welded together when large, heavy bars are required, or the individual pieces are welded together to a whole, and then brought under the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9440">cutting mills</term>, where square, round, or flat bars are formed in the gradually diminishing grooves, as the cutting mill delivers, in an instant, a bundle of bars anywhere from nine to two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8541">rows</term> square, as required. Only by means of these mechanisms, which work together in such a way that there is absolutely no loss of time, is it possible to sell the resulting small iron for twelve shillings a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centner</term>, despite the high wages in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, which amount to fifteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> or eight <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term> a week for the very lowest manual labourer, and sixteen to twenty guilders for most laborers. Not only is <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">English</placeName> <pb n="75" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557582"/> iron very affordable, but through strenuous efforts, which often make incredible things possible, it has become exceptionally good, as well – and this since the time when the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8591">war</term> some years ago, now, albeit of short duration, between <placeName ref="gfa-places-133">Sweden</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-127">Russia</placeName> closed the English markets to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1779"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8989">iron of Dannemora</term></placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-2063">Siberia</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Quite satisfied and with the clearest idea of the process and the ovens and machines employed, I left this home of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7964">Vulcan</persName>. Between the hundreds of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9224">charcoal piles</term>, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coals</term> are turned into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">cokes</term> , between coal mines with their deep shafts, and even past a district where millions of centners of self-ignited coals have burned for years, making their existence known at night with their blue flames, <pb n="76" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557583"/> like lonely spirits shining through the crevices of their crypts, we rode along back to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1751" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="111">Dudley</placeName>, where beef steak and delicious <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale</term> soon made us forget the hardships of our continuous <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">twenty-four-English-mile</term> journey on horseback, some of which were covered at a gallop.</p>
            <p>Our familiar conversation over dinner and the remedying of some technical matters made our time so brief that we had to make haste to catch a view of the surrounding country from the height of the beautiful <term ref="gfa-keywords-9409">ruins</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1757" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="112">Dudley-Castle</placeName>, where the rays of the sinking sun made a most remarkable contrast with the clouds of smoke from the furnaces, which formed a stormy sky of their own, extending over several hours in diameter. — We also managed to climb down into <term ref="gfa-keywords-9199"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1758" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="113">Dudley’s limestone quarry</placeName></term> to see the mouth of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1759" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="114">canal</placeName>, carved three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> underground and largely through rock, that exits on the other <pb n="77" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557584"/> side of the mountain. The phenomenon, extremely curious and extremely rare to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9069">geologist</term>, of the exact opposite stratification of the limestone deposit on the southeast and northwest sides of this hill, and of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8752">basalt</term> occurring in it, merit a more extensive discussion than space permits here.</p>
            <p>On the way home, we stopped for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> at the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7604"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2182" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-29" n="115" cert="0"/>home of Mr. Priestley<placeName/></persName>, son of the famous Doctor <persName ref="gfa-actors-7605">Priestley</persName>. He is considering the idea of powering carriages in <placeName ref="gfa-places-150">America</placeName>, where he will soon return, with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam engines instead of horses</term>, which is already being done successfully in England near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>. After riding another four miles, we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-30T00:00:00" n="116">Soho</placeName> around <date when="1814-08-30T00:00:00">midnight</date>, illuminated by more than one and a half hundred flames blazing from the chimneys of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">smelting furnaces</term>. After <pb n="78" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557585"/> sharing an idea with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>, of which I will speak again later, I continued to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-30T01:00:00" n="117">Birmingham</placeName>, and in the <date when="1814-08-30T01:30:00">morning</date> between one and two o’clock, well satisfied with the fruits of this day, I retired to bed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>First encounter with malleable cast iron in Birmingham, 30 August 1814</head>
            <p>The <date when="1814-08-30">30th</date> marked my first visit to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-30" n="118">Soho</placeName>, to bid farewell to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> and, at the same time, to obtain from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574">Murdoch</persName> a piece of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8558">platinum wire</term>, which he melts down by the pound and sells at fifteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">ounce</term>, for lining the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8560">touch holes</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">rifles</term>. In addition to the friendship he has already shown me, Mr. Watt was kind enough to provide me with a letter of introduction to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, owner of the largest <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7929">spinning mill</orgName></term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> (which is also remarkable for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lighting</term> introduced there), as well as another letter similar in kind to the famous <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568">Wedgwood</persName>, whose <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566">factory</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1761">New-Etruria</placeName> near <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762">Newcastle-under-Lide</placeName> was not far out <pb n="79" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557586" xml:id="p_79"/> of my way. The rest of the day I devoted to purchasing various products from <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-30" n="119">Birmingham</placeName> and to visiting some <term ref="gfa-keywords-55">foundries</term> and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">steel casting factory</term>, where I was very impressed by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7598">Hobday</persName>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9141">engraver</term>, from whom I had ordered various <term ref="gfa-keywords-8789">letters</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9330">stamps</term> and who knows Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7608" type="met">P.</persName>, the owner of this factory, very well. I also visited another manufactory of the so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-56">new cast iron</term>, of which the cast objects, such as <term ref="gfa-keywords-8593">wick trimmers</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9534">stirrups</term>, all manner of carriage harness, etc., are as pliable as <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, and yet can be forged and hardened like <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, which is why it is also called, albeit incorrectly, “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">Cast-Steel</term>”<note>It was here that Fischer saw <term ref="gfa-keywords-56">malleable cast iron</term> and the casting process for its production for the first time.</note>. On account of their rarity, I bought not only a few unprocessed cast pieces, but also a dozen and a half very beautiful, if expensive, patented wick trimmers, which, when reopened, <pb n="80" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557587"/> leave neither the wick cuttings nor the foul odour behind. This transaction made me so agreeable to the manufacturer that he invited me to see his workshop and foundry. His only regret was that I, as a gentleman, could not have a proper understanding of the matter and consequently could not sufficiently appreciate the advantages of this method and the procedure to keep the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term> completely pliable. I will only briefly note that the melting takes place in closed <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term>, in the same furnaces that are used in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> for casting steel.</p>
            <p>I had to wait a long time for Mr. P., who maintains the cast steel and cement steel factory and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2908">furnaces</term> for melting down the old iron in the same building. I was not displeased to wait, as it allowed me to explore at my leisure. His  <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term>, which he later uses to make <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, and then only with <pb n="81" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557588"/> the usual English addition (which is why it is inferior and of inconsistent quality, especially since he only produces twenty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> at a time), is made in a single chamber in a small furnace. I learned, however, that he is building a second plant to increase his output fourfold. Traditional iron smelting is done in a “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8816">Ball-Furnace</term>”, similar to “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">Puddling-Furnaces</term>”, but smaller. The rapidity with which the smelting is completed is remarkable, and if the process were only more generally known, it would have been taken to heart by many of the owners of works on the mainland, especially the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9440">cutting mills</term>. In the latter, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8539">lump</term> that had been pounded under the heavy hammer was instantly transformed into the desired <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bars</term> and rods.</p>
         </div>         
         <div type="day">
            <head>File manufactory and a trip to Newcastle-under-Lyme, 31 August 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-08-31">31st</date>, I was to leave for <pb n="82" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557589" xml:id="p_82"/> <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762">Newcastle-unter-Lide</placeName>, which is only two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> west of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1761">Etruria</placeName>, <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566">Wedgwood’s</orgName> famous factory. As the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">Mail-Coatch</term>” did not leave until ten o’clock, I made a quick visit to the rather remote <persName ref="gfa-actors-7608"><placeName type="itinerar" when="1814-08-31" n="121">file manufactory of Mr. P</placeName></persName>. As the supervisor or “Clark” had first to be awakened, I meanwhile ventured into the workshop where I saw the following, which may contribute a great deal to the perfection of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term>. Firstly, all the files are forged under two hammers until they reach <term ref="gfa-keywords-8563">brown heat</term>, and then they are given an indentation towards the centre of the entire length using a round, somewhat but only very slightly convex hammer on an equally convex anvil, whereby the corners become very sharp and very straight during grinding. The six <term ref="gfa-keywords-9433">grinding stones</term>, powered by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587">steam engine</term> were of coarse grain, but very <pb n="83" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557590"/> round and very even. Six very simple <term ref="gfa-keywords-9642">draft furnaces</term> were used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealing</term>, which takes place in advance. The different <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">strokes</term>, in German called, “rauh, bastard and schlicht”, are always made by the same workers. The two straps for securing the file are fixed more suitably than in our country and ensure reliable positioning on the point of the strike. A different technique is used for hammering in that the thumb is placed on the head of the hammer to ensure a safer stroke. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">tempering</term> is done by a single man. From the smell, and later upon inspection, I found that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8562">powder used for tempering</term> was one with which I am already familiar. It was very fine and mixed with brewer’s yeast, which results in a more uniform coating of the file. The files were <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealed</term> one by one, then immersed slowly and vertically in water. <pb n="84" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557591"/> The crooked ones were returned to the fire and directed with a wooden stick on a trestle to the opposite side to straighten. — In England, the triangular saw files are never hewn with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">upper cut</term>, but only with a narrow <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">lower cut</term>, which gives a sharper and more durable corner. Incidentally, the files were not bad, but expensive according to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8564">price</term> quoted to me.</p>
            <p>With some distress (having stayed so long) I <placeName ref="gfa-places-20" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-31T10:00:00" n="122">returned</placeName> just before the <date when="1814-08-31T10:00:00">departure</date> of the coach and boarded it at once. My traveling party consisted of an old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8565">Quaker</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName> and his grandson of about seventeen years, together with a worldling from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1763">Congleton</placeName>. It did not require long to make the old man’s acquaintance and, after I had given him sufficient information about the Jews <pb n="85" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557592"/> and pagans and the general Christian community of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName>, he made quite clear his wish to see me admitted as a member of their brotherhood. He cordially invited me to come to his country estate, three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName>, for eight or fourteen days, as he would only stay a few days at his own house in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, which he kept there only on account of his two <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term>. I politely declined this invitation but listened all the more attentively to a punitive sermon on drinking, something to which, he remarked, soldiers (of whom we encountered a great many in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1764" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-31" n="123">Walshale</placeName>) were particularly devoted. Our traveling companion from Congleton did not take kindly to this. For, by his word, no true Englishman had any qualms about being sozzled, and only those with a bad <pb n="86" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557593"/> conscience, who wished to seem better than others, abstained from the drink. His crimson nose, a testimony to his own lack of moderation, was, incidentally, the clearest evidence that his words were sincere. Young Rye, the old man’s grandson, however, despite his round low hat and plain “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8566">Drabcolour</term>” coat (the brown colour of the cloth used for Quaker coats), was cleary not entirely free from the maladies of more worldly children. For a rather beautiful young woman, who at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1765" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-31" n="124">Wolverhampton</placeName>, where we changed horses and stayed for a while, was standing at a window just opposite where the carriage was waiting, so captivated his attention that his eyeballs, as if he had had to look through two tubes, remained quite fixed. Upon observing this, the old man good-naturedly asked him to don his traveling cap <pb n="87" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557594"/> and, as the carriage was stationary, to sleep a while in its corner. However, as the effect on the young man of the object of his attention was anything but sedative, the old man’s admonishment was fruitless. — In the <date when="1814-08-31T18:00:00">evening at six o’clock</date>, we arrived at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-31T18:00:00" n="125">Castle-under-Lide</placeName>, where I took leave of my good Quaker and his grandson and set out for my night’s lodgings at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2223">Inn at the Ram</placeName>.</p>
            <p>I had not been long in my room when it occurred to me to ask the landlord when a coach to <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> would leave the following day. I returned downstairs to find him in the hallway. Without answer, however, he rushed past me and out the front door. I went after him, and behold, it was about a “Boxingmatch”, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8859">fistfight</term>, among four belligerent and drunken <term ref="gfa-keywords-9161">potters</term>, <pb n="88" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557595"/>who were already stripped down in the square and had assumed a fighting posture, awaiting only the arrival of the high nobility of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762">Newcastle</placeName> and a sufficient number of spectators of the fair sex to begin the match, which soon took place. As they fought rather unskilfully, growing heartily annoyed by the irregularity of the blows on both sides, they soon became combatants in earnest and the maternal earth the theatre of their war. There they rolled about until two of the contenders, after having received a sufficient number of kicks and blows, no longer showed much inclination to get back up. Now that they were no longer able to harm one another, the constable, or justice of the peace, until then a silent spectator, ordered them with his long baton to make peace. As soon as they could walk and stand again, he took them all <pb n="89" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557596"/> into custody where they could rest on their laurels. He made one small mistake, however, having locked them all up together, so that after half an hour, as the fight began again, they cried bloody murder through the jail bars. Consequently, a complete separation of the parties was necessary, allowing them to contemplate their grievances and reflections of the night in undisturbed solitude.</p>
            <p>Upon returning to my lodgings, I heard a cry from behind the door: <emph rend="italic"> Ah mon Dieu! est-ce qu’il n’y a personne ici, qui parle français?</emph> — I went up to the gentleman who had cried out and asked him in French if I could be of service to him in any way  — <emph rend="italic">Le bon Dieu nous nous envoye</emph>, he replied, <emph rend="italic">nous sommes ici déja depuis midi</emph> (gesturing towards a woman standing next to him), <emph rend="italic">et <pb n="90" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557597"/> malheureusement personne ne nous entend, et nous ne les entendons pas non plus</emph>. He then explained to me that he and his wife, both from <placeName ref="gfa-places-462">Turin</placeName>, had been in <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and, now, after having stopped in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1956">Etruria</placeName>, wished to proceed to <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, but that no one had understood them, nor had they accepted the money for the seats on the coach, which he had put down, making all manner of gestures. I returned with him to the “Post-Office”, where the clerk, a very decent fellow, told me that he had indeed understood that the couple wished to go to Birmingham, but that he had not taken their money because Newcastle, being the first stop, had no seats available, and that it all depended on whether the coach from Manchester was fully occupied. I explained <pb n="91" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557598"/> all of this to the man from Turin, and then, at his request, reserved the first vacant seats for the following day. — This incident shows how essential it is to understand something of the language if one wants to travel to England, as so few of the natives, especially among the common people (with whom one has the most contact during one’s travels), speak any other language. This is also true of other nations, and only the Germans and Swiss make a praiseworthy exception in this respect.</p>
            <p>While drinking <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term> and reading the newspaper (it was only a “Country-paper”), I was astonished to read under the header <emph rend="italic"><placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName></emph> the news that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Buonaparte</persName> had been brought from the island of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1942">Elba</placeName> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1990">Livorno</placeName>, where he had stayed for twelve hours. It was not  <pb n="92" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557599"/> the news itself but the connection of it with Schafhausen that astonished me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>In Wedgwood’s Etruria Works, 1 September 1814</head>
            <p>The next morning, <date when="1814-09-01">September 1st</date>, as soon as I had reserved a seat on the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">Mail-Coatch</term>” to <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName>, to which it departed in the evening at four o’clock, I set out for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1761" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-01" n="126">Etruria</placeName>, three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762">Newcastle-under-Lide</placeName>. — Just as with <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>, one passes first through a charming street of laborers’ dwellings. <term ref="gfa-keywords-169"> Iron “Rail-ways”</term> lead everywhere to and around the factory, which is also situated on a canal. As I handed my letter from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568" type="met">Wedgwood</persName>, who was already in his office, he said at once: “Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName>, if you would like to see the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1761">factory</placeName>, I will have someone show you around, and then you can come back to my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1780">house</placeName> and <pb n="93" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557600"/> join me for a ‘Luncheon’ (what we call a morning snack in German).” Quite methodically, that is, from the primum mobile of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> through to the storage and packaging of the finished tableware, I was now shown everything at the behest of Mr. Wedgwood.</p>
            <p>Under a tamper, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8569">flint</term> from the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1640">Gravesand</placeName> area is compacted after it has been fired, then ground in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9324">mills</term> (similar to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9130">glaze mills</term>, but between six and nine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> in diameter), which is also the case with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8568">pipe clay</term> and the other types of clay. Once this has been done, the two materials are mixed in equal parts, and are then transferred to somewhat smaller mills, where, with the addition of large amounts of water, they flow in liquid form through <term ref="gfa-keywords-9779">sieves</term> (made of the finest <term ref="gfa-keywords-9452">silkworm threads</term> <pb n="94" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557601"/> which are continuously shaken back and forth by machinery) to penetrate through them, achieving thus a degree of fineness of which one can hardly conceive, given that the density of the threads and their thinness do not allow any particle with even a thousandth part of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> in diameter to pass through. The mass is then transferred to the drying beds, having been caught in vessels placed beneath. These vessels, which are sixty feet long, twenty feet wide and nine inches high, are made of soft-fired <term ref="gfa-keywords-9634">bricks</term>, under which a mild fire is maintained, and the mass is stirred constantly until, after about twenty-four hours, it has acquired sufficient consistency to be transferred to the cylinders. These cylinders (not really cylinders but so called as they are in the form of truncated cones standing on the narrow end) are five <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> <pb n="95" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557602"/> high, three feet wide at the top and two feet wide at the bottom, with a short channel of one foot wide and nine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> high running out at a right angle from the lower part. Through these cylinders, or <emph rend="italic"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">Coni</term></emph>, runs an iron axle, which is driven by gears and on which the so-called knives are located spirally down the length, which, because they lie flat and almost touch the cone with their ends, form a kind of worm thread, seen from above, which moves the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> that is tossed in at the top from time to time downwards and presses it out through the hole at the end, where it is then cut off with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">wire</term> to form square blocks and put onto a nearby pile. After three or four days of fermentation, or rather uniform humidification, it is placed <pb n="96" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557603"/> once more in the cylinders, and again formed into blocks as described above. It is then carried on boards to the workers. Here is the place to mention that the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-169">Rail-ways</term>” or iron tracks that run throughout the factory are used primarily for the transportation of materials, which is done in small iron wagons fitted with open boxes. Such a wagon is pushed by a single man and weighs 1320 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> including the load, which was weighed in front of me for my assurance.</p>
            <p>Now, a common <term ref="gfa-keywords-9775">potter’s wheel</term> is used for the initial formation of the prepared <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> (with the exception of the flat plates, which I will discuss later). The wheel differs from ours in only two things: It is <pb n="97" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557604"/> made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8774">mahagony</term> to prevent warping, and operated not by a person but a machine, which makes the work much easier and almost doubles the output in the same amount of time.</p>
            <p>On this occasion, I saw one of the most useful and simplest devices for regulating the speed of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9775">potter’s wheel</term> instantly, while the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>, as can easily be seen, continues its steady and equal pace. Two hollow <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">cones</term>, one attached to the axle or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindle</term> of the wheel rather than to the pulley and the other in the reverse position (with the base upward) at a distance of twelve <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> between two blocks, form the driving and the driven gear by means of a leather belt looped around both. An iron fork attached to a pedal <pb n="98" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557605"/> guides the belt instantly upwards or downwards at the will of the operator, where, in the first case, the wheel moves slower and, in the second, faster, although the lateral surfaces of the cones remain parallel and consequently the tension of the belt remains constant. The same useful device is also used for the lathes, about which I will comment below.</p>
            <p>From the wheels, the objects go into the drying rooms, where at a temperature of eighty degrees <term ref="gfa-keywords-8567">Reaum.</term> they acquire in a short time a degree of hardness which is somewhat more than what the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9161">potters</term> in our country would call water hard. In this state, being hard enough to be handled without danger of deforming, they pass to the horizontal <term ref="gfa-keywords-9643">lathes</term>, where the method of clamping them on and in wooden chucks or <pb n="99" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557606"/> cartridges is very easy and safe. The only tool used for turning is a thin, variously curved scraping blade, which, once the dishes are turned, is also used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9742">polishing</term>, which is done remarkably well for such an extremely fine material. Once the dishes are hard enough to be put into the kiln, they are placed in containers made of coarse fireproof <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> according to the different sizes of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8597">dishes</term>. Here, I noticed something that is perhaps not known outside of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and yet is of the utmost importance to prevent warping, especially of the plates and platters. A coarse <term ref="gfa-keywords-9392">quartz sand</term> is poured into the bottom of the container, thus filling all the gaps between the inserted dishes, none of which may touch the other, so that each is placed as if in its own casing, in <pb n="100" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557607"/> other words, supported at every point. This sand is also an effective heat conductor, while its coarse grain allows any vapours that may develop during <term ref="gfa-keywords-9073">firing</term> to escape. The dishes are then placed in the round, domed, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">twelve-foot</term> high and wide kilns, which the Germans would call upright kilns. Ten hearths of fire arranged in a circle at equal distance from one another, each with a flue in the middle of the kiln and the others going in at the sides, give a tremendously uniform heat, which is carefully controlled by the eyes, or holes, all around for viewing inside. Sixty hours are generally required for this first or, in the language of the art, so-called overbaking. After this is completed, the oven is opened immediately, so <pb n="101" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557608"/> that it is always cold the following day and the dishes can be taken out. Incidentally, the oven is always enclosed by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8596">round structure in a conical shape</term>, which stands approximately eight <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> away from the oven.</p>
            <p>The production of the plates takes place quite simply by spreading a suitably sized lump of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> on a slab of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9123">gypsum</term> using a club of the same material. This clay disk is then placed on a plate mould and pressed on the underside with a sponge. Once the plate is sufficiently dry, it is turned and polished on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9643">lathe</term> like other dishes.</p>
            <p>The glazing of the fired objects is not done by basting, but by dipping them into large tubs full of prepared <term ref="gfa-keywords-9129">glaze</term>. This is not only very fast, but, more importantly, <pb n="102" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557609"/> it produces a uniform and not overly thick coating. On thin rings of fired clay, sharpened at the top like knife edges, the objects are placed to dry, then returned to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8597">containers</term> and fired for twelve to fourteen hours. This is the procedure when the product is to remain a single colour. If it is to be embellished with <term ref="gfa-keywords-2837">copper engravings</term>, this must be done first. For this purpose, the copper plates are warm rubbed with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9316">mineral paint</term> mixed with very thickly boiled <term ref="gfa-keywords-9270">linseed oil</term> and thus printed on silk paper, which is then rubbed onto the objects that have been coated with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9564">turpentine spirits</term>, causing the prints to reappear there. Rinsing in water removes the <term ref="gfa-keywords-5503">paper</term>, leaving the engraving or drawing. The dishes are lightly fired to eliminate the oil and turpentine, and then glazed. Anything to be coloured other than black <pb n="103" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557610"/> is painted with mineral pigments before the final <term ref="gfa-keywords-9073">firing</term>. This method of decorating earthenware with copper engravings was invented about thirty-five years ago by a man from <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName>. He was the director of the old <placeName ref="gfa-places-154"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9373"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1781">porcelain factory near Zurich</placeName></term></placeName> (which he had also founded). His name, now all but forgotten, was <persName ref="gfa-actors-7694">Adam Spengler</persName>. If he had had a more fortuitous upbringing and received an education earlier in life, something his parents’ poverty prevented him from obtaining, he might have become an excellent man in his trade, having made it despite adverse circumstances from a common <term ref="gfa-keywords-9161">potter</term> to a shrewd factory owner.</p>
            <p>I observed a very useful and probably little-known method to bring small objects, such as names, devices, etc., speedily onto these objects. A piece of <pb n="104" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557611"/> elastic <term ref="gfa-keywords-3522">rubber</term> of sufficient size to completely cover the engraved copper plate, which has been rubbed with the ink and cleaned off again, is pressed onto the engraved copper plate, where the drawing then transfers to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9173">resin</term> without being absorbed by it. The rubber is then rubbed back onto the plate that is to be printed, thus transferring the design onto it.</p>
            <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9371">painter’s</term> workshop, occupied by thirty or so individuals, exhibited some very good artists, particularly in landscape <term ref="gfa-keywords-9292">painting</term>. The more common objects, such as wreaths, etc., were generally painted by girls. The process of applying enamel colours, drawing concentric rings, etc. was the same as in other porcelain factories.</p>
            <p>It was still very strange to me to see how the black and other coloured dishes with such delightful ornamentation and <pb n="105" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557612"/> figures of semi-sophisticated work were made. The hollow moulds formed over metal are all made of very fine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8568">pipe clay</term> that is not hard-fired and thus readily absorbs moisture. The rather soft <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> is pressed into them, and all protruding parts are cut away. If very thin and weak parts do not come off easily, they are rubbed on the back or flat side with a spatula and, thus, immediately removed. The application of the decorative patterns produced in this way to the already water-hard objects is accomplished by wetting the area with water and pressing lightly with the finger, sometimes with the help of a wet, fine bristle brush, to achieve an even greater bond.</p>
            <p> <pb n="106" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557613"/> I should also note that the clay or mass from which the black tableware is made has a dark rust colour when soft, which is sufficient evidence that the black dye is made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8987">oxidized iron</term>. For the various types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8598">decorative</term> handles and so-called mountings, there are several hollow metal cylinders, into which a bottom, perforated as desired, can be inserted. Once the cylinder is filled with a mass of soft clay, the piston or plunger placed on it is pressed down by means of a screw, and in a short time many <term ref="gfa-keywords-8599">ells</term> of decorative strips are obtained, which are then sometimes used singly, sometimes interwoven three or four times, as can best be seen in the fruit baskets composed of such strips.</p>
            <p> <pb n="107" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557614"/> After I had inspected everything sufficiently (whereby I had to admire the simplicity of the procedure and the clever distribution of the work) and had selected a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9552">table service</term> for my own use, as well as black <term ref="gfa-keywords-9560">tableware</term> in the abundantly stocked warehouses, I proceeded to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568" type="met"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1780" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-01" n="127">Wedgwood’s residence</placeName></persName>, which is located on a charming hill half a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">mile</term> from the factory. The conversation at dinner was concerned largely with scientific and manufacturing matters. He appeared to be reluctant to discuss his own facilities. However, regarding the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8600">pyrometer</term> that bears his name<note>The pyrometer takes its name not from Fischer’s host but from his father, Josiah Wedgwood.</note>, he gave me the curious information that its contractile properties no longer followed the same laws, and that he must attribute this to a variation of the clay mass caused by time and internal <pb n="108" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557615"/> fermentation. When I remarked to him that I had wished to select a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porcelain</term> tea service, but had not found anything to suit my needs, he made the following strange reply: “Mr. Fischer, I cannot advise you to buy porcelain from me. As you are returning home via France, you will find more beautiful and better porcelain in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName>. I will most likely give up the production of porcelain altogether.” As to his reason for this opinion, he stated that <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName> possessed far better materials for the production of porcelain than <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. When I mentioned <placeName ref="gfa-places-29">Chinese</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8568">kaolin</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8601">pé-tun-tzé</term>, he replied that nothing of further importance had become known about these since Pater <persName ref="gfa-actors-7696">du Halde</persName> had <term ref="gfa-keywords-8602">written about the production</term> of this porcelain. He also noted <pb n="109" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557616"/> that this unique mixture can withstand a much higher degree of heat than <placeName ref="gfa-places-42">European</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373">porcelain</term>, which is already well known.</p>
            <p>While <term ref="gfa-keywords-2962">agriculture</term> is not a subject on which I could speak or judge as an expert, I must confess that I came to England with greater expectations of it than the actual state of affairs appeared to me afterwards to be, and the comparison of it with that in our <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName> (to say nothing of the monstrous stretches of uncultivated land in many provinces) was not a favourable one. What struck me most was that there was so little cultivation of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8603">clover</term> and just as little wet or dry fertilizer, which, however, results from the natural circumstance that one sees livestock of all kinds grazing on the pastures, while <term ref="gfa-keywords-9531">feeding in the stables</term> is only rarely practiced. <pb n="110" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557617"/> Seeing a number of white clumps on the meadow in front of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568">Wedgwood’s</persName> house, I inquired what it was and was told that it was <term ref="gfa-keywords-9198">lime</term> to promote the growth of grass. When I mentioned the effectiveness of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9123">gypsum</term> in planting clover, he replied that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7567">his father</persName>, as well as himself and other neighbours, had tried this several times, but without success. I asked him if they had ever fired the gypsum before stamping and sowing — as it turns out, this had never been done. However, this method of bringing about and increasing the fertilizing effect of the gypsum made such sense to him that he immediately resolved to make another attempt using this method. — As the time for my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1762" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-01T16:00:00" n="128">departure</placeName> was drawing near, I expressed my gratitude to Mr. Wedgewood, a man, whose <persName ref="gfa-actors-7567">father</persName>, a common <placeName ref="gfa-places-1330">Staf<pb n="111" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557618" break="no"/>fordshire</placeName> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9572">potter</term>, had founded an earthenware manufactory, the quality of whose products caused them to be shipped to all four corners of the world and whose well-earned reputation the son is now doing all he can to strengthen.</p>
            <p>I should also mention a traditional drink, which was brought to the table along with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9372">port wine</term> and which is loved in England, though unknown here: namely, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9472">Gooseberry wine</term>. This fruit, so commonly enjoyed in England in a variety of ways, but little appreciated in our country, is squeezed for its juice. Mixed with sugar and sufficient water, it makes a healthy drink, pleasant to the palate, which is also called <term ref="gfa-keywords-9618">wine</term> in English and which for me, at least, will always be preferable to the foreign wine, so expensive in England, which is adulterated with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8860">brandy</term> and <pb n="112" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557619"/> other things. In general, the English, with their excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term> (which is now brewed with great success in almost every family, rich or poor), could generally dispense with wine. However, just the opposite is true, and a lunch without wine is considered of little value.</p>
            </div>       
         <div type="day">
            <head>Manchester, 2 September 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of <date when="1814-09-02T02:00:00">September 2nd</date>, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-471" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-02T02:00:00" n="129">Manchester</placeName>, this now so vast and populous city, which was once so insignificant that it did not even have one member in Parliament. In the morning, as soon as it had reached the appropriate hour to submit to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607" type="met">Lee</persName> my letter of introduction from Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">Boulton et Watt</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>, I set off for the large <placeName ref="gfa-places-1782" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-02" n="130">spinning mill</placeName>, which has few equals in size. Mr. Lee was just leaving for the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1783" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-02" n="131">stock exchange</placeName> and invited me along. <pb n="113" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557620"/> “We will find a gentleman there who is at the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">mill</term> with me.” he said, “He will take you around Manchester, together with a Portuguese gentleman, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7925">Parienta</persName>, who visited me yesterday, and show you the most remarkable things. Then, in the evening at four o’clock, we will go together to my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1951" cert="0">country house</placeName> for lunch.” — It was two hours before we found Mr. Willoughby, so that I was already concerned about the lack of time for my main purpose, but he, a very insightful and understanding man, knew to distinguish the essential from the unessential and, so, my wish was fulfilled at last. He first took us to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">factory</term> where the so-called Manchester or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8614">Fustian</term> is woven and cut. The cutting is done by means of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">two-foot-long</term>, rappier-like instrument with a very small, forged knife somewhat to the rear of the fine <pb n="114" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557621"/> tip. Each stroke, or cut, is made at once over a length of six feet on the fabric, which is stretched on a frame, and, owing to extensive practice, with extraordinary safety and speed. From this factory, we proceeded to the mills for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9252">scouring</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8902">singeing</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8412">bleaching</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9037">dyeing</term> of the fabric, located in the same enclosure. The scouring mill is powered by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8587">steam engine</term>. Wooden cylinders, studded with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">iron sheet metal</term> perforated on the outside and thus roughened on the surface, pull the Manchester between long, stiff brushes moving crosswise with great efficiency, whereby all hairs that are not intimately connected with the fabric are ruffled up and raised. Thus prepared, the fabric is sent to be singed. <pb n="115" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557622"/> Over a half pipe of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8590">cast iron</term>, about eight to nine <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter and of a length somewhat greater than the width of the Manchester and kept continuously red-hot by means of a traversing <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> flame, the scoured fabric (which must be extremely dry) is now pulled firmly across the red-hot <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> at a speed of about three and a half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> per five seconds, and then subjected to rapid <term ref="gfa-keywords-8412">bleaching</term> by means of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8405">oxygenated hydrochloric acid</term>. Of this now well-known and already variously described <term ref="gfa-keywords-8846">bleaching</term> method, which immediately eliminates the frequent brown burn marks, I only note that, according to all testimony and experience, nothing harmful happens to the fabric treated in this way, provided that the acid is completely removed by washing. — The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9037">dyeing works</term> reveals nothing special in its equipment, <pb n="116" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557623"/> insofar as use of the steam engine to deliver water to the various boilers and rectangular vats is regarded as self-evident. In the preparation of the black Manchester, the only thing to be noted is that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9073">singeing</term> takes place only after <term ref="gfa-keywords-8625">dyeing</term>. Whether the prices of these products (about which I inquired with the owner of the factory, Mr. B.) are expensive or not compared to those of the mainland, I cannot say due to my ignorance of these commodities. He valued the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8604">yard</term> or one and a half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8599">ell</term> of our measure at sixteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> or about forty-four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8444">Kreuzer</term> for the lowest, and at four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shillings</term> six pence or two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">florins</term> twenty-eight Kreuzer for the highest quality. Of this Mr. B., whose very good manner of dress was no better than that of his workmen, and who had <pb n="117" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557624"/> a hand in everything himself, Mr. Willoughby told me, incidentally, that he was worth at least fifty thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term>.</p>
            <p>From this factory, we proceeded to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9614">machine spinning</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">weaving mill</term> of <persName ref="gfa-actors-8297">Mr. C</persName>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8606"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8605">“Mule-Jenny” machines</term></term>, each of which is equipped with two hundred and forty <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindles</term>, are powered by a steam engine, and, just as the carriage is all the way back, it reverses itself to allow time for twisting. Why is it that until now only human labour has been used for this purpose in Switzerland? — The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8916">carding machines</term> were very similar to ours, only, like the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">spinning machines</term>, they did not seem to me to be very well made. One can see that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9465">spindles</term> are made entirely of <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, on which the yarn is wound directly (and not, as with us, on spools). Since the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">cotton</term> was bul<pb n="118" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557625" break="no"/>bous, very thick and impure, spread out on a long cloth wound around a thin wooden cylinder, from which it was fed into the carding machine, I could not understand how this could form the foundation of a beautiful thread. However, after seeing the facilities for the pre-spinning, the procedure with the finished yarn taken from the spindles, and then the special final treatment of the same (which I never had the opportunity to witness on the mainland), I believe to have recognized therein the reason for the reputation of English yarn and cloth. What was spun here was No. 40 and was (of which I will speak more shortly) woven on the spot.</p>
            <p>Having read in the newspapers some years ago of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9613"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8608">uprising of the weavers</term></term> around <placeName ref="gfa-places-1807">Nottingham</placeName> and in some other places, <pb n="119" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557626"/> and their destruction of the machines and the buildings containing them, one will no longer be surprised at the indignation of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">unemployed</term> when one has seen these <term ref="gfa-keywords-3456"><term ref="gfa-keywords-3009">machine looms</term></term>. Fifty such looms, all driven by one and the same <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> that powers the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning mill</term>, stood in a moderately large room, as each occupied at most approximately four <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> of length, width, and height, and were attended by fifteen operators and a minder. As the movement of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8486">shuttle</term>, which was shot back and forth by spring power, as well as the movement of the beater, was somewhat faster than with human hands, the output in the same time was not only greater, but also, as the minder correctly remarked to me, since the machine does not tire as humans do, more uniform and <pb n="120" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557627"/> consequently superior. Being curious, I asked for samples of the woven cloth and was also given some of the black <term ref="gfa-keywords-8614">Manchester</term>, which is the clearest confirmation of all that was said.</p>
            <p>I would have liked to visit a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8610">calico printing works</term>, but time did not permit it. The only thing I was able to learn on the way to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName> was the method for removing the unpleasant odour from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8864">hydrogen gas</term> used to light the factory buildings and making it burn with a brilliant instead of a bluish flame, which is still being guarded as a secret.</p>
            <p>“<placeName ref="gfa-places-1951" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-02" n="134" cert="0">Wallnut-Cottage</placeName>” was the name of Mr. Lee’s country house surrounded by a pretty “Pleasure-ground” located just three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from Manchester, where we went and were <pb n="121" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557628"/> entertained by his sister<note>It is not known whether the person in question was <persName ref="gfa-actors-7727">Sophia Lee</persName> or her sister <persName ref="gfa-actors-7695">Harriet Lee</persName>.</note>, a very educated and witty woman, who is known as the author of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8611">Canterbury Tales</term>. — The lively conversation was ended in the evening at <date when="1814-09-02T20:00:00">eight o’clock</date> by a courier coming from the city, whose letter prompted Mr. Lee to set off for there immediately. Mr. Parienta and I accompanied him.</p>
            <p>When I inquired of Mr. Lee about the place in England where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">steam engine is used to drive carriages</term> instead of horses, he told me <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> an. So that I would not be without acquaintance there, he was kind enough to give me, with all due haste, a letter of introduction to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName>, the greatest <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">cloth manufacturer</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. As I had already reserved and paid for my seat in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">post coach</term> to Leeds for the following morning, I no longer had time to visit Mr. Lee’s <pb n="122" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557629"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1782">spinning mill</placeName></term>. He had wanted to show it to me himself that evening but was now no longer able to do so. All I could do was admire the splendid illumination of the dining room<note>The reference appears to be to the dining room in <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607"><placeName ref="gfa-places-2079">George August Lee’s residence</placeName></persName> beside the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1782" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-02" n="135">spinning mill</placeName>. Fischer accompanied Lee to the plant but was unable to visit it for lack of time.</note> by means of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8635">hydrogen gas</term> emanating from the mouths of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9104">crystal chandeliers</term>. On <date when="1814-09-03">September 3rd</date>, satisfied with all I had seen, I departed from a <placeName ref="gfa-places-471" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-03" n="136">place</placeName>, which had not even been on my original itinerary, given the brevity of my stay, and which I was able to visit only on account of the friendly counsel and recommendation of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>.</p>
            <p>Finally, I would like to note that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, who is certainly one of the most distinguished men in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, was the first to introduce the use of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lighting</term> on such a large scale and <pb n="123" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557630"/> that he had the equipment for this made by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574">Murdoch</persName>, who first had the idea of using <term ref="gfa-keywords-8635">hydrogen gas</term> as a more cost-efficient alternative, in the works of Msrs. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7573"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7572"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">Boulton et Watt</orgName></persName></persName>.</p>
            <p>A <term ref="gfa-keywords-8612">paper</term> on the comparative brightness and cost of a given quantum of hydrogen gas light versus light from <term ref="gfa-keywords-9209">candles</term> was submitted by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574">Murdoch</persName> to the <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7699">Royal Society</orgName>. Mr. Lee was kind enough to share it with me and, since it is so extremely interesting, I append it here to my remarks of today.</p> 
            <p>………</p>   
         </div>         
         <div>
            <head>Essay on the “comparative brightness” of William Murdoch</head>
            <p>The facts and results intended to be communicated in this <persName ref="gfa-actors-7574"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8612">Paper</term></persName>, are founded upon observations made, during the present winter, at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1782"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7929">cotton manufactory of Messrs. Philips and Lee</orgName></placeName> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName>, <pb n="124" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557631" xml:id="p_124"/> where the light obtained by the combustion of the gas from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> is used upon a very large scale; the apparatus for its production and application having been prepared by me at the works of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7571">Boulton, Watt and Co.</orgName> at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>.</p>
            <p>The whole of the rooms of this <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">cotton mill</term>, which is, I believe, the most extensive in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-402">United Kingdom</placeName> as well as its counting-houses and store-rooms, and the adjacent <placeName ref="gfa-places-2079">dwelling-house</placeName> of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, are lighted with the gas from coal. The total quantity of light used during the hours of burning, has been ascertained, by a comparison of shadows, to be about equal to the light which 2500 mould candles of six in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pound</term> would give; each <pb n="125" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557632"/> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9209">candles</term>, with which the comparison was made consuming at the rate of 4-10ths of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">ounce</term> (175 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8613">grains</term>) of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9554">tallow</term> per hour.</p>
            <p>The quantity of light is necessarily liable to some variation, from the difficulty of adjusting all the flames, so as to be perfectly equal at all times; but the admirable precision and exactness with which the business of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1782">this mill</placeName> is conducted, afforded as excellent an opportunity of making the comparative trials I had in view, as is perhaps likely to be ever obtained in general practice. And the experiments being made upon so large a scale, and for a considerable period of time, may, I think, be assumed as a sufficiently accurate standard for determining the advantages to be expected from the use of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lights</term> under favourable <pb n="126" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557633"/> circumstances. It is not my intention, in the present Paper, to enter into a particular description of the apparatus employed for producing the gas; but I may observe generally, that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> is <term ref="gfa-keywords-8549">distilled</term> in large iron retorts, which during the winter season are kept constantly at work, except during the intervals of charging; and that the gas, as it rises from them, is conveyed by iron pipes into large reservoirs, or <term ref="gfa-keywords-8550">gazometers</term>, where it is washed and purified, previous to its being conveyed through other pipes, called mains, to the mill. These mains branch off into a variety of ramifications (forming a total length of several miles), and diminish in size, as the quantity of gas required to be passed through them <pb n="127" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557634"/> becomes less. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-9164">burners</term>, where the gas is consumed, are connected with the above mains, by short tubes, each of which is furnished with a cock to regulate the admission of the gas to each burner, and to shut it totally off when requisite. This latter operation may likewise be instantaneously performed, throughout the whole of the burners in each room, by turning a cock, with which each main is provided, near its entrance into the room.</p>
            <p>The burners are of two kinds: the one is upon the principle of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7738"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8615">Argand lamp</term></persName>, and resembles it in appearance; the other is a small curved tube with a conical end, having three circular apertures or perforations, of about a thirtieth of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> in diameter, one at the <pb n="128" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557635"/> point of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8887">cone</term>, and two lateral ones, through which the gas issues, forming three divergent jets of flame, somewhat like a fleur-de-lis. The shape and general appearance of this tube, has procured it among the workmen, the name of the cockspur burner.</p>
            <p>The number of burners employed in all the buildings, amounts to 271 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8615">Argands</term> and 633 cockspurs; each of the former giving a light equal to that of four candles of the description abovementioned; and each of the latter, a light equal to two and a quarter of the same candles; making therefore the total of the gas light a little more than equal to that of 2500 <term ref="gfa-keywords-9209">candles</term> When thus regulated, the whole of the above burners require an hourly supply of 1250 cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> of the gas produced from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8616">cannel coal</term>; the superior quality and quantity of the gas <pb n="129" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557636"/> produced from that material having given it a decided preference in this situation, over every other coal, notwithstanding its higher price.</p>
            <p>The time during which the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas light</term> is used, may, upon an average of the whole year, be stated at least at two hours per day of twenty-four hours. In some mills, where there is over work, it will be three hours; and in the few where night- work is still continued, nearly twelve hours. But taking two hours per day as the common average throughout the year, the consumption in Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7929"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1782">Philips’ and Lee’s mill</placeName></orgName>, will be 1250 x 2 = 2500 cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>of gas per day; to produce which, seven hundred weight of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8616">cannel coal</term> is required in the retort. The price of the best <placeName ref="gfa-places-2075">Wigan</placeName> cannel (the sort used) is 13½ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">d.</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">cwt.</term> (22 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">s.</term><pb n="130" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557637"/> 6 d. per ton), delivered at the mill, or say about eight shillings for the seven hundred weight. Multiplying by the number of working days in the year (313), the annual consumption of cannel will be 110 tons, and its cost <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>125. About one-third of the above quantity, or say forty tons of good common coal, value ten shillings per ton, is required for fuel to heat the retorts; the annual amount of which is <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>20. The 110 tons of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8616">cannel coal</term> when distilled, produce about 70 tons of good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coak</term> which is sold upon the spot at 1<term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">s.</term> 4 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">d.</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">cwt.</term> and will therefore amount annually to the sum of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>93. — The quantity of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9561">tar</term> produced from each ton of cannel coal <pb n="131" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557638"/> is from eleven to twelve <term ref="gfa-keywords-8618"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale gallons</term></term>, making a total annual produce of about 1250 ale gallons, which not having been yet sold, I cannot determine its value; but whenever it comes to be manufactured in large quantities, it cannot be such as materially to influence the economical statement, unless indeed new applications of it should be discovered. The quantity of aqueous fluid which came over in the course of the observations which I am now giving an account of, was not exactly ascertained, from some springs having got into the reservoir; and as it has not been yet applied to any useful purpose, I may omit further notice of it in this statement.</p>
            <p>The interest of the capital expended in the necessary apparatus and buildings, together with what is considered as an ample allowance for wear and tear, is stated by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName> at about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>550 per annum in which some allowance is made <pb n="132" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557639"/> for this apparatus being made upon a scale adequate to the supply of a still greater quantity of light, than he has occasion to make use of. He is of opinion, that the cost of attendance upon <term ref="gfa-keywords-9209">candles</term> would be as much, if not more, than upon the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9061">gas apparatus</term>; so that in forming the comparison, nothing need be stated upon that score, on either side.</p>
            <p>The economical statement for one year then stands thus: Cost of 110 tons of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8616">cannel coal</term> — <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>125. Ditto of 40 tons of common <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">ditto</term> — 20; together 145. Deduct the value of 70 tons of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coak</term> — 93. The annual expenditure in coal, after deducting the value of the coak, and without allowing any thing <pb n="133" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557640"/> for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9561">tar</term>, is therefore 52. And the interest of capital, and wear and tear of apparatus — 550. Making the total expence of the gas apparatus, about <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>600 per annum. That of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9209">candles</term>, to give the same light, would be about £2000. For each candle consuming at the rate of 4-ioths of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8559">ounce</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9554">tallow</term> per hour, the 2500 candles burning upon an average of the year two hours per day, would, at one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> per <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>, the present price, amount to nearly the sum of money abovementioned.</p>
            <p>If the comparison were made upon an average of three hours per day, the advantage would be still more in favour of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas light</term>; the interest of the capital, and wear and tear of the apparatus continuing nearly the same as in the former case; thus, 1250 x 3 = 3730 cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> of gas per day, which would be produced by 10¾ <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">cwt.</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8616">cannel coals</term>; <pb n="134" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557641"/> this multiplied by the number of working days, gives 168 tons per annum, which valued as before, amounts to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>188. And 60 tons common coal for burning under the retorts, will commune to 30. Together 218. Deduct 105 tons of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">coak</term> at 26 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">s.</term> 8 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">d.</term> — 140. Leaving the expenditure in coal, after deduction of the coak, and without allowance for the tar, at 78. Adding to which the interest and wear and tear of apparatus, as before, the total annual cost will not be more than <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">£</term>650 whilst that of tallow, rated as before, will be £3000. It will readily occur, that the greater number of hours the gas is burnt, the greater will be its comparative economy; although in extending it beyond three hours, an increase of some parts of the apparatus would be ne<pb n="135" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557642" break="no"/>cessary. — If the economical comparison were made with oils, the advantages would be less than with <term ref="gfa-keywords-9554">tallow</term>. The introduction of this species of light into the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1782"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7929">establishment of Messrs. Philips and Lee</orgName></placeName>, has been gradual; beginning in the <date when="1805">year 1805</date>, with two rooms of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">mill</term>, the counting- houses, and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee’s</persName> <placeName ref="gfa-places-2079">dwelling-house</placeName>. After which, it was extended through the whole manufactory, as expeditiously as the apparatus could be prepared. At first, some inconvenience was experienced from the smell of the unconsumed, or imperfectly purified gas, which may in a great measure be attributed to the introduction of successive improvements in the construction of the apparatus, as the work proceeded. But since its completion, and since the persons to whose care it is con<pb n="136" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557643" break="no"/>fided, have become familiar with its management, this inconvenience has been obviated, not only in the mill, but also in Mr. Lee’s house, which is most brilliantly illuminated with it, to the exclusion of every other species of artificial light.</p>
            <p>The peculiar softness and clearness of this light, with its almost unvarying intensity, have brought it into great favour with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-2937">work people</term>. And its being free from the inconvenience and danger, resulting from the sparks and frequent <term ref="gfa-keywords-8593">snuffing</term> of candles, is a circumstance of material importance, as tending to diminish the hazard of <term ref="gfa-keywords-1221">fire</term>, to which cotton mills are known to be much exposed.</p>
            <p>………</p>
         </div>         
         <div type="day">
            <head>“The good nature of the English of the upper and lower orders”</head>
            <p> <pb n="137" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557644"/> By way of anecdote, I will mention two incidents — of minor importance, admittedly, more as a hiatus from my eternal talk of machines, relaying the accounts of which may soon turn me into one myself, insofar as such descriptions fetter the imagination and one’s free will — which are proof of the good-naturedness of proper <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">Englishmen</placeName> in both the upper and lower classes.</p>
            <p>It was almost <date when="1814-09-02T02:00:00">two o’clock in the morning</date> when the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">coach</term> arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName>, stopping not as usual in front of an “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">Inn</term>”, but in front of a “Post-Office”. Having already been told on the way that there was an inn opposite, I took my night bag (I had nothing else with me) under my arm as I disembarked and walked straight towards an open door through which I could see into the interior of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term>. Hardly had I crossed the threshold when I realized I had entered some sort of <pb n="138" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557645"/> murderous den. Drunken soldiers, sailors lying prostrate on tables and benches, lascivious women and their commensurate associates formed the assembly in which I was to take up my night’s quarters. Still undecided as to what to do, since it was otherwise dark in all the buildings, and calling for a glass of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term> to deliberate for a while, I felt myself being pulled by the back of my coat as I heard the summons: “Come away”. It was a very well dressed and equally respectable looking gentleman who signalled me to come away, and I immediately followed him. Once in the street, he explained that he had seen me enter the house as he was passing and as he knew it to be unfit, he wished to warn me as a stranger and inform me that there was a good inn on the high street by the name of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1784" cert="0">Bridgewater-Arms</placeName>, where I would be well <pb n="139" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557646"/> looked after in every respect. He accompanied me to its doors, where, on entering, I immediately confirmed the truth of his statement.</p>
            <p>The second incident occurred as follows: As I was leaving in the morning to visit Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, I asked in the area near the <term ref="gfa-keywords-4343"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1783">stock exchange</placeName></term> for the right way to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1782">spinning mill</placeName></term>. “It is quite far,” the man replied, “and I am not going along quite the same road; however, I will set you aright.” Yet he did accompany me all the way and even gave me his address. He was a cleaner, not of clothes but of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8614">Manchester</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8620">Nankin</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8610">Cattun</term>. Consequently, he could expect no advantage from his kindness to me. Before seeing Mr. Lee, I was obliged to return to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1784">my lodgings</placeName> for a briefcase I had left behind, and I encountered him again on the way, when, passing by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8920">chemist’s</term>, he politely invited me to join him for a glass of “Pop”. <pb n="140" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557647"/> For want of time, I declined and took leave of him, but that word, quite foreign to me, captured my attention. Sometime later, I went into this store especially for this reason and obtained for two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term> a glassful of very pleasant drink, composed, as I learned from the chemist, of sugar, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8860">brandy</term>, water, lime juice, and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8622">cremor tartari</term>. I mention the composition in such detail as it is not detrimental to health and can be enjoyed at any time of the year. It keeps for a very long time in stone jars.</p>
         </div>         
         <div type="day">
            <head>Travelling on the “Salamanca” to Leeds, 3 September 1814</head>
            <p>Via <placeName ref="gfa-places-1785" type="itinerar" when="1813-09-03" n="137">Middleton</placeName>, where not far from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term> “at the dusty Miller” there stands a factory building that was burnt down by the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9613">weavers</term> and has now been rebuilt as a monument to the effects of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8583">French Prohibition</term>, I arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-03T18:00:00" n="138">Leeds</placeName> at six o’clock in the <date when="1813-09-03T18:00:00">evening</date>, <pb n="141" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557648"/> up to which point I was accompanied by a very agreeable young man, the son of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9585">cloth manufacturer</term> Parr, and to whose instruction to take the straight road to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> Sheffield via Leeds I owe my good fortune that same evening to fulfil the purpose of my journey in that I encountered the coal transport <term ref="gfa-keywords-8592">wagons pulled by steam engines</term> over a distance of almost three <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> and witnessed them still in operation.</p>
            <p>From the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1793">site</placeName>, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coals</term> are excavated to the depot located near the city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName> runs an <term ref="gfa-keywords-169"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1792" type="itinerar" when="1813-09-03" n="139">iron railroad</placeName></term>, which differs from the ordinary kind in that on one side of it protruding “Cogs” have been cast on, about three and a half <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> long, two inches thick, rounded at the top, and spaced about two inches apart.</p>
            <p> <pb n="142" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557649"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8623">The wagon on which the steam engine is mounted</term>, and which in size and shape resembles a small wine wagon with a single barrel, also has four small all-iron wheels, like the coal wagons attached to it at the rear. It also has a fifth <term ref="gfa-keywords-9477">spur-gear wheel</term>revolving in the middle between the left rear and front wheels, which engages the cogs and is driven around by two smaller spur gears attached to two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">spiral arms</term> with cranks. These two cranks receive their motion directly from the rising and falling <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rods</term> in the two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">ten-inch</term> cylinders, which are located in the boiler itself and protrude only as far as required by the disposition of the vents, or rather valves, which are ope<pb n="143" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557650" break="no"/>ned and closed by the piston rods themselves by means of a simple mechanism for admitting the steam. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-90">furnace</term> is also located in the boiler itself, in order to produce the greatest amount of steam with a small amount of fire.</p>
            <p>The whole is framed with wooden staves bound by iron hoops, which gives it quite the appearance of a barrel, and the reason for which I will explain shortly. The back and front bottoms, also of very strong <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">sheet iron</term>,are left free. The opening for firing the furnace is at the back, and a cranked chimney, rising sixteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> into the air, is at the front. Two safety flaps are located on top of the barrel. As there is no <term ref="gfa-keywords-8954">condenser</term>, due to lack of space to transport water and to simplify the machine, the latter is driven only by the expansion of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> which is so strong that it presses on every square <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> <pb n="144" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557651"/> with a force of sixty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term>, hence the provision of the above-mentioned wooden frame to prevent the machine from bursting.</p>
            <p>Upon close observation of its progress on the second-hand dial, I calculated the average speed of the pistons to be sixty strokes per minute for each cylinder, with a piston stroke of two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>. The tempo of the machine is such that a man walking at a brisk pace can scarcely stay abreast of it. As I had walked nearly two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> towards the wagon before encountering it, the operator invited me to board the wagon that transported the steam engine, which is fitted with benches on the sides. To oblige me, he took it in to a proverbial trot, increasing the speed of the pistons to eighty strokes per minute by producing more steam. I was much relieved <pb n="145" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557652"/> when he let up speed, however, for an explosion appeared to be immanent. The steam was whistling as if half a dozen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8588">asthmatic horses</term> were harnessed to the wagon and been driven to their last breath. It was a delight, I might add, to make my entrance into <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-03" n="140">Leeds</placeName> on this triumphant chariot of the human spirit (as I would like to call this <term ref="gfa-keywords-8623">wagon</term>).For not often have the elements been harnessed for such a purpose and with such concentrated force, in such a small space. All at the same time, twenty-three such wagons, each loaded with sixty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term> of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term>, plus the weight of the wagons themselves, made entirely of iron and each weighing ten centners, are moved along a track which at times ascends somewhat, and at the same speed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Leeds, 4 September 1814</head>
            <p>I would have left the following morning (<date when="1814-09-04">September 4</date>) if I had not wished to meet <pb n="146" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557653"/> the inventor and manufacturer of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8623">this machine</term>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7700">Murray</persName>, not suspecting at that time what an engaging and, as it turned out, useful acquaintance I would make in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">this place</placeName>. — After I had written a letter from here, which I must mark as the turning point of my journey, to a friend in the true sense of the word, I went (in the morning at <date when="1814-09-04T10:30:00">half past ten o’clock</date>) to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1787" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-04T10:30:00" n="141" cert="0"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName></placeName>, to give him my letter from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, purely in the hope of learning how best to reach Mr. Murray. Upon my arrival, I was led by a servant to Mr. Gott’s study, into which he entered from an adjoining chamber. He had hardly read through the letter when he called out to <persName ref="gfa-actors-7701">his wife</persName>, who happened to be walking past the open door, “Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName> will be so good as to stay with us <pb n="147" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557654"/> over lunch”. To me he said merely that he hoped I would not refuse the invitation, only he must inform me that on Sunday there would be a meal at one o’clock instead of four o’clock, so that the servants could attend church in the afternoon. After a brief conversation, he searched for a map of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-77">canton of Schafhausen</placeName>, which he could not immediately find. I happened to have the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8624">Helvetic Almanac of the year 1811</term> in my pocket, which contains the map and topographical description of my beloved fatherland, so that I was able to provide him with the desired information, particularly with regard to the location of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8997">iron mines</term>, about which he inquired as did Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> . I noticed something striking that I had never seen before on the windows of the room we were in, namely, all of the panes were finely polished to a matte finish and in each one were the most charming transparent drawings of ancient fi<pb n="148" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557655" break="no"/>gures, with only their outlines in fine black strokes. As I admired the beauty and virtuosity of this completely new kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9126">stained glass</term>, he led me to an upstairs room, where instead of figures there were bouquets of flowers of the most beautiful colour. “All this, he said, was done by my daughter. This work brings her great pleasure.”</p>
            <p>At lunch I met the entire, certainly very amiable <persName ref="gfa-actors-8090">family</persName> of this equally prosperous and industrious man, consisting of ten children, of whom two sons and the above-mentioned daughter, who has an equally excellent education and grace of body and mind, are already adults.</p>
            <p>I had not felt as comfortable for a long time as I did among this family, who treated me more like a relative and friend they had known for many years than like a stranger who had entered the house for the first time that day. After dinner, <pb n="149" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557656"/> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName> accompanied <persName ref="gfa-actors-7701">his wife</persName> and daughters to church, which is attended more in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> than in any other country and with genuine devotion, while the two sons accompanied me to Mr. <placeName ref="gfa-places-1804" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-04" n="142">Murray’s</placeName>. As he was out of town, I left a letter for him, and the young Messrs. Gott then took me to that part of their very large <placeName ref="gfa-places-1795" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-04" n="143">factory buildings</placeName><note>The somewhat more distant factory was <placeName ref="gfa-places-1788">Armley Mill</placeName>.</note>, some <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> apart, which contains the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8533">gas lighting</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engines</term> and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8625">dye works</term>, where all the boilers are heated by steam.</p>
            <p>The gas lighting, an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term> of our time, equally appealing to mind and eye, is quite like that of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> and was also installed by him. The two iron reservoirs also hold three thousand cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> of gas. — The wool carding machines, of which there are sixty on two floors, are just like the cot<pb n="150" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557657" break="no"/>ton <term ref="gfa-keywords-8607">carding</term> machines, only wider and double, that is, each <term ref="gfa-keywords-8916">carding machine</term> has a second one independent of it and narrower, which, where the finished carded wool comes out, has a notched cylinder of one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">foot</term> in diameter, which forms the wool into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">half-inch</term> thick and two-foot-long sausages, which can be considered the first roving. This roving is then spun on machines similar to those used for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8822">cotton</term>, but even slimmer, and finally finished into thread on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8605">mule jenny</term>. The spinning of the wool requires an extraordinary amount of oil, namely two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> for every stone or sixteen pounds. For this reason, the floor is made entirely of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, as sometimes in the summer there are “Spontaneous Inflammations”. In addition, there is a large <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire hose</term> in every room, which is <pb n="151" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557658"/> connected to the steam engine that drives the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9466">spinning</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9607">fulling mills</term> and which discharges forty-five cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term> of water every minute through a calibre of five quarters of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term>. In the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8625">dye house</term>, the heating of all the dye tanks by steam from a single furnace was the main feature that caught my attention. The device is very simple. It has the advantage that by closing a single valve further heating can be interrupted or instantly restored by opening it. It permits the use of wooden, or (as here, where <term ref="gfa-keywords-8775">lead</term> is so extremely cheap) leaded vessels, instead of copper ones and entirely eliminates a great deal of inconvenience and expense connected with the provision of so many separate hearths. Mainly, however, the savings in fuel is the most vital point and <pb n="152" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557659"/> deserves the greatest attention, for this is so important that this device was designed to be most profitable in a place where hard <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coals</term> are in inexhaustible abundance and can be had at an extremely low price. To these important advantages must be added the saving of time, in that one of the largest boilers, the contents of which are about 1800 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8618">gallons</term>, or about 250 cubic <term ref="gfa-keywords-8449">feet</term>, filled with very cold water from the reservoir, is brought to the boiling point within half an hour (which is truly astonishing) and which would be difficult to accomplish in an hour with the largest possible fire that could be placed under such a boiler. The savings in fuel amounts to a third of what would otherwise be needed if each boiler had its own source of fire.</p>
            <p>With so many strange objects, <pb n="153" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557660"/> which I had the particular good fortune to observe during my short stay in England and to become acquainted with in some cases quite thoroughly, the observation forced itself upon me that the English not only have the mind to use everything in the field of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-604">chemistry</term> and applied <term ref="gfa-keywords-9626">mathematics</term> that can be aimed at the perfection of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3246">industry</term>, but that they also have the pluck to spend very considerable sums of money on experiments, which are virtually indispensable for the production of new and useful results, especially in factory work, and to carry through with perseverance what they have started.</p>
            <p>I cannot refrain from mentioning on this occasion a remark of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>, when I spoke with him on our excursion to the large <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">ironworks</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1789">Warwikshire</placeName><note>See the journal entry for <ref type="cross" target="d_29_8">29 August</ref>. The city of <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> was in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1789">Warwickshire</placeName>, but the iron works he visited, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1694">Soho Foundry</placeName> and <placeName ref="gfa-places-1723" cert="0">Soho Manufactory</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-1756">Wilkinson’s Bradley Ironworks</placeName> and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1754">Level Ironworks</placeName>, were all located in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1330">Staffordshire</placeName> and Worcestershire.</note> about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8628">file hewing machines</term> <pb n="154" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557661"/> (the possibility of which, incidentally, the venerated mechanic admitted) and mentioned that I knew a gentleman who had already spent more than six thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term>, on it and had now abandoned the matter on account of its failure. “That is a trifle,” he replied, “I can assure you that we often spend more than that much in a single week on experiments that give us no other benefit than to know that the thing cannot be done in that way.” As astounding as this is, it is even more believable when one sees the enormity of their operations and the scope of the work carried out. — And now, to conclude, two examples of failed and successful undertakings. An acquaintance of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>, likely misled by flawed experiments, spent eighty thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term> for the facilities and procedures to make a <pb n="155" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557662"/> new kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8629">potash</term>, and, since he did not succeed and used other people’s money in addition to the above sum, is now in gaol. — Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7597">Arkwright</persName> , on the other hand, the son of the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7535">famous inventor</persName> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8517"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9467">spinning machine</term></term>, who began as a poor barber, now enjoys an annual income of one hundred thousand <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds sterling</term>, or one million <term ref="gfa-keywords-8457">guilders</term>, as owner and partner of the largest and best spinning mills in England.</p>
            <p>Among so many extraordinary and useful devices and tools adorning the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1795">manufactory of Mr. Gott</placeName>, I also noticed the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9380"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8630">hydraulic press</term></term>, which is probably still little known on the continent, but which, due to its almost infinitely multipliable force, is highly remarkable, the inventor of which is a very famous London mechanic, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7517">Bramah</persName>, to whom we also owe a particularly <pb n="156" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557663"/> effective type of <term ref="gfa-keywords-2757">fire extinguisher</term>. The principle of this press is based on the so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8631">hydrostatic paradox</term>, and when one sees the machine and the simplicity of the idea that has been implemented, one feels like the <placeName ref="gfa-places-138">Spaniards</placeName> with <persName ref="gfa-actors-7799">Columbus’</persName> egg: astonished that the thing was not invented long ago, given that something similar was known in the field of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3048">physics</term> earlier than this machine, namely the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8632">hydrostatic bellows</term>, which was invented in the nineties of the last century.</p>
            <p>Just as in the hydrostatic bellows, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8630">this press</term> also pushes upward from below, and its main components are two very powerful cylinders or <term ref="gfa-keywords-2607">pumps</term> very different in diameter, which are fitted with pistons and filled with water, where, by injecting the water from the smaller <pb n="157" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557664"/> pump, on whose <term ref="gfa-keywords-8702">piston rod</term> a relatively long lever is attached, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8591">piston</term> in the larger one pushes upward against the object to be compressed, with a force that is so much greater than the square of the diameter of the small pump, that the piston in the larger one, which acts against the object to be compressed, is pushed upwards with a force that is so much greater than the square of the diameter of the small pump is contained in the square of the diameter of the large pump, multiplied by the length of the lever on the small pump and the force applied to it. So that, for example, if the diameter of the larger pump = one <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term>, the diameter of the smaller pump = a quarter of an inch, the length of the lever fifteen inches, and the distance from the centre of motion to the point of force is two inches, and at the end of the lever a man with a force of only fifty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pounds</term> presses it down, the rising piston of the large pump acts with a force <pb n="158" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557665"/> against the object to be pressed, in this case <formula rend="inline" notation="tex">= \frac{1^2}{(1/4)^2}\times\frac{15}{2}\times50 = 120\times50 = 6000</formula> pounds or 60 <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term>. Since in this calculation all ratios are assumed to be small and could easily be increased tenfold, it is easy to see how much greater the force can be multiplied with this machine, which also has the great advantage that the friction, which only takes place at the circumference of the pistons, is incomparably less than that of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8878">screw</term>, which is used almost without exception as the mechanical force in the construction of presses.</p>
            <p>From the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1795">manufactory</placeName>, which is also located on the large <placeName ref="gfa-places-1790">canal</placeName> that connects with the four main ports of the empire, we returned <placeName ref="gfa-places-1787" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-04" n="144" cert="0">to Mr. Gott</placeName> for <term ref="gfa-keywords-9558">tea</term>. This family pleasure, so dear to the English, lasted longer than usual as it was Sunday, and I was acquainted with some in<pb n="159" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557666" break="no"/>teresting information, since Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName> and his sons have not only a worldly but also an excellent scientific education. Yet, I was to receive even further demonstrations of friendship. After tea, the daughter brought to me a frosted glass plate and the apparatus she uses to make them, and said: “Mr. Fischer, since you like this kind of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9292">painting</term> so much, I would be delighted to show you the process, which is still a secret. But I do not want you to make it known to anyone in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, as I am under the same obligation.” I not only gladly promised the kind woman, but also extended my promise to the continent and the <placeName ref="gfa-places-8">fifth part of the world</placeName>, so as not to worry her. When, sooner or later, like many things in the world, this too becomes generally <pb n="160" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557667"/> known, it will provide the natural scientist with food for thought, especially from a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8633">dioptric perspective</term>, and perhaps shed light on phenomena that have not yet been adequately explained.</p>
            <p>My <term ref="gfa-keywords-9474"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8522">yellow steel</term></term> also particularly attracted the attention of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName>, and I gave him several pieces as samples, which pleased him very much. Not only did he recognize the significance of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8637">invention</term>, but also very intelligently noted what was likely to become its most prominent use. Since I intended to take my leave of him soon (for at <date when="1814-09-04T21:00:00">nine o’clock the same evening</date> I planned to continue my travels, as I wanted to be in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> early the following morning), and he heard from me that I might also be going to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786">R.</placeName>, he said, “Then I must give you a letter of introduction to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7707">W.</persName>. His <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005"><term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">iron and steel factories</term></term> are among the largest in the kingdom, and it will be <pb n="161" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557668"/> of great interest to you to see them. Since you were introduced to me by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7568">Wedgwood</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName>, which I will mention in my letter, and since you speak English fluently, you will certainly be well received.” — After receiving the letter, I took leave of these respectable people, having written a letter of introduction to an esteemed friend in <placeName ref="gfa-places-143">Stuttgart</placeName> on behalf of the son’s prospective trip to <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germany</placeName>. Heartfelt thanks were accompanied by the wish to have the opportunity to present them in person one day.</p>
            <p>So, here in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-04T21:00:00" n="145">Leeds</placeName>, two hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term> north of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, north of <pb n="162" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557669"/> auspicious signs good fortune had already afforded me on the crossing to these white shores of <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">Albion</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Off rolled the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">coach</term>, and inasmuch as a sleeping party of travellers is not a very entertaining one, there is not much to be said of it. Absorbed in reflection on the extraordinary phenomena of the day, I was glad, after having drunk a glass of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">ale</term> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1791" type="itinerar" n="146">Wakefield</placeName> (where the coach stopped a while) in honour of its vicar, to be able to rest a while longer in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-05T02:30:00" n="147">Sheffield</placeName>, where I arrived on the <date when="1814-09-05T02:30:00">5th</date> in the morning at half past two.</p>
         </div>           
         <div type="day">
            <head>Sheffield and Rotherham, 5 September 1814</head>
            <p>On <date when="1814-09-05">September 5th</date>, immediately after breakfast, I decided to go to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786" type="itinerar" when="1814-08-05" n="148">R.</placeName>, six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, to deliver to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7707">W.</persName> my letter of introduction from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7697">Gott</persName> and there to learn the addresses of the best cast steel manufacturers, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9110">file cutters</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlers</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9622">toolmakers</term>. <pb n="163" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557670"/> When I arrived at the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1798" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-05T12:00:00" n="149">factory</placeName> near R. after twelve o’clock, I was very politely directed by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7705" type="met">W.</persName><note>The person in question may be <persName ref="gfa-actors-7707">Joshua Walker</persName> (1750–1815).</note>, who seemed extraordinarily busy and nearly to the point of being overtaxed (which Mr. Gott had also foretold to me), to his principal agent Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7796">Clarke</persName>, to whom he said, “Please note that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName> is recommended by Mr. Gott through Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7607">Lee</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-471">Manchester</placeName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1693">Soho</placeName>”. — As I had expressed my wish to become acquainted with cast steel manufacturers, I was puzzled when he said to me, “I will take you to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7717">B.</persName><note>Possibly another member of the Booth family.</note>, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7705">W.’s</persName> associate. No one manufactures <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> on so large a scale as we do, and you can obtain all the information you need about price and quality from him.” — After Mr. Clarke had left us, Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7717" type="met">B.</persName> immediately took me to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9498">steel depots</term>, which contained perhaps a thousand <pb n="164" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557671"/> <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term> of cement steel, and showed me the different sorts, namely hard and soft, and also what the English call “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8668">German-Steel</term>”, which is made from bars of “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">Blister-Steel</term>”, having too large bubbles to be suitable for good work. These are welded together and then drawn. He did not have much <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> in stock at all, though what was forged of it had a much better breaking point and grain than that of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8298">P. et Comp</orgName>, in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName><note>See Fischer’s visit to the cast steel plant of P. on 30 August 1814.</note>. The cast bars, which looked and weighed the same as those in Birmingham, exhibited an exceptionally large number of holes along the broken edge and were swollen, which gave me sufficient information about the process of their production.</p>
            <p>Eager to see the cement- and cast-steel manufactory and knowing the proper way to express this wish, <pb n="165" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557672"/> Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7717">B.</persName>, who had already returned with me to the counting-room, went back again and showed me the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8904">burning furnaces</term>, which are set up with three boxes in the usual manner. “The <placeName ref="gfa-places-1797" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-05" n="150">cast-steel manufactory</placeName>,” he said, “is at a different location, but <emph rend="italic">‘if you please’</emph>, we will go there.” I did not doubt for a moment that this would be the place I had thought it to be on my way to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7705">W.’s</persName> and that I had recognized it quite rightly from the bits of old <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> lying around outside the mill. Sure enough, it was. Nowadays, one did not <term ref="gfa-keywords-8634">cast but make crucibles</term>, which I was very nearly compelled to do myself. Since I had never seen their method, nor they mine, I was astonished that people could choose precisely the same means to achieve the same end.</p>
            <p><pb n="166" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557673"/> While their method has the advantage of producing a crucible more quickly, mine has the advantage of better workmanship, for I saw by the amount of <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">run-out</term>on the ground that many of their crucibles had cracked. — In twelve individual <term ref="gfa-keywords-9624">blast furnaces</term>, heated with <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">cokes</term>, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term>, broken into pieces and mixed with the proper additives, is melted and poured into iron casts. They have as little mastery of the art of smooth casting as I have, or even less, and I was reluctant to ask what they did with all the various scrap steel. However, I inferred as much from a later statement by Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7796">Clarke</persName>, who told me that they sold the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> at a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8443">shilling</term> a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8511">pound</term>, and and some at a six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8463">pence</term>. As Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">B.</persName> had promised to furnish me with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8564">price list</term> of the various sorts of steel and their appli<pb n="167" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557674" break="no"/>cation, he brought me back <persName ref="gfa-actors-7796"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1798" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-05" n="151">to Mr. Clarke</placeName></persName>. “Would you not like to see how we make our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8638">tinplate</term> while Mr. B. finishes the list?” asked Mr. Clarke. I was delighted to do so, and we passed by an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8796">anchor forge</term> belonging to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1798">this manufactory</placeName>, which was large beyond all imagining, to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8843">tin works</term>, a quarter of an hour away. “The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8647">cannon foundry</term> is also immediately adjacent,” remarked Mr. Clarke, “and we should be just in time for the casting of six pieces. Should it be too late, however, and you wish to remain here, you may see it again tomorrow at eleven o’clock.” — So, we proceeded first to the sheet-metal factory. A detailed description of the same is all the more important, as it probably contains details little known on the continent and illustrates why the English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">sheet metal</term> does not <pb n="168" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557675"/> have a so-called lustre but is otherwise so beautiful.</p>
            <p>The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term>, forged to a thickness of three quarters of an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term>, is cut to the same length as the plates are to be wide, heated in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealing furnace</term>, and then rolled out under <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">ten-inch-thick</term> cast and, as Mr. Clarke expressly told me, “case hardened” rollers. When the plates begin to grow thin, they are double and then quadruple folded, giving them twice the length and corresponding width of a single sheet and, thus, yielding eight pieces when cut. — These sheets, cut on all four sides following an iron model, are dipped in “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9416">Muriatic acid</term>”, partially bent together so as to stand up at the edges, and then very gently annealed in an <term ref="gfa-keywords-3040">annealing furnace</term> once the Muriatic acid has dried. <pb n="169" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557676"/> When they are barely <term ref="gfa-keywords-8563">brown</term>, they are taken out, at which point the scale is removed with a light tap, and what does not fall off is removed with a brush. These cleaned sheets pass under a well-polished and well-hardened <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">rolling mill</term> to become hard and smooth, and from there into the clay and (diluted) <term ref="gfa-keywords-9604"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8640">vitriolic acid pickling</term></term>. Once they are removed from there, they are taken to the first tin pot, where they are placed in a pan filled with English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8706">tin</term>, which is covered with oil at all times. When the tin is heated to a fairly high temperature, which can be recognized by the yellow colour of the emerging sheets, they undergo the first <term ref="gfa-keywords-8641">tin plating</term>. From there, they are transferred to the second <term ref="gfa-keywords-9640">tin pot</term>, which is also heavily covered with oil, but not as hot. After immersion, the sheet is rubbed with a brush on <pb n="170" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557677"/> both sides, immersed again and then placed on a rack with one of the corners at the bottom so that the tin can collect and drip. While the tin is still liquid, another person takes the sheet and rinses it in a pan filled with boiling oil, whereby all excess tin runs off, and herein lies the mystery as to why the English sheets have no lustre. From this pan, the sheet is tossed into a pile of clay, with which it is rubbed on both sides, by three different people. The clay is also changed often.</p>
            <p>Though I did not have time to watch the procedure any longer than the present description required, I do not believe I have overlooked anything essential. The subsequent packing <pb n="171" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557678"/> is done in small boxes of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8993">sheet iron</term>, each containing 250 pieces.</p>
            <p>We were too late for the casting of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-1787">cannons</term>, which had been completed an hour before our arrival. The quantity of them lying about gave me every indication of the ease and safety of their manufacture, and the strength of the borings, some of which I asked to take with me, were proof of the rapidity with which this work is done. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7723" type="met">Yeates</persName>, Director of the foundry, who joined us, showed me around the workshops, where, in addition to two <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnaces</term> driven by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8933">cylinder blowers</term>, there are six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberating furnaces</term> and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9170">hand-operated melting furnace</term>. One of the reverberating furnaces is remarkable for its placement. Attached to the side of the blast furnace and at a lower level, it draws the required iron from the blast furnace and keeps it in a liquid state so that it can be <pb n="172" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557679"/> scooped out with a ladle as required. A <term ref="gfa-keywords-8644">wheel and axle</term> for a <term ref="gfa-keywords-2988">water mill</term> cast with a continuous cavity in the middle (which is very useful, as it reduces weight without compromising durability) had just been removed from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8705">casting pit</term>. There was defect in the casting, which made some workers upset. The cause was the obstructed exit of the air. I was very intrigued by the core rod. It was surrounded by long <term ref="gfa-keywords-8645">knob-iron</term>, which formed a bundle, then wrapped with the usual wreaths of straw. This device made it incredibly easy to extract the core rod, which is otherwise quite difficult.</p>
            <p>As the casting of two twenty-four-pounders, each weighing sixty <term ref="gfa-keywords-8451">centners</term> including the overpour, was prepared for the following morning, I decided to stay in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786">R.</placeName> <pb n="173" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557680"/> and return the next day at the appointed time to witness it. Consequently, I intended to take my leave, but Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7723">Yeates</persName> invited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7796">Clarke</persName> and me to lunch, at the same time giving instructions that the morning pour was not to proceed until I was present. Here, as everywhere else, I encountered not only gracious hospitality, but was also afforded the opportunity to obtain important information about <term ref="gfa-keywords-9005">iron</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-2707">steel works operations</term> on request.</p>
            <p>The description I gave the ladies who were present (Madame Yeates and her daughter, and the wife of young Mr. Yeates) of <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">my hometown</placeName> and its surroundings, and which I was able to illustrate in part by means of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8624">almanac</term> I had with me, put me in great favour, as did, in my opinion, the following <pb n="174" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557681"/> circumstance, of which I speak here only because it appears to be a sign of the times, or rather a characteristic of the prevailing ideas in a nation. Wherever I became known in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> and, in turn, somewhat familiar through conversation, I was asked about the prevailing <term ref="gfa-keywords-9401">religion</term> of my hometown, and as soon as people learned it was <term ref="gfa-keywords-9385">Protestant</term>, a greater affection seemed to set in. One should not be surprised at this phenomenon, considering the history of England, both ancient and contemporary, and, while the English government has the most liberal principles regarding freedom of thought and belief, individual opinion and concern can guide even the most enlightened of men in his feelings. Though it is a departure, perhaps the re<pb n="175" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557682" break="no"/>mark I had occasion to make in <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> is not entirely out of place: that a newly emerged vision of the Last Judgment, such as a Father <persName ref="gfa-actors-7724">Abraham a Sancta Clara</persName> or some exalted Dominican monk may have dreamed, attracted the multitude excellently and persistently; also the devils with their devices and the same application played a far more interesting role than the somewhat ill-designed angels, who showed the way to the New Jerusalem, which, however, was so narrow that not even man and woman could walk side by side on it. — Mr. Clarke accompanied me to my apartment in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-05" n="152">R.</placeName> that same evening, where, being well known there, he singled me out for special attention.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Cannon casting at the Walker works, 6 September 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786"><date when="1814-09-06T08:00:00">6th</date></placeName> at eight o’clock, I went with Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7796">Clarke</persName> by invitation <pb n="176" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557683"/> to young Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7723">Yeates’</persName> for breakfast and afterwards to see the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9053">refining hearth</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9245">rolling </term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9440">cutting mills</term> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1798" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-06" n="153">this great manufactory</placeName>. The process in the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9387">Puddling-Furnace</term>” was as I have already described, only with the difference that the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8539">Lumps</term>” were not hammered but <term ref="gfa-keywords-3621">rolled under a large mill</term>, where they were pressed into plates about half an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inch</term> thick, immediately cooled in water. Thereafter, again they were broken into pieces to be welded together in the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8849">Blooming-Furnace</term>” and worked into the required sizes under the rolling and cutting mills. The efficient method of making <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">sheet metal chips</term> and small <term ref="gfa-keywords-2965">scrap iron</term> and producing <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bars of iron</term> from them, also warrants a description as part of the manufactory’s work. These debris of old iron are piled by <term ref="gfa-keywords-9213">children</term>, with ex<pb n="177" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557684" break="no"/>cellent skill acquired through repeated practice, on a round bed of refractory <term ref="gfa-keywords-8773">clay</term> about ten <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> in diameter and one and a half inches thick. It is then exposed to the highest temperature in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8480">reverberating furnace</term>, where the iron settles and is completely welded together in the furnace itself by means of compression with a crowbar, after which it is also processed under the rollers into <term ref="gfa-keywords-8509">bars</term> or rods.</p>
            <p>The time had come to leave for the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8647">cannon foundry</term>, where everything had already been prepared for casting when we arrived. When the admittedly clever French foundryman <persName ref="gfa-actors-7726">Dardein</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-470">Strasbourg</placeName>, in his work <term ref="gfa-keywords-8648"><emph rend="italic">sur les différentes methodes de couler les bouches à feu</emph></term>, calls the English method of casting <term ref="gfa-keywords-8717">cannons</term> in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-3055">sand</term> a <emph rend="italic">perfidious method</emph>, it was either sheer flattery, thinking that he would win <pb n="178" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557685"/> <persName ref="gfa-actors-7486">Napoleon’s</persName> approval for his own work by this description, or he was entirely ignorant of the matter as it was. For, certainly, nothing better and simpler can be devised, of which the most valid proof is that, in addition to the quality of the canon, by means of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8649">sand moulding</term> (all other things being equal) as much is accomplished in a day as by <term ref="gfa-keywords-8649">clay moulding</term> in a month. These sand moulds of the cannons, which are made in four circular cast iron bottles somewhat similar to their outer circumference over cut wooden or hollow metal models, are only dried afterwards and then screwed onto each other, do not require damming or costly binding with iron rails, but are only placed upright in the walled <term ref="gfa-keywords-8705">dam pit</term> and secured on three sides so that they do not fall over.  An iron trough filled with sand, which runs from the con<pb n="179" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557686" break="no"/>fluence of the conduits of the two furnaces up to the mould of the cannon, feeds the molten iron to the latter, which is first held back and allowed to swell by a shovel extended into the trough until it has been cleared of the impurities floating on top. The cannon, freed from the easily removable sand that sticks to it, is taken to the adjacent <term ref="gfa-keywords-8398">drilling workshop</term>, which is similar to all the others, where the overpour, which is not nearly as extensive as with metal cannons, is then turned and drilled in the same facility with a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9158">point drill</term> and finished with the polisher. A single man carries out this work, which always entails six pieces at a time, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term> rotates them. The same worker transports the heaviest <pb n="180" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557687"/> pieces in and out of the storeroom and in and out of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8854">drilling workshop</term> by means of pulleys still connected to the gears. These various devices have made it possible for a job that once required the best brains and the most skilful hands to accomplish to be reduced to a common labourer’s day job, and the preparatory arrangements make success inevitable.</p>
            <p>Adjacent to the drilling workshop are large stocks of <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">ore</term>, some of which is <term ref="gfa-keywords-8652">unfired</term>, some of which is on grate piles, and some of which is already fired and ready to be fed into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-288">blast furnaces</term>. The ore is a low-grade <term ref="gfa-keywords-8653">clay ironstone</term>, containing frequent imprints of plants, especially <term ref="gfa-keywords-9599">Valeriana</term>. To get reasonably good iron and a better yield, an excellent <term ref="gfa-keywords-8654">hematite</term> from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1773">Cornwallis</placeName> is added.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="day">
            <head>Visits to factories in Sheffield, 6 September 1814</head>
            <p>The time had come for my <placeName ref="gfa-places-1786">departure</placeName>. Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7723">Yeates’</persName> atten<pb n="181" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557688" break="no"/>tiveness went so far as to have a saddled horse waiting for me at the door and a second brought for him, so that he might accompany me, as he said, to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> and, there, introduce me to someone who would not only show me the best <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">file</term> and tool, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razor</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8660">penknife</term>, shear and saw factories, but who would himself take me everywhere. As gratifying as this was for me, I was almost embarrassed by so much kindness, as I could only express my gratitude in words. To avoid a longer route, we rode through the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1668">River Don</placeName>, which had almost no water this time due to a general drought, and after an hour we were already in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-06" n="154">Sheffield</placeName>. There, Mr. Yeates entrusted me to Mr. R., a very fine young man, who works in the Sheffield office of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706">W. et B.</orgName>—</p>
            <p><pb n="182" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557689"/> My greatest desire was to visit a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8892">file factory</term>. Mr. R. took me to <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7708">that</orgName> of Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7788" type="met">Bramale</persName>, “<placeName ref="gfa-places-1799" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-06" n="155">at the Whitehouse</placeName>”, two <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">miles</term> from the city. After I had purchased eighty different exemplars from four to fifteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term> and three types of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">cut</term>, as well as “a set of <term ref="gfa-keywords-3153">turning tools</term>”, and had received a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8564">price list</term> of all his products, I asked, after having taken my leave, whether one might not also see how these files are made? We generally believe that they are made by machines. “In a moment, I will show you the opposite,” replied Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7788" type="met">Bramall</persName><note>The person in question may be either George or Daniel Bramall.</note>, and led me into the workshop. I found everyone there busy <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">forging</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8626">hammering</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term>, just as they were at <persName ref="gfa-actors-7608">P.’s</persName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName><note>See Fischer’s visit to P.’s file manufactory on 31 August 1814.</note>, only the work seemed better to me, as each worker only hammers the same <term ref="gfa-keywords-8627">cut</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> of roughly similar sizes. <pb n="183" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557690"/> There are also many files made of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, which are a third more expensive than those made of ordinary <term ref="gfa-keywords-8516">cement steel</term>. — During <term ref="gfa-keywords-8561">hardening</term>, which is always done by the same people, I noticed a difference from <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName> in that the file was first dipped in the adhesive and then rolled in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8562">hardening powder</term>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8657">dies</term> for triangular and semicircular files warrant particular remark, as well. They have no handle pins, as ours do, which always break off or cause the perpetual jiggling of the tool; nor are they made (which is better, but more costly) on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8658">anvils</term> themselves, but are inserted into dovetail-shaped cuts in the anvil, so that they hold fast and yet can be easily removed. As the English semicircular and triangular <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> do not taper from <pb n="184" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557691"/> back to front, but only from the middle, which is very sensible, and the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8657">dies</term> are not perfectly flat in the direction of their length, but rather somewhat convex in their trajectory towards the back, it is possible to forge the file entirely in one and the same die, which, moreover, always has a length of five to six <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>. In our country, by contrast, one and the same file always requires two to three different cuts or dies.</p>
            <p>I collected <term ref="gfa-keywords-8660">penknives</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8661">scissors</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> by the half-dozen and dozen from three different manufacturers, each of which produces all three articles, but as Mr. R. informed me, each only excels in one. The razors appeared to me better and less expensive than the French by comparison, but the penknives and scissors were costlier and not as tasteful.—</p>
            <p><pb n="185" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557692"/> From a saw manufacturer, I purchased <term ref="gfa-keywords-8662">circular saws</term> not yet known in our country, but extremely useful for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8976">woodturners</term>. They are manufactured in diameters of fifteen to eighteen <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">inches</term>. Any <term ref="gfa-keywords-2887">lathe</term> on which they can be mounted by means of the square holes in the centre is suitable for their use. I bought ordinary saw blades and foxtails only to have a terminus comparationis, for <persName ref="gfa-actors-7728">David Mathis</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1840">Ober-Oenz</placeName> in the <placeName ref="gfa-places-161">canton of Bern</placeName> makes them of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> of such quality that others can hardly equal them.</p>
            <p>There remained the tool factory to visit, which unfortunately had little stock in its storeroom. A neat <term ref="gfa-keywords-9623">twist drill</term> with two different inserts, a few dozen other <term ref="gfa-keywords-8663">drills</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8664"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9182"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9048">hollow and flat chisels</term></term></term> and so-<pb n="186" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557693" break="no"/>called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8665">English or <term ref="gfa-keywords-9179">double-plane irons</term></term> were all I could acquire. I selected everything from <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, though the manufacturer tried to get me to take the same sort made from ordinary steel. To show me what other kinds of tools he made, he brought a book with about three and a half hundred drawings of them in their original size and proportion. I asked him if he had more copies of this book and how much he sold it for, but he would not hear of it. At last, after a good deal of back and forth, and mainly out of courtesy to Mr. R., who was very much in favour of it, I obtained a copy at a rather moderate price. I consider this acquisition one of the most significant of those I made in England. Concerned that he might regret letting me have it and fearful of lo<pb n="187" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557694" break="no"/>sing it, I packed everything up and carried it to my apartment myself, although he repeatedly offered to have it brought there by one of his people. After unloading, I went with Mr. R. to Fontin-House to bid farewell to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7723">Yeates</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7717">B.</persName>, who had also arrived and brought a list of his steel prices.</p>
         </div>        
         <div>
            <head>Making the acquaintance of Francis Huntsman, 6 September 1814</head>
            <p>In <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName>, as well as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">R.</placeName> I had now seen everything. To carry out my plan to its fullest, however, I would have liked to see <placeName ref="gfa-places-1805" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-06" n="161">H—s cast steel manufactory</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1806" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-06" n="160">A.</placeName>, yet I was doubtful of the possibility, as I had a small order, but absolutely no introduction, and would not want to make use of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7717"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7705">W. et B.</persName></persName></orgName>, as they were competitors. Relying on my good fortune, I set out that same evening <pb n="188" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557695"/> so as not to lose any time. Much to my surprise, I had some trouble inquiring about the apartment of <persName ref="gfa-actors-7729">H—n</persName>, which, when I finally arrived, did not conform to my expectations. When I entered the room on the ground level, I found there a woman with a small child and two men smoking <term ref="gfa-keywords-9072">tobacco</term>. Uncertain whether I was in the right place, I inquired after Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540" type="met">H—n</persName>. “It is I myself,” replied one of these gentlemen: “What is it you want?” — I replied: “As I have been commissioned by my friend, Mr. D. Z. in W—r, whom you most likely also know, to purchase thin, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8994">cast-steel wire</term></term> on my way through <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265">Sheffield</placeName> I believe I can get it nowhere better than from you. It will also please Mr. D. Z. to receive news of you, as I believe you yourself once <pb n="189" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557696"/> spent some time in W—r.” — “That was my brother,” he said, “but he is no longer alive. I will show you the steel in the storeroom.” With these words he led me through the adjoining kitchen into a small courtyard, where the open smelting house was located, and where one of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-90">furnaces</term> was still glowing inside from the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8696">smelting</term> that had been recently completed. “This is where we make our <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">steel</term>,” he said, as his second brother joined us, standing in silence. As I had no occasion to leave, I examined the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucibles</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8666">furnaces</term> more closely to find they were of the same sort as those of Messrs. <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706">W. et B.</orgName>, or rather more likely that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7702">H—n</persName>, who founded the first factory of this type, had served as a model for them, just as perhaps some of his workers had gone elsewhere. At the same time, however, <pb n="190" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557697"/> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-336">slag</term> made it clear to me that <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">H—n</persName> had been able to keep his additive a secret, and that his steel and mine thus share a property not common to any other, and that neither <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7706">W. et B.</orgName> or the so-called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8667">Marshal steel</term>, nor that of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8298">P. et C.</orgName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-20">Birmingham</placeName>, could match it. There was a great deal of steel in the storeroom, especially rolled <term ref="gfa-keywords-8639">sheets</term>. I requested a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8564">price list</term> from Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">H—n</persName> for his steel, which he considers to be on average twenty-five percent more expensive than the other manufacturers. Once he had produced it, he showed me samples corresponding to the numbers, in <term ref="gfa-keywords-8460">four-inch</term> bars, all stamped with his name, from the thinnest round, flat, or square, to the thickest of the same type. I asked him if I might be allowed to purchase them. He was initially reluctant to do so, until I said <pb n="191" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557698"/> that I would like to have these samples to complement the small <term ref="gfa-keywords-8656">files</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8556">chisels</term> I had also purchased from him, at which point he finally permitted me to have them, though I was obliged to pay a relatively high price.</p>
            <p>I had, now, achieved all that I had set out to accomplish on my journey. The principal benefit of the above circumstances was not great for me, as I must always <term ref="gfa-keywords-2759">forge</term> the <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term> according to the dimensions requested. Nevertheless, the visit had flattered my ego, for I had put it into my head once never to leave a place without having accomplished something. My reverie in this success was soon disrupted, however, by a moment of some distress. — “Will you,” said  <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">H—n</persName>, as I was already at the door and taking my leave, “tell me your name?” Simultaneously, he handed me a pen and paper. It flashed through <pb n="192" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557699"/> my mind that he might have already heard of me, and that my visit and stay might be unpleasant for him were he to discover my identity. Still, I thought: you have never denied your name, and you shall not do so now, and so I wrote on the paper: <emph rend="italic"><persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Johann Konrad Fischer</persName> von <placeName ref="gfa-places-131">Schafhausen</placeName></emph>. He took the sheet, read it and said, “I know that name. It is the name of a <placeName ref="gfa-places-1967">steel manufacturer</placeName> in <placeName ref="gfa-places-134">Switzerland</placeName>.” — I replied with composure, “I believe so, as well, but how do you know this, if I may ask?” — “Read this letter,” he said, opening a drawer, “It was written to my deceased <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703">father</persName>.” — The letter was from the, now, likewise deceased Mr. v. K—s of W., who had known the <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703">old H—n</persName> well, and contained a proposal that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703">H—n</persName> send two of his best workers, equipped with the necessary knowledge, <pb n="193" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557700"/> to W. in order to work there in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9519">cast steel manufactory</term> he hoped to build with him at joint expense. To allay any fears, he also said, in case he was afraid of sharing his secret with anyone else, he would only have to tell him that a certain Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-35">Fischer</persName> had already been producing <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term> of excellent quality for several years with great success, and that he would thus have a competitor, in any case.</p>
            <p>I returned the letter to Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7540">H—n</persName> asking why his <persName ref="gfa-actors-7703">father</persName> had not accepted the proposal. — He stated the reasons and, without questioning me further as to whether I was that same person, very kindly invited me to lunch the following day. I was compelled to decline, however, as I had already taken a seat on the “<term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">Mail-Coatch</term>” (in the event that one was still free) arriving that night from <placeName ref="gfa-places-1745">Liverpool</placeName> <pb n="194" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557701"/> and bound for <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>. His brother, meanwhile, still had the courtesy to accompany me to a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutler</term>, for I wished to have some very good <term ref="gfa-keywords-8660">penknives</term> of his <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel</term>, so that I could compare them with others.</p>
            <p>Night had fallen by the time I returned to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1265" type="itinerar" n="163">Sheffield</placeName>. I did not go to bed, for I had enough to do to pack the things I had bought and to recount the day’s events.</p>
         </div> 
         <div>
            <head>Return to London, 7-8 September 1814</head>
            <p>On the <date when="1814-09-07T02:00:00">7th</date> in the morning at two o’clock the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9291">coach</term> arrived, staying only a few minutes. To my greatest annoyance, because it was raining, I was obliged to take a seat on the roof, as everything inside was already occupied. This inconvenient circumstance lasted until <placeName ref="gfa-places-1807" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-07" n="164">Nottingham</placeName>, where I was given a place inside the coach. In good <pb n="195" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557702"/> weather, sitting outside is pleasant and costs nearly half as much; however, it is extremely dangerous if you have the misfortune to overturn, which happens not infrequently when traveling at such high speed.</p>
            <p>In the small but charming town of <placeName ref="gfa-places-11" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-07" n="165">Bedford</placeName>, we briefly witnessed an evening ball, which took place in the local <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">inn</term> to conclude the day’s festivities (occasioned by a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8922">cockfight</term> and a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9361">horse race</term>), which are so important to the English). Many very beautiful women (as one is accustomed to seeing everywhere in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>) were present, and my traveling companion, Mr. Farrar from <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, regretted, as did I, that the coachman’s tinny trombone so quickly admonished us to depart. — We were joined, but only as far as the next stage, by a “<term ref="gfa-keywords-8930">Country-Squire</term>” who had <pb n="196" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557703"/> attended the honourable cock-fighting and horse-racing events and had got himself an honest stich. In a tirade of oaths and curses concerning that “damn’d Jade” on whom he had wagered, he told us that he had lost “a cool hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8410">pounds</term>” and yet the “Odds” had always been in his favour until towards the end, when the said Jade (the horse’s nickname) lost her breath and was “beaten” by the other horse. After releasing this heartfelt tension, he began to snore and, in this state, was pushed out of the coach at the next stage. Meanwhile, the pitch-dark night soon induced us to the same diversion, which we continued until the <date when="1814-09-08">morning</date> (of the 8th), when we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-08T04:00:00" n="166">London</placeName> at daybreak, and thus in twenty-six <pb n="197" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557704"/> hours (including the stop on the way) had covered one hundred and sixty-five <term ref="gfa-keywords-8445">English miles</term>. — This day passed with the purchase and packing of various things, during which I only had the opportunity to make some inquiries about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8669">home brewing</term>, which is now quite common in England and perhaps just as useful for other countries (especially those that do not grow wine). I was drawn to this subject by a remark that not only has home brewing been introduced in the richest and middle-class households, but that “home brew’d <term ref="gfa-keywords-8829">beer</term>” also tasted better and was certainly healthier than that brewed in public houses, of which the worker and common man always demand that it be “heady”, for which purpose, not infrequently, <pb n="198" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557705"/> injurious and narcotic ingredients are mixed in. — The result of my research was that the beer brewed at home costs only a little more than half of what one would be required to pay for it at the brewer’s, although, in addition to <term ref="gfa-keywords-9293">malt</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-9186">hops</term>, various drugs are added to make the beer pleasant and long-lasting, among which sugar plays a major role, which, of course, is not so expensive in England, but must be specially prepared for this purpose.</p>
            <p>The malt itself (for brewing in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> is divided into two special trades: malt making and beer boiling) is bought from the “Malster (malt maker)” for each occasion, and more or less dried, depending on whether one prefers a lighter or darker shade of beer, in larger or smaller portions.</p>
            <p><pb n="199" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557706"/> On the <date when="1814-09-09">9th</date>, I reserved a place in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>, took leave of my friends<note>One of these friends was <persName ref="gfa-actors-7709" type="met">Timothy Brown sen.</persName></note> and devoted the remaining time to inquiries about an object which, although of interest to only a few people, is still little known on the continent, although it was invented in England in the <date from="1740" to="1749">forties of the last century</date>. It is the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8670">browning</term> of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8643">copper</term>, which is used especially for tea machinery and other luxury equipment, because it not only makes the colour more striking, but also prevents the copper from tarnishing (which, even if it is brightly polished, always happens with time and sometimes very quickly). — Here, I confirmed what I had already learned from my own earlier experiments that the type of <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coal</term> used and the vapours <pb n="200" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557707"/> it emits contribute greatly to obtaining a beautiful colour, which, however, is subject to various gradations, depending on the powder applied and the degree of heat. That the process is based on an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8671">Oxidationsprozesse</term> of the surface and not on a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8490">coating</term> of varnish or lacquer, as some believe, hardly warrants mention.</p>
         </div>            
         <div xml:id="TB2_p_203">
            <head>Return to France, 10–12 September 1814</head>
            <p>On the morning of the <date when="1814-09-10T07:00:00">10th</date> at seven o’clock, I left <placeName ref="gfa-places-89" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-10T07:00:00" n="167">London</placeName> for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName>. In addition to a woman, there were five gentlemen in the coach, among them a <placeName ref="gfa-places-148">Turk</placeName> in his national dress. He did not understand the least bit of English or French. As a ridiculous yet necessary precaution, the house in <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName>, to which he had been recommended, had pinned an open bill of lading, as if to a box, to his outer garment and addressed it to his correspondents in Dover, requesting that they arrange <pb n="201" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557708"/> for his passage and send him to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118">Paris</placeName> in the same way. The man was a great nuisance to us, for not only was he dressed so thickly as to take the space of two persons, but he had a bundle of provisions on his lap, of which he partook from time to time, and which consisted of almonds and grapes, a green onion plant and small red sea-crabs, which gave off such an odour as if the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1865">Fleet-Market</placeName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-89">London</placeName> were at our heels the entire way. To this was added the smoking of tobacco, which only by force could be prohibited in that the “Guard”, or Conducteur confiscated the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9243">pipe</term> from him. — Since one of the springs on the coach broke underway, the coach had to be repacked in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1610" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-10" n="168">Canterbury</placeName>, so that we did not arrive in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-10T20:00:00" n="169">Dover</placeName> until eight o’clock in the <date when="1814-09-10T20:00:00">evening</date>, where I returned to my accustomed <pb n="202" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557709"/> inn, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1609" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-10" n="170">Paris-Hotel</placeName>, Mr. Kiriker, which deserves to be recommended to every traveller for its good and affordable service, though the Ship-lnn has a more elegant exterior.</p>
            <p>A storm was raging, and the ship’s captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7853">John Hayward</persName> of the parcel boat Elisabeth, who was also there, announced in advance that he would have difficulty setting sail the next day.</p>
            <p>In the event of better weather, I went to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-2153" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-11" n="170.1">customs house</placeName> early on the <date when="1814-09-11">12th</date><note>The date was 11 September 1814.</note> before the beginning of church service to have my things inspected and obtain a permit for departure. As it was Sunday, I again encountered difficulties, which I resolved in the same way as before. Since I was still alone with the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9301">customs officer</term> , he engaged me in a conversation asking, <pb n="203" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557710"/> among other things, about the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9401">religion</term> of my country. I answered that it was the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9385">Protestant religion</term>. “So!” he continued, “English missionaries will certainly come from time to time to preach in your country.” I had to laugh at this gross ignorance, in which he put us more or less on a par with the inhabitants of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1866">Otaheite</placeName>, without being very surprised about it, as in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>, with regard to the knowledge of foreign countries, one notices similar violations in more educated persons. I replied: Of course, many missionaries from England come to us, mostly in coaches with four horses; however, they never inquire about the church, but rather always about the best <term ref="gfa-keywords-9234">tavern</term>. — This answer amused him and, after receiving an explanation, he began to understand that the preaching <pb n="204" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557711"/> of the Gospel in our country was not as bad as he had imagined.</p>
            <p>The <persName ref="gfa-actors-8310">wind god</persName> was relentless this day, so there was no thought of departure. This initially unpleasant circumstance turned in my favour, however. I had taken a small sack filled with <term ref="gfa-keywords-316">iron ores</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8532">crucible fragments</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-613">steel samples</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8474">coals</term>, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8551">cokes</term> and especially samples of English <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> of the best and worst quality with me into the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term>. Unbeknownst to me, this was forgotten in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1610">Canterbury</placeName> during repacking, and it was not until <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608">Dover</placeName> that I discovered it missing and lamented my misfortune to the innkeepers. “Don’t worry,” they said, “if your sack was in the coach, you will have it this evening or tomorrow morning”, and immediately dispatched to the post office to report it to all the places where the coach had stopped and <pb n="205" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557712"/> made deliveries. That very evening the daughter came to my room, and to my astonishment and delight exclaimed: <emph rend="italic">“Sir! Your bay is come!”</emph> I immediately went down to receive it myself, fearing that it might get lost again. To the credit of the English <term ref="gfa-keywords-3355">postal system</term>, I must say that not only did it not cost me a penny to get this sack, but that my inquiry was addressed with the greatest alacrity. — I would not have liked to lose this sack, mainly for the sake of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8672">iron</term> samples that Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7572">Watt</persName> had given me, since, in response to his remark that English iron was not suitable for steelmaking and that many attempts had therefore already been made, I determined to attempt to solve the problem in my own way <pb n="206" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557713"/> once I had returned home.</p>
            <p>On the <date when="1814-09-12">12th</date>, the storm had subsided entirely during the night. A fresh but perfectly favourable wind continued to blow. The <placeName ref="gfa-places-2005">sea</placeName>, however, was rough. In the <date when="1814-09-12T08:00:00">morning</date> at eight o’clock we <placeName ref="gfa-places-1608" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-12T08:00:00" n="171">embarked</placeName>. I noted with pleasure the calm command of the captain and the quiet obedience of his crew. Like a bird, the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9747">ship</term> cut through the dark blue waves, which seem to roll out of the sea with foam on their crests. I gazed intently at the curious island from which I had only just departed, and, as its white shores faded from my view in the vicinity of <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>, bid it farewell (hopefully not forever).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Final visits in Paris, 12–17 September 1814</head>
            <p>At eleven o’clock and twenty minutes of <pb n="207" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557714"/> the same <date when="1814-09-12T11:20:00">morning</date>, we disembarked safely at <placeName ref="gfa-places-1607" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-12" n="172">Calais</placeName> after a crossing of not quite four and a half hours. We had to wait until eight o’clock in the <date when="1814-09-12T20:00:00-01:00">evening</date> (for what reason I do not know) for the departure of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> which brought us to <placeName ref="gfa-places-1808" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-13T12:00:00-01:00" n="174">Abbeville</placeName> on the <date when="1814-09-13T12:00:00-01:00">13th</date> at noon and to <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" when="1814-09-14T15:00:00-01:00" n="175">Paris</placeName> on the <date when="1814-09-14">14th</date> in the afternoon at three o’clock.</p>
            <p>I would have continued my journey immediately had not all the seats in the outbound diligences and courier coaches already been reserved until the <date to="1814-09-17" from="1814-09-14">18th</date>. — On the <date when="1814-09-15">15th</date>, I visited Mr. <persName ref="gfa-actors-7624">Gingembre</persName>, Director of the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1602" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-15" n="176">Royal Mint</placeName>, again, whom I delighted with my report on the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8673">steam engine without a condenser</term> that I had seen in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1760">Leeds</placeName>. He himself had an extremely beautifully and meticulously crafted model of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8651">steam engine</term>, which, in order to run and yet be protected from water vapours, necessary for <pb n="208" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557715"/> the filling and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8674">rarefaction</term> of the cylinders, was connected to an <term ref="gfa-keywords-8784">air pump</term>. He also had a much larger model without a condenser in one of the workshops, but it was not quite finished. With him and <persName ref="gfa-actors-7735">his son</persName>, a very skilled illustrator, I went to the <emph rend="italic"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1880" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-15" n="177" cert="0">Galerie de l’architecture royale de France</placeName></emph>, where there was an exhibition of <term ref="gfa-keywords-4069">architectural</term> designs for a public library for a city in central <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>. The public sentiment favoured the young Gingembre’s drawing, and it is likely he will be awarded the prize.</p>
            <p>A little-known, but extremely interesting and instructive collection of models in <term ref="gfa-keywords-9123">gypsum</term>, some in original size, some in tapered scale, can be found there in one of the halls and adjoining rooms. These models are fashioned after the an<pb n="209" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557716" break="no"/>tiquities of <placeName ref="gfa-places-72">Italy</placeName>, <placeName ref="gfa-places-821">Greece</placeName> und <placeName ref="gfa-places-3">Egypt</placeName>, and include capitals, cornices, rosettes, bas-reliefs and entire buildings, such as the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1882">Pantheon</placeName>, the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1883"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8707">Lantern of Demosthenes</term></placeName>, the temples of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1522">Paestum</placeName>, and especially several Egyptian temples, which were reproduced with the greatest accuracy during the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8675">presence of the French</term> in that country, under <term ref="gfa-keywords-9832"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7626">Denon’s</persName></term> direction. In the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9373"><orgName ref="gfa-actors-7712"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1809" cert="0">porcelain manufactory of Dihl</placeName></orgName></term>, which I visited on the <date when="1814-09-16">15th</date><note>The date was 16 September 1814.</note> , I found nothing particularly remarkable, especially since I had already seen the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1635"><placeName ref="gfa-places-1884">manufactory of Sevres</placeName></placeName>, the queen of all others. The impressions of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9066">gems</term> and small bas-reliefs of antiquities, in white pâte on a blue ground, were expensive and did not seem to me nearly as accomplished, that is, as sharp and smooth, as the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8752">basalt</term> impressions of <orgName ref="gfa-actors-7566">Wedgwood</orgName>, of which I possess some beautiful specimens. Incidentally, I must say <pb n="210" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557717"/> that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9292">painting</term>, gilding and shapes of the receptacles were pretty, and that the lightness and elegance peculiar to this nation in matters of taste is also distinctively manifest here.</p>
            <p>On the <date when="1814-09-17">17th</date> I went to the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1810" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-17" n="179" cert="0">weapons factory</placeName> of Artillery Captain <persName ref="gfa-actors-7713">Pauli</persName> of <placeName ref="gfa-places-17">Bern</placeName>, which he has established in the <emph rend="italic">Rue des trois frères, Chaussée d’Antin</emph>, to make his personal acquaintance and to see his facilities. Unfortunately, however, he had departed for <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName> some days ago. His associates, however, had the courtesy not only to show me the mechanisms of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8676"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">new type of rifle</term></term> (which can be loaded and fired from behind seven to eight times faster than ordinary rifles and which has no firing pan, pan cover, flint nor ramrod), but also to take me to the firing range behind the building, <pb n="211" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557718"/> which gave me all the more pleasure, as I thought I would be allowed to show off my skills there. We shot with double-barrelled shotguns and rifled <term ref="gfa-keywords-8681"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9367">pistols</term></term>, and I must admit my astonishment at the rapidity with which the shot was fired and discharged as soon as one touched the trigger or striker, which is the same as on any other rifle. The reason was that the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8680">primer</term> (Amorce), which resembled a hemp seed in colour and shape, and which they called <term ref="gfa-keywords-8510">Muriatique oxigenée</term> (?), was located in the centre of the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8726">powder</term> in the perforated base of the cartridge to be inserted for each shot and exploded instantly when the rifle was fired by means of the impact of a small steel rod called a <term ref="gfa-keywords-8512">hammer</term>. This rapidity of ignition was of great <pb n="212" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557719"/> advantage for the accuracy of the shot, as I myself experienced when I hit the mark on the pavilion three times in four shots, to the amazement of these gentlemen.</p>
            <p>The price of a double-barrelled <term ref="gfa-keywords-8907">shotgun</term> furnished in this manner is six hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8571">francs</term>, and that of a <term ref="gfa-keywords-9548">Stutzer</term> or pair of pistols only a little less. The high price, as it seemed to me, was due to the fact that it had to cover the expenses for experiments and improvements and that, being patented, they had no fear of competition. To what extent this reasoning is appropriate and beneficial for them, only success will show.</p>
         </div>         
         <div>
            <head>Return to Schaffhausen, 18–22 September 1814</head>
            <p>On Sunday, the <date when="1814-09-18">18th</date>, I finally left <placeName ref="gfa-places-118" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-18" n="180">Paris</placeName>. The <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> was filled with <orgName ref="gfa-actors-8277">officers</orgName> — with the exception of one emigrant who had recently returned, it seemed, and whose clothing and gauntness resembled those of the <emph rend="italic"><persName ref="gfa-actors-8279">Gentilhomme champêtre</persName></emph> in the comedy. <pb n="213" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557720"/> He had sought employment in Paris but was returning to his home in the region of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1816">Vesoul</placeName> without having achieved his objective. As their conversation revolved around the same subject as during my outward journey, I closed my eyes and began to think of possible improvements to <term ref="gfa-keywords-8676"><persName ref="gfa-actors-7713">Pauli’s rifles</persName></term>.</p>
            <p>One remark of the Knight of <placeName ref="gfa-places-1816">Vesoul</placeName> — that’s what I call him, as his name remained unknown to me — I must mention, nonetheless, since it is characteristic. It was with regard to the <term ref="gfa-keywords-9381">freedom of the press</term>, which was to have been introduced in <placeName ref="gfa-places-48">France</placeName>. He saw it as a dangerous thing, while the others claimed the opposite, citing their valuable influence in <placeName ref="gfa-places-41">England</placeName>. <emph rend="italic">Que voulez-vous! he cried, C’est tout quelqu’autre chose dans ce pays-là. Il vous faut un jour <pb n="214" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557721"/> entier pour monter un Anglais, pendant que cela se fait dans un clin d’oeil avec un de nous.</emph> — The comparison met with loud applause; the conclusion he drew from it, however, was not well received.</p>
            <p>On the <date when="1814-09-19T10:00:00-01:00">19th</date> at ten o’clock in the morning we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1811" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-19T10:00:00-01:00" n="181">Troyes</placeName>, where the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligences</term> were exchanged and had to be repacked. I used this time to write down my observations of the two previous days and to view the <placeName ref="gfa-places-1812" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-19" n="182">cathedral</placeName> again with its bold <term ref="gfa-keywords-9139">gothic</term> columns and pointed vaults, which, however, were in great need of repair. — We arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1813" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-19" n="183">Bar-sur-Aube</placeName> in the evening, where we spent the night. War had been quite intense there<note>A battle between the French and the advancing Coalition army took place here on 27 February 1814.</note> and by a cursory estimate there were far more than a hundred empty gables to which houses had once belonged. More striking than this, however, was the <pb n="215" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557722"/> smell of cadavers prevailing in the area. It was said that the reason for this was that some avaricious persons were scavenging the dead on the battlefield in the hope of finding something of value on them.</p>
            <p>At dinner, when the conversation turned to the fate of Bar and the surrounding area, one French officer said, “The <placeName ref="gfa-places-35">Germans</placeName> are a very different nation than we are! When we scorched and burned their country, six months later it was better and more beautiful again than it had been before, while with us everything lies in ruins for years and years.” He might not have been entirely wrong, for one could not yet see any efforts to clear away the rubble.</p>
            <p>On the <date when="1814-09-20T12:00:00-01:00">20th</date> at noon, we arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1814" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-20" n="184">Chaumont</placeName> and in the evening in the city of <term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">cutlers</term>, namely in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1815" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-20" n="185">Langres</placeName>. In Chaumont, I noticed in many houses in the design of the <pb n="216" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557723"/> staircases a unique, never seen before, but certainly very old <term ref="gfa-keywords-4069">construction</term>. They were spiral staircases, running through all the floors and inserted in the front of the house so that one half protruded, while the other half receded by so much and led to the rooms. What the motive of this arrangement may have been is unknown to me, presumably to gain space.</p>
            <p>In <placeName ref="gfa-places-1815">Langres</placeName>, I visited some of my correspondents from the so-called <emph rend="italic"><term ref="gfa-keywords-9305">Marchands coutéliers</term></emph>. I had them show me their wares, and on examining and comparing them, I found that the finer works were just as good as the English ones, for they used the same material, namely, <term ref="gfa-keywords-8482">cast steel</term>, for <term ref="gfa-keywords-8659">razors</term> and <term ref="gfa-keywords-8661">scissors</term>, of which the latter were far more tasteful, but also more expensive.</p>
            <p><pb n="217" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557724"/> On the <date when="1814-09-21">21st</date> early in the morning we left <placeName ref="gfa-places-1815" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-21" n="186">Langres</placeName> and arrived in <placeName ref="gfa-places-1816" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-21" n="187">Vesoul</placeName> in the evening. There I exchanged my place in the <term ref="gfa-keywords-8570">diligence</term> with one in the faster courier’s coach, reaching <placeName ref="gfa-places-1583" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-22" n="188">Belfort</placeName> on the morning of the <date when="1814-09-22">22nd</date> and, with a similar opportunity, <placeName ref="gfa-places-10" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-22T18:00:00-01:00" n="189">Basel</placeName> in the <date when="1814-09-22T18:00:00-01:00">evening</date> at six o’clock, where <persName ref="gfa-actors-7740">my oldest boy</persName>, whom I had sent there, was waiting for me at a good <persName ref="gfa-actors-7374">friend’s</persName>. After a brief stay, I departed the same evening for <placeName ref="gfa-places-1817" type="itinerar" n="190">Stein bei Säckingen</placeName> and arrived the following day, <date when="1814-09-23">September 22nd</date><note>The date was 23 September 1814.</note>, happy and healthy at <placeName ref="gfa-places-131" type="itinerar" when="1814-09-23" n="191">home</placeName> with my <persName ref="gfa-actors-6139">family</persName>.</p>
            <p>I have, thus, made this journey, amounting to a total of approximately three hundred <term ref="gfa-keywords-8407">German miles</term>, in a period of six weeks and five days. In this time, I experienced many very interesting things, and the wealth of new ideas it has given <pb n="218" facs="https://www.e-rara.ch/ebs/content/zoom/16557725"/> me and the acquaintance of the persons I made are sufficient compensation for everything, even if (which lies hidden in the future) no other benefit to me should arise from it.</p>
            <p>I now close my diary, being so happy to be able to say with considerable truth regarding its contents: <emph rend="italic"><term ref="gfa-keywords-8683">Nulla dies sine linea!</term></emph></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>